<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantcell</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id>
<journal-title>Plant Cell</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Cell</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="epub">1531-298X</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">1040-4651</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">109090</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.109090</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>RESEARCH ARTICLES</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>BRANCHED1 Interacts with FLOWERING LOCUS T to Repress the Floral Transition of the Axillary Meristems in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>[C]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[OA]</sup></xref></article-title>
<?RRH: BRC1<!-- Q1 --> Represses FT Function in the Axillary Meristem?>
<?LRH: The Plant Cell?>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>Masaki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Daimon</surname><given-names>Yasufumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn2"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kurotani</surname><given-names>Ken-ichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn3"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Higo</surname><given-names>Asuka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pruneda-Paz</surname><given-names>Jos&#x00E9; L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>Ghislain</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn4"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mitsuda</surname><given-names>Nobutaka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>Steve A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn5"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ohme-Takagi</surname><given-names>Masaru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>c</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>d</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>Motomu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>Takashi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib>
<aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Division of Integrated Life Science, Graduate School of Biostudies, Kyoto University, Sakyo-ku, Kyoto 606-8501, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Section of Cell and Developmental Biology, Division of Biological Sciences, University of California San Diego, La Jolla, California 92093</aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Bioproduction Research Institute, National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology, Tsukuba 305-8562, Japan</aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Institute for Environmental Science and Technology, Saitama University, Saitama 338-8770, Japan</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1105/tpc.112.109090">www.plantcell.org/cgi/doi/10.1105/tpc.112.109090</ext-link></p></fn>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>5</label>Address correspondence to <email>taraqui@lif.kyoto-u.ac.jp</email>.</corresp>
<fn id="afn1"><p>The<!-- Q2 --> author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org">www.plantcell.org</ext-link>) is: Takashi Araki (<email>taraqui@lif.kyoto-u.ac.jp</email>).</p></fn>
<fn id="afn2" fn-type="present-address"><label>1</label><p>Current address: Graduate School of Agricultural and Life Sciences, University of Tokyo, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113-8657, Japan.</p></fn>
<fn id="afn3" fn-type="present-address"><label>2</label><p>Current address: Bioscience and Biotechnology Center, Nagoya University, Chikusa-ku, Nagoya 464-8601, Japan.</p></fn>
<fn id="afn4" fn-type="present-address"><label>3</label><p>Current address: Department of Integrative Biology and Pharmacology, University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston, Houston, TX 77030.</p></fn>
<fn id="afn5" fn-type="present-address"><label>4</label><p>Current address: Dana and David Dornsife College of Letters, Arts, and Sciences, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA 90089.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>04</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day></day><year></year></pub-date>
<volume>25</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>000</fpage>
<lpage>000</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>03</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>04</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>&#x00A9; 2013 American Society of Plant Biologists</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<license license-type="open-access"><p/></license>
</permissions>
<self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="PC_109090_ic1.gif"/>
<abstract abstract-type="precis"><p>This study reports that BRC1 in axillary buds interacts with and inhibits the function of the florigen protein FT. This serves as an additional mode of regulation of floral transition in axillary meristems.</p></abstract>
<abstract>
<p>Plant architecture shows a large degree of developmental plasticity. Some of the key determinants are the timing of the floral transition induced by a systemic flowering signal (florigen) and the branching pattern regulated by key factors such as BRANCHED1 (BRC1). Here, we report that BRC1 interacts with the florigen proteins FLOWERING LOCUS T (FT) and TWIN SISTER OF FT (TSF) but not with TERMINAL FLOWER1, a floral repressor. FT protein induced in leaves moves into the subtended bud, suggesting that FT protein also plays a role in promotion of the floral transition in the axillary meristem (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AM</xref>). The <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant shows an earlier floral transition in the axillary shoots compared with the wild type, suggesting that <italic>BRC1</italic> plays a role in delaying the floral transition of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>. Genetic and gene expression analyses suggest that BRC1 interferes with florigen (FT and TSF) function in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>. Consistent with this, <italic>BRC1</italic> ectopically expressed in the shoot apical meristem delays the floral transition in the main shoot. These results taken together suggest that BRC1 protein interacts with FT and TSF proteins and modulates florigen activity in the axillary buds to prevent premature floral transition of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>.</p>
</abstract>
<counts><page-count count="0"/></counts>
</article-meta>
<notes>
<glossary><title>Glossary</title>
<def-list>
<def-item><term id="term1">SAM</term><def id="def1"><p>shoot apical meristem</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term id="term2">LD</term><def id="def2"><p>long-day</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term id="term3">AM</term><def id="def3"><p>axillary meristem</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term id="term4">SD</term><def id="def4"><p>short-day</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term id="term5">TF</term><def id="def5"><p>transcription factor</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term id="term6">BiFC</term><def id="def6"><p>bimolecular fluorescence complementation</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term id="term7">GUS</term><def id="def7"><p>&#x03B2;-glucuronidase</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term id="term8">EGFP</term><def id="def8"><p>enhanced green fluorescent protein</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term id="term9">Col</term><def id="def9"><p>Columbia-0</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term id="term10">ORF</term><def id="def10"><p>open reading frame</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term id="term11">GST</term><def id="def11"><p>glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase</p></def></def-item>
</def-list>
</glossary>
</notes>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="s1" sec-type="introduction">
<title>INTRODUCTION</title>
<p>There is a large degree of developmental plasticity in plant architecture, which is determined in part by the timing of floral transition and the branching pattern. The floral transition is induced by a systemic flowering signal (florigen), and plant architecture is often remodeled upon the floral transition in the shoot apical meristem (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref>). In the rosette-forming plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, floral transition is followed by rapid internode elongation and activation of axillary bud development in inductive long-day (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref>) conditions. Since axillary bud development proceeds differently than that of the main shoot, the systemic flowering signal may also be perceived differently in the two locations.</p>
<p>Appropriate regulation of axillary bud development is achieved through integrating internal and environmental signals at each of the three developmental stages: axillary meristem (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AM</xref>) initiation, bud differentiation, and shoot elongation. Among them, the regulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AM</xref> initiation and shoot elongation has been studied intensively. Molecular genetic approaches have helped identify genes required for initiation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>REVOLUTA</italic> and related HD-ZIP genes are required to specify adaxiality of lateral organs and act to form <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Talbert et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Emery et al., 2003</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AM</xref> initiation requires the GRAS family gene <italic>LATERAL SUPPRESOR</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Schumacher et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Greb et al., 2003</xref>) and the Myb-like transcription factor (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TF</xref>) <italic>REGULATOR OF AXILLARY MERISTEM1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Keller et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">M&#x00FC;ller et al., 2006</xref>). On the other hand, axillary shoot elongation is regulated by multiple plant hormones. Auxin produced in the main shoot suppresses axillary shoot elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Dun et al., 2006</xref>). Strigolactones, carotenoid-derived hormones produced in roots, also act as negative regulatory factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gomez-Roldan et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Umehara et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Crawford et al., 2010</xref>). Cytokinin is thought to be a secondary messenger and acts more locally in the buds to promote outgrowth.</p>
<p>Compared with initiation and elongation of the axillary bud, regulation of differentiation including floral transition is far less understood. One gene expressed in the axillary bud known to regulate differentiation is <italic>BRANCHED1/TEOSINTE BRANCHED1-LIKE1</italic> (<italic>BRC1/TBL1</italic>; hereafter referred as <italic>BRC1</italic>). <italic>BRC1</italic> encodes a member of the TEOSINTE BRANCHED1, CYCLOIDEA, and PCF (TCP) <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TF</xref> family and was identified as an ortholog of maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) <italic>Teosinte branched1</italic> (<italic>Tb1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Doebley et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Finlayson, 2007</xref>). It was suggested that <italic>Tb1</italic>-like genes act downstream of strigolactone signaling to suppress development of axillary shoots in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Finlayson, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brewer et al., 2009</xref>). Since axillary buds of the <italic>brc1</italic> mutant show advanced development compared with the wild type, it was suggested that <italic>BRC1</italic> acts as a negative regulator of differentiation in axillary buds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>). The <italic>brc1</italic> mutant occasionally develops ectopic <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> at cotyledonary axils, suggesting that <italic>BRC1</italic> also has an inhibitory role in initiation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>). It was also suggested that <italic>BRC1</italic> suppresses the elongation of axillary shoots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Finlayson, 2007</xref>). These pleiotropic effects reflect multiple roles of <italic>BRC1</italic> in axillary bud development. The expression of <italic>BRC1</italic> is regulated by environmental signals, such as planting density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Finlayson et al., 2010</xref>). Based on these observations, <italic>BRC1</italic> was proposed to be an integrator of axillary bud development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>). A <italic>BRC1</italic> paralog, <italic>BRC2</italic>, is thought to have a partially redundant but distinct role in axillary bud development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Finlayson, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Finlayson et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, initiation of axillary bud development is closely linked to floral transition in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref> under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Hempel and Feldman, 1994</xref>). The molecular mechanism controlling floral transition is well understood in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and other species. Among the key regulators of floral transition, <italic>FT</italic> acts as a floral pathway integrator. Both endogenous and environmental signaling pathways are integrated in the transcriptional regulation of <italic>FT</italic>, which encodes a 20-kD protein of the PEBP/RKIP (for phosphatidylethanolamine binding protein/Raf kinase inhibitor protein) family that acts as a long-distance flowering signal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Lifschitz et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Corbesier et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Jaeger and Wigge, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Lin et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Mathieu et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Tamaki et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Notaguchi et al., 2008</xref>). <italic>FT</italic> expression is induced in phloem companion cells in cotyledons and leaves under inductive <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Takada and Goto, 2003</xref>). FT protein then moves into the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref>, where it interacts with the bZIP <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TF</xref> FD, to induce the expression of a floral meristem identity gene, <italic>APETALA1</italic> (<italic>AP1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abe et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Wigge et al., 2005</xref>). A recent study in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) showed that the interaction between Hd3a (an FT ortholog) and FD1 (an FD ortholog) is not direct but is mediated by 14-3-3 proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Taoka et al., 2011</xref>). Os-FD1 interacts with a 14-3-3 protein through a conventional 14-3-3 recognition motif R/K-X-X-S-X-P, whereas Os-Hd3a has a noncanonical binding site for 14-3-3 proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Yaffe et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Pnueli et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Taoka et al., 2011</xref>). Other PEBP/RKIP proteins are also involved in the regulation of the floral transition in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. <italic>TWIN SISTER OF FT</italic> (<italic>TSF</italic>), the paralog of <italic>FT</italic>, also acts as a floral promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Michaels et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Yamaguchi et al., 2005</xref>). Although <italic>TSF</italic> has a minor role under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions in which <italic>FT</italic> is robustly expressed, <italic>TSF</italic> makes a prominent contribution to the floral transition under short-day (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">SD</xref>) conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Yamaguchi et al., 2005</xref>). By contrast, TERMINAL FLOWER1 (TFL1) delays the floral transition through interaction with FD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bradley et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hanano and Goto, 2011</xref>). <italic>TFL1</italic> also plays a key role in maintenance of inflorescence meristems. In the <italic>tfl1</italic> mutant under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions, the main inflorescence is terminated with a fused floral structure and the axillary shoots are replaced by single flowers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Shannon and Meeks-Wagner, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Alvarez et al., 1992</xref>).</p>
<p>In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, when floral transition is induced in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref>, preexisting primordia develop into cauline leaves and newly formed primordia become floral buds. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> are initiated and develop basipetally after floral transition of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref> in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Hempel and Feldman, 1994</xref>). It was suggested that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> are at first insensitive to flowering signals since they form vegetative nodes before making flowers even though a sufficient amount of the systemic flowering signal is produced to induce floral transition in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Hempel and Feldman, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Grbi&#x0107; and Bleecker, 1996</xref>). Therefore, florigen activity and/or perception are likely to be differently modulated in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> than in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref>.</p>
<p>In this study, we identified BRC1 as an interactor of FT without mediation by a 14-3-3 protein and demonstrated that BRC1 interacts with TSF but not TFL1. Our results indicate that <italic>BRC1</italic> modulates the florigen activity in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> and confers a specific mode of regulation to the floral transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s2" sec-type="results">
<title>RESULTS</title>
<sec id="s3">
<title>BRC1 Interacts with FT</title>
<p>The fact that FT acts with the bZIP protein FD in a transcriptional complex prompted us to seek other TFs as possible interacting proteins. To identify transcription factors that can interact with FT, we performed yeast two-hybrid screening using two different <xref ref-typehttp://www.google.com/url?sa=i&rct=j&q=&esrc=s&source=images&cd=&ved=0CAcQjRw&url=http%3A%2F%2Fgeneontology.org%2Fpage%2Flead-database-guide&ei=iqtvVLLBFNXSoAS45ICQCA&bvm=bv.80185997,d.eXY&psig=AFQjCNFadMx7EmhyrQ9w2XsDaKhm124RWA&ust=1416690910446007="list" rid="def5">TF</xref> libraries. Robotized screening of the first library (Steve Kay Lab) revealed 64 candidates when the threshold was set to twofold higher than the average (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Table 1</ext-link> online). By manual screening of a second <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TF</xref> library (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Mitsuda et al., 2010</xref>), 10 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TFs</xref> were found to show reproducible interaction with FT (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 1</ext-link> online). Interestingly, five candidates in the first screening and four in the second were TFs belonging to the TCP family. Because some TCP family members were not represented in the two <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TF</xref> libraries, we performed yeast two-hybrid assays with the individual TCP transcriptional factors that have been reported to be involved in various developmental processes. Among them, BRC1 reproducibly interacted with FT in yeast two-hybrid assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). We focused on BRC1 as a good candidate to be a link between the floral transition and concomitant architectural remodeling through branch development.</p>
<fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Protein Interaction between BRC1 and FT.</p><p><bold>(A)</bold> Yeast two-hybrid analysis of protein interaction between BRC1, BRC2, or GRF3 and FT, TSF, or TFL1. Clones containing each combination of bait and prey vectors were grown on nonselective medium (+His) or on selective medium (&#x2212;His). For the clones containing BRC1, 3-amino-1,2,4-triazole (3-AT) was added to the medium (left two rows). pCUY and pGAD424 empty vectors were used as a negative control (BD [binding domain] and AD [activation domain], respectively).</p><p><bold>(B)</bold> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">BiFC</xref> analysis of the interaction between BRC1 and FT in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaf epidermal cells. The N-terminal fragment of EYFP was fused to BRC1 (YN-BRC1) and the C-terminal fragment of EYFP to FT (FT-YC). The fusion proteins were transiently expressed under the cauliflower mosaic virus 35S promoter through agroinfiltration. EYFP fluorescence (top panels) and EYFP fluorescence merged with a bright-field (BF) image (bottom panels) are shown. Combinations in which one of the fusion constructs was replaced with a fragment of EYFP (YN or YC) were used as negative controls (central and right columns). Arrowheads indicate complemented EYFP fluorescence in the nucleus. Bar = 200 &#x03BC;m.</p><p><bold>(C)</bold> In vitro pull-down assay demonstrating the interaction between BRC1 and FT. Closed arrowhead, open arrowhead, and arrow indicate T7-FT, GST-BRC1, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">GST</xref>, respectively.</p><p><bold>(D)</bold> Yeast two-hybrid assay of protein interaction between FT and truncated versions of BRC1. TCP, TCP domain; R, R domain. a.a., amino acids.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pc_109090_fig1"></graphic></fig>
<p>We further investigated interaction between BRC1 and two FT homologs, TSF (in the FT clade) and TFL1 (in the TFL1 clade), by yeast two-hybrid assay. TSF also showed interaction with BRC1, while TFL1 did not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). No interactions between the TCP protein BRC2, which is closely related to BRC1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>), and these PEBP/RKIP proteins were detected in our yeast two-hybrid experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>).</p>
<p>Protein interaction between FT and BRC1 was further confirmed in plant cells by bimolecular fluorescence complementation (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">BiFC</xref>) assays in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> and in vitro by pull-down assays. A clear <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">BiFC</xref> signal was detected in the nucleus, indicating that FT interacts with BRC1 in plant cells and that the FT-BRC1 complex is localized to the nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1B</xref>). BRC1 was able to pull down FT in the in vitro assay, indicating that their interaction is likely direct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1C</xref>).</p>
<p>Analysis using a series of deletion constructs showed that the C-terminal region of BRC1 including the conserved R domain is dispensable for interaction with FT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>). However, removal of the entire C terminus after the TCP domain disrupted the interaction (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 2</ext-link> online). In addition, a relatively small deletion of the N-terminal 74 amino acid residues abolished the interaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1D</xref>). These results suggest the N-terminal region of BRC1 is necessary but not sufficient for interaction with FT.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s4">
<title>14-3-3 Proteins Do Not Mediate the Interaction between BRC1 and FT</title>
<p>In rice, 14-3-3 proteins mediate the interaction between Hd3a (an FT ortholog) and FD1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Taoka et al., 2011</xref>). Since <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> FT can interact with 14-3-3 proteins, it is likely that they mediate FT&#x2013;FD interaction in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> as well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Pnueli et al., 2001</xref>). This raises the question whether 14-3-3 proteins also mediate the interaction between BRC1 and FT. To explore whether 14-3-3 proteins mediate the interaction between BRC1 and FT, two sets of yeast two-hybrid assay were performed. First, we examined whether point mutations in FT that abolish interaction with 14-3-3 proteins also affect interaction with BRC1. All three mutant FT proteins tested still showed interaction with BRC1, suggesting that 14-3-3 proteins do not mediate the interaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). BRC1 has a sequence conforming to a recognition motif of 14-3-3 proteins (R/K-X-X-S-X-P) in the C-terminal region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Yaffe et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Taoka et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>). Mutation in this sequence (S390A) did not abolish interaction with FT, further supporting that 14-3-3 proteins are not required for the interaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2A</xref>). Second, Ala scanning was performed to identify residues in FT required for interaction with BRC1. Among 46 mutant FT proteins tested, seven did not show interaction with BRC1 but could interact with a 14-3-3 protein (GENERAL REGULATORY FACTOR3 [GRF3; 14-3-3 p.s.i<!-- Q3 -->.]) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref>; see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 3</ext-link> online). When these residues were plotted on the FT three-dimensional structure model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Ahn et al., 2006</xref>; Protein Data Bank ID 1WKP), the region required for the interaction with BRC1 was distinct from the interaction interface between FT and 14-3-3 proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Taoka et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2D</xref>). These results, taken together, indicate that the interaction between FT and BRC1 is not mediated by 14-3-3. Thus, BRC1 interacts with FT in a different manner than FD does.</p>
<fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>14-3-3 Proteins Do Not Mediate the Interaction between FT and BRC1.</p><p><bold>(A)</bold> Yeast two-hybrid analysis of interaction between BRC1 and mutant FT proteins defective in interaction with 14-3-3 proteins. T66I, P94L, G102D, and P75L are mutant FT proteins, the former three of which do not interact with 14-3-3 proteins. S390A is a mutated BRC1 in which a Ser residue in a putative 14-3-3 recognition site (S390) was substituted by Ala. GRF3 was chosen as a representative 14-3-3 protein. Yeasts were grown on nonselective medium (+His) or on selective medium (&#x2212;His and &#x2212;His+3-AT). WT, the wild type.</p><p><bold>(B)</bold> Schematic diagram of BRC1 protein depicting the putative 14-3-3 recognition site. a.a., amino acids.</p><p><bold>(C)</bold> Yeast two-hybrid assay of interaction between mutant FT proteins and BRC1 or GRF3. Representative results for seven FT mutants defective in interaction with the BRC1 protein and a mutant defective in interaction with GRF3 were shown. These mutants were obtained by screening of Ala-scanned FT mutants (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 3</ext-link> online). Yeasts were grown on nonselective medium (+His) or on selective medium (&#x2212;His and &#x2212;His+3-AT).</p><p><bold>(D)</bold> Amino acid residues essential for interaction with BRC1 (C, indicated by magenta) or 14<!-- Q10 -->-3-3 proteins (A, indicated by yellow; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Taoka et al., 2011</xref>) on a ribbon model of the FT protein.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pc_109090_fig2"></graphic></fig>
<p>Whether candidates from the yeast two-hybrid screen using the second <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TF</xref> library interact with FT through 14-3-3 proteins was also investigated. A bZIP TF, bZIP30, interacted with 14-3-3 proteins and failed to interact with the mutant FT that cannot interact with 14-3-3 proteins. This suggests that 14-3-3 is probably required to mediate the FT-bZIP30 interaction (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 1</ext-link> online). Other candidates interacted with at least one of the mutant FT proteins that cannot interact with 14-3-3 proteins, indicating they probably do not require 14-3-3 proteins for interaction with FT (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 1</ext-link> online).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s5">
<title>FT Protein Can Move to an Axillary Bud from the Subtending Leaf</title>
<p><italic>BRC1</italic> is expressed in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> and the <italic>brc1</italic> mutant shows defective phenotypes specifically in the axillary buds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Finlayson, 2007</xref>). On the other hand, <italic>FT</italic> is expressed in the leaf vasculature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Takada and Goto, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Yamaguchi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Notaguchi et al., 2008</xref>), and FT protein moves into the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref> to promote floral transition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Corbesier et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Jaeger and Wigge, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Mathieu et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Notaguchi et al., 2008</xref>). The observation that BRC1 and FT protein can interact in plant cells and in vitro strongly suggests that <italic>FT</italic> also has a role in the axillary buds.</p>
<p>To explore the possible expression of <italic>FT</italic> in the axillary buds, we examined the expression pattern of <italic>FT</italic> using <italic>gFT</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> (for &#x03B2;-glucuronidase) plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Notaguchi et al., 2008</xref>). Because of its large molecular mass (88.9 kD), FT-GUS fusion protein is a good indicator of expression pattern. It does not seem to move out of the cells where originally expressed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Notaguchi et al., 2008</xref>) and did not promote flowering when expressed in the leaf (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 4</ext-link> online). As previously reported, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GUS</xref> staining was observed in vascular bundles toward the periphery of the rosette leaf blade in <italic>gFT</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Takada and Goto, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Yamaguchi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Notaguchi et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A</xref>). As in the rosette leaves, <italic>FT</italic> expression was detected in the vasculature in the distal part of cauline leaves but not in the axillary bud (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3B</xref>). Further observations of sections of axillary buds did not reveal staining in the buds at the cauline or rosette leaf axils (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3D</xref>; see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 4</ext-link> online). We next examined whether FT protein expressed in a leaf blade moves into the axillary bud subtended by the leaf using the <italic>ProHSP18.2</italic>:<italic>FT-EGFP</italic>-inducible reporter system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Notaguchi et al., 2008</xref>). Induction of FT-EGFP (for enhanced green fluorescent protein) protein in a single leaf blade was confirmed after local transient heat treatment (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 5</ext-link> online). One leaf blade was heated for 2 h to induce FT-EGFP fusion protein, and 24 h after the end of the heat treatment, FT-EGFP fluorescence in the axillary bud subtended by the heat-treated leaf was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3E</xref>). When the heat-treated leaf blade was removed by cutting the base of the leaf blade immediately after the heat treatment, fluorescence was not detected in the axillary bud (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3F</xref>). These results showed that FT-EGFP fusion protein expressed in the leaf blade can move into the axillary bud. Based on expression in leaves and the ability to move into the axillary bud from the subtending leaf, we concluded that FT protein is likely to be present in axillary buds.</p>
<fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><italic>FT</italic> Expression Pattern and Movement of FT Protein into Axillary Buds.</p><p><bold>(A)</bold> to <bold>(D)</bold> <italic>FT</italic> expression patterns monitored by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GUS</xref> staining of <italic>gFT</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> plant. Whole-mount preparations of a rosette leaf <bold>(A)</bold> and the main stem of a plant with the axillary bud subtended by a cauline leaf <bold>(B)</bold>. Resin sections of the axillary buds subtended by a cauline leaf <bold>(C)</bold> and by a rosette leaf <bold>(D)</bold>. Arrowhead in <bold>(B)</bold> indicates staining in the peripheral region of the cauline leaf.</p><p><bold>(E)</bold> and <bold>(F)</bold> Movement of FT-EGFP into an axillary bud from the subtending leaf. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">EGFP</xref> fluorescence merged with a bright-field image of the axillary bud is shown. FT-EGFP expression was induced from the <italic>ProHSP18.2</italic>:<italic>FT-EGFP</italic> transgene by heat treatment of the leaf blade of a rosette leaf (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 5</ext-link> online). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">EGFP</xref> fluorescence was observed 24 h after the end of the heat treatment. The treated leaf blade was either left intact <bold>(E)</bold> or cut off immediately after the heat treatment to prevent FT-EGFP export <bold>(F)</bold>. The cut site is not seen in <bold>(F)</bold>.</p><p>ap, apical meristem; ax, axillary meristem; cl, cauline leaf; fl, floral bud, pt, petiole of the heat-treated rosette leaf; rl, rosette leaf; st, stem. Bar in <bold>(A)</bold> = 1 mm and bars in other panels = 100 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pc_109090_fig3"></graphic></fig>
</sec>
<sec id="s6">
<title><italic>brc1-2</italic> Mutants Show Accelerated Floral Transition in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref></title>
<p>In order to gain insight into the physiological role of the interaction between FT and BRC1, we looked for relevant phenotypes in the <italic>brc1-2</italic> (<italic>tbl1-1</italic>) mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Alonso et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Finlayson, 2007</xref>). As previously reported, more axillary shoots grew out in the <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant than in the wild type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Finlayson, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). We also confirmed that the development of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> is more advanced in <italic>brc1-2</italic> than in the wild type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). Further observation indicated that almost all the existing axillary buds proceeded to reproductive phase in <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant shortly after bolting of the main shoot. By contrast, lower axillary buds remained vegetative in the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>). Furthermore, the axillary shoots of the uppermost nodes formed no leaves in many <italic>brc1-2</italic> plants, whereas two leaves were usually formed in wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>). Quantification of leaf number showed that <italic>brc1-2</italic> has fewer leaves on the axillary shoots at every position compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref>). A similar phenotype was observed for the lowest cauline and uppermost rosette nodes in a previous report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Finlayson et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Early Floral Transition of the Axillary Shoots in <italic>brc1</italic> Mutants.</p><p><bold>(A)</bold> Axillary shoot phenotype of the wild type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) and <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant. Successive axillary shoots with the subtending leaf of 44-d-old plants are shown. Arrowheads and arrows indicate vegetative nodes and the first flowers in the most apical branches. Plus numbers represent cauline-leaf axils in the acropetal direction, and minus numbers represent rosette-leaf axils in the basipetal direction as shown in the right diagram. In the diagram, open circles, arrows, and bars represent flowers, shoots, and leaves, respectively.</p><p><bold>(B)</bold> Developmental stages of the buds in the axils of cotyledons (c1 and c2) and rosette leaves (L1 to L15) of 10 plants of wild-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref> (left) and <italic>brc1-2</italic> (right). Developmental stages were defined according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al. (2007)</xref>. Gray indicates absence of the leaf node such that the position is occupied by a flower. Observations were made on the days when the first floral buds became visible (before bolting), the main shoot became 1-cm long (1 cm bolting), and the main shoot became 5-cm long (5 cm bolting).</p><p><bold>(C)</bold> Number of leaves formed on axillary shoots at the five axil positions of the wild type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) and <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref>. The axil position is defined in <bold>(A)</bold>. Leaves in the basal part of axillary shoots without internodes are classified as axillary rosette leaves (ARL) and those with elongated internodes as cauline leaves (CL). Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 9). The differences significant between <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref> and <italic>brc1-2</italic> in two-tailed multiple <italic>t</italic> test with Bonferroni correction (P &lt; 0.05) are indicated with asterisks.</p><p><bold>(D)</bold> and <bold>(E)</bold> Expression of <italic>AP1</italic> in the axillary buds monitored by <italic>ProAP1</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic>. Number of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GUS</xref>-positive axillary buds in <italic>ProAP1</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> plants in wild-type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) and <italic>brc1-2</italic> background grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> <bold>(D)</bold>. Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc> (<italic>n</italic> &#x2265; 21). The differences significant in two-tailed multiple <italic>t</italic> test with Bonferroni correction (P &lt; 0.05) with respect to the wild type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) are indicated with asterisks. Representative 22-d-old <italic>ProAP1</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> plants in wild-type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) and <italic>brc1-2</italic> backgrounds <bold>(E)</bold>. Arrowheads indicate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GUS</xref>-positive axillary buds at rosette-leaf axils.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pc_109090_fig4"></graphic></fig>
<p>Because leaf number is generally considered to reflect the timing of the floral transition, we assumed that the reduction of leaf number in <italic>brc1-2</italic> indicates earlier floral transition in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>. To confirm this possibility in the context of gene expression, we examined <italic>AP1</italic> expression in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> using a <italic>ProAP1</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> reporter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hempel et al., 1997</xref>). In the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref>, the timing of the onset of <italic>AP1</italic> expression did not differ between <italic>brc1-2</italic> and wild-type backgrounds, in accordance with the fact that the leaf number of the main shoot did not significantly differ between the two genotypes. By contrast, the floral transition of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> proceeded differently between the <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant and wild-type plants. Eighteen days after germination, almost all the <italic>brc1-2</italic> plants (92%; 22/24) had at least one <italic>AP1</italic>-expressing axillary bud, whereas only about a half of the wild-type plants (53%; 16/30) did. The quantification of <italic>AP1</italic>-expressing buds indicated that the <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant formed more reproductive axillary buds than did the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figures 4D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4E</xref>). Introduction of a genomic fragment of <italic>BRC1</italic> into <italic>brc1-2</italic> complemented the leaf number phenotype (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 6</ext-link> online). Therefore, we concluded that floral transition of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AM</xref> is accelerated in the <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s7">
<title>The <italic>ft-2</italic> Mutation Is Epistatic to the <italic>brc1-2</italic> Mutation</title>
<p>The observations that the number of leaves on the axillary shoots differed depending on the node positions in the wild type and that floral transition of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> in the <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant was accelerated imply that floral transition of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> is a regulated process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). Furthermore, the observation that FT protein could move into the axillary buds suggests that FT could be involved in this regulation. To address this, we examined floral transition of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> in <italic>ft-2</italic> single and <italic>brc1-2 ft-2</italic> double mutants. Compared with the wild type, the <italic>ft-2</italic> mutant formed more leaves on its axillary shoots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>), suggesting that floral transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> was delayed in the <italic>ft-2</italic> mutant. The <italic>brc1-2 ft-2</italic> double mutant formed almost the same number of leaves as the <italic>ft-2</italic> single mutant on axillary shoots of cauline leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). Thus, the acceleration of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AM</xref> floral transition observed in the <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant requires functional <italic>FT</italic> in cauline axils. In axillary shoots of rosette leaves, the <italic>brc1-2 ft-2</italic> mutant formed fewer leaves than the <italic>ft-2</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>). The elongation of axillary shoots at the rosette axils was also enhanced in <italic>brc1-2 ft-2</italic> compared with <italic>ft-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Delayed Floral Transition of Axillary Shoots in <italic>ft</italic> and <italic>ft tsf</italic> Mutants and Genetic Interaction with <italic>brc1</italic>.</p><p><bold>(A)</bold> Number of leaves formed on the axillary shoots at the five axil positions of the wild type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) and <italic>brc1-2</italic>, <italic>ft-2</italic>, and <italic>brc1-2 ft-2</italic> mutants grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref>. Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 12 for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref> and <italic>brc1-2</italic>; <italic>n</italic> = 24 for <italic>ft-2</italic> and <italic>brc1-2 ft-2</italic>). The differences significant between <italic>ft-2</italic> and <italic>brc1-2 ft-2</italic> in two-tailed multiple <italic>t</italic> test with Bonferroni correction (P &lt; 0.05) are indicated with asterisks. ARL, axillary rosette leaves; CL, cauline leaves.</p><p><bold>(B)</bold> Representative plants of <italic>ft-2</italic> and <italic>brc1-2 ft-2</italic> mutants grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> for 60 days. Arrows indicate elongated axillary shoots at rosette axils.</p><p><bold>(C)</bold> Number of leaves formed on the axillary shoots at the three axil positions of the wild type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) and <italic>brc1-2</italic>, <italic>ft-2 tsf-1</italic>, and <italic>brc1-2 ft-2 tsf-1</italic> (triple) mutants grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref>. Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 12). The differences significant between <italic>ft-2 tsf-1</italic> and <italic>brc1-2 ft-2 tsf-1</italic> in two-tailed multiple <italic>t</italic> test with Bonferroni correction (P &lt; 0.05) are indicated with asterisks.</p><p><bold>(D)</bold> Axillary shoot phenotype of <italic>ft-2 tsf-1</italic> and <italic>brc1-2 ft-2 tsf-1</italic> mutants. Top panel shows the rosette part of the plants, and bottom panels show the uppermost rosette leaf with the axillary bud or shoot. Note that most of the primary rosette leaves on the main axis were decaying or senescent. Arrowheads in the bottom panels indicate the senescent rosette leaves. Bars = 5 mm.</p><p>Designation of the axil positions and classification of leaves in <bold>(A)</bold> and <bold>(C)</bold> are as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>.</p><p>[See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pc_109090_fig5"></graphic></fig>
<p>In the <italic>ft</italic> mutant background, <italic>TSF</italic> promotes the floral transition during prolonged vegetative phase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Yamaguchi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hiraoka et al., 2013</xref>). Because our yeast two-hybrid assay showed that TSF is also able to interact with BRC1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>), <italic>TSF</italic> is likely to be responsible for the acceleration of floral transition in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> at rosette axils in the <italic>brc1-2 ft-2</italic> mutant. To test this hypothesis, the phenotype of the <italic>brc1-2 ft-2 tsf-1</italic> triple mutant was examined. As observed in the <italic>brc1-2 ft-2</italic> and <italic>ft-2</italic> mutants, <italic>brc1-2 ft-2 tsf-1</italic> formed almost the same number of leaves as the <italic>ft-2 tsf-1</italic> double mutant in axillary shoots of cauline leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>). The <italic>ft-2 tsf-1</italic> double mutant did not form elongated axillary shoots on its rosette axils under our experimental conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hiraoka et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>). In the <italic>brc1-2 ft-2 tsf-1</italic> triple mutant, rosette leaves did form axillary buds and developed many leaves, but over 100 d after bolting of the main shoot, the buds failed to make flowers and did not elongate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5D</xref>). These results suggest that prompt floral transition and subsequent elongation of the axillary shoots in the <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant require either <italic>FT</italic> or <italic>TSF</italic> functions.</p>
<p>In contrast with the <italic>ft-2</italic> single and <italic>ft-2 tsf-1</italic> double mutants, both of which were epistatic to the <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant, the <italic>tfl1-17</italic> mutant showed an additive effect on reduction in leaf number of axillary shoots in the double mutant with <italic>brc1-2</italic> (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 7</ext-link> online). Taking this together with the results of yeast two-hybrid assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>), <italic>BRC1</italic> and <italic>TFL1</italic> are likely to act independently to suppress floral transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s8">
<title>Relationship between <italic>BRC1</italic> and Flowering-Time Genes</title>
<p>FT acts together with FD to promote floral transition in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref>. Because <italic>FD</italic> is also expressed in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abe et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Wigge et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>), it is likely that FD also has a role in floral transition of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>. Similar to the <italic>brc1-2 ft-2</italic> mutant, the <italic>brc1-2 fd-1</italic> mutant showed substantial suppression of the <italic>brc1-2</italic> phenotype in terms of the leaf number of axillary shoots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref>). This indicates that <italic>FD</italic> also acts as a promoter of the floral transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><italic>brc1</italic> and Genes Acting Downstream of Florigen.</p><p><bold>(A)</bold> Expression of <italic>FD</italic> in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> monitored by <italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic>. Longitudinal (left) and transverse (right) sections of <italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> plants grown for 18 d under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions are shown. Arrowheads indicate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> at rosette axils. Dotted lines show the outline of the tissues.</p><p><bold>(B)</bold> Number of leaves formed on the axillary shoots at the five axil positions of the wild type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) and <italic>brc1-2</italic>, <italic>fd-1</italic>, and <italic>brc1-2 fd-1</italic> mutants. Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 15). The difference significant between <italic>fd-1</italic> and <italic>brc1-2 fd-1</italic> in two-tailed multiple <italic>t</italic> test with Bonferroni correction (P &lt; 0.05) is indicated with an asterisk. ARL, axillary rosette leaves; CL, cauline leaves.</p><p><bold>(C)</bold> Relative expression levels of FT-downstream genes <italic>AP1</italic>, <italic>FUL</italic>, and <italic>SOC1</italic> after the shift from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">SD</xref> to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref>. Plants were grown for 24 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">SDs</xref> and transferred to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref>. Rosette-axil samples were analyzed (see Methods). Error bars indicate the <sc>se</sc> for three biological replicates. Differences significant in two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test (P &lt; 0.05) with respect to the wild type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) are indicated with asterisks.</p><p><bold>(D)</bold> Number of leaves formed on axillary shoots at the five axil positions of the wild type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) and <italic>brc1-2</italic>, <italic>soc1-2</italic>, and <italic>brc1-2 soc1-2</italic> mutants. Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 9). The differences significant between <italic>soc1-2</italic> and <italic>brc1-2 soc1-2</italic> in two-tailed multiple <italic>t</italic> test with Bonferroni correction (P &lt; 0.05) are indicated with asterisks.</p><p>Designation of the axil positions and classification of leaves in <bold>(B)</bold> and <bold>(D)</bold> are as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pc_109090_fig6"></graphic></fig>
<p>It was proposed that <italic>AP1</italic>, <italic>FRUITFULL</italic> (<italic>FUL</italic>), and <italic>SUPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CO1</italic> (<italic>SOC1</italic>) are downstream genes of the <italic>FT</italic>-<italic>FD</italic> floral transition pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abe et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Michaels et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Teper-Bamnolker and Samach, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Wigge et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Yoo et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Searle et al., 2006</xref>). To examine the effect of <italic>BRC1</italic> on the expression of these genes, wild-type and <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant plants were grown under noninductive <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">SD</xref> conditions and then transferred to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref>. After bolting of the main shoot, a plant section containing the axils of the rosette leaves was harvested by removing the main shoot, expanded leaves, hypocotyl, and root at three time points (13, 16, and 19 d after the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> shift) and subjected to expression analysis. Quantitative RT-PCR showed that <italic>AP1</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> were already upregulated 13 d after the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> shift in <italic>brc1-2</italic> compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). These two genes were further upregulated in <italic>brc1-2</italic> during further growth in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> but remained at a low level in the wild type. Although <italic>SOC1</italic> expression was not upregulated in <italic>brc1-2</italic> compared with the wild type at 13 d after the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> shift, a gradual increase was observed during the subsequent growth in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6C</xref>). The floral meristem identity gene <italic>LEAFY</italic> (<italic>LFY</italic>) is expressed in an <italic>FT</italic>-independent manner. Although <italic>LFY</italic> expression level was elevated in <italic>brc1-2</italic> 13 d after the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> shift, unlike <italic>AP1</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic>, subsequent upregulation did not occur at later time points (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 8</ext-link> online). These results indicate that <italic>BRC1</italic> represses photoperiod-dependent expression of <italic>FT</italic> downstream genes in axillary buds.</p>
<p><italic>SOC1</italic> functions in floral transition of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> together with <italic>FUL</italic> and other <italic>SOC1</italic>-related MADS box genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Melzer et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Dorca-Fornell et al., 2011</xref>). In accordance with this, the <italic>soc1-2</italic> mutant formed many more leaves on axillary shoots compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>). Nevertheless, the <italic>soc1-2</italic> mutation only partially suppressed the phenotype of the <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6D</xref>). These results suggest that, unlike the cases of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>TSF</italic>, the <italic>brc1-2</italic> phenotype is not fully dependent on <italic>SOC1</italic> function.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s9">
<title><italic>BRC1</italic> Can Delay Floral Transition When Expressed in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref></title>
<p>The observations described so far indicate that <italic>BRC1</italic> has a role in preventing <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> from undergoing early floral transition. The abilities of FT to be transported into the axillary buds and to interact with BRC1 suggest that <italic>BRC1</italic> is likely to act through inhibition of <italic>FT</italic> function. This raises the possibility that <italic>BRC1</italic> could delay the floral transition of the main shoot when expressed ectopically in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref>. To test this possibility, the flowering-time phenotype of transgenic plants expressing <italic>BRC1</italic> in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref> under the control of the <italic>FD</italic> promoter (<italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>BRC1</italic>) was examined. As expected, <italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>BRC1</italic> plants showed significant delay in floral transition of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref> under inductive <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>; see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 9</ext-link> online). Previously, it was shown that overexpression of <italic>BRC1</italic> under the control of cauliflower mosaic virus 35S promoter resulted in pleiotropic developmental defects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>). In this study, <italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>BRC1</italic> plants showed mild retarded growth in early developmental stages but no obvious morphological alterations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>). In <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">SD</xref>, the effect of <italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>BRC1</italic> was more subtle (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 10</ext-link> online).</p>
<fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Ectopic Expression of <italic>BRC1</italic> Delays Floral Transition in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref>.</p><p><bold>(A)</bold> Thirty-day-old plants of wild type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) and two independent lines of <italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>BRC1</italic> (#1 and #2) grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref>.</p><p><bold>(B)</bold> Flowering time measured by the number of rosette leaves (RL) and cauline leaves (CL). Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 15). The differences significant in two-tailed Dunnett&#x2019;s test (P &lt; 0.01) in the total leaf numbers with respect to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref> are indicated with asterisks.</p><p>[See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pc_109090_fig7"></graphic></fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s10" sec-type="discussion">
<title>DISCUSSION</title>
<p>In this study, we showed that the BRC1 interacts with FT. BRC1 interacts also with TSF, whereas it did not interact with TFL1. This establishes BRC1 as an interactor specific to the FT clade of PEBP/RKIP proteins. Our study indicates that FT protein expressed in the leaf is transported into the axillary bud and promotes floral transition of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AM</xref>. BRC1 expressed in the axillary bud interacts with FT to inhibit its function. Thus, <italic>BRC1</italic>, previously proposed to be an integrator of branching signals within the axillary buds, plays a role in modulating the activity of a long-distance florigen signal to delay floral transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>.</p>
<sec id="s11">
<title>FT Is Able to Interact with Various TFs</title>
<p>Yeast two-hybrid screening using <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TF</xref> libraries revealed numerous candidate FT-interacting proteins. Although the functional significances of these interactions are beyond the scope of this study, it is to be noted that some of the candidates obtained here overlapped with recently reported candidates for interactors of FT and related proteins. Yeast two-hybrid screening using a cDNA library from inflorescence meristems, floral meristems, and floral buds identified bZIP52, TCP8, TCP15, and TCP22 as candidates to interact with FT in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Liu et al., 2012</xref>). Yeast two-hybrid screening with Md-FT1, a homolog of FT in apple (<italic>Malus</italic> &#x00D7; <italic>domestica</italic>) showed that Md-VOZ1, Md-TCP2, and Md-TCP4 (belonging to the same clade as At-VOZ1, At-TCP2 and 24, and At-TCP3 and 4, respectively) interact with Md-FT1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Mimida et al., 2011</xref>). Given the repeated identification in separate screenings, these TCP, bZIP, and VOZ proteins are promising candidates for factors acting with FT protein.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s12">
<title>BRC1 Interacts with FT and TSF Proteins without Mediation by 14-3-3 Proteins</title>
<p>We identified BRC1 as specifically interacting with FT and TSF, but not with TFL1. By contrast, many of the previously reported FT interactors showed interaction with TFL1 as well. For example, FD and FD PARALOG interact with both FT/TSF and TFL1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abe et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Wigge et al., 2005</xref>). Tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) SELF-PRUNING&#x2013;interacting proteins (SPAK, SIP4, and SPGB) and maize FD homolog DELAYED FLOWERING also interact with FT clade and TFL1 clade proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Pnueli et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Danilevskaya et al., 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">2010</xref>). For some FT interactors, such as FT-INTERACTING PROTEIN1 and other factors from the screening mentioned above, it remains to be examined whether they interact with TFL1 clade proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Mimida et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Liu et al., 2012</xref>). FT clade and TFL1 clade proteins seem to share common interactors through the mediation of 14-3-3 proteins. FT and TFL1 share the ability to interact with a common subset of 14-3-3 isoforms (e.g., GRF3) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1A</xref>). In rice, 14-3-3 proteins mediate the formation of the Hd3a-FD1 (corresponding to FT-FD in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>) complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Taoka et al., 2011</xref>). In tomato, the SELF-PRUNING&#x2013;interacting factors mentioned above also interact with 14-3-3 proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Pnueli et al., 2001</xref>). By contrast, BRC1 does not seem to require 14-3-3 proteins for interaction with FT.</p>
<p>It is likely that FT interacts with a variety of proteins using 14-3-3 proteins as a hub. Here, bZIP30 was found to be a putative 14-3-3&#x2013;dependent FT interactor, whereas other candidates seemed to be independent of 14-3-3 proteins (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 1</ext-link> online). These observations indicate that interaction mediated by 14-3-3 is not the only way in which FT interacts with TFs, raising the possibility that the protein complex containing FT has more components than known at the moment. Another possibility is that FT uses different sets of partners in different cells or for different functions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s13">
<title><italic>BRC1</italic> Is a Negative Regulator of Floral Transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref></title>
<p>FT acts as a systemic flowering signal (florigen) and moves from the leaves to the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Corbesier et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Jaeger and Wigge, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Lin et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Mathieu et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Tamaki et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Notaguchi et al., 2008</xref>). FT protein expressed under the <italic>HSP18.2</italic> promoter in a single leaf also moved into the subtending axillary bud (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). In addition, <italic>ft-2</italic> mutants showed delayed floral transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). Taken together, these findings demonstrate that <italic>FT</italic> is a key regulator of floral transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> as well as in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref>. Recent work showed that <italic>FT</italic> is involved in the regulation of axillary shoot elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hiraoka et al., 2013</xref>), indicating that <italic>FT</italic> has an additional role in axillary buds after the transition.</p>
<p>On the other hand, <italic>BRC1</italic> was previously proposed to be an integrating repressor of axillary bud development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>). <italic>BRC1</italic> suppresses the initiation, differentiation, and elongation of axillary buds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Finlayson, 2007</xref>). In this study, the <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant showed a reduction in the number of leaves on axillary shoots, as was, in part, reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Finlayson et al., 2010</xref>), and earlier onset of <italic>AP1</italic> expression in the axillary buds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). Furthermore, when ectopically expressed in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref>, <italic>BRC1</italic> delayed floral transition of the main shoot, with an increase in the number of leaves formed on the main axis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>). These observations, taken together, strongly suggest that <italic>BRC1</italic> acts as a negative regulator of the floral transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>.</p>
<p>Since BRC1 protein interacts with FT and TSF proteins, and <italic>brc1</italic> and <italic>ft</italic> (<italic>tsf</italic>) mutants showed opposite phenotypes in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>, BRC1 and FT play antagonistic roles likely through their protein&#x2013;protein interaction. Genetic analyses indicated that the <italic>ft-2</italic> and <italic>tsf-1</italic> mutations are epistatic to <italic>brc1-2</italic>, suggesting that <italic>BRC1</italic> inhibits <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>TSF</italic> functions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>). This is supported by the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">SD</xref>-to-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> shift transcript profiling experiment, where genes downstream of <italic>FT</italic> were overinduced in the <italic>brc1-2</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
<p>TFL1 also antagonizes FT function, but through competitive interaction with the common partner, FD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bradley et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abe et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Wigge et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hanano and Goto, 2011</xref>). Under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions, when florigen activity is high, the main (primary) inflorescence of the <italic>tfl1</italic> mutant makes only a few flowers and terminates soon after bolting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Shannon and Meeks-Wagner, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Alvarez et al., 1992</xref>). In addition, <italic>TFL1</italic> is expressed in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> as well as in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAM</xref>, and some axillary shoots are replaced by solitary flowers in <italic>tfl1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Shannon and Meeks-Wagner, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Alvarez et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bradley et al., 1997</xref>), indicating <italic>TFL1</italic> is also involved in the suppression of phase transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>. However, BRC1 showed no interaction with TFL1, and the <italic>tfl1-17 brc1-2</italic> double mutant showed an additive reduction in the leaf number of axillary shoots under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">SD</xref> conditions (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 7</ext-link> online). These results suggest that <italic>TFL1</italic> and <italic>BRC1</italic> act independently.</p>
<p>Although the mechanism by which <italic>BRC1</italic> modulates the activity of <italic>FT/TSF</italic> remains to be clarified, the observation that FT interacts with BRC1 through a different region than the 14-3-3 protein interaction surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>) supports the possibility that BRC1 binds to the FT/14-3-3/FD complex. In the deduced structure of the FT/14-3-3/FD complex based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Taoka et al. (2011)</xref>, the positioning of the region of FT responsible for interaction with BRC1 would allow binding of BRC1 to the complex (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Figure 11</ext-link> online). If this is the case, BRC1 could inhibit the transcriptional activator function of the FT/14-3-3/FD complex. However, the possibility that BRC1 traps FT and prevents it from interacting with 14-3-3 proteins cannot be excluded.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s14">
<title>Possible Conservation of the Antagonistic Mechanism between <italic>BRC1</italic> and <italic>FT</italic></title>
<p>The <italic>BRC1</italic>-like and <italic>FT</italic>-like genes seem to be conserved among species. <italic>BRC1</italic> was first identified as a maize <italic>Tb1</italic> ortholog in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Finlayson, 2007</xref>). Similar to the phenotype of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> <italic>brc1</italic> mutants, maize <italic>tb1</italic> mutants show increased numbers of elongated axillary shoots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Doebley et al., 1995</xref>). Based on comparative genomics and expression analysis, it was suggested that <italic>Zea mays CENTRORADIALIS8</italic> (<italic>ZCN8</italic>) is a maize counterpart of <italic>FT</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Danilevskaya et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Meng et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lazakis et al., 2011</xref>). The <italic>FD</italic> orthologous gene Zm-<italic>DLF1</italic> was also identified. Mutation in Zm-<italic>DLF1</italic> resulted in a late-flowering phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Muszynski et al., 2006</xref>). Zm-ZCN8 interacts with Zm-DLF1, indicating that the FT-FD flowering activator complex is also conserved in maize. <italic>TB1/FINE CULM1</italic> from rice is orthologous to Zm-<italic>Tb1</italic>, and the <italic>fc1</italic> mutant shows enhanced tillering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Takeda et al., 2003</xref>). Os-Hd3a (an FT ortholog) and Os-FD1 interact with each other and promote floral transition in rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Taoka et al., 2011</xref>). The tomato <italic>BRC1b</italic> and <italic>SINGLE FLOWER TRUSS</italic> genes, <italic>BRC1</italic> and <italic>FT</italic> orthologs, respectively, were also characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Lifschitz et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mart&#x00ED;n-Trillo et al., 2011</xref>). These studies suggest that there is functional conservation of the <italic>FT</italic>-like and <italic>BRC1</italic>-like genes as florigens and integrators of the axillary bud development, respectively. Our study proposes that these two pathways interact in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. It is worth investigating whether <italic>BRC1</italic>-like genes have conserved function in regulation of floral transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> and whether FT-like and BRC1-like proteins interact with each other in these species.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s15">
<title>The Significance of Regulating <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AM</xref> Floral Transition with Florigen and <italic>BRC1</italic></title>
<p>In wild-type <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, not all axillary buds elongate, and in <italic>ProAP1</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> plants, buds formed at lower axils remain vegetative for longer after bolting of the main shoot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>). This may contribute to preventing existent buds from elongating simultaneously and preparing for future alterations in environmental and autonomous conditions.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AM</xref>-specific modulation of florigen activity by BRC1 might be more important under adverse growth conditions, when flowering is accelerated. For example, an increased number of neighboring plants leads to a change in light quality to a low ratio of red to far-red radiation (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Smith, 1982</xref>). When plants grow under far-red-rich light, <italic>FT</italic>, as an integrator gene of the flowering pathway, is upregulated and induces premature floral transition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Devlin et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Endo et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Sessa et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Wollenberg et al., 2008</xref>). On the other hand, expression of <italic>BRC1</italic> is also increased by a high planting density and in <italic>phyB</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Finlayson et al., 2010</xref>). Although overproduced FT protein potentially activates the developmental program in undesirable parts of the plant, such as <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>, increased levels of BRC1 will suppress florigen activity specifically in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> and thus enable the plant to concentrate its limited resources on the main shoot and promote reproductive success. Regulation of <italic>FT</italic> expression by environmental and internal signals is well studied (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Simpson and Dean, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Boss et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Fornara et al., 2010</xref>), and expression of <italic>BRC1</italic> is also affected by external and hormonal cues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Finlayson, 2007</xref>). These signals would converge to create a balance between FT and BRC1 and regulate floral transition in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref>. This additional mode of regulation in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">AMs</xref> enables modulation of the timing of axillary bud differentiation and thus determines plant architecture depending on external and internal conditions.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="s16" sec-type="methods">
<title>METHODS</title>
<sec id="s17">
<title>Plant Materials and Growth Conditions</title>
<p><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> Columbia-0 (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col</xref>) was used as the wild type. The <italic>ProAP1</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> reporter (<italic>POP40</italic>) was kindly provided by M.F. Yanofsky (University of California at San Diego). The T-DNA insertion mutant <italic>brc1-2</italic> (<italic>tbl1-1</italic>) was obtained from the ABRC and corresponds to the line SALK_091920 previously characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Finlayson, 2007</xref>). Plant materials below were previously described: <italic>gFT</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Notaguchi et al., 2008</xref>), <italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abe et al., 2005</xref>), <italic>ft-2</italic> (Imura et al., 2011<!-- Q4 -->), <italic>fd-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abe et al., 2005</xref>), and <italic>soc1-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lee et al., 2000</xref>). <italic>ProHSP18.2</italic>:<italic>FT-EGFP</italic> was constructed by fusing a promoter fragment (&#x2212;853 to &#x2212;1, relative to ATG) of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> <italic>HSP18.2</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Takahashi and Komeda, 1989</xref>) with the <italic>FT-EGFP</italic> open reading frame (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ORF</xref>). <italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>BRC1</italic> was constructed based on the previously described <italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> construct (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abe et al., 2005</xref>) by replacing the <italic>GUS</italic> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ORF</xref> with the <italic>BRC1</italic> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ORF</xref>. Seeds were stratified by keeping them at 4&#x00B0;C for 2 to 4 d and then transferred to 22&#x00B0;C <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> (16 h light/8 h dark) with white fluorescent light (&#x223C;80 &#x03BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">SD</xref> (8 h light/16 h dark) with white fluorescent light (&#x223C;100 &#x03BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) conditions. For analyses of the axillary shoot phenotypes and FT protein movement, plants were grown on vermiculite. Developmental stages of the axillary buds were determined according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez et al. (2007)</xref>. Observations were made on the days when the individual plant first showed a visible floral bud (before bolting), reached 1 cm in height (1 cm bolting), and reached 5 cm in height (5 cm bolting). The leaf number of the axillary shoot was counted after internode elongation. Leaves at the base of the axillary shoot without a visible elongated stem were counted as axillary rosette leaves and leaves on the elongated shoots as cauline leaves. For expression analyses, plants were grown on half-strength Murashige and Skoog medium supplemented with 0.5% Suc and 0.8% agar.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s18">
<title>Plasmid Constructs</title>
<p>Plasmid constructs used in this study and primers used for cloning are described in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Tables 2 and 3</ext-link> online.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s19">
<title>Yeast Two-Hybrid Assay</title>
<p>For the first yeast two-hybrid screening, a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TF</xref> library containing 1729 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TFs</xref> was used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Pruneda-Paz et al., 2009</xref>). The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ORF</xref> of the full-length FT protein was cloned in pENTR/D-TOPO (Life Technologies) and then transferred to pDEST32 (Life Technologies) using LR recombination reaction. The <italic>lacZ</italic> activity was measured by &#x03B2;-galactosidase assay. For the second screening and two-hybrid assays, the <italic>FT</italic> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ORF</xref> was cloned in pCUY vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Suzuki et al., 2001</xref>). A <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TF</xref> library containing 1503 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">TFs</xref> constructed in pDEST_GAD424 was described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Mitsuda et al., 2010</xref>). Plasmids isolated from positive colonies were transformed into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (DH5&#x03B1;) for sequencing. The interaction was confirmed after retransformation of yeast. pCUY and pGAD424 (Clontech/TAKARA) were used for construction of the other yeast two-hybrid constructs. The appropriate plasmids were transformed into a yeast strain AH109 (Clontech/Takara) using the lithium acetate method and selected on synthetic dropout medium plates lacking Leu and Trp. After 3 or 4 d of incubation at 30&#x00B0;C, yeast cells were transferred to liquid synthetic dropout medium lacking Leu and Trp and incubated for 24 h. After measuring OD<sub>600</sub>, 1 mL of each culture was centrifuged and resuspended in TE buffer, pH 7.4, to a final OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.33. Five microliters of suspended yeast was spotted on synthetic dropout medium lacking Leu, Trp, and His for the His requirement test (&#x2212;His). 3-Amino-1,2,4-triazole (0.5 mM) was added to the medium for prevention of nonspecific growth, where specified (&#x2212;His+3-AT). As positive controls, yeast cells were also spotted on synthetic dropout medium lacking Leu and Trp (+His). These plates were incubated at 30&#x00B0;C and scored for growth of the yeast cells. To visualize the location of the residues important for protein interaction, an FT ribbon model was produced using Pymol (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pymol.org">http://www.pymol.org</ext-link>) from the Protein Data Bank<!-- Q5 --> file (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Ahn et al., 2006</xref>; Protein Data Bank ID 1WKP).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s20">
<title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">BiFC</xref> Assay in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> Leaf Epidermal Cells</title>
<p>A split EYFP fragment encoding the N-terminal fragment of EYFP (YN; 1 to 155 amino acids) was cloned into pBI121 vector and then <italic>BRC1</italic> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ORF</xref> was inserted in frame after the YN to make YN-BRC1. Other constructs (FT-YC, YN, and YC in pBI121) were described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abe et al., 2005</xref>). <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> plants were grown under continuous light conditions at 23&#x00B0;C. <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain pMP90 containing an appropriate construct was grown at 28&#x00B0;C in L-broth to the stationary phase. Bacterial cells were harvested by centrifugation and resuspended in 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 10 &#x03BC;g/mL acetosyringone (Wako) and left for 3 h at room temperature. The bacterial suspensions were infiltrated into the abaxial air spaces of leaves of 2- to 4-week-old plants using 1-mL syringes. Plants were kept for 36 h after the infiltration in continuous light conditions at 23&#x00B0;C. Complemented EYFP fluorescence was excited at 515 nm by an argon laser and detected in a range from 530 to 630 nm with confocal laser scanning microscopy (FV1000; Olympus).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s21">
<title>In Vitro Pull-Down Assay</title>
<p>The <italic>BRC1</italic> full-length <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ORF</xref> was cloned into pET41a (Novagen), and <italic>FT</italic> full-length <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ORF</xref> was cloned into pET24d (Novagen). The plasmids were transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) to express glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase (GST)-BRC1 and T7-FT, respectively. pET41a empty vector was used to express <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">GST</xref>. For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">GST</xref> pull-down assays, GST-BRC1 or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">GST</xref> bacterial lysate was incubated with Glutathione Sepharose 4B beads (GE Healthcare), then 20 &#x03BC;L of the slurry (50% [w/v]) was mixed with 10 &#x03BC;L of T7-FT bacterial lysate and 220 &#x03BC;L of NETN buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, and 0.5% Nonidet P-40) and was gently stirred at 4&#x00B0;C for 2 h. The beads were washed thoroughly with the NETN buffer five times and subjected to SDS-PAGE and immunoblot analyses. T7-FT protein was detected with anti-T7 antibody (Novagen) and visualized using ECL plus (GE Healthcare) with Image Quant LAS 4000mini (GE Healthcare).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s22">
<title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GUS</xref> Staining</title>
<p>Plants were fixed for 15 min in 90% acetone on ice and washed in PBS buffer twice. Fixed samples were incubated at 37&#x00B0;C for &#x223C;16 h with staining solution (0.5 mg/mL X-Gluc, 50 mM sodium phosphate buffer, pH 7.0, 0.5 mM potassium ferrocyanide, 0.5 mM potassium ferricyanide, and 0.2% TritonX-100). For resin sectioning, samples were dehydrated through an ethanol series and embedded in Technovit 7100 (Heraeus Kulzer) and sectioned at a thickness of 5 &#x03BC;m with a microtome (RM2155; Leica). The <italic>ProAP1</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> plant was observed with microscopy, and the number of stained buds was counted.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s23">
<title>Single-Leaf Heat Treatment and Fluorescence Microscopy</title>
<p><italic>ProHSP18.2</italic>:<italic>FT-EGFP</italic> plants grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions for 22 d were subjected to single-leaf heat treatment essentially as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Notaguchi et al., 2008</xref>). The leaf blade of the sixth leaf was exposed to 37&#x00B0;C for 2 h by placing it in the water-filled space between a heated copper plate and a slide glass to ensure good contact. Twenty-four hours after heat treatment, plants were embedded in 4% agar gel with PBS and sectioned at a thickness of 80 &#x03BC;m with a vibratome (VIB-1500; Intracel). GFP fluorescence was excited at 488 nm by an argon laser and detected in a range from 500 to 600 nm with confocal laser scanning microscopy (FV1000; Olympus).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s24">
<title>Quantitative RT-PCR Analysis</title>
<p>Plants grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">SD</xref> for 24 d were transferred to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> and harvested after 13, 16, and 19 d. Rosette-axil samples were obtained by removing the main shoot, leaves, hypocotyl, and root. Total RNA was extracted using TRIzol reagent (Life Technologies) and treated with DNase I Amplification Grade (Life Technologies) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. Total RNA (0.5 &#x03BC;g) was reverse transcribed in a 20-&#x03BC;L reaction mixture using Transcriptor (Roche Applied Science). The resultant cDNA solution was diluted with 30 volumes of water, and 3-&#x03BC;L aliquots were analyzed. Quantitative RT-PCR analyses were performed with the CFX96 system (Bio-Rad Laboratories) using SYBR green I. The primers used are described in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1">Supplemental Table 4</ext-link> online. Quantitative RT-PCR results were normalized to the geometric means of <italic>ASCORBATE PEROXIDASE3</italic> (<italic>APX3</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hazen et al., 2005</xref>), <italic>REGULATORY PARTICLE TRIPLE-A 1A</italic> (<italic>RPT1a</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Michael et al., 2008</xref>), and <italic>THIOREDOXIN H-TYPE3</italic> (<italic>TRX3</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Michael et al., 2008</xref>) and shown as the average of nine different reactions (biological &#x00D7; technical triplicate). Internal control genes used in this study were selected from nine genes according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Vandesompele et al. (2002)</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s25">
<title>Accession Numbers</title>
<p>Arabidopsis Genome Initiative locus identifiers for genes mentioned in this article are as follows: At3g18550 (<italic>BRC1</italic>), At1g65480 (<italic>FT</italic>), At1g68800 (<italic>BRC2</italic>), At4g20370 (<italic>TSF</italic>), At5g03840 (<italic>TFL1</italic>), At5g38480 (<italic>GRF3</italic>), At2g21230 (<italic>bZIP30</italic>), At4g35900 (<italic>FD</italic>), At1g69120 (<italic>AP1</italic>), At5g60910 (<italic>FUL</italic>), At2g45660 (<italic>SOC1</italic>), At5g61850 (<italic>LFY</italic>), At4g35000 (<italic>APX3</italic>), At1g53750 (<italic>RPT1a</italic>), At5g42980 (<italic>TRX3</italic>), At5g59720 (<italic>HSP18.2</italic>), At1g06850 (<italic>bZIP52</italic>), At4g18390 (<italic>TCP2</italic>), At1g53230 (<italic>TCP3</italic>), At3g15030 (<italic>TCP4</italic>), At1g58100 (<italic>TCP8</italic>), At1g69690 (<italic>TCP15</italic>), At1g72010 (<italic>TCP22</italic>), and At4g18390 (<italic>TCP24</italic>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="s26">
<title>Supplemental Data</title>
<p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p>
<list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure 1.</bold></ext-link> Yeast Two-Hybrid Assay between FT and Putative FT-Interacting Proteins.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure 2.</bold></ext-link> Yeast Two-Hybrid Assay between FT and BRC1 Fragments.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure 3.</bold></ext-link> Yeast Two-Hybrid Assay between Ala-Scanned Mutant FT Proteins and BRC1 or GRF3.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure 4.</bold></ext-link> Expression Analysis Using FT-GUS Fusion Protein.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure 5.</bold></ext-link> Heat Treatment of Leaf Blades of <italic>ProHSP18.2</italic>:<italic>FT-EGFP</italic> Plants.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure 6.</bold></ext-link> Complementation Test of the <italic>brc1-2</italic> Mutant Using a Genomic Fragment of <italic>BRC1</italic>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure 7.</bold></ext-link> <italic>BRC1</italic> and <italic>TFL1</italic> Likely Act Independently in the Regulation of Floral Transition of Axillary Shoots.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure 8.</bold></ext-link> Relative Expression of <italic>LFY</italic> after a Shift from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">SD</xref> to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure 9.</bold></ext-link> Relative Expression of <italic>BRC1</italic> in <italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>BRC1</italic> Plants.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure 10.</bold></ext-link> Flowering-Time Phenotype of <italic>ProFD</italic>:<italic>BRC1</italic> Grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">SD</xref>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure 11.</bold></ext-link> Amino Acid Residues Essential for the Interaction with BRC1 Shown on a Ribbon Model of FT in the Complex with 14-3-3 Protein and FD.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table 1.</bold></ext-link> List of Candidate FT-Interacting Proteins Obtained from Yeast Two-Hybrid Screening of the Kay Lab Transcription Factor Library.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table 2.</bold></ext-link> Constructs.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table 3.</bold></ext-link> Primers Used in Plasmid Construction.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantcell.org/cgi/content/full/tpc.112.109090/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table 4.</bold></ext-link> Primers Used in qRT-PCR.</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank M.F. Yanofsky (University of California at San Diego) for <italic>POP40</italic> seeds and the ABRC for <italic>brc1-2</italic> seeds. We also thank Ayako Yamaguchi for discussion and<!-- Q6 --> Yuki Tomita and Fumie Tobe for excellent technical assistance. This work was supported by Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research on Priority Areas (19060012 and 19060016 to T.A.) from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology of Japan, Grants-in-Aid for the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science Fellows (22-6127 to M.N.), a Grant-in-Aid for Young Scientists (B) (21770064 to N.M.) from the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science, Mitsubishi Foundation (to T.A.), and National Institutes of Health Grants GM56006, GM67837, and GM092412 (to S.A.K.).</p>
</ack>
<ack>
<title>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</title>
<p>M.N., Y.D., S.A.K., M.O.-T., M.E., and T.A. designed the research. M.N., K.K., Y.D., A.H., J.L.P.-P., G.B., and N.M. performed research. M.N., J.L.P.-P, G.B, M.E., and T.A. analyzed data. M.N. and T.A. wrote the article.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group><fn id="fn1"><label>[C]</label><p>Some figures in this article are displayed in color online but in black and white in the print edition.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>Online version contains Web-only data.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn3"><label>[OA]</label><p>Open Access articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<fn-group>
<title>AUTHOR QUERIES</title>
<fn id="Q1" fn-type="other"><p>ASPB journals now support the ORCID ID program which provides you with a unique digital identifier.&#x00A0; If you have an ORCID ID, please provide it in your response to queries about this article.&#x00A0; If you do not have an ORCID ID, you can find more information about ORCID and register for an ID at https://orcid.org/register.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q2" fn-type="other"><p>Please confirm that Dr. Araki will be responsible for the distribution of materials.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q3" fn-type="other"><p>Is &#x201C;14-3-3 p.s.i.&#x201D; correct here? Please amend if needed.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q4" fn-type="other"><p>The in-text citation &quot;Imura et al., 2011&quot; is not in the reference list. Please correct the citation, add the reference to the list, or delete the citation.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q5" fn-type="other"><p>Please verify that all websites listed in the article are accessible.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q6" fn-type="other"><p>For consistency, please provide the affiliations for all those mentioned in Acknowledgments.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q7" fn-type="other"><p>Reference &quot;Imura, et al., 2012&quot; is not cited in the text. Please add an in-text citation or delete the reference.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q8" fn-type="other"><p>Reference &quot;Kardailsky, et al., 1999&quot; is not cited in the text. Please add an in-text citation or delete the reference.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q9" fn-type="other"><p>Reference &quot;Kobayashi, et al., 1999&quot; is not cited in the text. Please add an in-text citation or delete the reference.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q10" fn-type="other"><p>What do the &#x201C;A&#x201D; and &#x201C;C&#x201D; represent here?</p></fn></fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daimon</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichinoki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Notaguchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>FD, a bZIP protein mediating signals from the floral pathway integrator FT at the shoot apex</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>1052</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1056</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguilar-Mart&#x00ED;nez</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poza-Carri&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cubas</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> BRANCHED1 acts as an integrator of branching signals within axillary buds</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>458</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>472</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>V.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banfield</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henz</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A divergent external loop confers antagonistic activity on floral regulators FT and TFL1</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>614</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide insertional mutagenesis of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>301</volume>: <fpage>653</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>657</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title><italic>terminal flower</italic>: A gene affecting inflorescence development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>116</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boss</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastow</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mylne</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Multiple pathways in the decision to flower: Enabling, promoting, and resetting</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume> (<supplement>suppl.</supplement>): <fpage>S18</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>S31</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratcliffe</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Inflorescence commitment and architecture in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>275</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dun</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rameau</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Strigolactone acts downstream of auxin to regulate bud outgrowth in pea and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source> <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>482</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>493</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbesier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giakountis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrona</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gissot</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>FT protein movement contributes to long-distance signaling in floral induction of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>316</volume>: <fpage>1030</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1033</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieberer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hepworth</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Domagalska</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Strigolactones enhance competition between shoot branches by dampening auxin transport</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>2905</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2913</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danilevskaya</surname><given-names>O.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ananiev</surname><given-names>E.V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Concerted modification of flowering time and inflorescence architecture by ectopic expression of TFL1-like genes in maize</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source> <volume>153</volume>: <fpage>238</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>251</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danilevskaya</surname><given-names>O.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ananiev</surname><given-names>E.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A genomic and expression compendium of the expanded PEBP gene family from maize</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source> <volume>146</volume>: <fpage>250</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>264</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>A genomic analysis of the shade avoidance response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>1617</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1629</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doebley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stec</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustus</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>teosinte branched1 and the origin of maize: Evidence for epistasis and the evolution of dominance</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>141</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>346</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doebley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stec</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The evolution of apical dominance in maize</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>386</volume>: <fpage>485</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>488</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorca-Fornell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregis</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kater</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SOC1-like genes AGL42, AGL71 and AGL72 promote flowering in the shoot apical and axillary meristems</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>1006</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1017</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dun</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Apical dominance and shoot branching. Divergent opinions or divergent mechanisms?</article-title> <source>Plant Physiol.</source> <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>812</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>819</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Floyd</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawker</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Izhaki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Radial patterning of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> shoots by class III HD-ZIP and KANADI genes</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1768</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1774</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagatani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Phytochrome B in the mesophyll delays flowering by suppressing FLOWERING LOCUS T expression in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> vascular bundles</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1941</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1952</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Teosinte Branched1-like 1 regulates axillary bud outgrowth and is homologous to monocot Teosinte Branched1</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>667</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>677</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnareddy</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kebrom</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casal</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Phytochrome regulation of branching in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source> <volume>152</volume>: <fpage>1914</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1927</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="other"><bold>Fornara, F., de Montaigu, A., and Coupland, G.</bold> (2010). SnapShot: Control of flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Cell <bold>141:</bold> 550, 550.e551&#x2013;552.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez-Roldan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Strigolactone inhibition of shoot branching</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>455</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>194</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grbi&#x0107;</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleecker</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>An altered body plan is conferred on <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants carrying dominant alleles of two genes</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>2395</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2403</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greb</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarenz</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Theres</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Molecular analysis of the LATERAL SUPPRESSOR gene in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> reveals a conserved control mechanism for axillary meristem formation</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1187</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanano</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> TERMINAL FLOWER1 is involved in the regulation of flowering time and inflorescence development through transcriptional repression</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3172</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3184</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazen</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>T.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruneda-Paz</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borevitz</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>LUX ARRHYTHMO encodes a Myb domain protein essential for circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>10387</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10392</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hempel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Bidirectional inflorescence development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: Acropetal initiation of flowers and basipetal initiation of paraclades</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>192</volume>: <fpage>276</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>286</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hempel</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandel</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ditta</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zambryski</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Floral determination and expression of floral regulatory genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>3845</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3853</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiraoka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The florigen genes FT and TSF modulate lateral shoot outgrowth in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>352</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>368</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Furutani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasaka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>CRYPTIC PRECOCIOUS/MED12 is a novel flowering regulator with multiple target steps in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>303</lpage>.</citation></ref><!-- Q7 -->
<ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigge</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>FT protein acts as a long-range signal in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1050</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1054</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kardailsky</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagenais</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Activation tagging of the floral inducer FT</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>1962</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1965</lpage>.</citation></ref><!-- Q8 -->
<ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doerner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> REGULATOR OF AXILLARY MERISTEMS1 controls a leaf axil stem cell niche and modulates vegetative development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>598</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>611</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwabuchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>A pair of related genes with antagonistic roles in mediating flowering signals</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>1960</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1962</lpage>.</citation></ref><!-- Q9 -->
<ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazakis</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coneva</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colasanti</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>ZCN8 encodes a potential orthologue of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> FT florigen that integrates both endogenous and photoperiod flowering signals in maize</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>4833</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4842</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The AGAMOUS-LIKE 20 MADS domain protein integrates floral inductive pathways in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2366</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2376</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lifschitz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eviatar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalit</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldshmidt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amsellem</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The tomato FT ortholog triggers systemic signals that regulate growth and flowering and substitute for diverse environmental stimuli</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>6398</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6403</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belanger</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varkonyi-Gasic</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taoka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xoconostle-C&#x00E1;zares</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gendler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phinney</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lough</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>FLOWERING LOCUS T protein may act as the long-distance florigenic signal in the cucurbits</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1488</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1506</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>FTIP1 is an essential regulator required for florigen transport</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol.</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e1001313</fpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;n-Trillo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grand&#x00ED;o</surname><given-names>E.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x00ED;guez-Buey</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Theres</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bendahmane</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dopazo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cubas</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Role of tomato BRANCHED1-like genes in the control of shoot branching</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>701</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>714</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warthmann</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x00FC;ttner</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Export of FT protein from phloem companion cells is sufficient for floral induction in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1055</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1060</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melzer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lens</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gennen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanneste</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beeckman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Flowering-time genes modulate meristem determinacy and growth form in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet.</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1489</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1492</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muszynski</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Danilevskaya</surname><given-names>O.N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The FT-like ZCN8 gene functions as a floral activator and is involved in photoperiod sensitivity in maize</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>942</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>960</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Network discovery pipeline elucidates conserved time-of-day-specific cis-regulatory modules</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet.</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e14</fpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Himelblau</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schomburg</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Integration of flowering signals in winter-annual <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>156</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mimida</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwanami</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moriya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Voogd</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varkonyi-Gasic</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotoda</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Apple FLOWERING LOCUS T proteins interact with transcription factors implicated in cell growth and organ development</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiol.</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>566</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitsuda</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takiguchi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshizumi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohme-Takagi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Efficient yeast one-/two-hybrid screening using a library composed only of transcription factors in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>2145</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2151</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muszynski</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dam</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirbroun</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruggemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Archibald</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ananiev</surname><given-names>E.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Danilevskaya</surname><given-names>O.N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>delayed flowering1 encodes a basic leucine zipper protein that mediates floral inductive signals at the shoot apex in maize</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source> <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>1523</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1536</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Theres</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Blind homologous R2R3 Myb genes control the pattern of lateral meristem initiation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>586</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>597</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Notaguchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daimon</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Long-distance, graft-transmissible action of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> FLOWERING LOCUS T protein to promote flowering</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1645</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1658</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pnueli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutfinger</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hareven</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Naim</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adir</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lifschitz</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Tomato SP-interacting proteins define a conserved signaling system that regulates shoot architecture and flowering</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>2687</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2702</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pruneda-Paz</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Para</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A functional genomics approach reveals CHE as a component of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>323</volume>: <fpage>1481</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1485</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Theres</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The Lateral suppressor (Ls) gene of tomato encodes a new member of the VHIID protein family</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>290</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>295</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turck</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x00F6;ber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The transcription factor FLC confers a flowering response to vernalization by repressing meristem competence and systemic signaling in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>898</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>912</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sessa</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carabelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciolfi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Possenti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittempergher</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morelli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruberti</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A dynamic balance between gene activation and repression regulates the shade avoidance response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2811</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2815</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meeks-Wagner</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>A mutation in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> TFL1 gene affects inflorescence meristem development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>877</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>892</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the Rosetta stone of flowering time?</article-title> <source>Science</source> <volume>296</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>289</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Light quality, photoperception, and plant strategy</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Plant Physiol.</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>481</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>518</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Two types of putative nuclear factors that physically interact with histidine-containing phosphotransfer (Hpt) domains, signaling mediators in His-to-Asp phosphorelay, in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Terminal flower2, an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homolog of heterochromatin protein1, counteracts the activation of flowering locus T by constans in the vascular tissues of leaves to regulate flowering time</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2856</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2865</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Komeda</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Characterization of two genes encoding small heat-shock proteins in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol. Gen. Genet.</source> <volume>219</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>372</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suwa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The OsTB1 gene negatively regulates lateral branching in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>520</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talbert</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>H.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Comai</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The REVOLUTA gene is necessary for apical meristem development and for limiting cell divisions in the leaves and stems of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>2723</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2735</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamaki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimamoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Hd3a protein is a mobile flowering signal in rice</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>316</volume>: <fpage>1033</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1036</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taoka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>14-3-3 proteins act as intracellular receptors for rice Hd3a florigen</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>476</volume>: <fpage>332</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>335</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teper-Bamnolker</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samach</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The flowering integrator FT regulates SEPALLATA3 and FRUITFULL accumulation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> leaves</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>2661</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2675</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umehara</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanada</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arite</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda-Kamiya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magome</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirasu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyozuka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Inhibition of shoot branching by new terpenoid plant hormones</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>455</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib69"><citation citation-type="other"><bold>Vandesompele, J., De Preter, K., Pattyn, F., Poppe, B., Van Roy, N., De Paepe, A., and Speleman, F.</bold> (2002). Accurate normalization of real-time quantitative RT-PCR data by geometric averaging of multiple internal control genes. Genome Biol. <bold>3:</bold> RESEARCH0034.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wigge</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>J.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Integration of spatial and temporal information during floral induction in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>1056</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1059</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wollenberg</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerd&#x00E1;n</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Acceleration of flowering during shade avoidance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> alters the balance between FLOWERING LOCUS C-mediated repression and photoperiodic induction of flowering</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>1681</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1694</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rittinger</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Volinia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leffers</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamblin</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smerdon</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantley</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The structural basis for 14-3-3:phosphopeptide binding specificity</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>961</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>971</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>TWIN SISTER OF FT (TSF) acts as a floral pathway integrator redundantly with FT</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1189</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bib74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>CONSTANS activates SUPPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CONSTANS 1 through FLOWERING LOCUS T to promote flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>770</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>778</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
