<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">245316</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.245316</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Articles</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>BIOCHEMISTRY AND METABOLISM</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Reductase Activity of the Arabidopsis Caleosin RESPONSIVE TO DESSICATION20 Mediates Gibberellin-Dependent Flowering Time, Abscisic Acid Sensitivity, and Tolerance to Oxidative Stress<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>[W]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E9;e</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boachon</surname><given-names>Beno&#x00EE;t</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burcklen</surname><given-names>Michel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Le Gu&#x00E9;dard</surname><given-names>Marina</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hanano</surname><given-names>Abdulsamie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn2"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heintz</surname><given-names>Dimitri</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ehlting</surname><given-names>J&#x00FC;rgen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn3"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Herrfurth</surname><given-names>Cornelia</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Feussner</surname><given-names>Ivo</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bessoule</surname><given-names>Jean-Jacques</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff1">Institut de Biologie Mol&#x00E9;culaire des Plantes, Unit&#x00E9; Propre de Recherche 2357-Universit&#x00E9; de Strasbourg, 67083 Strasbourg cedex, France (E.B., B.B., M.B., A.H., D.H., J.E.)</aff><aff id="aff2">Laboratoire de Biog&#x00E9;n&#x00E8;se Membranaire, B&#x00E2;timent A3-Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique Bordeaux Aquitaine, 33140 Villenave d&#x2019;Ornon, France (M.L.G., J.-J.B.); and</aff><aff id="aff3">Georg-August-University, Albrecht-von-Haller Institute, Department of Plant Biochemistry, 37077 Goettingen, Germany (C.H., I.F.)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.114.245316">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.114.245316</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="afn1" fn-type="present-address"><label>2</label><p>Present address: Clinical Science, Actelion Pharmaceuticals Ltd., Gewerbestrasse 16, CH&#x2013;4123 Allschwil, Switzerland.</p></fn><fn id="afn2" fn-type="present-address"><label>3</label><p>Present address: Laboratory of Molecular Toxicology, Department of Molecular Biology and Biotechnology, Atomic Energy Commission of Syria, P.O. Box 6091, 011 Damascus, Syria.</p></fn><fn id="afn3" fn-type="present-address"><label>4</label><p>Present address: Department of Biology and Center for Forest Biology, University of Victoria, V8W2Y2 Victoria, BC, Canada.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Address correspondence to <email>elizabeth.blee@ibmp-cnrs.unistra.fr</email>.</corresp><fn id="afn4"><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Elizabeth Bl&#x00E9;e (<email>elizabeth.blee@ibmp-cnrs.unistra.fr</email>).</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>09</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>07</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>166</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>06</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>07</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#xa9; 2014 American Society of Plant Biologists. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="PP_245316_ic1.gif"/><self-uri content-type="alt-lang-pdf zh" xlink:href="109.chinese.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><italic>A peroxygenase controls floral transition and tolerance to oxidative stress</italic>.</p></abstract><abstract><p>Contrasting with the wealth of information available on the multiple roles of jasmonates in plant development and defense, knowledge about the functions and the biosynthesis of hydroxylated oxylipins remains scarce. By expressing the caleosin <italic>RESPONSIVE TO DESSICATION20</italic> (<italic>RD20</italic>) in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, we show that the recombinant protein possesses an unusual peroxygenase activity with restricted specificity toward hydroperoxides of unsaturated fatty acid. Accordingly, Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) plants overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic> accumulate the product 13-hydroxy-9,11,15-octadecatrienoic acid, a linolenate-derived hydroxide. These plants exhibit elevated levels of reactive oxygen species (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref>) associated with early gibberellin-dependent flowering and abscisic acid hypersensitivity at seed germination. These phenotypes are dependent on the presence of active RD20, since they are abolished in the <italic>rd20</italic> null mutant and in lines overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic>, in which peroxygenase was inactivated by a point mutation of a catalytic histidine residue. RD20 also confers tolerance against stress induced by Paraquat, Rose Bengal, heavy metal, and the synthetic auxins 1-naphthaleneacetic acid and 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid. Under oxidative stress, 13-hydroxy-9,11,15-octadecatrienoic acid still accumulates in RD20-overexpressing lines, but this lipid oxidation is associated with reduced <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> levels, minor cell death, and delayed floral transition. A model is discussed where the interplay between fatty acid hydroxides generated by RD20 and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> is counteracted by ethylene during development in unstressed environments.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">FAOH</term><def id="def1"><p>fatty acid hydroxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">2-HOT</term><def id="def2"><p>2-hydroxy-9,12,15-octadecatrienoic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">9-HOT</term><def id="def3"><p>9-hydroxy-10,12,15-octadecatrienoic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">ABA</term><def id="def4"><p>abscisic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">ROS</term><def id="def5"><p>reactive oxygen species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">FAOOH</term><def id="def6"><p>fatty acid hydroperoxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">13-HOT</term><def id="def7"><p>13-hydroxy-9,11,15-octadecatrienoic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8">13-HPOD</term><def id="def8"><p>13-hydroperoxy-9,11-octadecadienoic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></term><def id="def9"><p>hydrogen peroxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term10">GC-MS</term><def id="def10"><p>gas chromatography-mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term11">13-HOD</term><def id="def11"><p>13-hydroxy-octadeca-9,11-dienoic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term12">T-DNA</term><def id="def12"><p>transfer DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term13">Ws</term><def id="def13"><p>Wassilewskija</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term14">Col-0</term><def id="def14"><p>Columbia-0</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term15">qRT</term><def id="def15"><p>quantitative reverse transcription</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term16">NBT</term><def id="def16"><p>nitroblue tetrazolium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term17">DAB</term><def id="def17"><p>3,3&#x2032;-diaminobenzidine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term18">JA</term><def id="def18"><p>jasmonate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term19">NAA</term><def id="def19"><p>1-naphthaleneacetic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term20">cDNA</term><def id="def20"><p>complementary DNA</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>Originally thought to be seed specific and confined to the surface of lipid droplets, caleosins were assumed to be structural proteins of these organelles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Chen et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Naested et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Purkrtova et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Jiang and Tzen, 2010</xref>). Caleosins have now been endowed with new roles since they have also been detected in vegetative tissues, where they are associated with the endoplasmic reticulum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Hernandez-Pinzon et al., 2001</xref>), the vacuole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Carter et al., 2004</xref>), and the envelope of chloroplasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Partridge and Murphy, 2009</xref>). In Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> Seed1 (ATS1; At4g26740; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Nuccio and Thomas, 1999</xref>) appears to participate in the degradation of lipid reserves in seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Poxleitner et al., 2006</xref>), while the non-seed-specific Caleosin4 (CLO4; At1g70670; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Naested et al., 2000</xref>) and <italic>RESPONSIVE TO DESSICATION20</italic> (<italic>RD20</italic>; At2g33380; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Yamaguchi-Shinozaki et al., 1992</xref>) are negative and positive regulators of abscisic acid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>) responses during germination and dehydration processes, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Aubert et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Kim et al., 2011</xref>). However, the molecular mechanisms by which distinct caleosins exert their functions remained unknown. The recent identification of ATS1 and CLO4 as peroxygenases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hanano et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Bl&#x00E9;e et al., 2012</xref>) has prompted the suggestion that caleosins might fulfill their physiological functions via their enzymatic production of oxylipins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Partridge and Murphy, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Aubert et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Kim et al., 2011</xref>). Among the primary oxylipins formed in vitro by peroxygenases are the unsaturated fatty acid hydroxides (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Such oxylipins accumulate upon pathogen attack (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Rust&#x00E9;rucci et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">G&#x00F6;bel et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Montillet et al., 2005</xref>), and they may play significant roles in plant-pathogen interactions. They could act directly through their antimicrobial properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Prost et al., 2005</xref>) and/or they could be components of signaling pathways leading to defense responses. For example, 2-hydroxy-9,12,15-octadecatrienoic acid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">2-HOT</xref>), when applied on both tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>) and Arabidopsis leaves, prevents necrosis due to bacterial infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Ponce de Le&#x00F3;n et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Hamberg et al., 2003</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">2-HOT</xref> also participates in the defense of <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> against insect feeding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Gaquerel et al., 2012</xref>). In addition, 9-hydroxy-10,12,15-octadecatrienoic acid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">9-HOT</xref>) was reported to antagonize the action of ethylene, triggering molecular events such as the accumulation of callose, the production of reactive oxygen species (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref>), and transcriptional changes for genes involved in plant defense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Hwang and Hwang, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">L&#x00F3;pez et al., 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s also accumulate during oxidative stress, when their functions are still elusive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">op den Camp et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Montillet et al., 2004</xref>). Besides their roles in defensive responses, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s are involved in signaling pathways controlling physiological processes such as the regulation of lateral root development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Vellosillo et al., 2007</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Characterization of recombinant RD20 activity in yeast. A, Mechanistic scheme for peroxygenase activity. Enz represents the peroxygenase, and Fe represents the heme of the protein; Sub and SubO represent the substrate and its oxidized form, respectively; R-O-OH and R-OH represent the hydroperoxide cosubstrate and its corresponding alcohol, respectively. B, Cooxidation of radiolabeled polyunsaturated fatty acids in the presence of cumene hydroperoxide (CuOOH), <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref>, or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref>. <sup>14</sup>C-labeled substrates metabolized by microsomal fractions prepared from <italic>RD20</italic>-expressing yeast were separated by thin-layer chromatography and analyzed by radiodetection. 18:1, Oleic acid; 18:2, linoleic acid; 18:3, linolenic acid. Incubations of <sup>14</sup>C-labeled substrates in the presence of microsomal fractions prepared from untransformed yeast and from yeast transformed with empty vector did not exhibit any activity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_245316_f1"></graphic></fig><p>The biosynthesis of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s has only been partially elucidated. They most likely result from the reduction of fatty acid hydroperoxides (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s can to be formed either chemically (e.g. in the presence of free radicals; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Mosblech et al., 2009</xref>) or enzymatically by the oxygenation of C16 and C18 unsaturated fatty acids catalyzed by 9- and 13-lipoxygenases (9-LOXs and 13-LOXs; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Feussner and Wasternack, 2002</xref>) or &#x03B1;-dioxygenases (&#x03B1;-DOXs; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Hamberg et al., 1999</xref>). Thus, the biosynthesis of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>S is well established, but the endogenous enzyme(s) reducing these hydroperoxides to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s remain largely enigmatic. Peroxygenases were assumed to play such a role (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Hamberg et al., 1999</xref>), because of their known ability to efficiently reduce many hydroperoxides in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Ishimaru and Yamazaki, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Bl&#x00E9;e and Schuber, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hamberg and Hamberg, 1990</xref>). Accordingly, a recent study reported the production of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">2-HOT</xref> when recombinant &#x03B1;-DOX and the caleosin RD20 were incubated in vitro in the presence of linolenic acid. The resulting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref> was postulated to be implicated in biotic stress responses as a phytoalexin in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Shimada et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>To ascertain the role of caleosin/peroxygenases in reducing endogenous <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s and to test the implication of such an enzymatic activity in developmental and environmental responses, we have further studied <italic>RD20</italic>. This study describes the identification of RD20 as an unusual peroxygenase possessing substrate specificities restricted to polyunsaturated fatty acids and derivatives. This enzymatic activity is determinant for tolerance to oxidative stress conferred by RD20, resulting in reduced <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> accumulation and minor cell death. However, in an unstressed environment, overexpression of RD20 results in the accumulation of 13-hydroxy-9,11,15-octadecatrienoic acid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref>), coinciding with enhanced <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> levels, early GA-dependent floral transition, and increased sensitivity to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>. Based on our results, we discuss the role of ethylene in the generation and function of the products generated by the enzymatic activity of RD20 in the physiological responses during stress tolerance or escape. These studies allow a better understanding of the role of caleosin/peroxygenase in plant development and responses to abiotic stress.</p><sec id="s1" sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>Among all caleosin genes in Arabidopsis, <italic>RD20</italic> is the most stress and hormone inducible (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). <italic>RD20</italic> transcript levels respond to pathogen attack as well as to elicitors, hormones, and nutrient availability (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). Moreover, microarray data indicate that <italic>RD20</italic> expression is also up-regulated in response to abiotic stresses such as wounding, drought, salt, cold, anoxia, osmotic stress, freezing recovery, and auxin-herbicide treatment (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). Consistent with these large-scale expression data, dedicated analyses also characterized <italic>RD20</italic> as a general stress-inducible gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Yamaguchi-Shinozaki et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Takahashi et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Partridge and Murphy, 2009</xref>). In addition, analysis of microarray databases using coexpression analysis (as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Ehlting et al., 2008</xref>) shows that many genes with expression profiles similar to <italic>RD20</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>) are known to play roles in responses to environmental stress. These include homeobox-Leu zipper genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Manavella et al., 2006</xref>; hormone data set), &#x03B4;-1-<italic>pyrroline-5-carboxylate synthase</italic> involved in Pro biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Yoshiba et al., 1995</xref>; hormone data set), remorins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Raffaele et al., 2007</xref>; stress data set), potassium transporter family members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Szczerba et al., 2009</xref>; stress data set), cold-responsive genes (<italic>cor15a</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Baker et al., 1994</xref>; hormone data set), and the <italic>RD26</italic> gene encoding a NAC (for NAM [no apical meristem]ATAF [Arabidopsis Transcription Factor], and CUC [cup-shaped cotyledon]) transcription factor involved in drought and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Fujita et al., 2004</xref>; hormone and pathogen data sets). Thus, these observed coexpression patterns provide independent support in favor of a key function of <italic>RD20</italic> in stress responses. Moreover, microarray data, recently confirmed by GUS reporter gene analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Aubert et al., 2010</xref>), revealed an expression of <italic>RD20</italic> in late stages of seed formation but also in stems, leaves, and flowers, suggesting multiple physiological roles for this caleosin in unstressed plants. The divergent roles of RD20 in development and stress responses might involve the enzymatic activity of this caleosin. However, the identity of RD20 as a peroxygenase is not definitively established. It does possess in its amino acid sequence essential features that typify such enzymes, such as an EF-hand calcium-binding motif and two strictly conserved His residues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hanano et al., 2006</xref>). In addition, RD20 can form <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s in conjunction with &#x03B1;-DOX in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Shimada et al., 2014</xref>), and a peroxygenase-like activity was detected in crude extracts of salt-stressed Arabidopsis, which was postulated to result from the induction of <italic>RD20</italic> by salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Partridge and Murphy, 2009</xref>). Thus, further characterization of the oxidized compounds made in vivo by RD20 appears critical for a better understanding of its physiological function.</p><sec id="s2"><title>RD20 Is a Peroxygenase That Preferentially Accepts Lipids as Substrates</title><p>RD20 has been suggested to be a peroxygenase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hanano et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Shimada et al., 2014</xref>), and thus the enzymatic features of the recombinant protein expressed in yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) were studied. Peroxygenases are typically able to catalyze cooxidations of diverse substrates in the presence of various hydroperoxides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Bl&#x00E9;e, 1998</xref>). In particular, all caleosin-type peroxygenases identified so far actively catalyze aniline hydroxylation in the presence of cumene hydroperoxide in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hanano et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Bl&#x00E9;e et al., 2012</xref>). As a caleosin, RD20 was thus expected to catalyze such a reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Partridge and Murphy, 2009</xref>). Surprisingly, however, crude extracts from transformed yeast cells expressing <italic>RD20</italic> were unable to hydroxylate aniline in the presence of cumene hydroperoxide. Attempts to optimize assay conditions by varying enzyme and substrate concentrations or by adding exogenous heme or calcium were unsuccessful. Nevertheless, analysis of public microarray data revealed that <italic>RD20</italic> is closely coexpressed with several lipid metabolism- and signaling-related genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). These include the very-long-chain fatty acid-condensing enzyme <italic>CUT1</italic>, the lipoxygenase <italic>LOX2</italic> (both in the organ data set), several putative lipid transfer proteins (in the stress and hormone data sets), a putative lipase, and a long-chain fatty acid CoA ligase (<italic>LACS8</italic>; in the hormone data set). This coexpression pattern and the ability of peroxygenases to epoxidize double bonds of unsaturated fatty acids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Bl&#x00E9;e and Schuber, 1990</xref>) prompted us to examine whether lipids were substrates for RD20. Such a hypothesis could still be consistent with the previously noted slight increase, and apparently cumene hydroperoxide-dependent, of RD20-mediated peroxygenase in salt-stressed leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Partridge and Murphy, 2009</xref>). For this, one should consider the possibility of RD20 having used endogenous <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s present in the tested crude leaf extracts as cosubstrates to catalyze the hydroxylation of aniline rather than the exogenously added cumene hydroperoxide.</p><p>To test our hypothesis, RD20-dependent degradation of <sup>14</sup>C-labeled C18 fatty acids with one to three double bonds in the presence of cumene hydroperoxide, hydrogen peroxide (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref>), or 13-hydroperoxy-9,11-octadecadienoic acid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref>) was followed by thin-layer chromatography coupled to radiodetection. The most active cosubstrate was <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref> followed by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref>, whereas cumene hydroperoxide only poorly promoted epoxidation of the unsaturated fatty acids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>). Among the substrates tested, linolenic acid, a triple unsaturated fatty acid, was most actively epoxidized by RD20, whereas the single unsaturated oleic acid was hardly metabolized regardless of the hydroperoxide used. As negative controls, neither extract from wild-type Wa6 yeast strain nor yeast transformed with an empty vector displayed any catalytic activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>). To further characterize the peroxygenase identity of RD20, we tested whether it was able to catalyze the reduction of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s followed by oxidation of the resulting alcohol (i.e. cooxidation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s) in the absence of other oxidizable substrates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Such an activity was described previously for a soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic>) peroxygenase and ATS1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Bl&#x00E9;e et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hanano et al., 2006</xref>). To avoid the possibility of contaminant reductase activity present in yeast, recombinant RD20 fused to a C-terminal FLAG tag was purified to apparent homogeneity using affinity chromatography. SDS-PAGE analysis showed a single band, validated as RD20/FLAG by western blotting using a FLAG antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). The purified fraction did not perform oxidation of substrates, like aniline, thiobenzamide, or unsaturated fatty acids, with cumene hydroperoxide. This confirmed that cumene hydroperoxide is a very poor substrate for RD20 and showed that the lack of aniline hydroxylation with crude extracts or microsomes from transformed yeasts was not due to the presence of inhibitors in yeast.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Characterization of purified recombinant RD20. A, Analysis by SDS-PAGE of a purified fraction of the recombinant protein (left) and western-blot analysis of this fraction using a monoclonal anti-FLAG antibody produced in mouse (right). B, Metabolism scheme showing the products expected from the peroxygenase-catalyzed transformation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>. C, Radio-HPLC analysis of the metabolization of [1-<sup>14</sup>C]13-HPOT by purified RD20. Peaks are as follows: 1, 15,16-epoxy-13-hydroxy-9,11-octadecenoic acid; 2, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref>; 3, residual 13-HPOT. The bottom scan shows the absence of 13-HPOT transformation by boiled purified RD20 after 2 h of incubation at 27&#x00B0;C. D, Radio-HPLC analysis of the metabolization of [1-<sup>14</sup>C]<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref> by purified RD20. Top, products of [1-<sup>14</sup>C]<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref> formed by purified RD20 after 2 h of incubation at 27&#x00B0;C. Peaks are as follows: 4, trihydroxy-octadecanoates; 5, 13-hydroxy-9,11-octadecadienoic acid; 6, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref>. Middle, accumulation of trihydroxy-octadecanoates after overnight incubation of [<sup>14</sup>C]<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref> with purified RD20. Bottom, no epoxy or hydroxy derivatives were formed when [1-<sup>14</sup>C]<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref> was incubated overnight in the presence of a boiled purified RD20. E, Reduction of 9-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref> into its corresponding alcohol by purified RD20. Peaks are as follows: 7, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">9-HPOT</xref>; 8, 9-HOT.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_245316_f2"></graphic></fig><p>To test whether RD20 is able to catalyze the intramolecular transfer of an oxygen atom in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Bl&#x00E9;e et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>), we incubated purified recombinant RD20 with [1-<sup>14</sup>C]13-HPOT (for 13-hydroperoxy-9,11,15-octadecatrienoic acid) or [1-<sup>14</sup>C]<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref>. The reaction products were analyzed by radio-HPLC. After 2 h of incubation, about 70% of 13-HPOT was converted into two more polar compounds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>, top). Peak 3 represented the residual substrate. Peak 2 (elution time, 21 min) was identified as <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref> by coelution with an authentic standard, and its structure was confirmed by mass spectrometry. Peak 1 (elution time, 10.5 min) absorbed at 234 nm, similar to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref>, indicating that it still contained a <italic>Z</italic>,<italic>E</italic>-conjugated double bond system. Analysis by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">GC-MS</xref>) of the trimethylsilyl ether derivative of its methyl ester featured a molecular ion at mass-to-charge ratio 396, indicative of an additional oxygen atom, compared with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref>. Representative fragments were found identical to those observed with 15,16-epoxy-13-hydroxy-octadeca-9,11-dienoic acid (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Bl&#x00E9;e et al., 1993</xref>). In contrast to 13-HPOT, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref> was only slowly metabolized by RD20 under identical incubation conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2D</xref>, top). Peak 5 (elution time, 29.2 min) was 13-hydroxy-octadeca-9,11-dienoic acid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">13-HOD</xref>), the methyl ester-trimethylsilyl ether derivative of this compound cochromatographed with an authentic standard, and the mass spectra of these two compounds were identical. A mixture of 9,10,13- and 9,12,13-trihydroxy-octadecanoates, identified by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">GC-MS</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hamberg, 1991</xref>), rapidly eluted as peak 4 (elution time, 3.7 min). These trihydroxy derivatives (probably resulting from the chemical opening of unstable epoxy alcohols) accumulated only after prolonged incubation times (i.e. overnight; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2D</xref>, middle). In negative control experiments using boiled purified RD20, 13-HPOT and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref> were not metabolized when incubated either for 2 h or overnight (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, C and D</xref>, bottom). Thus, like ATS1, RD20 is capable, in the absence of any other oxidizable substrate, of catalyzing the reduction of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s with the concomitant formation of their corresponding epoxy alcohol. Of note, RD20 was also able to reduce the 9-hydroperoxide derivative of linolenic acid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2E</xref>). Taken together, these experiments indicate that the apparent lack of the canonical peroxygenase activity of RD20 might result from its preferential use of lipophilic molecules (unsaturated fatty acids and their hydroperoxide derivatives) as substrates.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Molecular Characterization of <italic>RD20</italic>-Overexpressing and Transfer DNA Insertion Lines</title><p>To explore the function of RD20 in development and stress, we used a loss- and a gain-of-function approach. A single Arabidopsis transfer DNA (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">T-DNA</xref>) insertion line was available in public libraries at the onset of this project. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">T-DNA</xref> was inserted into the second exon 572 bp downstream of the start codon. No RD20 transcripts were detectable in the <italic>rd20</italic> null mutant compared with its wild-type Wassilewskija (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">Ws</xref>) background. Introduction of a <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>RD20</italic> overexpression construct into the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant restored some RD20 expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). We also generated Arabidopsis Columbia-0 (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">Col-0</xref>) plants to overexpress <italic>RD20</italic> under the control of the cauliflower mosaic virus 35S promoter. In parallel, void plasmid was transformed into wild-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">Col-0</xref> Arabidopsis and used as a control. The two <italic>RD20</italic>-overexpressing lines used, <italic>RD20-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE2</italic>, showed 20- to 26-fold increases in <italic>RD20</italic> transcript levels as assessed by quantitative reverse transcription (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">qRT</xref>)-PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Characterization of <italic>RD20</italic> transgenic plants. A and B, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">qRT</xref>-PCR analysis of <italic>RD20</italic> gene expression in 3-week-old leaves. A, <italic>RD20</italic> was expressed in the <italic>rd20</italic> background, yielding the <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>RD20</italic> line. B, The control contains an empty vector used for the overexpression of <italic>RD20</italic>. Data represent means and <sc>se</sc> of three replicates obtained from three different biological samples. C, Oxylipin profiling. Free <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s present in leaves of the different lines were analyzed by HPLC. All lines were harvested at the bolting stage of <italic>RD20</italic>-overexpressing plants. Data represent means and <sc>se</sc> of two replicates from 20 different biological samples. fw, Fresh weight. D, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> status of 3-week-old rosette leaves. Superoxide radical (O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x2219;&#x2212;</sup>) levels were determined after staining leaves with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">NBT</xref> (top), whereas <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> contents were measured by staining leaves with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def17">DAB</xref> (bottom). Ratios of stained surface versus total surface were calculated with ImageJ. For all parts, results concerning transgenic lines versus their respective controls were considered statistically different as indicated: &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 (<italic>n</italic> &#x2265; 30 for each line; Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test analysis).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_245316_f3"></graphic></fig><p>To assess whether RD20 accepts <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s as substrates not only in vitro but also in planta, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref> content of the different <italic>RD20</italic>-transformed lines was analyzed by HPLC. Alcohols derived from 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s were the most abundant free oxylipins formed in untreated leaves of all lines studied. While <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">13-HOD</xref> levels were not significantly affected in any mutant, knock out of <italic>RD20</italic> led to a 50% reduction of free <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref> compared with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">Ws</xref> wild-plant plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>, top). The opposite metabolic phenotype is apparent in <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE1</italic> lines, which contain 2- to 3-fold higher free <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref> levels, respectively, than their vector-only counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>, bottom). These results were consistent with a functional expression of RD20 in the transgenic plants, able to reduce 13-HPOT, the main endogenous fatty acid hydroperoxide formed in green leaves.</p><p>Exogenous application of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">9-HOT</xref> was recently reported to trigger the formation of superoxide radicals in Arabidopsis leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">L&#x00F3;pez et al., 2011</xref>). To investigate whether such <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> accumulate when <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref> was produced endogenously by RD20, superoxide radical content was determined using the nitroblue tetrazolium (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">NBT</xref>) dye assay. No statistical difference could be observed between superoxide radical amounts in <italic>rd20</italic> mutant and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">Ws</xref> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3D</xref>, top). In contrast, about a 2-fold increased level of superoxide radical was found in the lines overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic> compared with their controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3D</xref>, top). It thus appears that 13-LOX-derived oxylipins endogenously produced by RD20 trigger the accumulation of superoxide radical species, similar to what is observed with exogenously applied <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">9-HOT</xref>. Next, we investigated whether transgenic lines accumulate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref>, the most chemically stable <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref>. Considering the hypothesis that, in analogy with the recombinant protein in vitro (see above), RD20 would also be able to reduce <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> in planta, reduced levels of this hydroperoxide were expected in plants overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic>. However, this was not observed when <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> content was estimated with the 3,3&#x2032;-diaminobenzidine (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def17">DAB</xref>) staining test. Instead, such plants accumulated 5 to 6 times more <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> than their respective controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3D</xref>, bottom). Conversely, <italic>rd20</italic> leaves contained about 4-fold less <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> than the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">Ws</xref> wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3D</xref>, bottom). Together, these results indicate that under unstressed conditions, RD20 leads to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> accumulation.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Alteration of <italic>RD20</italic> Expression Affects the Transition to Flowering</title><p>The most striking visual phenotypes of <italic>RD20</italic> transgenic lines were changes in the timing of the floral transition. Both <italic>RD20-OE</italic> lines were in bloom about 3 weeks before control plants under short-day conditions. In contrast, the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant showed delayed flowering compared with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">Ws</xref> wild-type plants. To test whether this phenotype is due to altered peroxygenase activity or due to altered RD20 levels per se, we generated transgenic Arabidopsis plants overexpressing catalytically inactive RD20. For this, we mutated His-133 to Ala. This His residue is strictly conserved in peroxygenases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4A</ext-link>) and is crucial for peroxygenase activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hanano et al., 2006</xref>). This substitution is assumed to prevent the cooxidation step, hence leading to an accumulation of the reaction intermediates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>) and ultimately to the inactivation of RD20 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Bl&#x00E9;e et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hanano et al., 2006</xref>). Accordingly, the recombinant RD20<sup>H133A</sup> was unable to catalyze epoxy derivative formation but still accumulated some <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref> when incubated with 13-HPOT (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4B</ext-link>). We selected two lines, <italic>RD20<sup>H133A</sup>-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20<sup>H133A</sup>-OE2</italic>, with transgene expression levels similar to or higher than those found in plants overexpressing the wild-type enzyme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>). No difference in the accumulation of oxylipins was observed in these two lines in comparison with the wild type (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4C</ext-link>). Importantly, these two transgenic lines displayed no apparent alterations in growth, morphology, or flowering time compared with the wild type. This shows that increased amounts of inactive RD20 are not sufficient to influence flowering time, indicating that, instead, increased oxylipin generation in the <italic>RD20-OE</italic> lines was required to accelerate the floral transition under nonstress conditions. These visual observations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>) were confirmed by quantifying bolting times, number of rosette leaves, and length of floral stems (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). In addition, phenotypes were preserved when plants were grown in phytochambers located at different places (Strasbourg, Bordeaux [both in France], and Damascus, Syria), indicating that they did not result from subtle differences in tap water or soil composition or local growth room conditions (e.g. light intensity/composition or temperature fluctuations).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>RD20 is involved in the floral transition. A, Peroxygenase activity was required for RD20 effects on flowering. Lines overexpressing enzymatically active (right) or inactive (left) <italic>RD20</italic> were grown under short-day conditions for 4 weeks, when the photograph was taken. B, Modifications of <italic>RD20</italic> expression or RD20 activity affect the floral transition of the mutant lines. Flowering changes were determined by measuring the bolting times (top), the number of rosette leaves at the bolting time of RD20-overexpressing lines (middle), and the length of the stems of 5-week-old plants (bottom). All lines were grown side by side under short-day conditions (SD). Data are means of two different biological samples (<italic>n</italic> = 35 per experiment per genotype). C, The RD20 accelerating effect on the floral transition is dependent on the photoperiod. Compared with controls, when grown under long-day conditions (LD), the bolting time is reduced in lines overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 28). The experiment was repeated twice. In all parts, differences between transgenic lines versus their respective controls were significant as indicated: &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_245316_f4"></graphic></fig><p>GAs are well-known regulators of the floral transition, and notably, this hormone class has a greater effect on flowering time under short-day than under long-day conditions in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Wilson et al., 1992</xref>). The early-flowering phenotype conferred by <italic>RD20</italic> overexpression was reduced from 3 weeks under short-day conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>, top) to only 4 d under long-day conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>). This immediately suggested a GA-mediated effect of <italic>RD20</italic> on flowering. Among other mechanisms, GA promotes flowering through transcriptional activation of the floral meristem identity gene <italic>LEAFY</italic> (<italic>LFY</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Wilson et al., 1992</xref>). <italic>LFY</italic> expression was up-regulated in both <italic>RD20-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>). To investigate whether the RD20-dependent control of flowering time involves the induction of GA biosynthesis or turnover, we analyzed the expression of some of the genes involved in GA metabolism. While no induction of GA biosynthetic genes (i.e. <italic>GA3ox1</italic>, <italic>GA20ox1</italic>, and <italic>GA20ox8</italic>) was apparent in any of the transgenic lines, a down-regulation of the GA-deactivating genes <italic>GA2ox1</italic> and <italic>GA2ox2</italic> in plants overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic> was indicative of a possible GA accumulation in these transgenic lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>). These results were overall consistent with a GA signaling-dependent control of the floral transition in plants overexpressing RD20. Because the GA signaling pathway is antagonized by jasmonates (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref>s; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Yang et al., 2012</xref>), we next examined the possibility that alteration of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> level might lead to early flowering of the lines overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic>. Actually, both RD20 and allene oxide synthase, the first enzyme of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> biosynthetic pathway, use <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref> as a substrate and thus might compete for it. According to such a scenario, a decrease of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> accumulation and not the production of oxylipins by caleosin would be responsible for the early-flowering phenotype of <italic>RD20</italic>-overexpressing lines. However, analysis of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> contents did not reveal any significant difference in hormone accumulation in lines overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic> when compared with their controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>), suggesting that the early flowering of the transgenic lines was unlikely driven by a competition between the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> and RD20 pathways.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Overexpression of RD20 modified the expression of the transcription factor LFY but not <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> contents. A, Quantitative PCR analysis of gene expression involved in signaling (<italic>LFY</italic>), biosynthesis (<italic>Ga3ox1</italic>, <italic>GA20ox1</italic>, and <italic>Ga20ox8</italic>), and metabolization (<italic>Ga2ox1</italic> and <italic>Ga2ox2</italic>) of GAs. Plants were harvested at the bolting time of <italic>RD20-</italic>overexpressing lines. Data represent means and <sc>se</sc> of three replicates. B, Analysis by liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> contents of lines overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic> and control plants. Data are means &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc> of triplicate assays. Transgenic plants did not significantly differ from control plants when analyzed by Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, with <italic>P</italic> = 0.66 for <italic>RD20</italic>-<italic>OE1</italic> versus control and <italic>P</italic> = 0.57 for <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> versus control. fw, Fresh weight.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_245316_f5"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s5"><title>RD20 Affects <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>-Dependent Germination and Seed Dormancy</title><p>GA not only controls the floral transition but also acts as an <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> antagonist during germination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Debeaujon and Koornneef, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Kucera et al., 2005</xref>). To investigate whether alterations in <italic>RD20</italic> expression also impacted the sensitivity to exogenous <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>, we studied seed germination and postgermination growth of the different RD20 transgenic lines in the presence of increasing concentrations of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>, fewer <italic>RD20-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> seeds germinated than wild-type seeds in an <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> dose-dependent manner. In contrast, <italic>rd20</italic> seeds germinated at higher frequency and faster than did wild-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">Ws</xref> seeds when treated with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5A</ext-link>). Noteworthy, without the addition of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>, the germination of <italic>rd20</italic> seeds was slightly delayed compared with control seeds (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5B</ext-link>). The insensitivity to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> was abolished in the mutant when complemented with a <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>RD20</italic> transgene construct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5A</ext-link>). Similar results were observed when considering seedling growth. While <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> negatively affected the postemergence growth of <italic>RD20</italic>-overexpressing seedlings, more <italic>rd20</italic> mutants showed expanded and green cotyledons after 6 d of light in the presence of 1 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> compared with the wild type and the complemented line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>). Together, complementary loss- and gain-of-function studies clearly showed that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> sensitivity is affected in plants with altered <italic>RD20</italic> expression. It should be noted that, when assayed without any treatment, freshly harvested seeds of <italic>RD20-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> showed a marked decrease of germination rate when compared with control seeds. In contrast, freshly harvested seeds of the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant germinated at higher frequency than did wild-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">Ws</xref> seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6C</xref>). However, after a cold treatment (stratification) to break dormancy, <italic>rd20</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE</italic> seeds displayed full germination indistinguishable from their respective wild-type controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>). These results suggest that <italic>RD20</italic> may impact seed dormancy by enhancing sensitivity to endogenous <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Alteration of <italic>RD20</italic> expression affects <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> sensitivity. A, Germination of seeds of RD20 transgenic lines and their respective controls was scored as emergence of the radicle 4 d after stratification under various concentrations of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>. B, Postemergence growth was estimated by the percentage of green cotyledons developed in the presence of 1 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> 6 d after stratification. C, Germination of fresh seeds (without stratification) was also accessed in the absence of exogenous <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>. Data are means &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc> for three different samples with <italic>n</italic> &gt; 30 per line per replicate. D and E, Sensitivity to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> conferred by <italic>RD20</italic> depends on the catalytic activity of the encoded enzyme. The germination of seeds containing an empty vector or overexpressing active or catalytically impaired enzyme was scored in the presence of 5 and 10 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> (D). Green cotyledons that developed in the presence of 5 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> were counted 4 d after stratification (E). Data are means &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc> of three different biological samples (<italic>n</italic> &gt; 30 per line per sample). In all parts, differences between transgenic plants versus their respective controls were significant as indicated: &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_245316_f6"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Are <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s Active Molecules during Germination?</title><p>To investigate whether peroxygenase activity was necessary for the altered <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> sensitivity of <italic>RD20</italic> transgenic lines, the seed germination and dormancy of <italic>RD20<sup>H133A</sup>-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20<sup>H133A</sup>-OE2</italic> lines were studied. Mutation of the RD20 active site His-133 (see above) rendered the resulting seeds resistant to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>, as observed for the insertion mutant lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6D</xref>). This effect was particularly obvious when cotyledon expansion and greening were considered after 6 d of growth in the presence of 1 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>. While less than 10% of the seedlings overexpressing active RD20 turned green, up to 80% of the seeds overexpressing the catalytically impaired enzyme developed green and expanded cotyledons. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>-dependent inhibition of greening in RD20<sup>H133A</sup>-OE lines was similar to the results obtained with knock-out mutant lines cultivated under the same conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6E</xref>). Thus, the altered sensitivity to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> of <italic>RD20</italic> transgenic lines was conferred by the enzymatic activity of the product of this gene.</p><p>To identify what product resulting from RD20 catalysis was involved, we examined whether the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> insensitivity of <italic>RD20<sup>H133A</sup>-OE</italic> seeds resulted from the action of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s or from additional unidentified oxygenated compounds produced during the cooxidation reactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). To differentiate between these two possibilities, we attempted to chemically complement the deficiency of RD20 catalytic activity by supplying exogenous <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s to <italic>RD20<sup>H133A</sup>-OE</italic> seeds. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A</xref>, addition of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref> fully reversed the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> insensitivity of these seeds. In the absence of external <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>, the four hydroxylated derivatives of linoleic or linolenic acid, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">13-HOD</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">9-HOT</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref>, and 9-HOD, impaired the development of green and fully expanded cotyledons of <italic>RD20<sup>H133A</sup>-OE2</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7C</xref>). Inhibition of germination by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s was observed not only for the <italic>RD20<sup>H133A</sup>-OE2</italic> line but also for other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>-insensitive lines, such as <italic>abi-5</italic>, which is devoid of a basic Leu zipper transcription factor required for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> responses in seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). Consistently, seed germination of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>-deficient <italic>aba1</italic> mutant (devoid of zeaxanthin epoxidase, an enzyme involved in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> biosynthesis) was also further delayed in the presence of 9-HOD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). Together, these results strongly suggest a major role of the RD20-catalyzed formation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>-mediated signaling during seed germination and postgermination growth.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s control <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> sensitivity and germination. A, Primary products of RD20 catalytic activity abolish <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> insensitivity. The insensitivity to 25 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> of lines overexpressing inactive RD20 was abolished by 50 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref>. B, Germination of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>-insensitive <italic>ABI5</italic> and the <italic>aba1</italic> mutant was inhibited in the presence of 100 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> 9-HOD. C, Postemergence growth was inhibited in the presence of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s. Data are means &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc> of three different biological samples, with <italic>n</italic> = 25 per line per sample. In all parts, differences were significant as indicated: &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 (by Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_245316_f7"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Stress-Induced RD20 Protects Arabidopsis against Oxidative Damage</title><p>The strong stress response of <italic>RD20</italic> expression suggests a role for the caleosin/peroxygenase RD20 in conditions known to generate oxidative damage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). We first investigated the impact of the herbicide Paraquat on the development of the different transgenic lines. Paraquat is a generator of superoxide radical that strongly activates the expression of <italic>RD20</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Ramel et al., 2012</xref>). Leaf bleaching is the primary visual effect of Paraquat phytotoxicity, and less than 30% of the total leaves of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">Col-0</xref> control plants remained green after 7 d of growth under continuous light in the presence of 0.5 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> Paraquat (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>). In sharp contrast, up to 75% and 78% of leaves on <italic>RD20-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> lines, respectively, remained green (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>). Conversely, plants devoid of <italic>RD20</italic> were more sensitive to Paraquat than <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">Ws</xref> control plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>). Leaf bleaching was observed about 1 week after germination in the presence of Paraquat, whereas cell death was apparent already 24 h after spraying the herbicide on mature leaves. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8B</xref> (top), Paraquat-treated <italic>rd20</italic> leaves exhibited much higher degrees of cell death, determined by Trypan Blue staining, than those from <italic>RD20</italic>-overexpressing lines. Decreased cell death was associated with an enhanced accumulation of 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s in <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>, bottom). In contrast, Paraquat minimally affected <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref> levels in the null mutant, suggesting that Paraquat-induced production of these oxylipins is RD20 dependent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>, bottom). Additional oxylipin profiling of <italic>rd20</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE</italic> plants revealed the induction of 9-ketodiene and 9-ketotriene derivatives (i.e. compounds that result from further transformations of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s by LOXs), suggesting that Paraquat likely has induced 9-LOX abundance/activity (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>). 12-Hydroxy-9,12,15-octadecatrienoic acid and 16-hydroxy-9,12,15-octadecatrienoic acid levels were also minimally affected by Paraquat treatment (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>). This suggested that 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s likely resulted from the catalytic activity of 13-LOX/RD20. Since cell death is linked to enhanced generation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Gechev et al., 2006</xref>), we examined whether RD20 may confer protection against cell death by lowering the accumulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref>. We first evaluated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> levels in the transgenic plants treated with Paraquat. Quantitative analysis of whole-leaf staining with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def17">DAB</xref> revealed that the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant accumulates significantly more <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> compared with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">Ws</xref> wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8C</xref>). Vice versa, <italic>RD20-OE</italic> lines contained 5- to 7-fold lower amounts of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> compared with their controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8C</xref>). Likewise, superoxide radical content assessed by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">NBT</xref> staining decreased 10-fold in Paraquat-stressed <italic>RD20-OE</italic> leaves compared with controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8D</xref>). Collectively, these data are consistent with a protective function of RD20 against oxidative damage by lowering <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> accumulation.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>RD20 confers stress tolerance. A, RD20 protects leaves from Paraquat toxicity. Green leaves from <italic>RD20</italic>-overexpressing lines, the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant, and their respective controls were counted after 1 week of growth under continuous light in the presence of 0.5 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> Paraquat. The experiment was repeated twice. Data-averaged values are means &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc> (<italic>n</italic> = 60 per genotype; differences were significant at &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 when analyzed by Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test). B, RD20 protects against cell death. Cell death was visualized by staining leaves of <italic>RD20</italic>-overexpressing lines and the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant with Trypan Blue (top). Oxylipins were measured from two independent experiments (bottom); data are means &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc> and differ between with or without Paraquat (P) at &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 (Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test analysis). fw, Fresh weight. C and D, RD20 decreases the accumulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref>. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> (C) and superoxide radical (D) contents of leaves of transgenic lines and control plants were measured by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def17">DAB</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">NBT</xref> staining, respectively. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> accumulation was estimated by the ratio of stained surface versus total leaf surface using ImageJ (<italic>n</italic> = 30). Differences between transgenic lines and their respective controls are highly significant with <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 by Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test. Bars = 1 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_245316_f8"></graphic></fig><p>To examine whether peroxygenase activity was necessary to realize the protective role of RD20, the two lines overexpressing inactive and active RD20 as well control plants were grown in the presence of the synthetic auxin 1-naphthaleneacetic acid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def19">NAA</xref>). Control plants developed green cotyledons and several adventitious roots, characteristic of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def19">NAA</xref> action (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9A</xref>). Both <italic>RD20-OE</italic> lines also developed green cotyledons but lacked additional roots, indicating that the presence of enzymatically active RD20 protected Arabidopsis against <xref ref-type="list" rid="def19">NAA</xref> effects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9A</xref>). In sharp contrast, the H133A mutation in <italic>RD20</italic>-overexpressing lines (see above) led to the development of small white/yellowish seedlings that resulted from the deleterious effects of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def19">NAA</xref> acting as an herbicide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9A</xref>). This suggested that abolishing peroxygenase activity in RD20-overexpressing plants impaired the protective function of RD20. Anthocyanin levels have recently been used as valuable markers to assess plant stress responses to environmental conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Izumi et al., 2009</xref>). Analysis of the red pigment content of the four lines overexpressing either active or inactive RD20, grown in the presence of Paraquat, Rose Bengal, and 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid, suggested reduced stress levels in <italic>RD20-OE</italic> lines compared with controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9B</xref>). In contrast, overexpression of enzymatically inactive RD20 led to higher degrees of stress in <italic>RD20<sup>H133A</sup>-OE</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9B</xref>). Taken together, these results underline that peroxygenase activity is required for RD20-mediated protection against oxidative stress in planta.</p><fig id="fig9" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Peroxygenase activity is a prerequisite for the protective function of RD20. A, Seedlings of control lines and lines overexpressing active or catalytically impaired enzyme were grown on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def19">NAA</xref>. Bars = 1 mm. B, The degree of stress of such lines was estimated by measuring their anthocyanin contents after 1 week of growth in the presence of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> inducers (<italic>n</italic> = 10 in four independent experiments; &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 and &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 when analyzed by Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test). fw, Fresh weight. C, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">qRT</xref>-PCR was used to access the expression of RD20 and ERF1 in leaves of wild-type plants and <italic>ctr1-1</italic> and <italic>ein2-1</italic> ethylene mutants treated with Paraquat. The results shown represent means &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc> of at least four biological replicates (&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.05 and &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 when analyzed by the Student-Newman-Keuls test).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_245316_f9"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s8"><title><italic>RD20</italic> Is Positively Regulated by Ethylene during Stress</title><p>Oxylipins such <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">9-HOT</xref> may exert protective roles through antagonistic action with ethylene. While the ethylene-overproducing <italic>eto1</italic> mutant fails to survive under oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">L&#x00F3;pez et al., 2011</xref>), the constitutive ethylene response mutant <italic>ctr1</italic> is resistant to high salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Achard et al., 2006</xref>), and the ethylene-insensitive <italic>ein2</italic> mutant is vulnerable to many stresses, including Paraquat-induced oxygen radicals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Alonso et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Silverman et al., 2005</xref>). Thus, there is an apparent discrepancy between ethylene-overproducing and ethylene response mutants. Because <italic>eto1</italic> failed to enhance <italic>RD20</italic> expression under oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">L&#x00F3;pez et al., 2011</xref>), we hypothesized that the opposing stress tolerance phenotypes of ethylene response are due to the presence of RD20 that generates <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s such as <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">9-HOT</xref>. To test this hypothesis, we analyzed by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">qRT</xref>-PCR the expression of <italic>RD20</italic> in <italic>ctr1-1</italic> and <italic>ein2-1</italic> mutants after treatment with 5 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> Paraquat or water. In addition, the expression of the ethylene response factor <italic>ERF1</italic> was analyzed, since a recent report highlighted its critical function during stress responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Cheng et al., 2013</xref>). When sprayed with water, <italic>ctr1</italic> accumulated <italic>RD20</italic> transcripts to significantly lower levels as compared with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">Col-0</xref>, while increased levels of <italic>RD20</italic> transcripts were found in <italic>ein2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9C</xref>). When sprayed with Paraquat, a significant induction of both <italic>RD20</italic> and <italic>ERF1</italic> expression was observed in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">Col-0</xref> seedlings compared with those sprayed with water (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9C</xref>). In contrast, the expression of both genes in the <italic>ein2</italic> mutant was largely reduced after treatment with Paraquat as compared with unstressed conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9C</xref>). In <italic>ctr1</italic> mutants, oxidative stress minimally affected <italic>EFR1</italic> expression but significantly induced <italic>RD20</italic> expression when compared with water treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9C</xref>). Such data suggest that the induction of <italic>RD20</italic> expression is positively regulated by Paraquat in ethylene perception mutants.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Copper-Induced Oxidative Stress Alters the Floral Transition in <italic>RD20</italic> Transgenic Lines</title><p>Our results indicated that the enzymatic activity of RD20 was involved in the floral transition and protection against oxidative stress. To investigate the interplay between these two roles, we examined the growth of transgenic plants in the presence of high copper concentrations known to trigger oxidative stress. Whole plants displayed reduced development under these conditions. However, independently of the photoperiod duration, inflorescence stems of stressed <italic>RD20-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> lines decreased in length by 53% and 47%, respectively, compared with controls, indicating that their growth was delayed by stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10A</xref>). The opposite effect was apparent in <italic>rd20</italic> mutants, where copper treatment led to longer inflorescence stems compared with the wild type, suggesting an earlier flowering of this mutant line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10A</xref>). Noteworthy, <italic>rd20</italic> mutants contained less anthocyanins than the wild-type plants in the absence of Cu<sup>2+</sup>. In contrast, the anthocyanin content of <italic>rd20</italic> leaves in the presence of the metal increased up to those observed in wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10B</xref>). These results suggested that loss of <italic>RD20</italic> increased sensitivity to copper and that <italic>rd20</italic> may escape stress by entering the floral stage early. In contrast, in the absence of copper, more anthocyanins were present in the leaves of <italic>RD20-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> lines than in those of the controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10B</xref>), whereas in the presence of copper, both <italic>RD20-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> lines exhibited significantly lower anthocyanin amounts than those of their controls. Together, these data suggested that <italic>RD20</italic>-overexpressing lines were less affected by copper than their controls, extending vegetative growth to favor defense mechanisms over early induction of reproduction.</p><fig id="fig10" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Copper affects the flowering and stress tolerance of <italic>RD20-</italic>overexpressing and knock-out lines compared with their respective controls. A, Growth was estimated by recording the relative stem length of the transgenic lines versus their respective controls after 7 weeks of growth in the presence of 485 &#x00B5;g Cu<sup>2+</sup> g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> soil. B, The degree of stress of such lines was estimated by measuring their relative anthocyanin contents versus their respective controls. All experiments were repeated three times; data are means &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc>. Treatment with copper was statistically different from water-treated controls when analyzed by Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test (&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). fw, Fresh weight.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_245316_f10"></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s10" sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>RD20 encodes a peroxygenase that uses <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s as substrates; thus, at least one member of the small family of caleosins is able to reduce this type of endogenous oxylipins. Beyond or instead of being structural proteins of lipid droplets, caleosins are endowed with distinctive peroxygenase activities, allowing them to produce various oxygenated compounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hanano et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Bl&#x00E9;e et al., 2012</xref>; this article). Our data show that the peroxygenase activity of RD20 is necessary for the diverse biological functions implied by our reverse genetics analyses and highlight the long neglected importance of these enzymes in plant development and stress response.</p><sec id="s11"><title>RD20 Is Involved in Regulating Plant Development</title><p>We show here that changes in either <italic>RD20</italic> expression or RD20 catalytic activity lead to alterations of GA-controlled floral transition, seed dormancy, and sensitivity to exogenous <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>. From these observations, a question is immediately raised: how could the catalytic activity of RD20 bring about such pleiotropic effects? A possible answer is that the reductase activity of RD20 might alter the accumulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref>. When <italic>RD20</italic> is overexpressed, 13-HPOT, which is a precursor of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref>, might be channeled away from the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> biosynthetic pathway to be converted into <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref>, thus leading to reduced <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> levels. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> has been reported to antagonize the GA signaling pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Yang et al., 2012</xref>) and GA biosynthesis by inhibiting the accumulation of <italic>Ga20ox</italic> and <italic>Ga3ox</italic> transcripts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Heinrich et al., 2013</xref>). If this occurs in lines overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic>, reduced <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> accumulation could result in early flowering of these lines. However, we did not detect any alteration in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> content in the leaves of transgenic plants, in accordance with the absence of an accumulation of the transcripts of the biosynthetic genes <italic>GA20ox</italic> and <italic>GA3ox</italic>. Thus, the production of oxylipins and not the decrease in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> accumulation seems to be the origin of phenotypes that result from the overexpression of RD20 Another possible explanation is that RD20-generated oxylipins positively influence GA signaling. Such an assumption would be consistent with the delay of flowering of the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant as well as its slower seed germination compared with wild-type plants. However, this hypothesis could hardly explain the rapid break of dormancy of the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant seeds or their insensitivity to exogenous <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> during germination. Alternatively, oxylipins formed by RD20 catalysis might antagonize ethylene, as recently demonstrated for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">9-HOT</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">L&#x00F3;pez et al., 2011</xref>). This oxylipin in particular has been found to trigger <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> accumulation. Therefore, a hypothetic antagonism between ethylene and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s generated by RD20 would lead to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> accumulation in <italic>RD20</italic>-overexpressing lines and, inversely, to a reduced quantity of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> in <italic>rd20</italic>. That is what we observed when superoxide radical and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> levels were estimated. In agreement with the proposed antagonism between ethylene and oxylipins is the accumulation of <italic>RD20</italic> transcripts in the ethylene-insensitive mutant <italic>ein2</italic>. Consistently, this contrasts with the low expression of the caleosin gene in the ethylene constitutive response mutant <italic>ctr1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9C</xref>).</p><p>Furthermore, this hypothesis predicts that the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant, impaired in the production of oxylipins, would be more sensitive to ethylene perception and/or signaling. Ethylene has been reported to delay flowering by inhibiting GA signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Achard et al., 2007</xref>). In agreement, <italic>rd20</italic> mutants flowered late compared with controls, similar to plants treated with ethylene. In sharp contrast, the <italic>RD20-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> lines, by generating high amounts of oxylipins, would be expected to be less sensitive to ethylene. Indeed, these mutants flowered earlier than their control counterparts. Ethylene is also known as a negative regulator of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> response during seed germination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Beaudoin et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Ghassemian et al., 2000</xref>). In agreement with an antagonism between ethylene and oxylipins, lines overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic> showed an increased responsiveness to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> similar to ethylene-insensitive mutants. Both fresh seeds of <italic>RD20</italic>-overexpressing and <italic>ein2</italic> lines germinated later than their respective controls. Similarly, the germination of seeds of <italic>RD20-OE1</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE2</italic> lines was hypersensitive to exogenous <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>, as was that of <italic>ein2</italic> seeds. Together, all these results support the hypothesis that oxylipins generated by RD20 interact with ethylene to promote GA-dependent flowering, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref> sensitivity, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> accumulation. They also suggest that, among the oxylipins produced by RD20, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s are the active molecules. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref> appears to be a major factor in the regulation of GA-dependent flowering. The absence of other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s in oxylipin profiling, such as 12-hydroxy-9,12,15-octadecatrienoic acid or 16-hydroxy-9,12,15-octadecatrienoic acid, which would be characteristic of a chemical lipid oxidation pathway, suggests that active <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref> is of enzymatic origin. In accordance, an increase of chloroplastic 13-LOX activity has been shown to occur at the developmental transition to flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Ye et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Ba&#x00F1;uelos et al., 2008</xref>). Moreover, 13-LOX stimulation was also associated with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> increases, mainly due to a decline in ascorbate peroxidase activity acting as an enzymatic <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> scavenger (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Ye et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Chai et al., 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>RD20 Confers Stress Tolerance</title><p>Our results are in agreement with an antagonism between <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s and ethylene during development, leading to an accumulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref>. However, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> levels were strongly reduced in Paraquat-treated plants overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic> compared with controls, suggesting that an antagonism between <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref> and ethylene is unlikely to be relevant during defense responses. In support of this conclusion, lines overexpressing <italic>RD20</italic>, presumably less sensitive to ethylene in the scenario of an <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref> and ethylene antagonism, are remarkably resistant to Paraquat, while the ethylene-insensitive <italic>ein2</italic> mutant was susceptible to the herbicide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Alonso et al., 1999</xref>). Actually, tolerance to Paraquat appears to be linked to the presence of <italic>RD20</italic> rather than to ethylene perception, as shown by the analysis of the accumulation of RD20 transcripts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9C</xref>). This observation, however, is not in agreement with a recent report showing that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">9-HOT</xref> counteracts ethylene responses under oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">L&#x00F3;pez et al., 2011</xref>). The latter conclusion was mainly supported by the inability of the ethylene-overproducing mutant <italic>eto1</italic> to survive Rose Bengal treatment. Since ethylene was shown to induce defense genes, including <italic>RD20</italic>, through the activation of <italic>EFR1</italic> in response to harmful environmental conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Cheng et al., 2013</xref>), one possible explanation resides in the apparent lack of stimulation of <italic>ERF1</italic> expression in <italic>eto1</italic> by superoxide radical (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">L&#x00F3;pez et al., 2011</xref>), which might impair <italic>RD20</italic> expression and subsequent defense responses. Alternatively, we cannot exclude that ethylene biosynthesis and not its perception is determinant for its interplay with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s.</p><p>Both the 13- and 9-LOX pathways were induced by Paraquat. Sequential up-regulation of these pathways was also reported under high-light conditions and after severe cadmium treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Montillet et al., 2004</xref>). Among the oxylipins formed by these pathways, 13-LOX-derived <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s (in particular <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref>) accumulate after Paraquat treatment. Similarly, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref> has been found to accumulate during the initial stress responses to the release of singlet oxygen. This oxylipin was postulated to act as a second messenger in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">op den Camp et al., 2003</xref>). A putative role of caleosin in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> signaling is further supported by the recent report of the binding of a wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) RD20 homolog to G-proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Khalil et al., 2011</xref>) that are involved in signaling mediated by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Joo et al., 2005</xref>). The inability of the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant to enhance the production of 13-LOX-derived <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s rendered this mutant sensitive to Paraquat. Similarly, the absence of the 9-LOX pathway in the <italic>lox1 lox5</italic> mutant made this mutant particularly vulnerable to Rose Bengal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">L&#x00F3;pez et al., 2011</xref>). Thus, it seems that tolerance to oxidative stress requires the production of oxylipins derived from both the 13- and 9-LOX pathways. Additionally, &#x03B1;-dioxygenases might contribute to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref> accumulation and stress tolerance. In support of this hypothesis is the induction of <italic>&#x03B1;-DOX1</italic> by salt stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Tirajoh et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Aung, 2009</xref>) and the high sensitivity to Paraquat and salt exhibited by <italic>&#x03B1;-dox1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Ponce de Le&#x00F3;n et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Aung, 2009</xref>). Of note, roots of these mutants were reported to accumulate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> under salt treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Aung, 2009</xref>). Thus, at a given time, the composition of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref> mixture would depend on the induction of lipid peroxidation and/or on the expression/activity of the different biosynthetic enzymes that vary based on the nature of the stress (e.g. photooxidation, heavy metals, or salt) and on the fatty acid composition of the organ examined. In this context, RD20 plays a determinant role by generating <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s that affect the oxidative status. From our data and the points discussed here, we propose a model according to which RD20 produces oxylipins that alleviate stress through tolerance mechanisms that include <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> reduction and, thereby, allow the delay of flowering. In consequence, the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant, depleted in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s, is more vulnerable to stress and in response activates the reproductive stage early to escape stress. Our results clearly highlight the importance of the peroxygenase catalytic activity of RD20 in the regulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> accumulation during the floral transition and stress tolerance and open new perspectives for caleosin function.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s13" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>The Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) ecotypes <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">Col-0</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">Ws</xref> were used for this study. Generally, seeds were sown on a standard soil compost mixture, and seedlings were grown individually in growth chambers under white fluorescent lamps (60 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. The temperature was 22&#x00B0;C during the day (12 h) and 19&#x00B0;C during the night (12 h). To study the effect of the photoperiod on flowering, young seedlings (about 1 cm in height) were placed in growth chambers with similar controlled temperature and humidity under either short (8 h) or long (16 h) light conditions. Copper toxicity studies were performed with transgenic and control lines that were transferred as young seedlings (about 1 cm in height) into soil containing pentahydrated CuSO<sub>4</sub> (485 &#x00B5;g g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> soil). To study the effect of oxidative stress, seeds were sterilized using the vapor-phase sterilization protocol. To that end, seeds were placed in open 1.5-mL tubes under a bell jar containing a beaker with 20 mL of bleach (sodium hypochlorite solution). Two milliliters of fuming hydrochloric acid (37% v/v) was added to the bleach, and seeds were sterilized for 4 h. Sterilized seeds were sown on 2.2 g L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Murashige and Skoog basal medium (Sigma-Aldrich) with 7% (w/v) agar and 15 g L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Suc at pH 5.7 supplemented with 0.5 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> Paraquat, 20 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> Rose Bengal, or 0.1 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid. After 2 d of stratification at 4&#x00B0;C, plants were grown under continuous light, and 7-d-old leaves were analyzed for anthocyanin contents. Alternatively, plants were grown at 22&#x00B0;C during the day (16 h) under 70 to 90 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> light and 20&#x00B0;C at night (8 h) without the presence of superoxide inducers. Two-week-old seedlings were then sprayed with water or Paraquat solutions (5 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> in water). At 12 h after this treatment, green leaves were counted, and after an additional 12 h, the leaves were harvested and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen for quantitative PCR analysis. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> status, number of green leaves, and cell death were analyzed on 7-d-old plants after 24 h of treatment with 5 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> Paraquat or water. Importantly, to ensure the reproducibility of our results, we compared plants sown and grown side by side under identical environmental conditions. To test germination, seeds were rapidly washed with ethanol containing 0.01% Tween 20 (v/v) and then surface sterilized with 40% (v/v) bleach and washed five times with distilled water. Sterile seeds were plated on freshly prepared Murashige and Skoog medium supplemented with 1.5% (w/v) Suc and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>, or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s, as needed. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s were purchased from Cayman Chemical (SPI-BIO), and their purity was controlled by HPLC. Freshly made plates were stratified in darkness for 2 to 4 d at 4&#x00B0;C and then transferred to a tissue culture room at 23&#x00B0;C under 4,000 lx light intensity with a 16-h-light period. Seeds were considered as germinated when radicles completely penetrated the seed coats. Postemergence growth was estimated by counting green cotyledons. Of note, the transgenic plants and their respective controls underwent two consecutive reproductive developmental cycles in a similar environment before their seeds were collected. Seeds were stored under identical conditions for at least 1 month before the experiments. In contrast, seeds used to study the break of dormancy were used immediately after harvesting and analyzed for germination without the stratification step.</p><sec id="s14"><title>Generation of <italic>RD20</italic>-Overexpressing Plants</title><p>To obtain overexpressing plants, <italic>RD20</italic> full-length complementary DNA (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def20">cDNA</xref>) was PCR amplified (primers 1 and 2; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>) and transferred to the binary vector pB7WG<sub>2</sub> using Gateway technology procedures (Invitrogen, Life Technologies). Plasmids containing <italic>RD20</italic> or the empty vector were introduced into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain GV3101 by electroporation. Transgenic Arabidopsis plants were generated by the floral dip method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Clough and Bent, 1998</xref>) and screened to homozygosity with the herbicide phosphinothricin (Basta; 0.3 g L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). To generate <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>RD20<sup>H133A</sup></italic> lines, the residue His-133 was mutated to Val using the QuickChange site-directed mutagenesis kit of Stratagene (Agilent Technologies) with the sense mutations primer called H133 in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link> (the modified codon is underlined, and the nucleotide changed is indicated in boldface). The mutated gene was transferred to the vector pB7WG<sub>2</sub>, and the resulting plasmid was used to transform <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> and wild-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">Col-0</xref> Arabidopsis.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">T-DNA</xref> Insertion Mutant and Complementation</title><p><italic>rd20</italic> was discovered in the Arabidopsis thaliana Integrated Database, and seeds were obtained from the Arabidopsis thaliana Resource Centre for Genomics (line DSA78, T-DNA_LB.FLAG.237F07; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ijpb.versailles.inra.fr">http://www.ijpb.versailles.inra.fr</ext-link>). Primers 3, 4, and 5 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>) were used to screen for homozygous mutants. For complementation of the <italic>rd20</italic> mutant, we used Gateway technology procedures to transfer the <italic>RD20</italic> gene from the vector pB7WG<sub>2</sub> to the binary pH<sub>2</sub>GW<sub>7</sub> vector to gain hygromycin resistance. The latter vector was used to transform <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">Ws</xref> wild-type Arabidopsis via <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> transformation and floral dipping.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Protein Expression and Purification</title><p>Full-length <italic>RD20</italic> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def20">cDNA</xref> was PCR amplified using primers 6 and 7 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). The amplified product after sequencing verification was transferred to the yeast constitutive vector pVT102U (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Vernet et al., 1987</xref>) in the <italic>Bam</italic>HI and <italic>Xba</italic>I sites. The expression of the recombinant FLAG-tagged <italic>RD20</italic> in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> Wa6 was conducted as described for other peroxygenases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hanano et al., 2006</xref>), and its purification on anti-FLAG M2 affinity gel was mostly according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s procedures (Sigma-Aldrich), except that each step was realized in the presence of detergent (0.1% CHAPS). Western-blot analysis was performed as reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hanano et al., 2006</xref>) by using a monoclonal anti-FLAG M2 antibody produced in mouse (Sigma-Aldrich).</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Enzymatic Activity of RD20</title><p>Aniline hydroxylation in the presence of a hydroperoxide cosubstrate produces <italic>N</italic>-phenylhydroxylamine that is spontaneously transformed into nitrobenzene. The absorbance of nitrobenzene was followed at 310 nm in a spectrometric cuvette containing yeast extract or microsomes expressing RD20 or RD20 purified fraction in 0.1 <sc>m</sc> KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> (pH 7.4) containing 1 m<sc>m</sc> aniline. The reaction was initiated by adding 1 m<sc>m</sc> cumene hydroperoxide (total volume, 1 mL). Epoxidase activities supported by peroxygenase were assayed as described before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Bl&#x00E9;e and Durst, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Bl&#x00E9;e and Schuber, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">1990</xref>). Hydroperoxide reductase activity of purified RD20 was measured using radiolabeled <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s. [1-<sup>14</sup>C]<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">13-HPOD</xref> and [1-<sup>14</sup>C]13-HPOT were synthesized enzymatically from [1-<sup>14</sup>C]linoleic acid (50 Ci mol<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) and [1-<sup>14</sup>C]linolenic acid (50 Ci mol<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>; PerkinElmer Life Sciences) in the presence of soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic>) lipoxygenase (Sigma-Aldrich). Potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>) lipoxygenase (Cayman Chemical, SPI-BIO) was used to obtain 9-HPOT from linolenic acid as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Galliard and Phillips, 1971</xref>). [1-<sup>14</sup>C]<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s were incubated with purified RD20 (5 &#x00B5;g of protein) in 500 &#x00B5;L of 0.1 <sc>m</sc> sodium acetate (pH 5.5) for 2 h or overnight at 27&#x00B0;C. The reaction was stopped by adding two drops of 4 <sc>n</sc> HCl, and the products were extracted by 3&#x00D7; 2 mL of a mixture of dichloromethane:ether (1:1, v/v). The organic phase was evaporated under argon, and the residue was dissolved into 25 &#x00B5;L of acetonitrile. Metabolites of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s were separated by HPLC on a Lichrospher 100 RP-18 (5 &#x00B5;m) column (Interchim) using a mixture of acetonitrile:water:acetic acid (50:50:0.1, v/v/v) as solvent (0.5 mL min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). Radioactivity was analyzed with a 500 TR Radiomatic-Flo-one detector (Packard Instrument, PerkinElmer). Identification of the metabolites of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s was performed using a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">GC-MS</xref> spectrometer (Agilent 5973N) with an ionizing energy of 70 eV. The sample was injected directly in splitless mode (injector temperature of 250&#x00B0;C) into a DB-5-coated fused column (30 m, 0.25 mm i.d.) with a temperature program of 6&#x00B0;C min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> from 60&#x00B0;C to 100&#x00B0;C followed by 3&#x00B0;C min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> from 100&#x00B0;C to 300&#x00B0;C (mass-to-charge ratio = 50&#x2013;700).</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>RNA Analysis</title><p>Total RNA was isolated from pooled leaf tissues using the Nucleospin RNA plant kit (Macherey-Nagel). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def20">cDNA</xref> was synthesized from total RNA using SuperScript III (Invitrogen, Life Technologies) with random hexamer primers according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">qRT</xref>-PCR plates were prepared with a Biomek 3000 (Beckman Coulter) and run on a Light Cycler 480 II (Roche). Each reaction was prepared using 2 &#x00B5;L of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def20">cDNA</xref>, 5 &#x00B5;L of Light Cycler 480 SYBR Green I Master (Roche), and 250 n<sc>m</sc> of forward and reverse primers in a total volume of 10 &#x00B5;L. The amplification profile consisted of 95&#x00B0;C for 10 min and 40 cycles (95&#x00B0;C denaturation for 10 s, annealing at 60&#x00B0;C for 15 s, and extension at 72&#x00B0;C for 15 s), followed by melting curve analysis from 55&#x00B0;C to 95&#x00B0;C to check the specificity of transcripts. All reactions were performed in triplicate. Primers used for all the quantitative PCRs performed in this study are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>. Vacuolar protein Monensin Sensitivity1 (At2g28390), TAP42 Interacting Protein1-like (At4g34270), and the uncharacterized conserved protein UCP022280 (At4g26410) were taken as reference genes to normalize the expression of genes of interest.</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Anthocyanin Determination</title><p>The pigments were extracted and their content in leaves was estimated by spectrophotometry essentially as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Rabino and Mancinelli, 1986</xref>). Plant tissues (about 9 mg) in 300 &#x00B5;L of acidic methanol (containing 1% [w/v] HCl) were rapidly frozen in liquid nitrogen and ground (2&#x00D7; 30 s) in the presence of two steel balls and left for 48 h at 4&#x00B0;C in the dark to extract the pigments. The absorbance of the methanol layer was measured on a Shimadzu MPS-2000 spectrophotometer at wavelengths of 530 and 657 nm. The formula <italic>A</italic><sub>530</sub> &#x2212; 0.25 &#x00D7; <italic>A</italic><sub>657</sub> was used to compensate for the contribution of chlorophyll and its degradation products to the absorption at 530 nm.</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Oxylipin Profiling</title><p>For analysis of free oxylipins, 0.8 to 2.1 g of frozen plant material was extracted as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">G&#x00F6;bel et al., 2002</xref>) with some modifications. After adding 20 mL of extraction medium (3:2 [v/v] <italic>n</italic>-hexane:2-propanol with 0.0025% [w/v] butylated hydroxytoluene) containing 13-hydroperoxy-6,9,11-octadecatrienoic acid, plant material was immediately homogenized with an Ultra Turrax homogenizer under streaming argon on ice for 30 s. The extract was shaken for 10 min and centrifuged at 3,200<italic>g</italic> at 4&#x00B0;C for 10 min. The upper phase was collected, and a 6.7% (w/v) solution of potassium sulfate was added to a volume of 32.5 mL. After vigorous shaking and centrifugation at 3,200<italic>g</italic> at 4&#x00B0;C for 10 min, the upper hexane-rich layer was subsequently dried under streaming nitrogen. The remaining lipids were redissolved in methanol:water:acetic acid (75:25:0.1, v/v/v). Further analysis was carried out on an Agilent 1100 HPLC system coupled to a diode array detector. At first, oxylipins were purified by reverse-phase HPLC on an ET250/2 Nucleosil 120-5 C18 column (2.1 &#x00D7; 250 mm, 5 &#x00B5;m particle size; Macherey-Nagel), with a solvent system of methanol:water:acetic acid (85:15:0.1, v/v/v) and a flow rate of 0.18 mL min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. For the detection of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s, <italic>A</italic><sub>234</sub> indicating the conjugated diene system was recorded. For the quantification of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s, straight-phase HPLC was carried out on a Zorbax Rx-SIL column (2.1 &#x00D7; 150 mm, 5 &#x00B5;m particle size; Agilent) with a solvent system of <italic>n</italic>-hexane:2-propanol:trifluoroacetic acid (100:1:0.02, v/v/v) and a flow rate of 0.2 mL min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. Free oxylipins were quantified using 13-hydroperoxy-6,9,11-octadecatrienoic acid as an internal standard to determine the recovery of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">FAOH</xref>s and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">FAOOH</xref>s. Calibration curves (five-point measurements) for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">13-HOD</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">13-HOT</xref> were established.</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Characterization and Quantification of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref></title><p>Characterization and quantification of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> were performed by comparing retention times and mass spectrometry and tandem mass spectrometry transition analyses using an ultra-performance liquid chromatograph coupled to a tandem mass spectrometer. All analyses were performed using a Waters Quattro Premier XE equipped with an electrospray ionization source and coupled to an Acquity ultra-performance liquid chromatography system (Waters). Chromatographic separation was achieved using the Acquity UPLC BEH C<sub>18</sub> column (100 &#x00D7; 2.1 mm, 1.7 &#x00B5;m; Waters) coupled to the Acquity UPLC BEH C<sub>18</sub> precolumn (2.1 &#x00D7; 5 mm, 1.7 &#x00B5;m; Waters). The mobile phase consisted of a mixture of water (99.9%; acidified with 0.1% formic acid [A]) and methanol (99.9%; acidified with 0.1% formic acid [B]). The following gradient was used: 95% solvent A and 5% solvent B (1 min), linear gradient of 95% A to 100% B (10 min), 100% B was maintained during 2 min, and then during 2 min the gradient was set to the initial condition. The total run time was 15 min. The column was operated at 35&#x00B0;C with a flow rate of 0.35 mL min<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> (sample injection volume of 3 &#x00B5;L). Nitrogen generated from pressurized air in an N2G nitrogen generator (Mistral) was used as the drying and nebulizing gas. The nebulizer gas flow was set to approximately 50 L h<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> and the desolvation gas flow to 900 L h<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. The interface temperature was set at 400&#x00B0;C and the source temperature at 135&#x00B0;C. The capillary voltage was set at 3.2 kV and the cone voltage at 25 V. The ionization mode (positive and negative) was adjusted by using commercially available standard molecules. Low-mass and high-mass resolution were 13 for both mass analyzers, ion energies 1 and 2 were 0.5 V, entrance and exit potentials were 2 and 1 V, and detector (multiplier) gain was 650 V. Collision-induced dissociation of protonated or deprotonated parent ions was accomplished with a collision energy of 10 V. Daughter scan monitoring permitted us to identify for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> the transition from the parent ion. The combination of chromatographic retention time, parent mass, and unique fragment ion analysis was used to selectively monitor <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> (209 &gt; 59). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">JA</xref> quantification was obtained by injecting different concentrations (ng mL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> to &#x00B5;g mL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) of commercially available standard phytohormone. The peak area of each peak obtained after ultra-performance liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry analysis was used for the establishment of calibration curves. Data acquisition and analysis were performed with the MassLynx software (version 4.1) running under Windows XP Professional on a Pentium personal computer.</p></sec><sec id="s22"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ROS</xref> Content and Cell Death Estimations</title><p>Detection of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></xref> by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def17">DAB</xref> staining and superoxide radical by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">NBT</xref> staining were performed by standard methods as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Thordal-Christensen et al., 1997</xref>). Images were obtained with a Leica macrofluo Z16 APO equipped with a Leica DFC camera (Leica Microsystems). Quantification of the staining was performed with ImageJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Schneider et al., 2012</xref>) in arbitrary units. Leaves were stained with Trypan Blue to visualize cell death, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Koch and Slusarenko (1990)</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s23"><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Figure S1.</ext-link></bold> Expression analysis of the <italic>RD20</italic> caleosin/peroxygenase gene in Arabidopsis.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Figure S2.</ext-link></bold> Coexpression analysis of <italic>RD20</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Figure S3.</ext-link></bold> Mass spectrum of the methyl trimethylsilyl ester of 15,16-epoxy,13-hydroxy-9,11-octadecenoic acid.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Figure S4.</ext-link></bold> Inhibition of peroxygenase activity by mutation of the catalytic residue His-133.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Figure S5.</ext-link></bold> Deletion of RD20-modified seed germination and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">ABA</xref>-dependent germination.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Figure S6.</ext-link></bold> Free oxylipin analysis of <italic>rd20</italic> and <italic>RD20-OE</italic> leaves sprayed with water or with 5 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> parathion.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Table S1.</ext-link></bold> Primers used for the generation of transgenic plants and expression in yeast.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.245316/DC1">Supplemental Table S2.</ext-link></bold> Primers used for reverse transcription-PCR analysis.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the following colleagues from the Institut de Biologie Mol&#x00E9;culaire des Plantes for support: Martine Flenet for molecular cloning; Vincent Compagnon for primary reverse transcription-PCR analysis; Martha Ramel, Michel Kerneis, and S&#x00E9;bastien Staerck for plant production; J&#x00E9;r&#x00F4;me Mutterer and Mathieu Erhardt for microscopy; Alain Rahier for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">GC-MS</xref> technique; and Patrick Achard for stimulating discussions. We thank Sabine Freitag from the Albrecht-von-Haller Institute for technical help with oxylipin analysis and also Francis Schuber from School of Pharmacy, University of Strasbourg, Illkirch, France for critical reading of the article.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique and the French Ministry for Research.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baghour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapple</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Straeten</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Genschik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The plant stress hormone ethylene controls floral transition via DELLA-dependent regulation of floral meristem-identity genes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>6484</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6489</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>De Grauwe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Decat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoutteten</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Straeten</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Integration of plant responses to environmentally activated phytohormonal signals</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>311</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>94</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nourizadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>EIN2, a bifunctional transducer of ethylene and stress responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>284</volume>: <fpage>2148</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2152</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aubert</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vile</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pervent</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranty</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Simonneau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vavasseur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Galaud</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>RD20, a stress-inducible caleosin, participates in stomatal control, transpiration and drought tolerance in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1975</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1987</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="thesis"><bold>Aung TST</bold> (2009) Regulation of &#x03B1;-dioxygenase expression and functional analysis in salt-stressed Arabidopsis thaliana. PhD thesis. Simon Fraser University, Burnaby, Canada</citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomashow</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The 5&#x2032;-region of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana cor15a</italic> has <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements that confer cold-, drought- and ABA-regulated gene expression</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>701</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>713</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ba&#x00F1;uelos</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Argumedo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vellanoweth</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The developmental transition to flowering in Arabidopsis is associated with an increase in leaf chloroplastic lipoxygenase activity</article-title>. <source>Plant Sci</source> <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>366</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>373</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaudoin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Serizet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraudat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Interactions between abscisic acid and ethylene signaling cascades</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1103</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1115</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E9;e</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Phytooxylipins and plant defense reactions</article-title>. <source>Prog Lipid Res</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>72</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E9;e</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Durst</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Hydroperoxide-dependent sulfoxidation catalyzed by soybean microsomes</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source> <volume>254</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>52</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E9;e</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Flenet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boachon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauconnier</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A non-canonical caleosin from Arabidopsis efficiently epoxidizes physiological unsaturated fatty acids with complete stereoselectivity</article-title>. <source>FEBS J</source> <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>3981</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3995</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E9;e</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Mechanism of S-oxidation reactions catalyzed by a soybean hydroperoxide-dependent oxygenase</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>4962</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4967</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E9;e</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Efficient epoxidation of unsaturated fatty acids by a hydroperoxide-dependent oxygenase</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>265</volume>: <fpage>12887</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12894</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E9;e</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marnett</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Mechanism of reaction of fatty acid hydroperoxides with soybean peroxygenase</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>268</volume>: <fpage>1708</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1715</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zouhar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Avila</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Girke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Raikhel</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The vegetative vacuole proteome of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> reveals predicted and unexpected proteins</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>3285</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3303</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lio</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Regulation of the flowering time of Arabidopsis thaliana by thylakoid ascorbate peroxidase</article-title>. <source>Afr J Biotechnol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>7151</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7157</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JCF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Cloning and secondary structure analysis of caleosin, a unique calcium-binding protein in oil bodies of plant seeds</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1079</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1086</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis ETHYLENE RESPONSE FACTOR1 regulates abiotic stress-responsive gene expression by binding to different cis-acting elements in response to different stress signals</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>162</volume>: <fpage>1566</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1582</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Floral dip: a simplified method for Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>743</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Debeaujon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Gibberellin requirement for <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> seed germination is determined both by testa characteristics and embryonic abscisic acid</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>415</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>424</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehlting</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauveplane</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Olry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginglinger</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Provart</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Werck-Reichhart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>An extensive (co-)expression analysis tool for the cytochrome P450 superfamily in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feussner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasternack</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The lipoxygenase pathway</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>297</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiratsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohme-Takagi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A dehydration-induced NAC protein, RD26, is involved in a novel ABA-dependent stress-signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>863</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>876</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galliard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>Lipoxygenase from potato tubers: partial purification and properties of an enzyme that specifically oxygenates the 9-position of linoleic acid</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>438</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaquerel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Steppuhn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Nicotiana attenuata &#x03B1;-DIOXYGENASE1 through its production of 2-hydroxylinolenic acid is required for intact plant defense expression against attack from Manduca sexta larvae</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>196</volume>: <fpage>574</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>585</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gechev</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Breusegem</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Denev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Laloi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Reactive oxygen species as signals that modulate plant stress responses and programmed cell death</article-title>. <source>BioEssays</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1091</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1101</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghassemian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nambara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawaide</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>McCourt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Regulation of abscisic acid signaling by the ethylene response pathway in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1117</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1126</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x00F6;bel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Feussner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosahl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Oxylipin profiling in pathogen-infected potato leaves</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1584</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>64</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Regio- and stereochemical analysis of trihydroxyoctadecenoic acids derived from linoleic acid 9- and 13-hydroperoxides</article-title>. <source>Lipids</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>415</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Hydroperoxide-dependent epoxidation of unsaturated fatty acids in the broad bean (Vicia faba L.)</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>409</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>416</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Alpha-oxidation of fatty acids in higher plants: identification of a pathogen-inducible oxygenase (piox) as an alpha-dioxygenase and biosynthesis of 2-hydroperoxylinolenic acid</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>274</volume>: <fpage>24503</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24513</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Activation of the fatty acid alpha-dioxygenase pathway during bacterial infection of tobacco leaves: formation of oxylipins protecting against cell death</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>278</volume>: <fpage>51796</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>51805</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burcklen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Flenet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivancich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Louwagie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bl&#x00E9;e</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Plant seed peroxygenase is an original heme-oxygenase with an EF-hand calcium binding motif</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>33140</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>33151</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hettenhausen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x00FC;nsche</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>High levels of jasmonic acid antagonize the biosynthesis of gibberellins and inhibit the growth of <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic> stems</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>591</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>606</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hernandez-Pinzon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Brassica napus</italic> calcium-binding protein caleosin has distinct endoplasmic reticulum- and lipid body-associated isoforms</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>615</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>622</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The pepper 9-lipoxygenase gene <italic>CaLOX1</italic> functions in defense and cell death responses to microbial pathogens</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>152</volume>: <fpage>948</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>967</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishimaru</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Hydroperoxide-dependent hydroxylation involving &#x201C;H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-reducible hemoprotein&#x201D; in microsomes of pea seeds: a new type enzyme acting on hydroperoxide and a physiological role of seed lipoxygenase</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>252</volume>: <fpage>6118</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6124</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Utsugi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanakamaru</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Enomoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsuhara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Biomarkers of green roof vegetation: anthocyanin and chlorophyll as stress marker pigments for plant stresses of roof environments</article-title>. <source>J Environ Econ Manage</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>27</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzen</surname><given-names>JTC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Caleosin serves as the major structural protein as efficient as oleosin on the surface of seed oil bodies</article-title>. <source>Plant Signal Behav</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>449</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedoroff</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Different signaling and cell death roles of heterotrimeric G protein &#x03B1; and &#x03B2; subunits in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> oxidative stress response to ozone</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>957</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>970</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ralevski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Donayo</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulick</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Heterotrimeric G&#x03B1; subunit from wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>), GA3, interacts with the calcium-binding protein, Clo3, and the phosphoinositide-specific phospholipase C, PI-PLC1</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>158</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeung</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A stress-responsive caleosin-like protein, AtCLO4, acts as a negative regulator of ABA responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>874</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>884</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Slusarenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is susceptible to infection by a downy mildew fungus</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>445</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kucera</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leubner-Metzger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Plant hormone interactions during seed dormancy release and germination</article-title>. <source>Seed Sci Res</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>307</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x00F3;pez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulasekaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vellosillo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Irigoyen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Casc&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bannenberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Antagonistic role of 9-lipoxygenase-derived oxylipins and ethylene in the control of oxidative stress, lipid peroxidation and plant defence</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>458</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manavella</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Arce</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dezar</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Renou</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Crespi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Cross-talk between ethylene and drought signalling pathways is mediated by the sunflower Hahb-4 transcription factor</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>137</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montillet</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cacas</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Montan&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Douki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessoule</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Polkowska-Kowalczyk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Maciejewska</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vial</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The upstream oxylipin profile of Arabidopsis thaliana: a tool to scan for oxidative stresses</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>451</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montillet</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chamnongpol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rust&#x00E9;rucci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Cotte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Battesti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Inz&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Breusegem</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Triantaphylid&#x00E8;s</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Fatty acid hydroperoxides and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in the execution of hypersensitive cell death in tobacco leaves</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>1516</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1526</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mosblech</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Feussner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Heilmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Oxylipins: structurally diverse metabolites from fatty acid oxidation</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>511</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>517</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naested</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Frandsen</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Jauh</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Pinzon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Caleosins: Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding proteins associated with lipid bodies</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>463</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>476</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nuccio</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>ATS1 and ATS3: two novel embryo-specific genes in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1153</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1163</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>op den Camp</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Przybyla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochsenbein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Laloi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Danon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hideg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x00F6;bel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Feussner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Rapid induction of distinct stress responses after the release of singlet oxygen in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2320</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2332</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Roles of a membrane-bound caleosin and putative peroxygenase in biotic and abiotic stress responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>796</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>806</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ponce de Le&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Involvement of the Arabidopsis &#x03B1;-DOX1 fatty acid dioxygenase in protection against oxidative stress and cell death</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>62</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poxleitner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacey Samuels</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A role for caleosin in degradation of oil-body storage lipid during seed germination</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>917</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>933</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prost</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhondt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kift</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonne</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Esquerr&#x00E9;-Tugay&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosahl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of the antimicrobial activities of plant oxylipins supports their involvement in defense against pathogens</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1902</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1913</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purkrtova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Bon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kralova</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ropers</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Anton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chardot</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Caleosin of Arabidopsis thaliana: effect of calcium on functional and structural properties</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>11217</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11224</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabino</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancinelli</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Light, temperature, and anthocyanin production</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>922</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>924</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raffaele</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mongrand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Niebel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide annotation of remorins, a plant-specific protein family: evolutionary and functional perspectives</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>593</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>600</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Birtic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Soubigou-Taconnat</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Triantaphylid&#x00E8;s</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Havaux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Carotenoid oxidation products are stress signals that mediate gene responses to singlet oxygen in plants</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>5535</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5540</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rust&#x00E9;rucci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Montillet</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Battesti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessoule</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Etienne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Suty</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Blein</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Involvement of lipoxygenase-dependent production of fatty acid hydroperoxides in the development of the hypersensitive cell death induced by cryptogein on tobacco leaves</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>274</volume>: <fpage>36446</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>36455</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasband</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliceiri</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>671</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>675</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Leaf oil body functions as a subcellular factory for the production of a phytoalexin in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>164</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>118</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Petracek</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fledderman</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Heiman</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Warrior</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Salicylate activity. 1. Protection of plants from paraquat injury</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>9764</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9768</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szczerba</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Britto</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronzucker</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>K<sup>+</sup> transport in plants: physiology and molecular biology</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source> <volume>166</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>466</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>An Arabidopsis gene encoding a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding protein is induced by abscisic acid during dehydration</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>898</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>903</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thordal-Christensen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Collonge</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Subcellular localization of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in plants: H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation in papillae and hypersensitive response during the barley-powdery mildew interaction</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1187</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1194</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tirajoh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aung</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Plant</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Stress-responsive alpha-dioxygenase expression in tomato roots</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>713</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>723</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vellosillo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x00F3;pez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Casc&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Oxylipins produced by the 9-lipoxygenase pathway in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> regulate lateral root development and defense responses through a specific signaling cascade</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>831</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>846</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vernet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dignard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>A family of yeast expression vectors containing the phage f1 intergenic region</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>233</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Heckman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Gibberellin is required for flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> under short days</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>408</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koizumi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Urao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of 9 cDNAs for genes that are responsive to desiccation in Arabidopsis thaliana: sequence analysis of one cDNA that encodes a putative transmembrane channel protein</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>224</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Plant hormone jasmonate prioritizes defense over growth by interfering with gibberellin signaling cascade</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>E1192</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>E1200</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>de los Santos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vellanoweth</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The developmental transition to flowering represses ascorbate peroxidase activity and induces enzymatic lipid peroxidation in leaf tissue in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Plant Sci</source> <volume>158</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>127</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshiba</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyosue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Correlation between the induction of a gene for delta 1-pyrroline-5-carboxylate synthetase and the accumulation of proline in Arabidopsis thaliana under osmotic stress</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>751</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>760</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
