<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">199109</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.199109</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>RESEARCH ARTICLES - FOCUS ISSUE</subject></subj-group><series-title>FOCUS ISSUE ON UBIQUITIN IN PLANT BIOLOGY</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Light-Response BTB1 and BTB2 Proteins Assemble Nuclear Ubiquitin Ligases That Modify Phytochrome B and D Signaling in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[OA]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Christians</surname><given-names>Matthew J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn2"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gingerich</surname><given-names>Derek J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>Zhihua</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lauer</surname><given-names>Timothy D.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>Richard D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><aff>Department of Genetics, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin 53706 (M.J.C., D.J.G., Z.H., R.D.V); and Department of Biology, University of Wisconsin, Eau Claire, Wisconsin 54702 (D.J.G., T.D.L)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation Arabidopsis 2010 Program (grant no. MCB&#x2013;0929100 to R.D.V.), by the National Science Foundation Research in Undergraduate Institutions Program (grant no. 0919678 to D.J.G.), and by the National Institutes of Health (Ruth L. Kirschstein postdoctoral fellowship no. F32&#x2013;GM68361 to D.J.G.).</p></fn><fn id="afn1" fn-type="equal"><label>2</label><p>These authors contributed equally to the article.</p></fn><fn id="afn2"><label>3</label><p>Present address: Department of Cellular and Molecular Biology, Grand Valley State University, Allendale, MI 49401.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>vierstra@wisc.edu</email>.</corresp><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Richard D. Vierstra (<email>vierstra@wisc.edu</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[OA]</label><p>Open Access articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.199109">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.199109</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>9</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>160</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>04</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2012 American Society of Plant Biologists. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p></p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Members of the Bric-a-Brac/Tramtrack/Broad Complex (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref>) family direct the selective ubiquitylation of proteins following their assembly into Cullin3-based ubiquitin ligases. Here, we describe a subfamily of nucleus-localized <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> proteins encoded by the <italic>LIGHT-RESPONSE BTB1</italic> (<italic>LRB1</italic>) and <italic>LRB2</italic> loci in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) that strongly influences photomorphogenesis. Whereas single <italic>lrb1</italic> and <italic>lrb2</italic> mutants are relatively normal phenotypically, double mutants are markedly hypersensitive to red light, but not to far-red or blue light, and are compromised in multiple photomorphogenic processes, including seed germination, cotyledon opening and expansion, chlorophyll accumulation, shade avoidance, and flowering time. This red light hypersensitivity can be overcome by eliminating phytochrome B (phyB) and phyD, indicating that LRB1/2 act downstream of these two photoreceptor isoforms. Levels of phyB/D proteins but not their messenger RNAs are abnormally high in light-grown <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> plants, implying that their light-dependent turnover is substantially dampened. Whereas other red light-hypersensitive mutants accumulate phyA protein similar to or higher than the wild type in light, the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants accumulate less, suggesting that LRB1/2 also positively regulate phyA levels in a phyB/D-dependent manner. Together, these data show that the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> ubiquitin ligases assembled with LRB1/2 function redundantly as negative regulators of photomorphogenesis, possibly by influencing the turnover of phyB/D.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">BTB</term><def id="def1"><p>Bric-a-Brac/Tramtrack/Broad Complex</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">UPS</term><def id="def2"><p>ubiquitin/26S proteasome system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">Ub</term><def id="def3"><p>ubiquitin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">CRL</term><def id="def4"><p>cullin-RING ligase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">phy</term><def id="def5"><p>phytochrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">B</term><def id="def6"><p>blue light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">R</term><def id="def7"><p>red light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8">FR</term><def id="def8"><p>far-red light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9">Col-0</term><def id="def9"><p>ecotype Columbia-0</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term10">PIF</term><def id="def10"><p>Phytochrome-Interacting Factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term11">bHLH</term><def id="def11"><p>basic helix-loop-helix</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term12">BACK</term><def id="def12"><p>BTB-and-C-terminal-Kelch</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term13">NLS</term><def id="def13"><p>nuclear localization sequence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term14">RT</term><def id="def14"><p>reverse transcription</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term15">Y2H</term><def id="def15"><p>yeast two-hybrid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term16">LDs</term><def id="def16"><p>long days</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term17">SDs</term><def id="def17"><p>short days</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term18">Rc</term><def id="def18"><p>continuous red light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term19">FRc</term><def id="def19"><p>continuous far-red light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term20">Bc</term><def id="def20"><p>continuous blue light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term21">EOD</term><def id="def21"><p>end-of-day</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term22">q</term><def id="def22"><p>real-time quantitative</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term23">JA</term><def id="def23"><p>jasmonic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term24">JTT</term><def id="def24"><p>Jones-Taylor-Thornton</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term25">MS</term><def id="def25"><p>Murashige and Skoog</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term26">qRT</term><def id="def26"><p>quantitative reverse transcription</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term27">cDNA</term><def id="def27"><p>complementary DNA</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>The selective breakdown of short-lived regulatory proteins is a key feature of many signal transduction pathways, thus providing a mechanism to enhance or quench output when repressors or activators are the respective targets. In eukaryotes, much of this specific turnover is mediated by the ubiquitin/26S proteasome system (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">UPS</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Smalle and Vierstra, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Kerscher et al., 2006</xref>). Here, polymeric chains of ubiquitin (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ub</xref>) are covalently attached to proteins destined for degradation via an ATP-dependent, E1-E2-E3 conjugation cascade. These poly-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ub</xref> moieties are then recognized by the 26S proteasome, a 2.5-MD protease complex that directs proteolysis of the target with the concomitant release of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ub</xref> moieties for reuse. The specificity of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">UPS</xref> resides mainly in the E3 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ub</xref> protein ligases that choose appropriate proteins for ubiquitylation. E3s recognize structural motifs in the target and then catalyze an isopeptide linkage between the C-terminal Gly of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ub</xref> and an accessible lysl &epsiv;-amino group in the target, using an E2-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ub</xref> thioester intermediate as the donor. Substantial variations in E3 sequence and organization generate the wide range of specificities needed to handle the myriad of likely <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">UPS</xref> substrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Vierstra, 2009</xref>). In Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), for example, phylogenetic analyses have identified well over 1,500 possible E3 genes, with genetic studies on a few implying that many have unique substrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Vierstra, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hua and Vierstra, 2011</xref>).</p><p>The multisubunit Cullin-RING Ligases (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRLs</xref>) are a highly polymorphic collection of E3s composed of a Cullin (CUL) backbone subunit onto which assembles the E2-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ub</xref>-docking RING Box1 (RBX1) protein and a diverse assortment of adaptors that recruit ubiquitylation substrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hua and Vierstra, 2011</xref>). One prominent <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRL</xref> subtype encompasses the Bric-a-Brac/Tramtrack/Broad Complex (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref>) E3s. They contain RBX1, the CUL3 isoform, and a member from the large family of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> target-recognition adaptors that docks with CUL3 via a signature approximately 95-amino acid <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Furukawa et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Xu et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Stogios et al., 2005</xref>). In Arabidopsis and rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic>), 81 and 149 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> proteins are predicted that employ an array of target recognition domains, including Meprin and TRAF Homology, NON-PHOTOTROPIC HYPOCOTYL3, ankyrin, TAZ-zinc finger, and tetratricopeptide repeat domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Dieterle et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Figueroa et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gingerich et al., 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">2007</xref>). Initial genetic analyses with Arabidopsis have shown that several <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> subfamilies regulate physiologically important processes in plants. Examples include roles in ethylene biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Wang et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Christians et al., 2009</xref>), abscisic acid signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Lechner et al., 2011</xref>), plant defense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Spoel et al., 2009</xref>), gametophyte development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Robert et al., 2009</xref>), phototropism and auxin-regulated organogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Motchoulski and Liscum, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Sakai et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Cheng et al., 2007</xref>), and leaf/flower morphogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hepworth et al., 2005</xref>).</p><p>Given the importance of light for both photosynthesis and as a measure of diurnal and seasonal cycles, plants have evolved a sophisticated set of interconnected transduction pathways to perceive and respond appropriately to light. Upstream are three main classes of photoreceptors, UVR8, cryptochromes/phototropins, and phytochromes (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phys</xref>), which enable detection of the near-UV, blue (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">B</xref>), and red (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref>)/far-red (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref>) light regions of the light spectrum, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Schafer and Nagy, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Rizzini et al., 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phys</xref> are a collection of dimeric biliproteins that can assume two photointerconvertible states, a R-absorbing Pr conformer that represents the ground state, and a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref>-absorbing Pfr conformer that represents the biologically active state and is generated only upon <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> excitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Quail, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Rockwell et al., 2006</xref>). Through their ability to phototransform repeatedly between Pr and Pfr, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phys</xref> uniquely act as long-lived photoswitches in various signaling cascades. As Pr, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phys</xref> are mostly localized to the cytoplasm, but after photoconversion to Pfr, they are rapidly imported into the nucleus, where they substantially alter much of the transcriptome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Quail, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bae and Choi, 2008</xref>). Ultimately, almost all aspects of a plant&#x2019;s life cycle are affected, including seed germination, seedling photomorphogenesis, leaf expansion, shade avoidance, entrainment of circadian rhythms, and floral induction. Whereas processes early in the transition from etiolated to green seedlings respond acutely to the amount of Pfr, processes in more mature green plants often respond to the relative ratio of Pr to Pfr, thus providing a simple form of color vision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Quail, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Rockwell et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p>Plants typically express a small family of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phys</xref> that have distinct and overlapping roles in R/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> perception. For example, Arabidopsis ecotype Columbia-0 (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col-0</xref>) assembles five isoforms, phyA to phyE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Quail, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Rockwell et al., 2006</xref>). phyA is the dominant member in etiolated seedlings early during photomorphogenesis and under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref>-rich environments, whereas phyB, and to a lesser extent its paralog phyD, are the dominant members in more mature plants in white light or R-rich environments.</p><p>Although the initial signaling event(s) after Pfr photoconversion have not been completely resolved, genetic studies have implicated members of the Phytochrome-Interacting Factor (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">PIF</xref>) family as key intermediates, which belong to the basic helix-loop-helix (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">bHLH</xref>) superfamily of transcriptional regulators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bae and Choi, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Leivar and Quail, 2011</xref>). For most <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">PIFs</xref> studied, degradation is greatly accelerated upon association with Pfr, suggesting that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phys</xref> act primarily to promote <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">PIF</xref> turnover, thus releasing their influence on photomorphogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Monte et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Al-Sady et al., 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">PIFs</xref> typically act as negative photomorphogenic regulators (e.g. PIF1, -3, -4, -5, and -7; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Huq and Quail, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Leivar et al., 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">2008b</xref>). However, an example where a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">PIF</xref>-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">bHLH</xref> acts in opposition to other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">PIFs</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Hornitschek et al., 2009</xref>) implies that the relationship between this <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">bHLH</xref> subfamily and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> signaling is complex.</p><p>In addition to the downstream activities that process <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> signals, the amount of each <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> isoform can influence proper photoperception (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Clough and Vierstra, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Quail, 2002</xref>). Whereas decreased <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> levels lead to R/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> hyposensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Parks and Quail, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Reed et al., 1993</xref>), even subtle increases in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> levels (e.g. 2-fold) often generate plants hypersensitive to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref>/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Boylan and Quail, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cherry et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Wester et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Leivar et al., 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">2008b</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> levels are delicately balanced by controls on the rates of <italic>PHY</italic> gene transcription and on the rates of photoreceptor degradation. For example, phyA levels drop dramatically in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> as a consequence of decreased transcription coupled with rapid breakdown of the Pfr conformer (half-life approximately 1&#x2013;2 h; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Somers and Quail, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Clough and Vierstra, 1997</xref>). Similar but less dramatic declines in phyB to phyE levels also occur following <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> irradiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Sharrock and Clack, 2002</xref>). The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">UPS</xref> has been implicated in phyA breakdown following photoconversion, but the exact mechanism remains unclear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Shanklin et al., 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Jabben et al., 1989</xref>). To date, the CONSTITUTIVE PHOTOMORPHOGENIC1 (COP1) accessory subunit of CUL4-based <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRL</xref> E3s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Seo et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Jang et al., 2010</xref>) and the CUL1 scaffold subunit in Skp1-CUL1-F-box protein (SCF)-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRLs</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Quint et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Gilkerson et al., 2009</xref>) have been implicated in Arabidopsis.</p><p>In this report, we add another set of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">UPS</xref> components to the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> regulatory system with the discovery of a pair of nucleus-localized LIGHT-RESPONSE <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> (LRB1 and -2) proteins in Arabidopsis that negatively influences <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> action. Whereas the single <italic>lrb1</italic> and <italic>lrb2</italic> null mutants respond normally to light, the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> double mutants have altered photomorphogenesis and are strongly hypersensitive to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> but not <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">B</xref> or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref>. Genetic analyses pinpoint their activity downstream of phyB/D, with biochemical studies implicating the resulting BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> E3 complexes in the control of phyB/D accumulation. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> hypersensitivity of the mutants further demonstrates the importance of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> levels to appropriate light responsiveness.</p><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>LRB1 and LRB2 Are Members of a Conserved Subfamily of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> Proteins in Plants</title><p>To investigate the range of functions controlled by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> E3s in plants, we undertook a reverse genetic analysis of representative loci from the 81-member Arabidopsis family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Dieterle et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Figueroa et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gingerich et al., 2005</xref>). Two genes of particular interest were At2g46260 and At3g61600 (now designated <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic>, respectively), based on their high amino acid sequence identity (88%) and the colinearity of their encoded proteins, both within the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domain and the surrounding regions, some of which we presume are involved in target recognition (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Figs. S1, S2, and S4</ext-link>). A third locus, At4g01160 (designated <italic>LRB3</italic>), was also identified that has the same domain organization and shares reasonable amino acid sequence similarity (55% identity). Alignments and homology searches discovered a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref>-and-C-terminal-Kelch (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">BACK</xref>) domain downstream of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domain and a putative nuclear localization sequence (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">NLS</xref>) near the N terminus of all three polypeptides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Description of the <italic>LRB</italic> gene family and associated T-DNA insertion mutants. A, Diagrams of the <italic>LRB1</italic>, <italic>LRB2</italic>, and <italic>LRB3</italic> genes in Arabidopsis. Boxes and lines denote exons and introns, respectively. Numbers to the right indicate amino acid (aa) length. The positions of the T-DNA insertions are indicated by triangles. The locations of the primers used for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR analysis in B are shown by the half arrows. Regions predicted to encode <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">NLS</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">BACK</xref> domains are highlighted by the shaded boxes. B, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR analysis of mRNA isolated from wild-type (WT) and homozygous <italic>lrb1-1</italic>, <italic>lrb2-1</italic>, <italic>lrb2-2</italic>, <italic>lrb2-3</italic>, and <italic>lrb3-1</italic> seedlings. The locations of the primers used are shown in A. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR analysis of <italic>PAE2</italic> is included as a control. C, Phylogenetic tree of LRB sequences from 11 plant species. The tree was generated by maximum likelihood (ML) analysis from a Gblocks-edited full-length sequence alignment (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). Asterisks at selected internal nodes indicate branches identified by maximum likelihood, maximum parsimony, and neighbor-joining analyses at 70% or greater bootstrap values. Species abbreviations are as follows: Arabidopsis (<italic>At</italic>), <italic>A. lyrata</italic> (<italic>Al</italic>), <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> (<italic>Vv</italic>), <italic>G. max</italic> (<italic>Gm</italic>), <italic>P. trichocarpa</italic> (<italic>Pt</italic>), rice (<italic>Os</italic>), <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> (<italic>Sb</italic>), <italic>Brachypodium distachyon</italic> (<italic>Bd</italic>), <italic>Zea mays</italic> (<italic>Zm</italic>), <italic>S. moellendorffii</italic> (<italic>Sm</italic>), <italic>and Physcomitrella patens</italic> (<italic>Pp</italic>). Gene locus names, corresponding accession numbers, and database identifiers are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Data Set S1</ext-link>. The scale bar reflects the number of substitutions per site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_199109_gs_f1"></graphic></fig><p>Analysis of the Genevestigator and Massively Parallel Signature Sequencing DNA expression databases revealed that <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic> are broadly transcribed in a wide variety of tissues and throughout all stages of Arabidopsis development and are not dramatically up- or down-regulated by a host of environmental conditions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genevestigator.ethz.ch">http://www.genevestigator.ethz.ch</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mpss.udel.edu">http://mpss.udel.edu</ext-link>). The only notable difference was a higher level of <italic>LRB1</italic> mRNA in pollen. Transcripts for <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic> were also evident in the EST database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org">www.arabidopsis.org</ext-link>), with values of 57 for <italic>LRB1</italic> and 64 for <italic>LRB2</italic>, implying a similar expression strength for the two loci. Comparable expression data were absent for <italic>LRB3</italic> (last checked on September 27, 2011), suggesting that this gene is silent. However, we could generate sequence-verified complementary DNAs (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def27">cDNAs</xref>) for <italic>LRB3</italic> by reverse transcription (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>)-PCR of Arabidopsis seedling mRNA, indicating that the locus is transcribed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>).</p><p>Confirmation that the LRB1 and LRB2 proteins assemble with CUL3 to generate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref>-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ub</xref> ligases was provided by yeast two-hybrid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">Y2H</xref>) and coimmunoprecipitation assays. Both <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> proteins interacted specifically with the CUL3a and CUL3b isoforms by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">Y2H</xref>, similar to another <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> family member from Arabidopsis (At4g08455), but not with CUL1, which scaffolds SCF-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRLs</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). CUL1 was shown to be active by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">Y2H</xref> interaction with its adaptor protein ASK1. Interestingly, LRB1 and LRB2 associated with self and each other but not with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> protein At4g08455 or the representative F-box proteins CORONATINE-INSENSITIVE1 (COI1) and UNUSUAL FLORAL ORGANS (UFO), which serve as target adaptors for SCF <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRLs</xref>, indicating that LRB1 and LRB2 may homodimerize and heterodimerize (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Such associations have been found with other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRL</xref>-based substrate adaptor proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bosu and Kipreos, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hua and Vierstra, 2011</xref>), suggesting that the assembled BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> complexes work as dimers.</p><p>Using transgenic seedlings expressing LRB1 and -2 fused to the C terminus of GFP (see below), we confirmed that LRB1/2 also interact with CUL3 in planta. Immunoprecipitation of GFP-LRB1/2 from the resulting crude extracts with anti-GFP antibodies enriched for CUL3 as compared with extracts from plants expressing GFP alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Notably, the amount of CUL3 detected with the anti-CUL3a antibodies (which should detect both the CUL3a and -b isoforms) was higher in seedlings irradiated with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> for 12 h as compared with dark-grown seedlings, suggesting that the interaction between LRB1/2 and CUL3a/b is strengthened by light.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>LRB1 and LRB2 interact with CUL3. A, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">Y2H</xref> interaction of LRB1 and LRB2 with CUL3a and CUL3b. Interactions of CUL3 with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> protein At4g08455, CUL1 with ASK1, and UFO with ASK1 were included as positive controls. The empty <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">Y2H</xref> vectors pGBKT7 and pGADT7 and p53 in pGBKT7 were used as negative controls. B, Coimmmunoprecipitation of CUL3 with GFP-LRB1/2. Extracts prepared from transgenic lines expressing GFP, GFP-LRB1, or GFP-LRB2 maintained in the dark (D) or irradiated for 12 h with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> (20 &#x03BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) were immunoprecipitated with anti-GFP antibodies, and the immunoprecipitates were subjected to SDS-PAGE and immunoblot analysis with anti-CUL3a antibodies (top panel). The middle and bottom panels show the input extracts probed with anti-GFP and anti-tubulin (TUB) antibodies (control). A shorter exposure was used to show the presence of GFP in the plants expressing free GFP alone. The asterisk identifies a species cross-reacting with the anti-GFP antibodies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_199109_gs_f2"></graphic></fig><p>To help appreciate the importance of the LRB subfamily, we queried a number of other sequenced plant genomes for relatives. Likely orthologs with identical <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">NLS</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">BACK</xref> organizations, similar <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domain sequences, and similar C-terminal regions were identified in representative seedless plants, monocots, and eudicots but not in any algae, fungi, or animals, implying that the LRB subfamily appeared early in plant evolution and thus likely influences a land plant-specific process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Figs. S1&#x2013;S5</ext-link>). Many species contain multiple members (four in <italic>Glycine max</italic> and <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> and gene pairs in many monocots and eudicots) that cluster phylogenetically with LRB1/2. In contrast, a close relative of LRB3 was found only in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> <italic>lyrata</italic>, suggesting that the <italic>LRB3</italic> locus appeared more recently during the emergence of the Arabidopsis lineage. <italic>LRB3</italic> sits within a segmental duplication block on chromosome 2 that is syntenic with a region on chromosome 4 that includes <italic>LRB1</italic>, implying that <italic>LRB1</italic> is its likely progenitor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Vision et al., 2000</xref>). Using the analysis of nonsynonymous (Ka) versus synonymous (Ks) substitution frequencies as an estimate of evolution rates, it appears that <italic>LRB3</italic> has experienced much less purifying selection as compared with <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic>. Whereas the Ka/Ks values for the <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic> orthologs from Arabidopsis and <italic>A. lyrata</italic> are 0.062 and 0.031, respectively, the Ka/Ks value for the <italic>LRB3</italic> counterparts is 0.29, thus representing a 5- to 10-fold increase in diversification rate. This higher diversification rate combined with poor evidence of expression and limited species distribution strongly imply that the <italic>LRB3</italic> locus is a recent addition to the <italic>LRB</italic> subfamily and is on the path to pseudogenization.</p></sec><sec><title>LRB1 and LRB2 Together Control R-Mediated Responses in Arabidopsis</title><p>Searches of the SIGNAL T-DNA insertion population generated with the Arabidopsis <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col-0</xref> ecotype identified single mutants in <italic>LRB1</italic> (<italic>lrb1-1</italic>) and <italic>LRB3</italic> (<italic>lrb3-1</italic>) and three mutants in <italic>LRB2</italic> (<italic>lrb2-1</italic>, <italic>lrb2-2</italic>, and <italic>lrb2-3</italic>) that might disrupt expression of the affected genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR analysis of homozygous lines indicated that all five mutations block synthesis of the full-length transcript but that often partial transcripts upstream but not downstream of the insertion site accumulate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Based on the fact that mRNAs generated from the <italic>lrb1-1</italic>, <italic>lrb2-1</italic>, and <italic>lrb3-1</italic> mutants would be missing the region encoding the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domain, we predict that these mutations represent protein-null alleles even if the truncated mRNAs are translated.</p><p>Initial observations of the <italic>lrb</italic> single mutant collection grown under standard growth chamber conditions (22&#x00B0;C under white light in long days [<xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">LDs</xref>; 16 h of light/8 h of dark] or short days [<xref ref-type="list" rid="def17">SDs</xref>; 8 h of light/16 h of dark]) did not reveal any striking phenotypic abnormalities, suggesting that the trio, or at least LRB1 and LRB2, work together in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). The only obvious effect was a slight compaction of rosette growth for <italic>lrb2</italic> plants in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def17">SDs</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>). Consequently, we generated double homozygous mutants combining <italic>lrb1-1</italic> with the <italic>lrb2-1</italic>, <italic>lrb2-2</italic>, or <italic>lrb2-3</italic> allele and found that they displayed dramatic photomorphogenic defects. All three <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> combinations (<italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic>, <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-2</italic>, and <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-3</italic>) grown under white light developed dwarfed rosettes with significantly shorter petioles in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">LDs</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def17">SDs</xref> and flowered later, as determined by the number of leaves generated before bolting in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">LDs</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). Whereas etiolated <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> seedlings were phenotypically normal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>), those exposed to light had substantially shorter hypocotyls and increased cotyledon size, consistent with the possibility that the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants are light hypersensitive.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Mature <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> plants have altered morphogenesis. A, Representative 18-d-old plants grown under white light in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">LDs</xref> (16 h of light/8 h of dark). B, Representative 8-week-old plants grown under white light in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def17">SDs</xref> (8 h of light/16 h of dark). C, Flowering time of plants grown under white light in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">LDs</xref>. Each bar represents the average number of leaves &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> generated before bolting of 18 or more plants. D, Petiole length from 23-d-old seedlings grown under white light. Each bar represents the average length &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of the two longest petioles measured from 18 or more plants. Asterisks in C and D represent significant differences from the wild type (WT; Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_199109_wc_f3"></graphic></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>LRB1 and LRB2 together regulate responses to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref>. A, Hypocotyl elongation of wild-type (WT) and homozygous single and double <italic>lrb</italic> mutant seedlings in darkness or in various fluence rates of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def19">FRc</xref>, or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def20">Bc</xref> for 4 d. Each point represents the average &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of 30 or more seedlings. The null <italic>phyA-211</italic> and <italic>phyB-9</italic> mutants are included as controls. B, Photographs of representative seedlings grown in darkness (top panel) or in 10 &#x03BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> (bottom panel) for 4 d. Two representatives are shown for each genotype. C, Expression of the <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>Flag-LRB1</italic> transgene in homozygous <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR was performed on total RNA isolated from the wild type and three independent <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>Flag-LRB1 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> lines (lines 5, 14, and 23) using <italic>Flag-</italic> and <italic>LRB1</italic>-specific primers. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR of <italic>UBC9</italic> was used as a control. D, Immunoblot detection of the Flag-LRB1 protein using an anti-Flag monoclonal antibody. Total protein was extracted from wild-type and <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>Flag-LRB1 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings after exposure to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d. The arrowhead locates the Flag-LRB1 protein, and the asterisk locates a nonspecific cross-reacting protein. Anti-PBA1 antibodies were used to confirm equal protein loading. E, Flag-LRB1 protein partially rescues the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> hypersensitivity of <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings. The photograph shows representative transgenic seedlings irradiated with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d. Two representatives are shown for each line. F, Hypocotyl lengths of seedlings irradiated with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d. Each bar represents the average &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of 30 or more seedlings.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_199109_wc_f4"></graphic></fig><p>To identify which of the photoreceptor systems might be affected, we exposed etiolated <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> seedlings to various fluence rates of continuous red light (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>), continuous far-red light (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def19">FRc</xref>), or continuous blue light (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def20">Bc</xref>) and measured their hypocotyl lengths after 4 d. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>, the three <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> combinations but not the single mutants displayed a striking hypersensitivity to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> only. Under all <xref ref-type="list" rid="def19">FRc</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def20">Bc</xref> fluences tested, the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants responded identically to the wild type, but under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>, the mutant hypocotyls were significantly shorter (e.g. 10.4 mm for the wild type versus 1.6 mm for <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> seedling exposed to 10 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>).</p><p>Whereas the <italic>lrb1-1</italic> single mutant had the same <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> sensitivity as the wild type with respect to hypocotyl elongation, we noticed that the <italic>lrb2-1</italic>, <italic>lrb2-2</italic>, and <italic>lrb2-3</italic> single mutants were slightly more sensitive to intermediate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> fluence rates (1&#x2013;10 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Thus, consistent with the morphology of more mature <italic>lrb2</italic> plants in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def17">SDs</xref>, LRB2 may have more impact on photomorphogenesis as compared with LRB1. Given that LRB1 and LRB2 likely work with CUL3a and CUL3b in BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> complexes, we also tested the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> response of the <italic>cul3a-1</italic> and <italic>cul3b-1</italic> null single mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gingerich et al., 2005</xref>). (The <italic>cul3a-1 cul3b-1</italic> double mutant is embryo lethal, thus precluding its analysis.) Like the <italic>lrb2-1</italic> line, hypocotyl elongation of these <italic>cul3</italic> mutant lines was also slightly more sensitive to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6A</ext-link>). It was reported previously that Suc availability modulates <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> perception in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Kozuka et al., 2005</xref>), suggesting that the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> hypersensitivity seen here could be driven by Suc hypersensitivity. Repeat analysis of seedlings grown on medium without Suc indicated that this scenario is not the case for the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants. Hypocotyl elongation of <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings remained <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> hypersensitive as compared with the wild type and the single <italic>lrb1-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1</italic> mutant seedlings (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6B</ext-link>).</p><p>Even though the accumulating genomic data implied that <italic>LRB3</italic> is nonfunctional, it remained possible that it plays a minor role as compared with <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic> or becomes important when its paralogs are absent. To test for these scenarios, we generated all homozygous mutant combinations of <italic>lrb3-1</italic> with <italic>lrb1-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1</italic>. The single <italic>lrb3-1</italic> mutant, the double <italic>lrb1-1 lrb3-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1 lrb3-1</italic> mutant combinations, and the triple <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1 lrb3-1</italic> mutant behaved similar to comparable lines wild type for <italic>LRB3</italic>, strongly suggesting that the LRB3 protein contributes little or nothing to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> perception, at least in young seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Inactivation of <italic>LRB3</italic> does not accentuate the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> hypersensitivity of <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings. Hypocotyl elongation was measured in wild-type (WT) and single, double, and triple <italic>lrb</italic> mutant seedlings kept in darkness or exposed to various fluence rates of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d. Each point represents the average &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of 35 or more seedlings. The <italic>phyB-9</italic> mutant is included as a control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_199109_wc_f5"></graphic></fig><p>To confirm that disruption of <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic> alone generated the photomorphogenic defects, we attempted to link the phenotypes to the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> genotype by cosegregation analysis and by complementation of the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> mutant with a <italic>LRB1</italic> transgene. In the former approach, individual seedlings from a segregating population obtained by self-crossing a heterozygous <italic>lrb1-1/&#x002B; lrb2-1/&#x002B;</italic> parent were tested for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> hypersensitivity and PCR genotyped for the wild-type and <italic>lrb1-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1</italic> alleles. As shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Figure S7</ext-link>, we observed a tight linkage between the short-hypocotyl phenotype in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> and homozygosity for both <italic>lrb1-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1</italic>. In the latter approach, we attempted to rescue the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>-hypersensitive phenotype of <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings with the full-length LRB1 protein bearing an N-terminal Flag epitope tag and expressed under the control of the cauliflower mosaic virus <italic>35S</italic> promoter. A number of independent transgenic lines were identified that expressed the <italic>Flag-LRB1</italic> mRNA and accumulated the Flag-LRB1 protein in the homozygous <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> background (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, C and D</xref>). These lines substantially rescued the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> hypersensitivity of hypocotyl elongation near to that of the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, E and F</xref>). Taken together, we conclude that LRB1 and LRB2 act redundantly in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> E3 complexes to negatively regulate photomorphogenesis in response to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>LRB1 and LRB2 Influence Light Responses Controlled by phyB and phyD</title><p>The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> hypersensitivity of <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> seedlings, the phenotype of white light-grown rosettes, and the late flowering of mature plants were all consistent with the encoded <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> proteins repressing pathway(s) initiated by phyB and possibly phyD. To further examine this possibility, we tested the reaction of <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> plants to a range of responses under phyB/D control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Schafer and Nagy, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bae and Choi, 2008</xref>). For example, phyB is the principal inducer of seed germination when seeds kept in the dark are irradiated with white light via a mechanism that can be reversed by a subsequent irradiation with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Shinomura et al., 1996</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref>, such white light irradiation can substantially improve the germination of wild-type seeds but not of seeds harboring the previously described <italic>PHYB</italic> null allele <italic>phyB-9</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Reed et al., 1993</xref>). Subsequent irradiation with a short pulse of 3 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> can block this promotion, indicating that the Pfr form of phyB is required. Whereas the <italic>lrb1-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1</italic> single mutant seeds responded like the wild type to the light stimulus, the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> double mutant seeds were relatively immune to subsequent <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> inhibition; even a high-fluence-rate pulse of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> (50 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) failed to inhibit the germination of most white light-irradiated <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> double mutants are altered in phyB/D-mediated light responses. The response of the <italic>phyB-9</italic> mutant is included as a control in A, B, and D. A, Percentage seed germination after exposure to a pulse of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref>. Seeds hydrated under white light for 2 h were either kept in darkness or irradiated with various fluences of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> for 5 min and then examined for germination after 4 d in darkness. Each bar represents the average &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of three separate experiments involving 60 or more seeds. B, Response to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def21">EOD</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref>. Seedlings were exposed for 4 d to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def17">SDs</xref> followed by a 10-min pulse of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> before darkness. Dark reflects a 10-min incubation in darkness instead of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> pulse. Each bar represents the average &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of 47 or more seedlings. Asterisks identify <xref ref-type="list" rid="def21">EOD</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> averages that are significantly different from the dark controls for each genotype (Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). C, Relative expression of the <italic>CAB2</italic> gene as determined by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def26">qRT</xref>-PCR of seedlings irradiated for various times with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref>. Each bar represents the average &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of three experiments using expression from the <italic>PP2A-2</italic> gene for normalization. Asterisks identify significant differences between <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> and wild-type (WT) seedlings (Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). D, Cotyledon opening in response to various fluences of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>. Each point represents the average angle &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> at the junction between the cotyledon and petiole for 40 or more cotyledons from 4-d-old seedlings. The diagrams on the right illustrate where on the seedling the cotyledon angles were measured.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_199109_gs_f6"></graphic></fig><p>phyB also plays a central role in the end-of-day (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def21">EOD</xref>) <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> response of young seedlings, in which a short pulse of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> before a prolonged dark period can partially overcome the R-induced inhibition of hypocotyl elongation by converting most phyB back to Pr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>). Consistent with previous studies on <italic>phy</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Devlin et al., 1998</xref>), we found that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def21">EOD</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> did not affect hypocotyl elongation of <italic>phyB-9</italic> seedlings. In contrast, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def21">EOD</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> strongly stimulated the elongation of <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> hypocotyls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>). phyB promotes the unfolding and expansion of young cotyledons in response to increasing <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> fluence rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Fankhauser and Casal, 2004</xref>). Whereas cotyledon opening and expansion were substantially blocked in <italic>phyB-9</italic> seedlings, these processes were more robust in <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings as compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6D</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S8A</ext-link>). At the molecular level, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> irradiation signaled through the Pfr form of phyB is known to stimulate the expression of various photosynthetic genes, including the nuclear locus encoding the CAB2 chlorophyll <italic>a</italic>/<italic>b</italic>-binding protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hamazato et al., 1997</xref>), and to enhance chlorophyll accumulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Huq et al., 2004</xref>). Accordingly, we readily detected by real-time quantitative (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def22">q</xref>)PCR an increased amount of <italic>CAB2</italic> transcript in wild-type seedlings within 4 h after <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> irradiation, which increased faster and more strongly in <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6C</xref>). Likewise, chlorophyll levels in seedlings exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d were lower than normal in the <italic>phyB-9</italic> mutant, unaltered in the <italic>lrb1-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1</italic> single mutants, and higher than normal in the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> double mutant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S8B</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title><italic>PHYB</italic> and <italic>PHYD</italic> Are Epistatic to <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic></title><p>All the phenotypic defects observed here for <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> plants were consistent with the BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> complexes negatively regulating signaling downstream of phyB and possibly phyD. To test for this epistasis directly, we introgressed the <italic>lrb1-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1</italic> mutations into the <italic>phyB-9</italic> and <italic>phyD-2</italic> null mutant backgrounds and examined how the mutant combinations responded to various light regimes detected by phyB/D (see above). The <italic>phyB-9</italic> allele in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col-0</xref> background (formally called <italic>hy3</italic>-EMS142 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Reed et al., 1993</xref>]) contains a premature stop codon that was introduced by ethyl methanesulfonate mutagenesis; it is a null protein but still expresses low levels of the <italic>PHYB</italic> transcript (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Figs. S9D and S11, A and B</ext-link>). The <italic>phyD-2</italic> mutant used here was obtained from the SIGNAL mutant collection generated with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col-0</xref> background. It contains a T-DNA insertion within the first exon and was found by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR and by immunoblot analysis to block accumulation of the full-length <italic>PHYD</italic> transcript and the phyD polypeptide, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Figs. S9, A and B, and S11A</ext-link>). Homozygous plants harboring various combinations of the <italic>lrb1-1</italic>, <italic>lrb2-1</italic>, <italic>phyB-9</italic>, and <italic>phyD-2</italic> mutations were located by genomic PCR and, for the <italic>phyB-9</italic> mutation specifically, by the absence of the phyB protein as determined by immunoblot analysis of seedling extracts (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S9, C and D</ext-link>).</p><p>The sum of the epistasis analyses confirmed that LRB1 and LRB2 work downstream of phyB and phyD. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7, A and B</xref>, the effects of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> (10 and 125 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def21">EOD</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> on etiolated hypocotyl elongation, which were absent or weakened in homozygous <italic>phyB-9</italic>, <italic>phyD-2</italic>, and <italic>phyB-9 phyD-2</italic> plants and accentuated in <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> plants, were absent in the <italic>phyB-9 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> triple mutant and the <italic>phyB-9 phyD-2 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> quadruple mutant. In fact, the quadruple mutant was insensitive to even high fluence rates of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>, similar to the <italic>phyB-9 phyD-2</italic> double mutant. Flowering time in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">LDs</xref> was earlier in <italic>phyB-9</italic> and <italic>phyB-9 phyD-2</italic> plants but later in <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7C</xref>). The flowering delay for <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> plants was partially reversed by introgressing the <italic>phyB-9</italic> allele and more fully reversed in the quadruple mutant. Likewise, cotyledon expansion for triple and quadruple mutant seedlings when exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> resembled <italic>phyB-9</italic> seedlings but not <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7D</xref>). For both hypocotyl elongation and chlorophyll accumulation in response to white light, introgressing both the <italic>phyB-9</italic> and <italic>phyD-2</italic> alleles similarly reversed the phenotype of the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> mutant so that they now mirrored <italic>phyB-9 phyD-2</italic> plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S10, A and B</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p><italic>PHYB</italic> and <italic>PHYD</italic> are epistatic to <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic>. The bars in each panel represent averages &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of 30 or more seedlings. Quad refers to the homozygous <italic>phyB-9 phyD-2 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> genotype. A, Hypocotyl elongation of seedlings exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d. Hypocotyl lengths (in mm &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc>) for the set of genotypes were indistinguishable when the seedlings were grown in the dark (wild type [WT], 11.1 &#x00B1; 2.4; <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic>, 10.3 &#x00B1; 0.9; <italic>phyB-9</italic>, 11.8 &#x00B1; 2.1; <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1 phyB-9</italic>, 10.2 &#x00B1; 1.5; <italic>phyD-2</italic>, 9.8 &#x00B1; 1.1; <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1 phyD-2</italic>, 9.5 &#x00B1; 1.0; <italic>phyB-9 phyD-2</italic>, 10.2 &#x00B1; 0.8; Quad, 9.8 &#x00B1; 1.2). B, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def21">EOD</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> response. Dark represents a 10-min incubation in darkness instead of a 10-min <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> light pulse. C, Flowering time for plants grown under white light in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">LDs</xref>. Each bar reflects the average number of leaves generated before bolting. D, Cotyledon expansion of seedlings grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_199109_gs_f7"></graphic></fig><p>For all the responses, inactivation of <italic>PHYB</italic> in the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> background had the greatest impact in reversing the phenotype of <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> plants, indicating that the BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> complexes work primarily through phyB. However, for some of the phenotypes, we either observed subtle suppression of the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> phenotype when <italic>PHYD</italic> was inactivated alone or accentuated suppression when the <italic>phyB-9</italic> and <italic>phyD-2</italic> mutants were combined in the quadruple mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figs. 7D</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S10, B and C</ext-link>), suggesting that these E3s also impact phyD signaling. The nearly complete suppression of the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> phenotypes in the quadruple mutant further implied that the BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> complexes do not also act through the remaining phyA, phyC, and phyE isoforms.</p></sec><sec><title>phyB and phyD Protein Stability Is Controlled by LRB1 and LRB2</title><p>Given that even small increases in phyB (and possibly phyD) levels can profoundly alter Arabidopsis photomorphogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Boylan and Quail, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Wester et al., 1994</xref>; Leivar et al., 2008a) and the likely role of BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> in protein ubiquitylation and turnover, we tested whether the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> phenotypes are generated by increased phyB/D accumulation as a consequence of dampened <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">UPS</xref>-mediated breakdown. Whereas phyB and phyD levels in the <italic>lrb1-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1</italic> single mutants as well as all three combinations of <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> double mutants were unaltered in dark-grown seedlings as compared with the wild type (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S11A</ext-link>), increased relative amounts of the two photoreceptors were obvious when the double mutants were exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d (2- to 4-fold and 5- to 8-fold, respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>), indicating that LRB1 and LRB2 together suppress phyB/D accumulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig8" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>LRB1 and LRB2 regulate phyB and phyD protein levels. phyB and phyD protein levels in crude extracts from the wild type (WT) and the indicated mutant backgrounds were assayed by immunoblot analysis with anti-phyB and anti-phyD monoclonal antibodies. Anti-PBA1, anti-RPN1a, and anti-histone H3 antibodies were used to confirm equal protein loading. A, phyB and phyD levels are increased in <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> seedlings grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d. The numbers indicate the relative abundance (%) of each <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> polypeptide as compared with the wild type, using the signal from PBA1 to normalize the phy signals. B, Loss of phyB and phyD proteins during <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> is slowed in the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> (<italic>lrb</italic>) mutants as compared with the wild type. C, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>-induced loss of phyB in the wild type is inhibited by 100 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> MG132.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_199109_gs_f8"></graphic></fig><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def26">qRT</xref>-PCR analyses showed that the steady-state levels of the <italic>PHYB</italic> and <italic>PHYD</italic> mRNAs were not significantly affected by the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> combination in the dark or under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>, implying that these increases were not driven by up-regulated transcription in the absence of LRB1/2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S11B</ext-link>). Conversely, we found that LRB1 and LRB2 together likely promote light-induced turnover of the phyB/D proteins. Upon <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> irradiation of etiolated seedlings, phyB and phyD levels steadily declined in the wild type such that after 48 h most of the photoreceptors disappeared (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>). These rates of loss were markedly slower in the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> background. Importantly, phyB breakdown was also substantially attenuated upon exposing wild-type seedlings to the proteasome inhibitor MG132, thus implicating the 26S proteasome in particular (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8C</xref>). MG132 treatment also slightly stabilized phyB levels in <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8C</xref>), implying that other factors besides LRB1 and LRB2 might also direct phyB/D breakdown. It should be noted that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> appeared to have little or no impact on <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic> transcript levels, indicating that the light-induced loss of phyB/D is not driven by increased expression of <italic>LRB1/2</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S12C</ext-link>).</p><p>In addition to phyB/D, we discovered that LRB1/2 is turned over in Arabidopsis seedlings via a process that appears to be light independent (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S12, A and B</ext-link>). Treatment of etiolated seedlings with the translation inhibitor cycloheximide accelerated the loss of Flag-LRB1 both in darkness and during <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> irradiation. This loss could be slowed by MG132, suggesting that these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> proteins may be targets of autoubiquitylation and subsequent breakdown.</p></sec><sec><title>LRB1 and LRB2 Are Nucleus Localized</title><p>Given that phyB degradation is proposed to occur in the nucleus following import as Pfr and subsequent association with punctate nuclear bodies also called speckles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Jang et al., 2010</xref>), it was possible that LRB1/2 colocalize with phyB/D and/or affect their relocalization. Using a previously developed phyB C-terminal-GFP reporter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Boccalandro et al., 2009</xref>) combined with fluorescence confocal microscopy, we confirmed the nuclear sequestering and aggregation of phyB under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>. As observed previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Yamaguchi et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Kircher et al., 2002</xref>), we found phyB-GFP diffusively distributed throughout the cytoplasm and nucleus in etiolated hypocotyls and then more enriched in the nucleus under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> concomitant with its concentration in nuclear speckles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9A</xref>). The R-induced redistribution of phyB-GFP into speckles was indistinguishable in the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> background, indicating that LRB1/2 does not influence this nuclear aggregation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig9" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Cellular localization of LRB2 and the effect of <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants on phyB localization. A, Fluorescence confocal microscopic images of hypocotyl cells expressing <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>PHYB-GFP</italic> in the wild-type (WT) or <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> background. Four-day-old dark-grown plants were either kept in darkness (D) or irradiated with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 24 h prior to imaging. Bars &#x003D; 10 &#x03BC;m. B, Fluorescence confocal microscopic images of root tip cells expressing <italic>UBQ10</italic>:<italic>GFP-LRB2</italic> in the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> mutant background. Four-day-old plants were either kept in darkness or irradiated with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 24 h prior to imaging. Images of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> seedlings are shown as a control. BF, Bright-field images; Merge, superimposition of fluorescence and bright-field images. Bars &#x003D; 20 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_199109_wc_f9"></graphic></fig><p>To determine if LRB1 and LRB2 also localize to the nucleus, possibly via their predicted <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">NLS</xref> motifs, and similarly coalesce in nuclear speckles, we examined their intracellular distribution in root tips using full-length, N-terminal GFP fusions expressed under the control of the <italic>UBQ10</italic> promoter. Following introduction of the <italic>UBQ10</italic>:<italic>GFP-LRB1</italic> and <italic>UBQ10</italic>:<italic>GFP-LRB2</italic> transgenes into homozygous <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> plants, GFP fusion proteins of the expected mass (approximately 95 kD) were detected immunologically with anti-GFP antibodies and in association with CUL3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>), demonstrating that intact and functional fusions accumulated (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S13A</ext-link>). Segregation analysis of selfed T1 progeny from lines hemizygous for the <italic>GFP-LRB1/2</italic> transgenes and homozygous for the <italic>lrb1-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1</italic> mutations demonstrated that the fusion proteins also retained phenotypic functionality based on their ability to reverse the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> suppression of hypocotyl elongation in <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S13B</ext-link>). When the rescued lines were examined by fluorescence confocal microscopy, we detected nuclear enrichment of both GFP-LRB1 and GFP-LRB2 in dark-grown roots as compared with those expressing free GFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9B</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S13C</ext-link>). Long-term <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> irradiation had no detectable effect on this nuclear distribution, nor did the GFP-LRB1/2 reporters coalesce in nuclear speckles, indicating that the nuclear/cytoplasmic partitioning of LRB1/2 is not under light control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9B</xref>). Thus, while LRB1/2 and phyB/D are together in the nucleus upon <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> irradiation of seedlings, LRB1/2 do not appear to follow phyB/D into punctate nuclear bodies.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>PHYA</italic> Expression Is Up-Regulated by LRB1/2</title><p>Based on the synergism between phyB and phyA in regulating low-fluence <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> responses of etiolated seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Franklin and Quail, 2010</xref>) and the known ability of phyB to attenuate <italic>PHYA</italic> expression in light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Cant&#x00F3;n and Quail, 1999</xref>), we tested whether LRB1/2 might also affect phyA accumulation even though <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings are not detectably altered in phyA-mediated responses (e.g. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> inhibition of hypocotyl elongation; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). For dark-grown seedlings, phyA protein levels were indistinguishable in the <italic>lrb1-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1</italic> single mutants and the three combinations of <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> double mutant as compared with those in the wild type and <italic>phyB-9</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10A</xref>). However, the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> seedlings had dramatically less phyA upon exposure to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>, whereas <italic>phyB-9</italic> seedlings accumulated substantially more. The response of the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> seedlings indicated that the resulting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> E3s somehow enhance phyA accumulation in addition to its ability to dampen phyB/D levels. This drop in phyA was at least partially suppressed in <italic>phyB-9 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings, implying that LRB1/2 works through phyB to control phyA abundance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig10" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>The levels of phyA protein and <italic>PHYA</italic> mRNA are reduced in the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants. phyA protein was detected by immunoblot analysis with an anti-phyA monoclonal antibody in crude extracts from seedlings of the indicated genotypes either kept in darkness or exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d. Anti-PBA1 antibodies were used to confirm nearly equal protein loading. Analysis of the <italic>phyA-211</italic> null mutant was used to help identify the phyA protein. A, <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants accumulate less phyA in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>. B, The drop in phyA protein levels in <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> mutants exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> can be overcome by inactivation of <italic>PHYB</italic>. C, <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> mutants affect phyA protein level differently compared with <italic>cop1-6</italic> and <italic>pif3-3 pif4-2</italic> mutants. D, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def26">qRT</xref>-PCR analysis of <italic>PHYA</italic> mRNA extracted from seedlings either kept in darkness or exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d. Bars represent averages &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of three experiments. Asterisks indicate values for the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> mutant that are significantly different from the wild-type (WT) values (Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). E, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def26">qRT</xref>-PCR analysis of <italic>PHYA</italic> mRNA extracted from <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic>, <italic>cop1-6</italic>, and <italic>pif3-3 pif4-2</italic> seedlings either kept in darkness or exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for 4 d. <italic>PHYA</italic> transcript levels were normalized to that of the <italic>PP2A-2</italic> transcript in D and E.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_199109_gs_f10"></graphic></fig><p>Given the negative control of phyB as Pfr on <italic>PHYA</italic> transcription, one likely possibility was that the increased level of phyB in the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> background subsequently attenuated <italic>PHYA</italic> gene expression. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def26">qRT</xref>-PCR measurement of <italic>PHYA</italic> transcripts confirmed this scenario (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10C</xref>). Dark-grown <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic>, <italic>phyB-9</italic>, and <italic>phyB-9 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings had <italic>PHYA</italic> transcript levels comparable to that in the wild type. However, when the seedlings were exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>, <italic>PHYA</italic> transcript abundance was significantly lower in <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings but significantly higher in <italic>phyB-9</italic> and <italic>phyB-9 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings. Collectively, it seems that LRB1 and LRB2 do not directly promote phyA protein accumulation but enhance it indirectly by inhibiting the phyB-dependent process that suppresses <italic>PHYA</italic> transcription.</p><p>Other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>-hypersensitive mutants, including those affecting members of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">PIF</xref> family and COP1, contrast the effects of <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants on phyA protein levels. In as much as they increase phyB levels, they either do not alter phyA levels (e.g. <italic>pif3 pif4</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Khanna et al., 2004</xref>; Leivar et al., 2008]) or increase them (e.g. <italic>cop1</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Seo et al., 2004</xref>]). Direct comparison of homozygous <italic>cop1-6</italic>, <italic>pif3-1 pif4-1</italic>, and <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> plants confirmed this result and showed that LRB1/2 work differently from these other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> regulators in the control of phyA levels, even though all three mutants dampen the accumulation of the <italic>PHYA</italic> mRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10, D and E</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>LRB1 and LRB2 Are Involved in Many Developmental Processes Mediated by phyB/D</title><p>Recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Qu et al. (2010)</xref> reported that the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-2</italic> double mutant (proteins generically named POZ/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref>-Containing Protein2 and -1, respectively) is mildly hypersensitive to jasmonic acid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref>), up-regulates more robustly the signature defense gene <italic>PDF1.2</italic>, and is more resistant to fungal pathogens, thus directing the authors to conclude that the corresponding BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> E3s regulate biotic defense in Arabidopsis. However, under our growth conditions, we either failed to recapitulate the responses or found that these responses were much more subtle than those regulated by light. For example, in either dark or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref>, root elongation in the presence of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> or methyl-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> for the homozygous <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic>, <italic>phyB-9</italic>, <italic>phyB-9 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic>, and the quadruple mutant was indistinguishable statistically from that of the wild type (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S14, A and B</ext-link>). Like wild-type seedlings, <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> seedlings increased the abundance of the <italic>PDF1.2</italic> transcript in response to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> but to a level only slightly greater than the wild type. This up-regulation of <italic>PDF1.2</italic> mRNA by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> was attenuated when the <italic>phyB-9</italic> mutation was combined with <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> and absent in <italic>phyB-9</italic> seedlings (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S14C</ext-link>), in agreement with previous studies on the control of <italic>PDF1.2</italic> transcript abundance by phyB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Moreno et al., 2009</xref>). Given that light is known to profoundly influence plant defense responses through the circadian clock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Wang et al., 2011</xref>), we consider it likely that the responses seen previously for the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> double mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Qu et al., 2010</xref>) actually reflect an indirect role of LRB1/2 on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> perception and biotic defense mediated by a more direct role of LRB1/2 on phyB/D accumulation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Extensive genetic and transcriptomic analyses of light perception in Arabidopsis have revealed an interconnected web of signaling components that regulate and respond to the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> family of R/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref>-absorbing photoreceptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Quail, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bae and Choi, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Leivar and Quail, 2011</xref>). Here, we add another level of regulation to this web with the discovery of two <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref>-type E3s assembled with the LRB1 and LBR2 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> proteins that together negatively regulate many aspects of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> signaling. Whereas the single homozygous mutants are relatively normal phenotypically, the double mutants are strongly hypersensitive to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref>, but not <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> or B, with respect to hypocotyl elongation, and they are compromised for numerous white light or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> responses at various stages of the Arabidopsis life cycle, including seed germination, cotyledon opening and expansion, chlorophyll accumulation, expression of the R-regulated <italic>CAB2</italic> gene, the effect of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def21">EOD</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> on hypocotyl growth, petiole elongation, rosette shape, and flowering time. This phenotypic connection is firmly supported genetically by the assay of multiple alleles affecting LRB2, cosegregation analysis, and complementation with Flag- and GFP-tagged transgenes.</p><p>Most, if not all, of the phenotypic defects associated with the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> double mutants are primarily mediated through phyB (with assistance from phyD). Accordingly, we found that all the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> phenotypes could be largely abrogated by further removal of phyB and phyD, indicating that LRB1 and LRB2 together affect signaling by these two <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> isoforms specifically. While the normal sensitivity of <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> plants to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> rules out a role for these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> E3s in phyA signaling, it remains possible that they affect signaling by phyC and phyE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Devlin et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Franklin et al., 2003a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">2003b</xref>). However, the nearly complete phenotypic congruence of <italic>phyB-9 phyD-2 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> plants with <italic>phyB-9 phyD-2</italic> plants argues that phyC and phyE signaling is not compromised or, at a minimum, is altered below the sensitivity of our phenotypic assays. Whereas a recent preliminary study attempted to link LRB1/2 to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> signaling and pathogen defense, our data instead more strongly connect this <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> protein pair to light signaling. Given the negative effect of light on pathogen invasion through its control of circadian rhythms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Wang et al., 2011</xref>), we consider it likely that LRB1/2 affect plant defense indirectly, working through a more direct control on phyB/D levels and/or action.</p><p>In addition to LRB1 and LRB2, Arabidopsis encodes a third related <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> protein (LRB3) with an identical <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">NLS</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">BACK</xref> domain organization. An obvious LRB3 ortholog could only be found in <italic>A. lyrata</italic>, indicating that this relative is a more recent addition to the plant <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> superfamily, possibly appearing after emergence of the Arabidopsis lineage. The low expression of <italic>LRB3</italic>, its relatively high diversification rate, and the inability of the <italic>lrb3-1</italic> mutant to alter phyB/D signaling phenotypically, either by itself or in combination with <italic>lrb1</italic> and <italic>lrb2</italic> mutants, strongly suggest that this locus is inactive despite an intact coding region and is possibly on the way to pseudogenization.</p><p>Both LRB1 and LRB2 likely function as parts of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRL</xref> complexes based on their specific interaction with both isoforms of CUL3 both in yeast and in planta and our observations here that mutants partially compromising CUL3 levels (<italic>cul3a-1</italic> and <italic>cul3b-1</italic> single mutants; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gingerich et al., 2005</xref>) also generate a R-hypersensitive phenotype. A connection between the LRB1/2-CUL3 complexes and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> signaling is also supported by our observations that GFP-LRB1/2 binding to CUL3 is enhanced by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> irradiating the seedlings. Interestingly, we and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Qu et al. (2010)</xref> found by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">Y2H</xref> that LRB1 and LRB2 can homodimerize and heterodimerize, suggesting that the BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> E3s assembled with these substrate adaptors act as dimers in vivo. Such dimerization has been demonstrated for several other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRL</xref>-type E3s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bosu and Kipreos, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Hua and Vierstra, 2011</xref>). This association could theoretically increase the target range of individual <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> complexes combinatorially via the assembly of heterodimers or provide a mechanism to assemble poly-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ub</xref> chains on a target protein via ubiquitylation in trans across the dimer. That the R-hypersensitive phenotypes can only be seen well in the double <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutant background is inconsistent with them acting in obligate heterodimeric BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> complexes, but biochemical characterizations of these complexes are clearly needed to support such speculation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Qu et al. (2010)</xref> proposed that LRB1 and LRB2 dimerize through their <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domains, suggesting that such self-association might block the assembly of LRB1/2 with CUL3 and thus negate LRB1/2 action. However, as dimerization of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRL</xref> complexes and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref>-CUL3 interactions are proposed to occur via different interfaces in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Stogios et al., 2005</xref>), such dimerization and docking might be concurrent.</p><p>At present, the target(s) of the BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> E3s remain to be identified, but the nuclear localization of both LRB1 and LRB2 implies that they are involved in nuclear aspects of phyB/D signaling. Clearly, possible targets are phyB and phyD themselves upon photoconversion to Pfr and subsequent import into the nucleus. This proposal is supported by our observations that (1) the R-hypersensitive <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> phenotypes are consistent with the mutant plants accumulating more of these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> isoforms, (2) the hypersensitive phenotypes can be negated by removing phyB and phyD, (3) etiolated <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> plants have normal levels of phyB and phyD proteins but retain higher levels of both upon prolonged exposure to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> without effects on the corresponding mRNA levels, and (4) the turnover of at least phyB is dampened by the proteasome inhibitor MG132, thus implicating the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">UPS</xref> more generally. That LRB1 and LRB2 do not follow phyB into nuclear speckles upon <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> irradiation might indicate that these speckles are not the sites of phyB/D turnover or might simply reflect the possibility that LRB1/2 overexpression driven by the <italic>UBQ10</italic> promoter overwhelms their normal distribution within the nuclear compartment.</p><p>Unfortunately, numerous attempts to prove that LRB1/2 directly interact with phyB/D have been unsuccessful. These approaches include coimmunoprecipitation of phyB with Flag-LRB1 or GFP-LRB1/2 expressed in Arabidopsis, in vitro interaction assays using recombinant phyB and glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase-LRB1 or glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase-LRB2, nondirected <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">Y2H</xref> assays, and directed <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">Y2H</xref> assays with phyB. Challenges have included difficulties in assembling photoactive full-length phyB chromoproteins in heterologous systems and the insolubility of recombinant LRB1/2 proteins and their poor expression in planta. A further impediment might be that phyB/D turnover requires a heretofore unknown modification of the chromoproteins (e.g. phosphorylation) after photoconversion to Pfr before they can be recognized by BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup>. It is also possible that phyB/D are not the direct targets of BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup>. However, they must be close to phyB/D signaling and turnover in the nucleus after photoconversion to Pfr, given the nuclear localization of LRB1/2 and the strong effects of <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants on phyB/D signaling and abundance in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref>.</p><p>In addition to their negative control on phyB/D levels, LRB1/2 have a strong positive effect on phyA levels, with light-exposed <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> double mutants accumulating substantially less phyA protein. Our observations that <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> plants accumulate significantly less <italic>PHYA</italic> mRNA implies that this effect is an indirect consequence of increased phyB levels repressing <italic>PHYA</italic> transcription. It was also possible that LRB1/2 indirectly control phyB and phyD levels by regulating the action of COP1 and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">PIFs</xref>. However, the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants clearly act in a different manner than <italic>cop1</italic> or the <italic>pif</italic> mutants. First, <italic>cop1</italic> and higher order <italic>pif</italic> mutants display a constitutive photomorphogenic phenotype in the dark (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Ang et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Leivar et al., 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">2008b</xref>), whereas the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants do not. This suggests that LRB1/2 action depends on light, whereas COP1 and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">PIFs</xref> act constitutively even in the dark. Second, we showed that the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants and the <italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>pif</italic> mutants differ in the R-dependent inhibition of phyA accumulation. Although all three mutants (<italic>cop1</italic>, <italic>pif3 pif4</italic>, <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic>) have similarly decreased levels of <italic>PHYA</italic> mRNA (most likely caused by hyperactivation of phyB signaling), only the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants have reduced levels of phyA protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10</xref>).</p><p>Regardless of the targets, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> E3s assembled with LRB1 and LRB2 likely represent a key conserved step in phyB/D signaling. Obvious orthologs based on sequence homology can be found in all land plants but not in algae, implying that their roles in light signaling appeared early in land plant evolution. With the exception of the lycophyte <italic>Selaginella moellendorffii</italic>, all land plant genomes analyzed appear to encode at least two functional <italic>LRB</italic> genes, suggesting that genetic redundancy may help underpin their functions. However, at this point, we see no functional or expression differences between Arabidopsis <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic> to imply subfunctionalization.</p><p>The fact that the strong light-hypersensitive phenotype of <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> plants is presumably elicited by only 2- to 4-fold more phyB (and 3- to 8-fold more of its minor partner phyD) further illustrates the importance of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> levels on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> signaling. This accumulation is regulated at multiple levels, including controls on transcription and light-dependent degradation. Whereas phyA turnover by the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">UPS</xref> has been well established (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Shanklin et al., 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Jabben et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Seo et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Quint et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Gilkerson et al., 2009</xref>), our studies with the BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> E3s strongly support the involvement of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">UPS</xref> in phyB/D turnover and its subsequent influence on plant photomorphogenesis. It should be emphasized that phyB/D levels drop much more slowly in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> (half-life approximately 12&#x2013;24 h) as compared with phyA (half-life approximately 1&#x2013;2 h; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Sharrock and Clack, 2002</xref>; this report). Much of this distinction likely reflects the stronger negative feedback control of Pfr on phyA synthesis relative to phyB due to the strong repression of <italic>PHYA</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Somers and Quail, 1995</xref>). It remains possible that the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRLs</xref> assembled with LRB1/2 are not completely responsible for phyB/D turnover and that other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">UPS</xref> E3s are also involved. This notion is supported by the fact that <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants do not completely stabilize phyB/D levels and prior studies implicating the COP1 subunit of DWD <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">CRLs</xref> in phyB turnover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Jang et al., 2010</xref>). Whereas increasing <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phy</xref> levels through transgenic expression has been offered as a mechanism to manipulate agronomically important processes controlled by these photoreceptors (e.g. seed germination and yield, shade avoidance, and flowering time; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Garg et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Boccalandro et al., 2009</xref>), we propose that manipulating the action of BTB<sup>LRB1/2</sup> might offer an alternative route, at least for phyB/D-mediated photoresponses.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Sequence Alignment, Domain Predictions, and Phylogenetic Analyses</title><p>The predicted full-length <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic> nucleotide and protein sequences from the Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col-0</xref> ecotype were used as queries in BLAST searches for related loci in other plant genomes available at the Phytozome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.phytozome.net/">http://www.phytozome.net/</ext-link>), National Center for Biotechnology Information (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>), Rice Genome Annotation Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu">http://rice.plantbiology.msu.edu</ext-link>), The Arabidopsis Information Resource (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arabidopsis.org/">http://arabidopsis.org/</ext-link>), Genoscope (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genoscope.cns.fr/externe/English/corps_anglais.html">http://www.genoscope.cns.fr/externe/English/corps_anglais.html</ext-link>), and Department of Energy Joint Genome Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jgi.doe.gov/">http://www.jgi.doe.gov/</ext-link>) Web sites (for the complete list, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). Methods for reannotating the <italic>LRB</italic> gene and pseudogene models when necessary are described in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Materials and Methods S1 in the Supplemental Data</ext-link>. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">BACK</xref> domains and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def13">NLS</xref> motifs were predicted by SMART (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de">http://smart.embl-heidelberg.de</ext-link>), Pfam (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pfam.sanger.ac.uk/">http://pfam.sanger.ac.uk/</ext-link>), and sequence alignments. Multiple sequence alignments of the predicted full-length amino acid sequences and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domains alone were generated independently by progressive, iterative, and consistency-based approaches. Progressive alignments were obtained with ClustalW2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/clustalw2/index.html">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/clustalw2/index.html</ext-link>) using the default settings, iterative alignments were obtained in Multiple Alignment with Fast Fourier Transform (MAFFT; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mafft.cbrc.jp/alignment/software/index.html">http://mafft.cbrc.jp/alignment/software/index.html</ext-link>) using the Fast Fourier Transform with a Normalized Similarity matrix (FFT-NS-i) iterative strategy and the default settings, and consistency-based alignments were obtained using T-Coffee (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tcoffee.org/">http://www.tcoffee.org/</ext-link>) using the default settings. A consensus alignment was generated for the full-length LRB proteins using the Combine function in T-coffee, which then underwent minor hand editing in Jalview (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jalview.org/">http://www.jalview.org/</ext-link>) to produce the final alignment (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). Prior to phylogenetic analysis, poorly aligned and divergent positions were removed with Gblocks (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://molevol.cmima.csic.es/castresana/Gblocks.html">http://molevol.cmima.csic.es/castresana/Gblocks.html</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). Evolutionary models were selected by ProtTest 2.4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abascal et al., 2005</xref>) using the fast strategy (model parameters and branch lengths, but not tree topology, were optimized), and a Biology Neighbor-Joining (BIONJ) tree was calculated by the program. For both the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domain and Gblocks-edited full-length LRB alignments, the most probable model according to the Akaike Information Criterion score was Jones-Taylor-Thornton (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def24">JTT</xref>) with &#x03B3;-correction (Akaike weight [probability] in both cases &#x003D; 0.73). ProtTest estimated the &#x03B3;-parameter at 0.83 for the Gblocks-edited full-length sequence alignment and 0.91 for the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domain alignment (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>).</p><p>Distance-based neighbor-joining trees were generated with MEGA4 using the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def24">JTT</xref> substitution matrix, a fixed &#x03B3;-shape parameter of 0.83 (tree generated from the Gblocks-edited full-length LRB protein alignment) or 0.91 (tree generated from the predicted LRB <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domain alignment), pairwise deletion, and 1,000 bootstrap trials. Maximum parsimony trees from 1,000 bootstrap trials were generated with MEGA4 using the Close-Neighbor-Interchange algorithm at search level 3, in which the initial trees were obtained with the random addition of sequences (10 replicates). All alignment gaps were treated as missing data. Maximum likelihood trees were generated with PhyML (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.atgc-montpellier.fr/phyml/">http://www.atgc-montpellier.fr/phyml/</ext-link>) with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def24">JTT</xref> substitution matrix, zero invariable sites (as estimated from the data sets), four substitution rate categories, a fixed &#x03B3;-shape parameter of 0.83 (tree generated from the Gblocks-edited full-length LRB protein alignment) or 0.91 (tree generated from the predicted LRB <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domain alignment), and the initial tree generated by BIONJ. In each case, 500 bootstrap trials were performed. The three phylogenetic trees generated from the Gblocks-edited full-length sequence alignment or just the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domains can be found in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Figures S3 and S5</ext-link>. The method for calculating Ka/Ks estimations of evolution rates was determined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Nei and Gojobori (1986</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of Mutant Alleles</title><p>The <italic>lrb1-1</italic> (Salk_145146), <italic>lrb2-1</italic> (Salk_001013), <italic>lrb2-2</italic> (Salk_044446), <italic>lrb2-3</italic> (Salk_100118), <italic>lrb3-1</italic> (Salk_082868), and <italic>phyD-2</italic> (Salk_027956) T-DNA insertion lines in the Arabidopsis <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col-0</xref> background were obtained from the SIGNAL T-DNA insertion collection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Alonso et al., 2003</xref>) available from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center. The <italic>cul3a-1</italic>, <italic>cul3b-1</italic>, and <italic>pif3-3 pif4-2</italic> T-DNA mutants were as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gingerich et al. (2005</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Leivar et al. (2008a)</xref>, respectively. The <italic>phyA-211</italic>, <italic>phyB-9</italic> (<italic>hy3</italic>-EMS142), and <italic>cop1-6</italic> missense alleles were as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Reed et al., 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">McNellis et al., 1994</xref>). Genotypes of the mutants were determined by genomic PCR using gene-specific and/or T-DNA left border-specific primers. The <italic>phyB-9</italic> allele was tracked by PCR amplification of the genomic region surrounding the point mutation followed by assessing the sensitivity of the mutated site to <italic>Sty</italic>I digestion (New England Biolabs; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Reed et al., 1993</xref>). All PCR primers used in this study are described in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>. The primer pairs used for genotyping in combination with the T-DNA-specific Lba1 primer were as follows: P1&#x002B;P2 (<italic>lrb1-1</italic>), P3&#x002B;P4 (<italic>lrb2-1</italic>), P7&#x002B;P8 (<italic>lrb2-2</italic>), P9&#x002B;P10 (<italic>lrb2-3</italic>), P11&#x002B;P12 (<italic>lrb3-1</italic>), and P13&#x002B;P14 (<italic>phyD-2</italic>). Linkage of the <italic>lrb1-1</italic> and <italic>lrb2-1</italic> alleles to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> hypersensitivity was accomplished with segregating progeny from a self-crossed heterozygous <italic>lrb1-1/&#x002B; lrb2-1/&#x002B;</italic> plant by their hypersensitivity of hypocotyl growth inhibition to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> (5 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). Individual seedlings were genotyped by PCR using primers P1&#x002B;P2 (<italic>lrb1-1</italic>) and P5&#x002B;P6 (<italic>lrb2-1</italic>).</p></sec><sec><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def26">qRT</xref>-PCR Analyses</title><p>For light-specific treatments, total mRNA was extracted from seedlings grown for 4 d in darkness or in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> (20 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> treatments, seedlings were grown on Murashige and Skoog (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def25">MS</xref>) agar and exposed to white light in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">LDs</xref> for 10 d prior to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> treatment. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> or methyl-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> (100 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc>; Sigma) or water alone was sprayed onto the plants until the leaves were coated with liquid and the tissue was then collected at 0, 1, or 3 h afterward. RNA was extracted using the RNeasy kit (Promega) and treated with RQ1 DNase (Promega). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def27">cDNA</xref> synthesis was performed with an oligo(dT)<sub>20</sub> primer using the SuperScript III <xref ref-type="list" rid="def27">cDNA</xref> Synthesis kit (Invitrogen). For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR, equal amounts of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def27">cDNA</xref> were subjected to PCR and the products were examined by ethidium bromide staining after agarose gel electrophoresis. Primers used for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR were P15, P16, P17, P18 (<italic>LRB1</italic>), P19, P20, P21, P22 (<italic>LRB2</italic>), P23, P24, P25, P26, P27 (<italic>LRB3</italic>), P28, P29, P30, P31, P32 (<italic>PHYD</italic>), and P33, P34 (<italic>PAE2</italic>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def26">qRT</xref>-PCR was performed using the MyIQ5 two-color real-time detection system (Bio-Rad). Relative expression was calculated with the comparative deltaT method using the <italic>PP2A-2</italic> gene (<italic>At1g13320</italic>) as the reference gene because its expression varies little in response to light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Czechowski et al., 2005</xref>). For <italic>CAB2</italic> expression, total mRNA was extracted from 4-d-old dark-grown seedlings treated with 20 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for the indicated times. Primers used for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def26">qRT</xref>-PCR were P35&#x002B;P36 (<italic>CAB2</italic>), P37&#x002B;P38 (<italic>PP2A-2</italic>), P39&#x002B;P40 (<italic>PHYB</italic>), P41&#x002B;P42 (<italic>PHYD</italic>), P43&#x002B;P44 (<italic>PHYA</italic>), P45&#x002B;P46 (<italic>LRB1</italic>), P47&#x002B;P48 (<italic>LRB2</italic>), P49&#x002B;P50 (<italic>PDF1.2</italic>), and P451&#x002B;P52 (<italic>ACT2</italic>).</p></sec><sec><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">Y2H</xref> and Coimmunoprecipitation Assays</title><p>For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">Y2H</xref>, full-length coding regions for <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic> were expressed as C-terminal fusions to the Gal4-AD in <italic>pGADT7</italic> and the Gal4-BD in <italic>pGBKT7</italic>. The primers used during PCR for the constructs in both <italic>pGADT7</italic> and <italic>pGBKT7</italic> are P53&#x002B;P54 (<italic>LRB1</italic>) and P55&#x002B;P56 (<italic>LRB2</italic>). Constructs encoding CUL1, CUL3a, CUL3b, RBX1, ASK1, UFO, p53, COI1, and At4g08455 were as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gingerich et al., 2005</xref>). All constructs were transformed into haploid yeast strains YPB2a and LB414&#x03B1; and assayed for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def15">Y2H</xref> interactions by the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gingerich et al. (2005)</xref>. For the coimmunoprecipitation assays, seedlings expressing GFP, GFP-LRB1, or GFP-LRB2 (see below) were grown in the dark for 4 d and either kept in the dark or irradiated with 20 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> for an additional 12 h. Frozen seedlings were pulverized and extracted (mL g<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> fresh weight) into 100 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl (pH 8.3), 140 m<sc>m</sc> ammonium sulfate, 10 m<sc>m</sc> Na<sub>2</sub>EDTA, and 50% ethylene glycol with 3.8 mg mL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> sodium metabisulfite, 4 m<sc>m</sc> phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, 50 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> MG132 (Selleck Chemicals), and 1&#x00D7; protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma-Aldrich) added just before use. GFP proteins were immunoprecipitated from the clarified protein extracts by incubation with 3 &#x03BC;L of rabbit anti-GFP antibodies (Abcam) for 2 h, collection with anti-protein A/G magnetic beads (Pierce), and then elution into SDS-PAGE sample buffer. All manipulations were done in the dark under a green safelight. Immunoblot analyses were performed using anti-GFP and anti-CUL3 antibodies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Figueroa et al., 2005</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Plant Growth Conditions and Morphological Measurements</title><p>Wild-type and mutant seeds were surface sterilized and plated on one-half-strength <xref ref-type="list" rid="def25">MS</xref> medium supplemented with 10 g L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Suc and 0.7% agar (pH 5.7; <xref ref-type="list" rid="def25">MS</xref> agar). For light treatments, seeds were first cold treated for 4 d in the dark at 4&#x00B0;C, exposed at 23&#x00B0;C to white light (140 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) for 8 h to induce germination, incubated for 16 h at room temperature in darkness, and then exposed to various light regimes. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> (670 nm), <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> (735 nm), and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">B</xref> (470 nm) was provided by SNAP-LITE light-emitting diode modules (Quantum Devices), and white light was provided by Octron 800 4100K cool-white fluorescent bulbs (Osram Sylvania Products).</p><p>Hypocotyl lengths, cotyledon angles, and cotyledon areas were measured and analyzed using ImageJ software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>). Cotyledon angles represented the angle between a straight line drawn between the tip of the cotyledon and the cotyledon blade/cotyledon petiole junction and a straight line drawn through the cotyledon petiole. An angle of 180&#x00B0; reflected a fully folded cotyledon. For the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def21">EOD</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> response, seedlings were subjected to 8 h of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref> (100 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), a 10-min pulse of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> (100 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), and then 16 h of darkness for 4 d. Control seedlings were not exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> but instead placed in darkness for an additional 10 min. For germination assays, seeds were surface sterilized, plated on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def25">MS</xref> agar, irradiated for 5 min with various fluence rates of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">FR</xref> 2 h after plating, and then placed in darkness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Oh et al., 2007</xref>). Germination was scored 5 d later by the emergence of the radicle. For flowering time, seedlings were first grown on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def25">MS</xref> agar, transferred to soil after 10 d, and then exposed at 21&#x00B0;C to white light in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">LDs</xref>. Flowering time was determined by the number of rosette leaves present when the inflorescence stem reached 1 cm. For petiole length measurements, seedlings were transferred from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def25">MS</xref> agar to soil after 7 d, grown for 8 d under high-fluence white light (140 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def16">LDs</xref>, and then exposed to low-fluence white light (8 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) for an additional 7 d. For chlorophyll measurements, seedlings were ground in 80% acetone buffered with 50 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), clarified at 12,000<italic>g</italic> for 10 min, and the total amount of chlorophyll was determined by measuring the absorbance of the supernatant at 663 and 646 nm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Porra, 2002</xref>). For root elongation measurements, seedlings were grown vertically on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def25">MS</xref> agar supplemented with either <xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> or methyl-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def23">JA</xref> under 10 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> or under continuous white light for 7 or 10 d, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Rescuing the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> Phenotype with <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>Flag-LRB1</italic></title><p>The full-length coding sequence for <italic>LRB1</italic> (using the upstream start codon) was PCR amplified from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col-0</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def27">cDNA</xref> using primers P56 and P57 and introduced in frame into the pEARLEYGATE 202 destination vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Earley et al., 2006</xref>) to express the LRB1 protein bearing a N-terminal Flag epitope (MDYKDDDDK) under the control of the <italic>35S</italic> promoter. This construct was transformed into <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> plants using the <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> floral dip method. Transformants were selected by Basta resistance and for expression of the <italic>Flag-LRB1</italic> transcript by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR using primers P59 (<italic>Flag</italic>) and P60 (<italic>LRB1</italic>), using <xref ref-type="list" rid="def14">RT</xref>-PCR of the <italic>UBC9</italic> gene as the control for equal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def27">cDNA</xref> loading (primers P61 and P62). Lines homozygous for the <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>Flag-LRB1</italic> transgene were identified by segregation of Basta resistance in the T3 generation. The Flag-LRB1 protein was detected in crude soluble extracts by immunoblot analysis with a mouse monoclonal antibody against the Flag sequence (Sigma; F1804).</p></sec><sec><title>Immunoblot Analyses of phyA, phyB, and phyD</title><p>The phyA, phyB, and phyD proteins were extracted from 4-d-old seedlings grown in darkness or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> (20 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) using the phyB extraction buffer developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Al-Sady et al. (2006</xref>) with modifications. Briefly, seedlings were homogenized in 100 m<sc>m</sc> MOPS-KOH (pH 7.6), 50 m<sc>m</sc> sodium metabisulfate, 2% SDS, 10% glycerol, 4 m<sc>m</sc> Na<sub>2</sub>EDTA, and 1&#x00D7; Complete Plant Protease Inhibitor cocktail (Sigma). After heating for 10 min, the solution was clarified for 2 min at 10,000<italic>g</italic> and then subjected to SDS-PAGE. Following electrophoretic transfer onto polyvinylidene difluoride membranes, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">phys</xref> were detected with monoclonal antibodies that recognize the phyA (073D), phyB (B1&#x002B;B7), and phyD (2c1) polypeptides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Shanklin et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Hirschfeld et al., 1998</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Cycloheximide and MG132 Treatments</title><p>Seeds were sown on 24-well plates containing liquid one-half-strength <xref ref-type="list" rid="def25">MS</xref> plus 10 g L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Suc, exposed to white light for 8 h at 23&#x00B0;C to induce germination, and then placed on a shaker in the dark for 4 d. For cycloheximide or MG132 exposure, the seedlings were incubated in the dark in the presence of 100 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> of the inhibitor for either 1 h (cycloheximide) or 12 h (MG132) and then either irradiated with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> (20 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) or kept in the dark for additional times before sample collection.</p></sec><sec><title>Subcellular Localization of LRB1/2 and phyB</title><p>The full-length <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic> coding sequences were PCR amplified with primers P63 and P64 (<italic>LRB1</italic>) and P65 and P66 (<italic>LRB2</italic>) from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Col-0</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def27">cDNA</xref> and introduced in frame into a modified pMDC99 vector to express the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> proteins as a C-terminal fusion to GFP under the control of the <italic>UBQ10</italic> promoter. <italic>UBQ10</italic>:<italic>GFP-LRB1/2 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> transformants generated by the floral dip method were selected by hygromycin resistance. Phenotypic rescue was assessed by hypocotyl elongation in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> (20 &#x03BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) on T2 plants segregating for the presence of the <italic>GFP-LRB1/2</italic> transgenes as determined by PCR with primers P69 (<italic>GFP</italic>), P67 (<italic>LRB1</italic>), and P68 (<italic>LRB2</italic>). GFP-LRB/2 proteins were detected in crude soluble extracts by immunoblot analysis with mouse monoclonal antibody against the GFP moiety (Abcam; Ab1218). For GFP-LRB1/2 localization, segregating T2 seedlings were grown on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def25">MS</xref> agar for 4 d in darkness or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> (20 &#x03BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) prior to imaging. R-induced concentration of phyB into nuclear speckles was observed by fluorescence confocal microscopy of the <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>PHYB-GFP</italic> reporter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Boccalandro et al., 2009</xref>) introgressed into the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> double mutant. Triple homozygous 4-d-old seedlings grown in the dark on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def25">MS</xref> agar were exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> (20 &#x03BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) for 24 h and imaged for GFP fluorescence with a Zeiss 510-Meta scanning laser confocal microscope using 488-nm light excitation.</p><p>Sequence data for <italic>LRB1</italic>, <italic>LRB2</italic>, and <italic>LRB3</italic> described in this article can be found in the GenBank/EMBL databases under accession numbers NM_130189.2 (<italic>At2g46260</italic>), NM_180402.1 (<italic>At3g61600</italic>), and NM_116346.2 (<italic>At4g01160</italic>), respectively. Sequence identifiers and accession numbers for the other <italic>LRB</italic> genes in this study can be found in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1">Supplemental Data Set S1</ext-link>. The reannotated <italic>At4g01160</italic> sequence is also described in this data set.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> Multiple sequence alignment of full-length LRB proteins.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> Gblocks-edited sequence alignment of full-length LRB proteins.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S3.</bold></ext-link> Neighbor-joining, maximum parsimony, and maximum likelihood phylogenetic trees from the full-length Gblocks-edited multiple sequence alignment of the LRB protein family.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S4.</bold></ext-link> Multiple sequence alignment of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domains from the LRB protein family.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S5.</bold></ext-link> Neighbor-joining, maximum parsimony, and maximum likelihood phylogenetic trees from the multiple sequence alignment of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BTB</xref> domains from the LRB protein family.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S6.</bold></ext-link> R-induced suppression of hypocotyl elongation for <italic>cul3a</italic> and <italic>cul3b</italic> mutants and <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants when grown without Suc.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S7.</bold></ext-link> The R-hypersensitive phenotype cosegregates with the <italic>lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> mutations.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S8.</bold></ext-link> Additional light responses for the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S9</bold></ext-link>. Description of the <italic>phyD-2</italic> mutant and genotypic confirmation of quadruple homozygous <italic>phyB-9 phyD-2 lrb1-1 lrb2-1</italic> mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S10</bold></ext-link>. Light responses of <italic>phyB-9</italic>, <italic>phyD-2</italic>, <italic>lrb1-1</italic>, and <italic>lrb2-1</italic> mutant combinations.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S11.</bold></ext-link> phyB and phyD protein levels in the dark and mRNA levels in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def18">Rc</xref> or dark are not regulated by LRB1 and LRB2.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S12.</bold></ext-link> LRB1 and LRB2 proteins are regulated by the 26S proteasome but not by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">R</xref>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S13.</bold></ext-link> Rescue of the <italic>lrb1 lrb2</italic> phenotype with GFP-LRB1/2 and fluorescence confocal microscopic localization of GFP-LRB1 in root cells.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S14.</bold></ext-link> <italic>LRB1</italic> and <italic>LRB2</italic> may be involved in R-dependent plant defense responses.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S1.</bold></ext-link> Oligonucleotide primers used in this study.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Data Set S1.</bold></ext-link> LRB family reannotations and sequence identifiers for the LRB proteins in various plant species.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.199109/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Materials and Methods S1.</bold></ext-link></p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Joseph Walker for technical advice. The phyB (B1&#x002B;B7) and phyD (2C1) monoclonal antibodies were graciously provided by Dr. Peter Quail.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abascal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zardoya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>ProtTest: selection of best-fit models of protein evolution</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>2104</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2105</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Leisse</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barajas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheuk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide insertional mutagenesis of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>301</volume>: <fpage>653</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>657</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Sady</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kircher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x00E4;fer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Photoactivated phytochrome induces rapid PIF3 phosphorylation prior to proteasome-mediated degradation</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>446</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Batschauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Molecular interaction between COP1 and HY5 defines a regulatory switch for light control of Arabidopsis development</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>222</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Decoding of light signals by plant phytochromes and their interacting proteins</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>311</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boccalandro</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rugnone</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ploschuk</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Serna</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Casal</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome B enhances photosynthesis at the expense of water-use efficiency in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>1083</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1092</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosu</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kipreos</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cullin-RING ubiquitin ligases: global regulation and activation cycles</article-title>. <source>Cell Div</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boylan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Oat phytochrome is biologically active in transgenic tomatoes</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>765</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>773</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boylan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome A overexpression inhibits hypocotyl elongation in transgenic Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>10806</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>10810</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cant&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Both phyA and phyB mediate light-imposed repression of <italic>PHYA</italic> gene expression in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>1207</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1216</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>NPY1, a BTB-NPH3-like protein, plays a critical role in auxin-regulated organogenesis in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>18825</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>18829</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cherry</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hondred</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome requires the 6-kDa N-terminal domain for full biological activity</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>5039</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5043</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christians</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gingerich</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieber</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The BTB ubiquitin ligases ETO1, EOL1 and EOL2 act collectively to regulate ethylene biosynthesis in Arabidopsis by controlling type-2 ACC synthase levels</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>332</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>345</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome degradation</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>713</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>721</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Czechowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide identification and testing of superior reference genes for transcript normalization in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>17</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitelam</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome E influences internode elongation and flowering time in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1479</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1487</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dieterle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Renou</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmentier</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cognat</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemonnier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Genschik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Molecular and functional characterization of Arabidopsis Cullin 3A</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>386</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>399</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Earley</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Opper</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Juehne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pikaard</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Gateway-compatible vectors for plant functional genomics and proteomics</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>616</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>629</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Casal</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Phenotypic characterization of a photomorphogenic mutant</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>747</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>760</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gusmaroli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Serino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Habashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bostick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Callis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> has two redundant Cullin3 proteins that are essential for embryo development and that interact with RBX1 and BTB proteins to form multisubunit E3 ubiquitin ligase complexes in vivo</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1180</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1195</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoddart</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitelam</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year><comment>a</comment>) <article-title>Mutant analyses define multiple roles for phytochrome C in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> photomorphogenesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1981</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1989</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Praekelt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoddart</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Billingham</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name><name><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitelam</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year><comment>b</comment>) <article-title>Phytochromes B, D, and E act redundantly to control multiple physiological responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>1340</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1346</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome functions in Arabidopsis development</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>24</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Borchers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Targeting of protein ubiquitination by BTB-Cullin 3-Roc1 ubiquitin ligases</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1001</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1007</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawers</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brutnell</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Parthasarathy</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Light-regulated overexpression of an Arabidopsis phytochrome A gene in rice alters plant architecture and increases grain yield</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>223</volume>: <fpage>627</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>636</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilkerson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Callis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Isolation and characterization of <italic>cul1-7</italic>, a recessive allele of <italic>CULLIN1</italic> that disrupts SCF function at the C terminus of CUL1 in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> <italic>thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>181</volume>: <fpage>945</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>963</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gingerich</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagne</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salter</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Estelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Cullins 3a and 3b assemble with members of the broad complex/tramtrack/bric-a-brac (BTB) protein family to form essential ubiquitin-protein ligases (E3s) in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>280</volume>: <fpage>18810</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>18821</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gingerich</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Large-scale, lineage-specific expansion of a bric-a-brac/tramtrack/broad complex ubiquitin-ligase gene family in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2329</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2348</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamazato</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinomura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanzawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Fluence and wavelength requirements for Arabidopsis <italic>CAB</italic> gene induction by different phytochromes</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>1533</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1540</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hepworth</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>McKim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Haughn</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>BLADE-ON-PETIOLE-dependent signaling controls leaf and floral patterning in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1434</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1448</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirschfeld</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tepperman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clack</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharrock</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Coordination of phytochrome levels in <italic>phyB</italic> mutants of Arabidopsis as revealed by apoprotein-specific monoclonal antibodies</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>149</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>535</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hornitschek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorrain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoete</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Michielin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of the shade avoidance response by formation of non-DNA binding bHLH heterodimers</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>3893</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3902</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The cullin-RING ubiquitin-protein ligases</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>334</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Sady</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Apel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome-interacting factor 1 is a critical bHLH regulator of chlorophyll biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>305</volume>: <fpage>1937</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1941</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>PIF4, a phytochrome-interacting bHLH factor, functions as a negative regulator of phytochrome B signaling in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>2441</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2450</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jabben</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanklin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Ubiquitin-phytochrome conjugates: pool dynamics during in vivo phytochrome degradation</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>264</volume>: <fpage>4998</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5005</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagatani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> PHYTOCHROME INTERACTING FACTOR proteins promote phytochrome B polyubiquitination by COP1 E3 ligase in the nucleus</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2370</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2383</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerscher</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Felberbaum</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochstrasser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Modification of proteins by ubiquitin and ubiquitin-like proteins</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>180</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikis</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Sady</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanzatella</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A novel molecular recognition motif necessary for targeting photoactivated phytochrome signaling to specific basic helix-loop-helix transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>3033</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3044</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kircher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozma-Bogn&#x00E1;r</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fejes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Speth</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Husselstein-Muller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ad&#x00E1;m</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x00E4;fer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Nucleocytoplasmic partitioning of the plant photoreceptors phytochrome A, B, C, D, and E is regulated differentially by light and exhibits a diurnal rhythm</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1541</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1555</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Horiguchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohgishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsukaya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The different growth responses of the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> leaf blade and the petiole during shade avoidance are regulated by photoreceptors and sugar</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>223</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lechner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonhardt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmentier</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Alioua</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacquet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Genschik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MATH/BTB CRL3 receptors target the homeodomain-leucine zipper ATHB6 to modulate abscisic acid signaling</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1116</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1128</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leivar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Monte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Sady</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Carle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Storer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year><comment>a</comment>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> phytochrome-interacting factor PIF7, together with PIF3 and PIF4, regulates responses to prolonged red light by modulating phyB levels</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>352</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leivar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Monte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Castillon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year><comment>b</comment>) <article-title>Multiple phytochrome-interacting bHLH transcription factors repress premature seedling photomorphogenesis in darkness</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1815</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1823</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leivar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>PIFs: pivotal components in a cellular signaling hub</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>28</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNellis</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>von Arnim</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Komeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mis&#x00E9;ra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Genetic and molecular analysis of an allelic series of <italic>cop1</italic> mutants suggests functional roles for the multiple protein domains</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>487</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>500</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tepperman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Sady</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaczorowski</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The phytochrome-interacting transcription factor, PIF3, acts early, selectively, and positively in light-induced chloroplast development</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>16091</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>16098</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballar&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Ecological modulation of plant defense via phytochrome control of jasmonate sensitivity</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>4935</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>4940</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motchoulski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liscum</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis NPH3: a NPH1 photoreceptor-interacting protein essential for phototropism</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>961</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>964</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gojobori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Simple methods for estimating the numbers of synonymous and nonsynonymous nucleotide substitutions</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>418</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>426</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusuke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>PIL5, a phytochrome-interacting bHLH protein, regulates gibberellin responsiveness by binding directly to the <italic>GAI</italic> and <italic>RGA</italic> promoters in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1192</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1208</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title><italic>hy8</italic>, a new class of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> long hypocotyl mutants deficient in functional phytochrome A</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>48</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porra</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The chequered history of the development and use of simultaneous equations for the accurate determination of chlorophylls a and b</article-title>. <source>Photosynth Res</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>156</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Two BTB proteins function redundantly as negative regulators of defense against pathogens in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Botany</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>953</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>960</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome photosensory signalling networks</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>93</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quint</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Characterization of a novel temperature-sensitive allele of the CUL1/AXR6 subunit of SCF ubiquitin-ligases</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>383</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagatani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Elich</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome A and phytochrome B have overlapping but distinct functions in Arabidopsis development</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>1139</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1149</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagpal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Mutations in the gene for the red/far-red light receptor phytochrome B alter cell elongation and physiological responses throughout <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>147</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>157</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rizzini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Favory</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cloix</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Faggionato</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x2019;Hara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiserli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x00E4;fer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Perception of UV-B by the Arabidopsis UVR8 protein</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>332</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>106</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Quint</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivian-Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Offringa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>BTB and TAZ domain scaffold proteins perform a crucial function in Arabidopsis development</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>121</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rockwell</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagarias</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome structure and signaling mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>837</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>858</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishiguro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>RPT2: a signal transducer of the phototropic response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>236</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Photomorphogenesis in Plants and Bacteria: Function and Signal Transduction Mechanisms</article-title>, <comment>Ed 3. Springer-Verlag, Dordrecht, The Netherlands</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokutomi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagatani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Photoreceptor ubiquitination by COP1 E3 ligase desensitizes phytochrome A signaling</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>617</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>622</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shanklin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jabben</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Red light-induced formation of ubiquitin-phytochrome conjugates: identification of possible intermediates of phytochrome degradation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>363</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shanklin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jabben</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Partial purification and peptide mapping of ubiquitin phytochrome conjugates in oat</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>6028</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>6034</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharrock</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clack</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Patterns of expression and normalized levels of the five Arabidopsis phytochromes</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>442</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>456</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shinomura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagatani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanzawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Action spectra for phytochrome A- and B-specific photoinduction of seed germination in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>8129</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>8133</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smalle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The ubiquitin 26S proteasome proteolytic pathway</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>590</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome-mediated light regulation of <italic>PHYA-</italic> and <italic>PHYB-GUS</italic> transgenes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> seedlings</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>534</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spoel</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Spivey</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Genschik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Proteasome-mediated turnover of the transcription coactivator NPR1 plays dual roles in regulating plant immunity</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>860</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>872</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stogios</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jauhal</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nandra</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Priv&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Sequence and structural analysis of BTB domain proteins</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>R82</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The ubiquitin-26S proteasome system at the nexus of plant biology</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>397</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vision</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The origins of genomic duplications in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>290</volume>: <fpage>2114</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2117</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lurin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Regulation of ethylene gas biosynthesis by the Arabidopsis ETO1 protein</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>428</volume>: <fpage>945</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>950</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnaby</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>T&#x00F6;r</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldelari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DU</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Timing of plant immune responses by a central circadian regulator</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>470</volume>: <fpage>110</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>114</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wester</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Clack</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharrock</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Transgenic complementation of the <italic>hy3</italic> phytochrome B mutation and response to PHYB gene copy number in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>272</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Reboul</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaglio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>T-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elledge</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>BTB proteins are substrate-specific adaptors in an SCF-like modular ubiquitin ligase containing CUL-3</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>425</volume>: <fpage>316</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>321</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagatani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Light-dependent translocation of a phytochrome B-GFP fusion protein to the nucleus in transgenic Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>445</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
