<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">147371</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.147371</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>CELL BIOLOGY AND SIGNAL TRANSDUCTION</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MCA1 and MCA2 That Mediate Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> Uptake Have Distinct and Overlapping Roles in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7"><sup>[OA]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>Takuya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>Yuko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>Kendo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>Masataka</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>Tomomi</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>Hajime</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Terashima</surname><given-names>Asuka</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>Kazuko</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>Itaru</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>Takeshi</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>Kazuo</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>Hidetoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&ast;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Biology, Tokyo Gakugei University, Koganei, Tokyo 184&ndash;8501, Japan (T.Y., Y.N., K.M., M.N., T.I., H.K., A.T., H.I.); Core Research for Evolutional Science and Technology, Japan Science and Technology Agency, Kawaguchi, Saitama 332&ndash;0012, Japan (T.Y., Y.N., K.S., H.I.); Laboratory of Cell Biology, Institute for Molecular and Cellular Regulation, Gunma University, Maebashi, Gunma 371&ndash;8510, Japan (Y.N., I.K.); Gene Research Center, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, Tokyo 183&ndash;8509, Japan (M.N.); Biomembrane Signaling Project 2, Tokyo Metropolitan Institute of Medical Science, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113&ndash;8613, Japan (K.I.); Laboratory of Plant Molecular Biology, RIKEN Tsukuba Institute, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305&ndash;0074, Japan (Y.N., T.K., K.S.); and Okazaki Institute for Integrative Bioscience, National Institutes of Natural Sciences, Okazaki 444&ndash;8787, Japan (H.I.)</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&ast;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>iida@u-gakugei.ac.jp</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by a grant from Core Research for Evolutional Science and Technology, Japan Science and Technology Agency to H.I.; by Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research on Priority Areas from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology of Japan (nos. 19045009 and 21026009 to H.I.); by a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research (B) from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology of Japan (no. 21370017 to H.I.); by a grant from The Novartis Foundation (Japan) for the Promotion of Science (no. KEN20&ndash;191 to H.I.); and by a grant for the Frontiers of Membrane Protein Research (a joint project between the Institute for Protein Research, Osaka University, and Okazaki Institute for Integrative Bioscience to H.I.).</p></fn><fn id="fn2" fn-type="equal"><label>2</label><p>These authors contributed equally to the article.</p></fn><fn id="fn3" fn-type="present-address"><label>3</label><p>Present address: Department of Applied Biological Science, Tokyo University of Science, 2641 Yamazaki, Noda, Chiba, 278&ndash;8510 Japan.</p></fn><fn id="fn4" fn-type="present-address"><label>4</label><p>Present address: Laboratory of Cell Biology, Institute for Molecular and Cellular Regulation, Gunma University, Maebashi, Gunma 371&ndash;8510, Japan.</p></fn><fn id="fn5" fn-type="present-address"><label>5</label><p>Present address: Tamagawa Academy Upper Secondary Division, Machida, Tokyo 194&ndash;8610, Japan.</p></fn><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Hidetoshi Iida (<email>iida@u-gakugei.ac.jp</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn6"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn7"><label>[OA]</label><p>Open Access articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.109.147371">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.109.147371</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>3</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>152</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1284</fpage><lpage>1296</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2010 American Society of Plant Biologists</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p></p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> is important for plant growth and development as a nutrient and a second messenger. However, the molecular nature and roles of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>-permeable channels or transporters involved in Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake in roots are largely unknown. We recently identified a candidate for the Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>-permeable mechanosensitive channel in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), named MCA1. Here, we investigated the only paralog of MCA1 in Arabidopsis, MCA2. cDNA of <italic>MCA2</italic> complemented a Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake deficiency in yeast cells lacking a Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> channel composed of Mid1 and Cch1. Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction analysis indicated that <italic>MCA2</italic> was expressed in leaves, flowers, roots, siliques, and stems, and histochemical observation showed that an <italic>MCA2</italic> promoter::<italic>GUS</italic> fusion reporter gene was universally expressed in 10-d-old seedlings with some exceptions: it was relatively highly expressed in vascular tissues and undetectable in the cap and the elongation zone of the primary root. <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants were normal in growth and morphology. In addition, the primary root of <italic>mca2</italic>-null seedlings was able to normally sense the hardness of agar medium, unlike that of <italic>mca1</italic>-null or <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null seedlings, as revealed by the two-phase agar method. Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity was lower in the roots of <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants than those of wild-type plants. Finally, growth of <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants was more retarded at a high concentration of Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> added to medium compared with that of <italic>mca1</italic>-null and <italic>mca2</italic>-null single mutants and wild-type plants. These results suggest that the MCA2 protein has a distinct role in Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake in roots and an overlapping role with MCA1 in plant growth.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Calcium ion (Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>) is an essential element in plants, as in animals. In plants, Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> is required for the formation of the cell wall as a determinant of structural rigidity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Jones and Lunt, 1967</xref>) and for the regulation of intracellular physiological events as a second messenger of extracellular stimuli, including chemical, physical, and mechanical stimuli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Fasano et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Sanders et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Braam, 2004</xref>). Thus, this ion is a crucial modulator of plant growth and development. In response to those stimuli, Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> moves to the cytoplasm through Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>-permeable ion channels or transporters located in the plasma membrane or organellar membranes. Recent electrophysiological and bioinformatic analyses have found that there are several types of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>-permeable ion channels in plants, including depolarization-gated, hyperpolarization-gated, ligand-gated, and mechanosensitive channels, although the structural entity and physiological functions of most are still obscure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">V&eacute;ry and Sentenac, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">White et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Dutta and Robinson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Qi et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Telewski, 2006</xref>).</p><p>Our recent study has identified a plasma membrane protein (named MCA1; locus name, At4g35920) involved in Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>). Overexpression of <italic>MCA1</italic> from a strong promoter increases Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake in roots and also enhances a rise in the cytoplasmic free Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> concentration upon hypoosmotic shock. The primary root of <italic>mca1</italic>-null seedlings is unable to enter the lower, harder agar medium from the upper, softer one, suggesting that the <italic>mca1</italic>-null root cannot sense and/or respond to the hardness of the agar. In addition, heterologous expression of <italic>MCA1</italic> markedly increases Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake in a yeast mutant lacking the high-affinity Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx system composed of Mid1 and Cch1. Therefore, MCA1 is a potential component of the Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>-permeable mechanosensitive channel in Arabidopsis.</p><p><italic>MCA2</italic> (locus name, At2g17780) is the only paralog of <italic>MCA1</italic> found in the Arabidopsis genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>). MCA2 is 72.7% identical and 89.4% similar to MCA1 in amino acid sequence. The two proteins share the same structural features: The N-terminal half has a region similar to the putative regulatory region of many rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) putative protein kinases, an EF-hand-like motif, and a coiled-coil motif. The C-terminal half possesses two to four putative transmembrane segments and a Cys-rich domain of unknown function, called the PLAC8 motif (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Galaviz-Hernandez et al., 2003</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we made an <italic>mca2</italic>-null single mutant and an <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant to investigate fundamental functions of MCA1 and MCA2 in terms of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake, plant growth, and mechanosensing. We demonstrate that both mutants are defective in Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake from the roots, and the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant has a slow growth phenotype compared with the wild type. In addition, the growth of the double mutant is more sensitive to excess Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup>. We also show that the primary root of the <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant appears to be normal in sensing and/or responding to the hardness of agar medium. Since this phenotype contrasts with the phenotype of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null mutant previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>), we discuss possible similarities and differences in function between <italic>MCA1</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic>.</p><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>MCA2 Complements the Yeast <italic>mid1</italic> Mutation</title><p>To test the functional similarity of <italic>MCA2</italic> to <italic>MCA1</italic>, we employed functional complementation of the <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae mid1</italic> mutant, which is defective in a putative Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>-permeable mechanosensitive channel component and thus dies upon exposure to mating pheromone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Iida et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Kanzaki et al., 1999</xref>). The <italic>mid1</italic> mutant was transformed with the yeast expression plasmid YEpTDHXho-MCA2 containing <italic>MCA2</italic> cDNA placed under the control of the yeast <italic>TDH3</italic> promoter. Quantitative assays showed that <italic>MCA2</italic> complemented the low Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity of <italic>mid1</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>) and partially rescued the <italic>mid1</italic> cells from mating pheromone-induced death (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Function of <italic>MCA2</italic> in yeast cells. A, <italic>MCA2</italic> has the ability to increase Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> accumulation even in the <italic>mid1 cch1</italic> double mutant. <italic>MCA1</italic> or <italic>MCA2</italic> cDNA on a multicopy plasmid was expressed under the control of the <italic>TDH3</italic> promoter in each yeast mutant (<italic>mid1</italic>, <italic>cch1</italic>, or <italic>mid1 cch1</italic>) as well as the parental strain (wild type). The yeast <italic>MID1</italic> gene with its own promoter was also expressed from a multicopy plasmid, YEpMID1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>). Data are the mean &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> for three independent experiments. &ast;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 versus the vector in each mutant. Note that the data for vector, <italic>MID1</italic>, and <italic>MCA1</italic> are from our previous article (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>). B, <italic>MCA2</italic> has the ability to increase viability after exposure to <italic>&alpha;</italic> -factor even in the <italic>mid1 cch1</italic> double mutant. The yeast cells used in this experiment are the same as in A. Data are the mean &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> for three independent experiments. &ast;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 versus the vector (control) in each mutant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp147371F01_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>In <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, Mid1 coworks with Cch1 to function as the sole high-affinity Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Muller et al., 2001</xref>); therefore, <italic>MID1</italic> cannot complement the <italic>cch1</italic> single and the <italic>mid1 cch1</italic> double mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Iida et al., 2004</xref>). By contrast, <italic>MCA1</italic> can do so (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1, A and B</xref>, shows that <italic>MCA2</italic> was also capable of complementing the low Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity and low viability phenotypes of the <italic>cch1</italic> single and the <italic>mid1 cch1</italic> double mutants. These results indicate that MCA2 functions as a Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx system in yeast cells, independently of Mid1 and Cch1, just like MCA1.</p></sec><sec><title>Overlapping and Distinct Expression of MCA1 and MCA2</title><p>A reverse transcription PCR (RT-PCR) analysis showed <italic>MCA2</italic> to be expressed in all the organs examined, including leaves, flowers, roots, siliques, and stems (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). The spatial pattern of <italic>MCA2</italic> expression was examined with an <italic>MCA2</italic> promoter::<italic>GUS</italic> fusion reporter gene construct (<italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2B</xref>, i&ndash;k, shows that <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was universally expressed in 10-d-old seedlings, with relatively high levels in vascular tissues and no expression in the root cap, promeristem, and adjacent elongation zone of the primary root. <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was also expressed in mesophyll cells and vascular tissues of cotyledons and leaves. In addition, it was expressed at the center of rosettes in a region corresponding to the shoot apical meristem (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, l). A cross section of the primary root indicated that <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was expressed in the stele and endodermis, but not in the cortex and epidermis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, m). We noticed that the level of <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> expression was gradually lowered in cotyledons as they aged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, i). In 22-d-old plants, <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was expressed in leaves and roughly the upper half of the inflorescence, but not in petioles of rosette leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, n&ndash;p). It was also expressed at the center of rosettes and the inflorescence.</p><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic>MCA2</italic>. A, RT-PCR of the <italic>MCA2</italic> transcript. Total RNA was isolated from leaves, flowers, roots, siliques, and stems of wild-type Arabidopsis plants (5 to 6 weeks old) and subjected to RT-PCR. <italic>&beta;</italic> -Tubulin mRNA was used for an internal control. B, Spatial patterns of <italic>MCA1</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic> transcription as revealed by <italic>GUS</italic> staining. Ten-day-old (a&ndash;e and i&ndash;m) and 22-d-old (f&ndash;h and n&ndash;p) <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> plants are shown. a and i, A whole plant (an arrow indicates the extreme end of the primary root); b and j, a leaf (not a cotyledon); c and k, the tip of a primary root; d and l, a region corresponding to the shoot apical meristem; e and m, a cross section of a primary root, showing GUS activity in the stele and endodermis; f and n, an upper view of a 22-d-old plant; g and o, magnification of the base of the inflorescence shown in f and n, respectively; h and p, a side view of a 22-d-old plant. Note that two photographs were joined to make h. C, GFP fluorescence images of MCA2-GFP expressed in root cells. The top row represents intact roots of 6-d-old seedlings and the bottom row those treated for at least 10 min with 0.8 <sc>m</sc> mannitol to induce plasmolysis. The membrane marker proteins used are as follows: plasma membrane, a GFP fusion to the plasma membrane channel protein PIP2A expressed in line Q8; endoplasmic reticulum (ER) membrane, a GFP fusion to an endoplasmic reticulum membrane protein expressed in line Q4; vacuolar membrane, a GFP fusion to the vacuolar membrane channel protein <italic>&delta;</italic> -TIP expressed in line Q5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Cutler et al., 2000</xref>); and cytoplasmic GFP.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp147371F02_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig><p><italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was found to be expressed with overlapping and distinct spatial expression patterns compared with <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic>. Like <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic>, in 10-d-old seedlings, <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was expressed in vascular tissues of cotyledons, leaves, and the primary root and at the center of rosettes in a region corresponding to the shoot apical meristem (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, a&ndash;d). It was also expressed in the stele and endodermis, but not in the cortex and epidermis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, e). In 22-d-old plants, <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was expressed weakly in vascular tissues of leaves and at the center of rosettes and the inflorescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, f and g). No expression of both <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was detected in the root hair (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, c and k).</p><p>Unlike <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic>, <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was expressed in the promeristem and adjacent elongation zone of the primary root (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, c). Notably, it was not expressed in the root cap, including the columella and peripheral cap. In addition, no expression of <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was detected in mesophyll cells of leaves and cotyledons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, a and b). In 22-d-old plants, <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was expressed weakly at the lower part of the inflorescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, h). Three independent <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> transgenic lines showed very similar <italic>GUS</italic> expression patterns, and four independent <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> transgenic lines showed essentially the same <italic>GUS</italic> expression pattern, although the levels of <italic>GUS</italic> expression varied from line to line. Detailed results for mature plants will be published elsewhere.</p><p>We also examined subcellular localization of the MCA2-GFP fusion protein produced under the control of the 35S promoter of the <italic>Cauliflower mosaic virus</italic> (CaMV) by fluorescence microscopy. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2C</xref> (top row) suggested that MCA2-GFP was present in the plasma membrane of root cells. This suggestion was strengthened by treatment with a high osmotic solution, 0.8 <sc>m</sc> mannitol, which induced plasmolysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>, bottom row). Fluorescent images and behavior of MCA2-GFP before and after plasmolysis were similar to those of the plasma membrane marker protein PIP2A and different from those of marker proteins for the endoplasmic reticulum and the vacuole as well as those of cytoplasmic GFP, all of which were expressed under the control of the CaMV 35S promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Cutler et al., 2000</xref>). This result is consistent with a structural feature that MCA2 has at least two potential transmembrane segments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>). We noted that a portion of the MCA2-GFP proteins remained on the cell wall after plasmolysis, suggesting that this protein might associate with a cell wall component.</p></sec><sec><title>Basic Phenotypic Analysis of <italic>mca2</italic>-Null and <italic>MCA2</italic>-Overexpression Lines</title><p>To investigate the function of MCA2 in planta, we obtained the <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant line SALK_129208 from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center. In this mutant line, T-DNA was inserted into the fourth exon of the <italic>MCA2</italic> gene to disrupt the <italic>MCA2</italic> open reading frame (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>), resulting in no detectable production of the <italic>MCA2</italic> transcript, as revealed by RT-PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>). To ensure that this mutation is a knockout, we compared the relative transcript levels of <italic>MCA2</italic> in the mutant with wild-type transcript levels using quantitative real-time PCR with a primer set spanning from the fifth exon to the sixth exon. The result indicated that the levels of the <italic>MCA2</italic> transcript were background levels in the mutant relative to the wild type (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Supplemental).</p><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Construction of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant. A, Genomic organization of the <italic>MCA1</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic> genes. Boxes represent exons, and their black areas show the open reading frame. The T-DNA is drawn to an arbitrary size. B, RT-PCR showing no detectable production of the <italic>MCA2</italic> transcript in the <italic>mca2</italic> and <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null line. <italic>&beta;</italic> -Tubulin mRNA is a control. RNA was purified from whole seedlings grown for 10 d.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp147371F03_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>The <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants appeared to grow normally under the ordinary growth conditions we employed, like wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Since MCA1 and MCA2 function similarly in yeast cells as described above and have the same structural features (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>), it is possible that the <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutation is complemented by the intrinsic <italic>MCA1</italic> gene. We therefore constructed the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant by crossing the <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant with the <italic>mca1</italic>-null mutant. RT-PCR revealed that neither the <italic>MCA1</italic> nor <italic>MCA2</italic> transcript was produced in the resulting double mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>). In addition, the quantitative real-time PCR described above indicated that the levels of the <italic>MCA1</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic> transcripts were background levels in the double mutant relative to the wild type (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.005 and <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, respectively; Supplemental).</p><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Growth phenotypes. A, Growth of wild-type, <italic>mca1</italic>-null, <italic>mca2</italic>-null, and <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants. Plants were grown for 20 d on MS medium and for an additional 5 d in soil under a 16-h-light/8-h-dark cycle at 22&deg;C. Bolting of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant was retarded. B, Timing of the appearance of first and second rosette leaves. Thirty-eight to 40 plants were grown for the indicated times on MS medium under a 16-h-light/8-h-dark cycle at 22&deg;C. Percentages of plants that had developed first and second rosette leaves are indicated. A result representative of three independent experiments is shown. In all three experiments, the appearance of first and second rosette leaves was retarded most severely in the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant followed by the <italic>mca1</italic>-null mutant, although the absolute timing of leafing varied from experiment to experiment. C, Timing for bolting. Thirty-eight to 40 plants were grown for 14 d on MS medium and for additional days in soil under a 16-h-light/8-h-dark cycle at 22&deg;C. Percentages of bolted plants are indicated. A result representative of three independent experiments is shown. In all three experiments, the timing of bolting was retarded most severely in the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant followed by the <italic>mca1</italic>-null mutant, although the absolute timing of bolting varied from experiment to experiment.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp147371F04_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>We then performed phenotypic analyses of these mutant lines. Unlike the <italic>mca1</italic>-null and <italic>mca2</italic>-null single mutants, the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant showed an obvious growth defect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). The timing of germination of the seeds of the double mutant appeared to be normal on Murashige and Skoog (MS) medium (data not shown). We thus investigated the timing of leafing and bolting. The results showed that the appearance of first and second rosette leaves of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant was retarded by about half a day (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>) and that the bolting of the mutant was retarded by about 2 d, compared with that of the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>). The leafing and bolting of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null single mutant were also retarded, and the delays were reproducibly smaller than those of the double mutant. These delays were not observed in the <italic>mca2</italic>-null single mutant. Thus, it is possible that <italic>MCA1</italic> might compensate for the function of MCA2 in the <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant but not vice versa. To examine this possibility, we investigated using quantitative real-time PCR whether the transcript levels of <italic>MCA1</italic> are elevated in the <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant. The result showed that the levels were not elevated in this mutant (Supplemental). Likewise, the transcript levels of <italic>MCA2</italic> were not elevated in the <italic>mca1</italic>-null mutant.</p><p>We also constructed Arabidopsis mutant lines (designated <italic>MCA2</italic>ox) that overexpress <italic>MCA2</italic> cDNA under the control of the 35S promoter of CaMV. Quantitative real-time PCR experiments showed that the three <italic>MCA2</italic>ox lines we examined had significantly increased levels of the <italic>MCA2</italic> transcript (Supplemental). This figure also showed that the levels of the <italic>MCA1</italic> transcript were not increased in the three <italic>MCA2</italic>ox lines. Contrary to <italic>MCA1</italic>ox lines whose growth is severely retarded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>), <italic>MCA2</italic>ox lines grew normally (data not shown). This result suggests a possible difference in function between MCA1 and MCA2 under conditions for their overexpression in planta. An alternative possibility would be a difference in the expression levels and patterns of MCA1 and MCA2 in the shoot of wild-type plants. The GUS-staining experiments described above showed that the levels of <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> expression were much lower than those of <italic>MCA2</italic>p:<italic>GUS</italic> expression and that tissues expressing <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> seemed limited compared with those expressing <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, f, h, n, and p). Thus, overexpression of <italic>MCA1</italic> under the control of the 35S promoter may have a greater impact on plant growth than that of <italic>MCA2</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> Uptake Is Defective in the Roots of Mature <italic>mca2</italic>-Null Plants</title><p>Since MCA2 has Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity when expressed in yeast cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), we measured Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake in the intact roots of 5-week-old plants of various mutant lines using <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref> shows that Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity, which is sensitive to GdCl<sub>3</sub> (a blocker for ion channels, including mechanosensitive channels) and resistant to verapamil (a voltage-gated Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> channel blocker), was 46% and 50% lower in the <italic>mca2</italic>-null and <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant roots than wild-type ones, respectively. As already reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>), there was no significant difference in Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity between the <italic>mca1</italic>-null and wild-type roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). Therefore, it is possible that the low Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity in the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null roots is ascribable to the disruption of the <italic>MCA2</italic> gene only. In other words, MCA2, but not MCA1, functions as a major Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake protein in the roots under the experimental conditions we used.</p><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity of the roots of wild-type, <italic>mca1</italic>-null, <italic>mca2</italic>-null, and <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants. Transgenic and wild-type plants were grown for 21 d on MS medium and for an additional 14 d in aerated hydroponics. Shoots were removed and roots were weighed and incubated for 20 min in an assay solution (2 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 3 MBq/L <sup>45</sup>CaCl<sub>2</sub> [30 MBq/mmol]) in the absence and presence of 1 m<sc>m</sc> GdCl<sub>3</sub>, a blocker of mechanosensitive ion channels, or 20 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> verapamil, a blocker of voltage-gated Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> channels. The roots were washed five times with a washing solution composed of 2 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 m<sc>m</sc> LaCl<sub>3</sub>, and the radioactivity retained in the roots was counted in a liquid scintillation counter. Data are the mean &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> for five independent experiments. &ast;, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 versus the wild type.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp147371F05_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Sensing the Hardness of Agar Is Normal in the Primary Root of <italic>mca2</italic>-Null Seedlings</title><p>Since the primary root of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null seedlings is unable to sense and/or respond to the hardness of agar medium as revealed by the two-phase agar method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>), we applied this method to the <italic>mca2</italic>-null seedlings. According to this method, seeds were sowed on the surface of the upper, softer (0.8%) agar medium made on the lower, harder (1.6%) agar medium and allowed to develop into seedlings for 9 d. As reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>), wild-type primary roots reached the interface of the two agar media in 5 to 7 d and then were capable of entering the lower, harder medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). Essentially the same result was obtained with the <italic>mca2</italic>-null primary roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). Therefore, MCA2 might not be responsible for sensing and/or responding to the hardness of agar in the primary root under our experimental conditions.</p><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Primary roots of <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants, but not of <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants, fail to enter the lower, harder agar (1.6%) medium from the upper, softer agar (0.8%) medium. Seeds of transgenic and wild-type lines were sowed on the surface of the upper medium, incubated for 9 d, and photographed to examine the ability of the primary roots to enter the lower medium. The percentage of primary roots that had not entered the lower medium was calculated. Number of seedlings examined: wild type, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 104; <italic>mca1</italic>-null, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 91; <italic>mca2</italic>-null, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 52; <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 52. Data are the mean &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc>. &ast;, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; &ast;&ast;, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp147371F06_LW" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>In contrast, the primary root of a significant population of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null seedlings was unable to enter the lower, harder medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). This result is phenotypically the same as that for the <italic>mca1</italic>-null seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>). Therefore, the phenotype of the double mutant might be ascribed to the disruption of the <italic>MCA1</italic> gene only. The phenotypic difference between the <italic>mca1</italic>-null and <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutants may be related to a difference in spatial expression of the two genes in the tip of the primary root, as described above (see Discussion).</p></sec><sec><title>Development of the Primary Root Is Normal in <italic>mca2</italic>-Null Seedlings But Not in <italic>mca1</italic>-Null <italic>mca2</italic>-Null Seedlings</title><p>Although the two-phase agar method revealed no detectable difference in the phenotype of the primary root between <italic>mca2</italic>-null and wild-type seedlings, the primary root&apos;s development might still be affected. To examine this possibility, we measured the length of the primary root of the wild type and the null mutants grown at different concentrations of agar and CaCl<sub>2</sub>. Seeds were sown on MS medium containing 0.8% or 1.6% agar and 0.1, 0.5, 3.0, or 13.0 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub> and incubated for 9 d. Note that ordinary MS medium contains 0.8% agar and 3.0 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub>. The primary roots were then taken out and laid softly on MS medium containing 1.6% agar to become straight for the measurement of length. This experiment was performed three times independently, and similar results were obtained. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref> shows a representative result. As a whole, the primary roots of every line were slightly shorter in 1.6% agar medium than in 0.8% agar medium irrespective of CaCl<sub>2</sub> concentration. In 0.8% agar medium, the primary root length of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null and <italic>mca2</italic>-null single mutants was essentially the same as that of the wild type regardless of the CaCl<sub>2</sub> concentrations tested. However, the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic> null double mutant had a shorter primary root than the single mutants as well as the wild type. This phenotype was not effectively suppressed by a high concentration of CaCl<sub>2</sub> (13 m<sc>m</sc>). Since 13 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub> seemed to shorten slightly the primary root of the wild type grown in 0.8% agar medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>), CaCl<sub>2</sub> at this concentration might have both positive and negative effects on the short root length phenotype of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic> null double mutant. In 1.6% agar medium, similar results were observed for every line with some exceptions. For example, at 3.0 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub>, there was no significant difference in the length of the primary root between the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant and the wild type, although a small difference (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 15) was observed between the <italic>mca1</italic>-null single mutant and the wild type. The latter observation was inconsistent with that reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>). This inconsistency could be due to a measurement error because there was no significant difference between the <italic>mca1</italic>-null mutant and the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 15). Taken together, it is suggested that only the primary root of the double mutant has an obvious slow growth phenotype in most of the growth conditions we employed and that this phenotype is not rescued by a high concentration of CaCl<sub>2</sub>.</p><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Effect of the concentration of agar and CaCl<sub>2</sub> on primary root growth. Seeds of transgenic and wild-type lines were sowed on MS medium containing 0.8% or 1.6% agar and 0.1, 0.5, 3.0, or 13.0 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub> and incubated for 9 d. Seedlings were picked up, laid on another MS/1.6% agar medium, and photographed. Primary root length was measured with ImageJ software. The length is presented as the mean for 15 seedlings of each line with the <sc>sd</sc>. A result representative of three independent experiments is shown. a, Wild-type seedling; b, <italic>mca1</italic>-null seedling; c, <italic>mca2</italic>-null seedling; d, <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2-</italic>null seedling. The black bar represents null lines whose primary root lengths are significantly shorter (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) than those of the wild-type line under each incubation condition.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp147371F07_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>External Excess Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> Retards the Growth of the <italic>mca1</italic>-Null <italic>mca2</italic>-Null Mutant</title><p>Since Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> and Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> compete for the same sites of absorption on the plant plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Yermiyahu et al., 1994</xref>), it is possible that an increase in the Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> concentration in medium negatively affects the growth of plants lacking either <italic>MCA1</italic> or <italic>MCA2</italic> or both. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref> shows the effect of adding Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> to the medium on the growth of those lines. The <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant exhibited a severer growth defect when grown for 24 d on MS medium with 30 m<sc>m</sc> MgSO<sub>4</sub> added, compared with that of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null and <italic>mca2</italic>-null single mutants and the wild type. This phenotype was partially alleviated by adding 10 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub> to the medium containing 30 m<sc>m</sc> MgSO<sub>4</sub>. The <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant also exhibited a severe growth defect when grown on MS medium with 20 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>. This result suggests that the phenotype is due to excess Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup>. Complementation of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant with the extrinsic wild-type <italic>MCA1</italic> or <italic>MCA2</italic> gene confirmed that MCA1 and MCA2 are indeed responsible for this phenotype. The Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup>-induced growth defect of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null and <italic>mca2</italic>-null single mutants was comparable to that of the wild type, indicating that MCA1 and MCA2 redundantly function under the high Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> growth conditions we employed.</p><fig id="fig8"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Severe growth defect of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant grown on medium containing high Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup>. Plants were grown for 24 d on MS medium under 16-h-light/8-h-dark conditions at 22&deg;C and photographed. Note that the color tone of each sample varies delicately from photograph to photograph; thus, a difference in the color tones presented here is not a significant factor for the interpretation of the results. Also note that the retardation of growth in the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> is not obvious in the first row of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref> showing the transgenic lines grown on MS medium with no additive because upper views are shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp147371F08_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>To test the possibility that the Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup>-induced growth defect observed in <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant is due to an inhibitory effect of Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> on Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> accumulation in plants, we measured the levels of Ca and Mg in the root and shoot of the wild type and <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants grown for 24 to 26 d on MS medium with or without 30 m<sc>m</sc> MgSO<sub>4</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>). In control MS medium to which MgSO<sub>4</sub> was not supplemented, the Ca and Mg contents of the double mutant did not differ significantly from those of the wild type in both roots and shoots (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 3). When 30 m<sc>m</sc> MgSO<sub>4</sub> was included in MS medium, the Ca content was decreased by approximately 50% in roots and 60% in shoots, whereas the Mg content was increased approximately 5-fold in roots and 7-fold in shoots. Notably, however, the degrees of the increase and decrease in both Ca and Mg contents were not significantly different between the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null and wild-type plants (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 3). When 10 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub> was added to the MS/Mg medium, the Ca content was recovered nearly to the control level in roots and increased more than the control level in shoots, whereas the Mg content hardly changed. Again, the Ca content was not different between the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null and wild-type plants (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> &equals; 3). These results indicate that while Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> added to MS medium indeed lowers Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> accumulation in plants, this effect influences equally both wild-type and <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants. Therefore, the Ca content seems not to explain the Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup>-induced growth defect observed in <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant.</p><fig id="fig9"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Ca and Mg accumulation in <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null and wild-type plants. Plants were grown for 24 to 26 d under the conditions described in the legend to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref>, and roots and shoots were subjected to inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometer analysis to determine the content of Ca (A) and Mg (B). a, Wild-type plants; b, <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants. Data are the mean &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> of three independent experiments. Note that there was no significant difference (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05) in the Ca and Mg contents between <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2-</italic>null and wild-type plants, except for two cases (&ast;<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.0207; &ast;&ast;<italic>P</italic> &equals; 0.0026).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp147371F09_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><sec><title>MCA2 Mediates Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> Uptake in Yeast</title><p>In this study, we have shown that the Arabidopsis <italic>MCA2</italic> cDNA complements both the lethality and low Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity of the yeast <italic>mid1</italic> mutant defective in a putative Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>-permeable mechanosensitive channel component (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). In addition, <italic>MCA2</italic> also complements the <italic>cch1</italic> single mutant and the <italic>mid1 cch1</italic> double mutant. Since this complementing activity of <italic>MCA2</italic> is the same as that of <italic>MCA1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>), we conclude that MCA2 has the same function as MCA1 in yeast cells regarding Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake.</p><p>The yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> has only one high-affinity Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx system, which is composed of Mid1 and Cch1 and becomes functional when cells are grown in low Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> media, such as SD.Ca100 medium that contains 100 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub> as the sole Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> source (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Muller et al., 2001</xref>). Since we have used the SD.Ca100 medium to measure the complementing activity of <italic>MCA2</italic> in the <italic>mid1</italic>, <italic>cch1</italic>, and <italic>mid1 cch1</italic> mutants, it is likely that MCA2 alone can constitute a Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx system, independently of yeast Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx systems. This interpretation is applicable to the function of MCA1 in yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>). In this context, it is interesting to investigate whether the two proteins can form a homomultimeric complex. Our recent study using SDS-PAGE under nonreducing conditions has shown that both proteins expressed in yeast cells form a homodimer and homotetramer (M. Nakano, K. Iida, H. Nyunoya, and H. Iida, unpublished data). We have also obtained data showing that MCA2 is localized in the yeast plasma membrane (M. Nakano, K. Iida, H. Nyunoya, and H. Iida, unpublished data), and this result is consistent with the observation that MCA2-GFP is localized in the plasma membrane of Arabidopsis root cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>). Since MCA1 is reported to be a plasma membrane protein in yeast and Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>), it is concluded that both MCA1 and MCA2 mediate Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx in the plasma membrane.</p></sec><sec><title>Relevance of the Spatial Pattern of <italic>MCA1</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic> Expression to Calcium Nutrition</title><p>Our GUS staining experiments have suggested that in the primary root, both MCA1 and MCA2 are expressed in the stele and endodermis, but not in surrounding tissues, such as the cortex and epidermis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Considering this spatial expression pattern and a role for Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx in the plasma membrane, it is possible that both proteins are involved in symplastic Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> transport and/or the generation of a Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> signal in endodermal and vascular cells.</p><p>In terms of calcium nutrition, do MCA1 and MCA2 have a role? The delivery of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> from the soil solution to the xylem is thought to be dependent on both apoplastic and symplastic pathways, although the relative magnitude of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> transport through the two pathways is unknown, and it is suggested that the Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx system in the plasma membrane of endodermal cells plays a major role in symplastic Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">White, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">White and Broadley, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cholewa and Peterson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hayter and Peterson, 2004</xref>). The cortex and epidermis contribute to apoplastic Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> transport. Thus, it seems likely that the current notion for Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> transport to the xylem meets the spatial expression and potential function of MCA1 and MCA2. However, our experiments on the determination of the Ca content are not consistent with this possibility. Namely, the Ca content was shown to be essentially the same between the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null and wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>), although the double mutant showed a slow growth phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>) and had a relatively short primary root (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). In addition, although Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity of the <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant is significantly lower than that of the wild type, this mutant does not show any defect regarding growth under our experimental conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figs. 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">8</xref>). Therefore, a possible role of MCA1 and MCA2 in calcium nutrition, if any, remains to be investigated with further studies.</p><p>Why do <italic>mca2</italic>-null roots have low Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity relative to wild-type roots, while <italic>mca1</italic>-null roots have a wild-type level of the activity? It is possible that deletion of the <italic>MCA2</italic> gene results in the up-regulation of the <italic>MCA1</italic> transcript. Our real-time PCR data, however, do not support this possibility because the amount of the <italic>MCA1</italic> transcript in the <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant was the same as that in the wild type (Supplemental). The second possibility is a difference in the spatial expression of MCA1 and MCA2 in the root. Our data with GUS staining, however, appears not to sustain this possibility too. Both <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> were found to be expressed throughout the root, except that while <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was expressed in most regions of the root tip, <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>). It is reported that the root tip is not the only site of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">White, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cholewa and Peterson, 2004</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cholewa and Peterson (2004)</xref> found that the tip (apical 8 mm) of the onion adventitious root (maximum 160 mm long) did not translocate Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> to the transpiration stream and explained that this would be due to a lack of mature xylem in the tip. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Huang et al. (1993)</xref> reported that the tip (apical 5&ndash;15 mm) of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) roots (80&ndash;93 mm long) contributed to only about 30% of total Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> translocation to the shoot. The third possibility is a functional difference between MCA1 and MCA2 in cells of the root. Although the two proteins were suggested to have roughly similar levels of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake activity when expressed in yeast cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>), MCA2 might have a greater activity of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake than MCA1 in cells of the root. Further studies are needed to test this possibility.</p><p>The delay of leafing and bolting seen in the <italic>mca1</italic>-null and <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>) may be related to the expression of MCA1 at the center of rosettes in a region corresponding to the shoot apical meristem (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, d). In this region, <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> was suggested to be expressed more intensively than <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, l). Since this region contains actively dividing cells to produce rosette leaves and the inflorescence, deletion of MCA1 could affect the timing of leafing and bolting severer than that of MCA2.</p></sec><sec><title>Relevance of the Spatial Pattern of <italic>MCA1</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic> Expression to Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> Signaling</title><p>Differential expression of <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> in the root apical meristem and adjacent elongation zone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>, c and k) appears to explain a phenotypic difference in the ability to enter the harder agar form the softer agar between the <italic>mca1</italic>-null and <italic>mca2</italic>-null roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). Although the root cap, where <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> are not expressed, is reported to be a site for sensing touch stimuli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Darwin, 1880</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Massa and Gilroy, 2003</xref>), the root elongation zone, where <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic>, but not <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic>, is expressed, could be a site for mechanosensing and/or mechanotransduction. It is shown that touch stimulation induces an increase in [Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> not only in the root cap but also in the root elongation zone in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Legu&eacute; et al., 1997</xref>). In addition, it is shown that the maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) primary root whose cap has been surgically removed still has an ability to curve away from a small piece of agar applied unilaterally to the decapped tip (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Ishikawa and Evans, 1992</xref>). This negative curvature response is somewhat reinforced when Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> is included in the agar. In addition, the same authors have shown that unilateral application of agar containing Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> to the distal elongation zone or elongation zone induces positive curvature, and this response is not observed when plain agar is applied. Thus, it is of interest to investigate whether MCA1 takes part in touch sensing and signal transduction in the root apical meristem and/or the adjacent elongation zone.</p><p>In terms of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> signaling, the endodermis and pericycle of the root, where <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> are expressed, are thought to be important regions. It is suggested that endodermal and pericyclar cells may have a Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> signaling system in response to drought and salt stress because these cells respond with an initial peak and a lower secondary rise in the cytosolic Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> concentration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kiegle et al., 2000</xref>). We are now studying the role of MCA1 and MCA2 in the salt stress response.</p><p>Recent molecular and electrophysiological studies have shown that Arabidopsis MSL9 and MSL10, homologs of the bacterial mechanosensitive channel MscS, are required for a mechanosensitive channel activity in the plasma membrane of root cells and permeable to Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>, though more permeable to Cl<sup>&minus;</sup> than Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Haswell et al., 2008</xref>). It is noteworthy that their expression patterns, especially those of <italic>MSL10</italic>, are similar to those of <italic>MCA1</italic>, as revealed by GUS-staining analysis. For example, both <italic>MCA1</italic> and <italic>MSL10</italic> are expressed in the root tip and throughout the vasculature of the root and leaf. <italic>msl9</italic>, <italic>msl10</italic>, and <italic>msl9 msl10</italic> mutants and even the <italic>msl4 msl5 msl6 msl9 msl10</italic> quintuple mutant showed no detectable phenotype upon osmotic, salt, mechanical, dehydration, or rehydration stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Haswell et al., 2008</xref>), suggestive of the presence of a complementary mechanism. It is worth examining the possible genetic interaction between <italic>MSL</italic> and <italic>MCA</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Increased Sensitivity of <italic>mca1</italic>-Null <italic>mca2</italic>-Null Double Mutant to Excess Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> Is Alleviated by Adding Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup></title><p>The <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutation causes a severe growth defect on media supplemented with 30 m<sc>m</sc> MgSO<sub>4</sub> or 20 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). Interestingly, this phenotype is opposite to that of the Arabidopsis <italic>cax1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bradshaw, 2005</xref>). CAX1 is a high-capacity calcium-proton antiporter located on the tonoplast membrane. The <italic>cax1</italic>-null mutant shows tolerance to low Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>:Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup>ratios, at which the growth of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant is slowed. The phenotype of the <italic>cax1</italic> mutant is explained as follows: An absence of sequestration of cytosolic Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> to the vacuole by CAX1 reduces Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> toxicity. In this context, it is possible that the phenotype of the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant is due to the deficiency of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx to the cytoplasm, resulting in low Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>:Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> ratios there, thus causing Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> toxicity.</p><p>The balance of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> and Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> in soil is an important factor for plant growth. Plants cannot grow normally in soil with low Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>:Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> ratios, which is thought to be a main reason for the growth defect in serpentine soils derived from the weathering of ultramafic rocks and characterized by the presence of excessive Mg, high levels of heavy metals, and low levels of important plant nutrients, including Ca. Studies of serpentine-tolerant and serpentine-intolerant plant species suggested that the adaptation to serpentine soils is mediated by unknown genetic elements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Brady et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Asemaneh et al., 2007</xref>). To explore elements involved in tolerance to soil with low Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>:Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup> ratios, a genetic approach using Arabidopsis has been performed and has isolated the <italic>cax1</italic> mutant described above (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bradshaw, 2005</xref>). The molecular identity of other elements is basically unknown. However, proteins involved in Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake, including MCA1 and MCA2, could be appropriate candidates for the elements.</p><p>Our study demonstrated that the addition of 30 m<sc>m</sc> MgSO<sub>4</sub> to MS medium decreased the Ca content by approximately half in roots and more than half in shoots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>), suggesting that this decrease is associated with the slow growth of both <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null and wild-type plants. This suggestion is supported by the observation that supplementation of CaCl<sub>2</sub> to the Mg-rich medium remedied partially the Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup>-induced severe growth defect of the double mutant. However, no significant difference in the Ca content was detected between the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null and wild-type plants, suggesting that the Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup>-induced severe growth defect observed in the double mutant is not simply explained by the Ca content of plants. Since the majority of the total Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> is bound to the cell wall and anionic macromolecules in the cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Hirschi, 2004</xref>), free Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> rather than bound Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> would be related to the Mg<sup>2&plus;</sup>-induced severe growth defect. We speculate that the intracellular free Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> supplied through MCA1 and MCA2 from the bound Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> and/or free Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> included in medium could play an important role in plant growth and development.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Subcloning of <italic>MCA2</italic> cDNA in a Yeast Expression Vector</title><p><italic>MCA2</italic> cDNA (locus name, At2g17780) with a <italic>Bam</italic>HI site at each of the 5&prime;- and 3&prime;-ends was synthesized by PCR using the plasmid pBluescript SK&minus; MCA2 as a template and the primers B-5&prime;Bam (409F), 5&prime;-GG<underline>GG</underline><underline>ATCC</underline><bold>ATG</bold>GCTAATTCATGGGATCAGTTAG-3&prime;, and B3-3&prime;SB (1659R), 5&prime;-GGGTCGAC<underline>GGATCC</underline>T<bold>TCA</bold>TTCTTCCATAAACTGAGGTGTTGGTG-3&prime;, where the <italic>Bam</italic>HI site is underlined and the initiation and termination codons are boldfaced. The resulting product was cut with <italic>Bam</italic>HI and inserted into the <italic>Bam</italic>HI site of a YEplac181-based, multicopy expression vector, YEpTDHXho (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Gietz and Sugino, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hashimoto et al., 2004</xref>), in which a cDNA of interest is transcribed under the control of the <italic>TDH3</italic> promoter. The resulting plasmid was designated YEpTDHXho-MCA2.</p></sec><sec><title>Yeast Strains and Medium Used in This Study</title><p>The parental strain used was H207 (<italic>MAT</italic><bold>a</bold> <italic>his3</italic>- &Delta;<italic>1</italic> <italic>leu2-3,112 trp1-289 ura3-52 sst1-2</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Iida et al., 1994</xref>). The following mutant strains were derivatives of H207:H311 (<italic>MAT</italic><bold>a</bold> <italic>mid1</italic>- &Delta;<italic>5</italic>::<italic>HIS3</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Tada et al., 2003</xref>), H317 (<italic>MAT</italic><bold>a</bold> <italic>cch1</italic>&Delta; ::<italic>HIS3</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Iida et al., 2007</xref>), and H319 (<italic>MAT</italic><bold>a</bold> <italic>mid1</italic>- &Delta;<italic>5</italic>::<italic>HIS3</italic> <italic>cch1</italic>&Delta; ::<italic>HIS3</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>). The low Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> medium SD.Ca100 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Iida et al., 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">1994</xref>), which contains 100 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub> as the Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> source, was used in most of this study. The yeast strains were transformed with YEpTDHXho-MCA1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>) and YEpTDHXho-MCA2 by a method described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Mount et al., 1996</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Yeast Cell Viability Assay</title><p>Yeast cells were grown to the exponentially growing phase (2 &times; 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL) in SD.Ca100 medium at 30&deg;C and incubated with 6 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> <italic>&alpha;</italic> -factor for 8 h, after which viability was determined by the methylene blue method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Iida et al., 1990</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> Accumulation in Yeast</title><p>The method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Iida et al. (1990)</xref> was followed. Yeast cells were grown to 2 &times; 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL in SD.Ca100 medium at 30&deg;C and incubated for 2 h with 185 kBq/mL <sup>45</sup>CaCl<sub>2</sub> (1.8 kBq/nmol). Samples (100 <italic>&mu;</italic> L) were filtered with Millipore filters presoaked with 5 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub> and washed five times with the same solution. The radioactivity retained on each filter was counted as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Iida et al., 1990</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Plant Growth Conditions</title><p>The Columbia-0 (Col-0) ecotype of Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) and its isogenic, transgenic lines were used. Seeds were sterilized with 70% ethanol and 1% Antiformin and sown on MS medium composed of MS salts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Murashige and Skoog, 1962</xref>), 1 &times; Gamborg&apos;s vitamin solution (Sigma-Aldrich), 2.56 m<sc>m</sc> MES-KOH (pH 5.7), 1% Suc, and 0.8% agar. Additional CaCl<sub>2</sub>, MgSO<sub>4</sub>, and MgCl<sub>2</sub> were added to the MS medium after autoclaving. In some experiments, plants were transferred to soil (Dio Chemicals) after bolting. Plants were grown under 16-h-light/8-h-dark conditions at 40 to 60 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> m<sup>&minus;2</sup> s<sup>&minus;1</sup> and 22&deg;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Establishment of the <italic>mca2</italic>-Null Mutant and the <italic>mca1</italic>-Null <italic>mca2</italic>-Null Double Mutant</title><p>Arabidopsis seeds with a T-DNA inserted in the <italic>MCA2</italic> gene (SALK_129208) were obtained from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center (Columbus, OH). Confirmation of the insertion was conducted by genomic PCR using a set of the T-DNA left border primer LBa1 (forward, 5&prime;-TGGTTCACGTAGTGGGCCATCG-3&prime;) and the <italic>MCA2</italic>-specific primer Ap1237 (reverse, 5&prime;-GAGGTGTTGGTGGACTCATTTCCTTATTAC-3&prime;) that binds to the ninth exon of the <italic>MCA2</italic> gene. Then, the homozygous and heterozygous <italic>mca2</italic> T-DNA insertion mutations were confirmed by genomic PCR using the <italic>MCA2</italic>-specific primer Ap1s (forward, 5&prime;-ATGGCTAATTCATGGGATCAGTTAG-3&prime;) that binds to the third exon of the <italic>MCA2</italic> gene and Ap1237 (reverse; see above). The <italic>mca1</italic>-null line produced by the insertion was described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>). To construct the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null double mutant, the <italic>mca1</italic>-null mutant was crossed with the <italic>mca2</italic>-null mutant, and the F1 generation was self-crossed to produce the F2 generation. The resulting plants were confirmed to be homozygous for the <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null alleles by isolation of total RNA followed by RT-PCR. Total RNA was isolated from whole plants grown for 10 d on MS medium using the RNeasy plant mini kit (Qiagen). The primers for RT-PCR were as follows: for <italic>MCA1</italic> mRNA, 5&prime;-TGCTCCCTCTTTTAGTCAATTCTCG-3&prime;(forward primer) and 5&prime;-CCTGTTGGATGCTGCAGTGGCAATC-3&prime;(reverse primer); for <italic>MCA2</italic> mRNA, 5&prime;-ATGGCTAATTCATGGGATCAGTTAG-3&prime;(Ap1s) and 5&prime;-GAGGTGTTGGTGGACTCATTTCCTTATTAC-3&prime;(Ap1237); and for control <italic>&beta;</italic> -tubulin mRNA, 5&prime;-ATCCCACCGGACGTTACAAC-3&prime;and 5&prime;-TTCGTTGTCGAGGACCATGC-3&prime;.</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of Total RNA from Various Tissues for RT-PCR</title><p>Total RNA was isolated from various tissues of plants grown for 5 to 6 weeks using the RNeasy plant mini kit (Qiagen) or by the method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Miyama and Tada (2008)</xref>. Aliquots (1 <italic>&mu;</italic> g) of total RNA were subjected to cDNA synthesis using a reverse primer (5&prime;-GAGGTGTTGGTGGACTCATTTCCTTATTAC-3&prime;for <italic>MCA2</italic> [Ap1237] and 5&prime;-TTCGTTGTCGAGGACCATGC-3&prime;for <italic>&beta;</italic> -tubulin as a control) and a TaKaRa RNA PCR kit (AMV), version 3.0 (Takara Bio), according to the manufacturer&apos;s protocol. Then, using a specific primer set (5&prime;-ATGGCTAATTCATGGGATCAGTTAG-3&prime;[Ap1s] and 5&prime;-GAGGTGTTGGTGGACTCATTTCCTTATTAC-3&prime;for <italic>MCA2</italic> [Ap1237]; 5&prime;-ATCCCACCGGACGTTACAAC-3&prime;and 5&prime;-TTCGTTGTCGAGGACCATGC-3&prime;for <italic>&beta;</italic> -tubulin) and the synthesized cDNA as a template, PCR amplifications were performed using a TaKaRa RNA PCR kit (AMV), version 3.0, as follows: 35 cycles of 94&deg;C for 1 min, 55&deg;C for 1 min, and 72&deg;C for 2 min.</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative Real-Time PCR</title><p>Total RNA was purified from 5 to 10 plants grown for 13 d on MS medium using an RNeasy plant mini kit, treated with DNase I (Takara Bio), and used for cDNA synthesis with Superscript III reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen), random primer (Takara Bio), and oligo(dT)<sup>12-18</sup> (Invitrogen). Quantitative real-time PCR was performed with the 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR system (Applied Biosystems). The PCR mixture consisted of a first-strand cDNA template, the SYBR GREEN PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems), and the following primers: for <italic>MCA1</italic>, 5&prime;-AAGATTGCCACTGCAGCATCC-3&prime;(forward primer) and 5&prime;-ACGCCATTAGCTCATTACATGCTTC-3&prime;(reverse primer); for <italic>MCA2</italic>, 5&prime;-AAGATCATTGCAACACCGTGGA-3&prime;and 5&prime;-GTGTCTTCAAGCAAAGACAAGGTTC-3&prime;; for EF1 <italic>&alpha;</italic>, 5&prime;-TGAGCACGCTCTTCTTGCTTTCA-3&prime;and 5&prime;-GGTGGTGGCATCCATCTTGTTACA-3&prime;; and for <italic>&beta;</italic> -tubulin as a control, 5&prime;-ACCACTCCTAGCTTTGGTGATCTG-3&prime;and 5&prime;-AGGTTCACTGCGAGCTTCCTCA-3&prime;. In all cases, the expression of each transcript was corrected with that of <italic>&beta;</italic> -tubulin measured in the same sample in parallel on the same plate.</p></sec><sec><title>GUS Assay of <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> Transgenic Plants</title><p>The DNA fragment of the <italic>MCA1</italic> promoter region was prepared with PCR by synthesizing the 5&prime;-noncoding region spanning &minus;3.0 to 0 kb from the 5&prime;-end of the first exon using Arabidopsis (Col-0) genomic DNA as a template and the following primers: forward primer (RF4B14-81934), 5&prime;-AACGTACTGGATTATTAATTGAGTG-3&prime;; reverse primer (BmFF4B14-78800), 5&prime;-CGGGATCCGGAGCTCAAGAGCCCCC-3&prime;, where the underline indicates the <italic>Bam</italic>HI site. The <italic>MCA1</italic> promoter region synthesized, which contains the intrinsic <italic>Hin</italic>dIII site near the forward primer, was inserted between the <italic>Hin</italic>dIII and <italic>Bam</italic>HI sites of the <italic>GUS</italic> expression vector pBI121 (CLONTECH).</p><p>The DNA fragment of the <italic>MCA2</italic> promoter region was prepared with PCR by synthesizing the 5&prime;-noncoding region spanning &minus;1.5 to 0 kb from the initiation codon of the <italic>MCA2</italic> gene using Arabidopsis (Col-0) genomic DNA as a template and the following primers: forward primer (pA2&Prime;pro1), 5&prime;-GG<underline>AAGCTT</underline>GGAGGGAAGCAGTTTATAATG-3&prime;, where the underline indicates the <italic>Hin</italic>dIII site; reverse primer (pA2&Prime;pro2), 5&prime;-GG<underline>TCTAGA</underline>CTCTTCCTAACCAAAAACAGC-3&prime;, where the underline indicates the <italic>Xba</italic>I site. The <italic>MCA2</italic> promoter region synthesized was inserted between the <italic>Hin</italic>dIII and <italic>Xba</italic>I sites of the promoterless <italic>GUS</italic> expression vector pBI101 (CLONTECH).</p><p>The resulting plasmid containing either the <italic>MCA1</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> or <italic>MCA2</italic>p::<italic>GUS</italic> fusion construct was introduced into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> DH5 <italic>&alpha;</italic> and then transferred from it to <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> <italic>tumefaciens</italic> GV3101 containing pMP90 via triparental mating with a helper <italic>E. coli</italic> strain containing the mobilization plasmid pRK2013 as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Valvekens et al., 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Benfey et al., 1993</xref>). Arabidopsis plants (Col-0) were transformed by the vacuum infiltration method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bechtold et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bechtold and Pelletier, 1998</xref>). T2 and T3 transgenic Arabidopsis plants were grown at 22&deg;C under a 16-h-light/8-h-dark cycle for experiments. Histochemical localization of GUS activity in situ was performed as follows. Samples were fixed for 1 h with 90% acetone in Eppendorf tubes placed on ice and washed four times with 100 m<sc>m</sc> sodium phosphate buffer, pH 7.0. The samples were then incubated for 6 h at 37&deg;C in 1 mL of X-Gluc buffer (0.5 mg/mL 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl glucuronidase [CLONTECH], 100 m<sc>m</sc> sodium phosphate buffer, pH 7.0, 0.5 m<sc>m</sc> potassium ferrocyanide, and 0.5 m<sc>m</sc> potassium ferricyanide) and then cleaned and fixed by rinsing for 1 h each with 50%, 70%, 90%, and 100% (v/v) ethanol successively. The fixed samples were stored in 100% ethanol before being photographed under a stereomicroscope (Leica MZ125) or a differential interference contrast microscope (Olympus BX50).</p></sec><sec><title>Observation of Subcellular Localization of MCA2-GFP in Root Cells</title><p>To generate transgenic plants expressing MCA2-GFP, the coding region of the <italic>MCA2</italic> cDNA was amplified by PCR using primers 5&prime;-T<underline>GGATCC</underline>ATGGCTAATTCATGGGATCAG-3&prime;and 5&prime;-T<underline>GGATCC</underline>TTCTTCCATAAACTGAGGTG-3&prime;, where the <italic>Bam</italic>HI site was underlined. After treatment with <italic>Bam</italic>HI, the product was inserted into the <italic>Bam</italic>HI site of the pBE2113 vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Mitsuhara et al., 1996</xref>) so that the <italic>MCA2</italic> sequence would be fused in frame to the 5&prime;-end of the <italic>GFP</italic> gene and the resulting <italic>MCA2-GFP</italic> fusion gene would be driven by the CaMV 35S promoter. The transformation plasmid was introduced into <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> to transform wild-type Arabidopsis (Col-0) plants. T3 seeds were used for GFP fluorescence imaging.</p><p>GFP fluorescence images were observed using a confocal fluorescence microscope equipped with a Nikon TE 300 in conjunction with Micro Radiance (Bio-Rad). Nikon Plan Apo 60 &times; /1.40 oil was used as an objective lens. Images were processed using Adobe Photoshop Element 6.0 (Adobe Systems). The Arabidopsis GFP T-DNA tag lines Q4, Q5, and Q8 donated by D. Ehrhardt, S. Cutler, and C. Somerville (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Cutler et al., 2000</xref>) were obtained from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center.</p></sec><sec><title>Measurement of Primary Root Length</title><p>Seeds were sterilized, chilled for 3 d at 4&deg;C in the dark, and sown on MS medium. Seedlings were grown under 16-h-light/8-h-dark conditions for 9 d at 22&deg;C. To measure the length of the primary root, 15 seedlings were laid and straightened softly on another MS/1.6% agar medium and photographed as digital data. Root length was measured with ImageJ software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>), and the average and <sc>sd</sc> of the samples were determined.</p></sec><sec><title>Complementation of the <italic>mca1</italic>-Null <italic>mca2</italic>-Null Mutation</title><p>For complementation by the <italic>MCA1</italic> gene, the T-DNA clone pGreenII0229-<italic>MCA1</italic>-MS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al., 2007</xref>) was used for plant transformation. For complementation by the <italic>MCA2</italic> gene, the T-DNA clone pGreenII0229-<italic>MCA2</italic> was constructed. A DNA fragment harboring the <italic>MCA2</italic> gene was amplified from Arabidopsis Col-0 genomic DNA by PCR using pfu DNA polymerase (Stratagene). The primers used for the PCR have a <italic>Bam</italic>HI site at their 5&prime;terminus. Their sequences are 5&prime;-CGGGATCCTCAAGTGTTTCTTATGAAGATG-3&prime;and 5&prime;-CGGGATCCATATCTCTTAGTTCTATTAGAC-3&prime;. The amplified fragment was ligated into the <italic>Bam</italic>HI site of the T-DNA vector pGreenII0229. pGreenII0229-<italic>MCA2</italic> and the helper plasmid pSOUP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Hellens et al., 2000</xref>) were coelectroporated into <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> GV3101 containing pMP90 and used to transform Arabidopsis <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null plants by the floral dipping method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Desfeux et al., 2000</xref>). Transgenic plants were selected on MS medium, 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> Basta, and 100 <italic>&mu;</italic> g/mL Carbenicillin. Successful construction of a complementation line was confirmed by genomic PCR using a vector-specific primer for <italic>MCA1</italic> complementation (5&prime;-TGAATTGTAATACGACTCACTATAG-3&prime;), an <italic>MCA1</italic>-specific primer (5&prime;-TCGAACTTCAGCGGTCGCAGGAGCA-3&prime;), a vector-specific primer for <italic>MCA2</italic>;complementation (5&prime;-TGGTTCACGTAGTGGGCCATCGG-3&prime;), and <italic>MCA2</italic>-specific primer (5&prime;-GAGGTGTTGGTGGACTCATTTCCTTATTAC-3&prime;). T3 homozygous lines were used to examine <italic>mca1</italic>-null <italic>mca2</italic>-null phenotypes.</p></sec><sec><title>Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> Uptake in Intact Arabidopsis Roots</title><p>Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> uptake was measured according to the method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al. (2007)</xref>. Briefly, plants were grown for 21 d on standard MS medium containing 0.8% agar and for an additional 14 d in aerated hydroponics according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Demidchik et al. (2002)</xref>. Shoots were removed from the plants, and roots were weighed, incubated for 20 min in an assay solution (2 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 3 MBq/L <sup>45</sup>CaCl<sub>2</sub> [30 MBq/mmol; Perkin-Elmer, catalog no. NEZ013]) in the absence or presence of 1 m<sc>m</sc> GdCl<sub>3</sub> or 20 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> verapamil, and then washed five times with a <sup>45</sup>CaCl<sub>2</sub>-free solution containing 2 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 0.1 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 m<sc>m</sc> LaCl<sub>3</sub> to remove <sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> from the cell wall. Radioactivity retained in the roots was measured with a liquid scintillation counter.</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of Ca and Mg Contents in Roots and Shoots</title><p>Approximately 10 plants grown for 24 to 26 d on MS medium or that containing 30 m<sc>m</sc> MgSO<sub>4</sub> with or without 10 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub> were separated into roots and shoots (approximately 0.1 g wet weight each). The samples were washed in water deionized with Milli-Q Plus (Millipore) and dried for 16 h at 92&deg;C in 25-mL Teflon vessels (Isis). The dried samples were weighed with a Mettler analytical balance (model AE163) and incubated for 3 h at 120&deg;C in 2.3 mL of HNO<sub>3</sub> (Wako Pure Chemical Industries) to be fully dissolved. The dissolved samples were filled up to 100 mL with Milli-Q water, and Ca and Mg contents of aliquots (approximately 10 mL or less) were determined with an inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometer (model SPS 1200A; Seiko Instruments).</p></sec><sec><title>Two-Phase Agar Method</title><p>The method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nakagawa et al. (2007)</xref> was strictly followed.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Statistical significance was determined using an unpaired Student&apos;s <italic>t</italic> test, with a maximum <italic>P</italic> value of &lt; 0.05 required for significance.</p><p>Sequence data from this article can be found in the GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ data libraries under accession numbers AB196960 for <italic>MCA1</italic> and AB196961 for <italic>MCA2</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold> The levels of the <italic>MCA1</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic> transcripts in various <italic>MCA1</italic> and <italic>MCA2</italic> mutants.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dr. Akitoshi Iwamoto for advice on histochemical techniques, Dr. Masayoshi Maeshima for critical reading of the manuscript and valuable comments, Dr. Shuji Ninomiya for advice on the determination of Ca and Mg contents, Drs. Masahiro Sokabe, Hitoshi Tatsumi, and Kazuyuki Kuchitsu for helpful discussions, Dr. Hiroshi Nyunoya for encouragement, and Ms. Yumiko Higashi for secretarial assistance.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asemaneh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghaderian</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Responses to Mg/Ca balance in an Iranian serpentine endemic plant, <italic>Cleome heratensis</italic> (Capparaceae) and a related non-serpentine species, <italic>C. foliolosa</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source> <volume>293</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>59</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bechtold</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title><italic>In planta Agrobacterium</italic> mediated gene transfer by infiltration of adult <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> plants</article-title>. <source>CR Acad Sci III, Sci Vie</source> <volume>316</volume>: <fpage>1194</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1199</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bechtold</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>In planta <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of adult <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> plants by vacuum infiltration</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>266</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benfey</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Linstead</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiefelbein</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Aeschbacher</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Root development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>: four mutants with dramatically altered root morphogenesis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>70</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braam</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>In touch: plant responses to mechanical stimuli</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>165</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>389</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>HD</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Mutations in <italic>CAX1</italic> produce phenotypes characteristic of plants tolerant to serpentine soils</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>167</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>88</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruckeberg</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>HD</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Evolutionary ecology of plant adaptation to serpentine soils</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>266</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cholewa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Evidence for symplastic involvement in the radial movement of calcium in onion roots</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>1793</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1802</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrhardt</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffitts</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Random GFP:cDNA fusions enable visualization of subcellular structures in cells of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> at a high frequency</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>3718</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3723</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darwin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1880</year>) <article-title>The Power of Movement in Plants</article-title>. <publisher-name>John Murray</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demidchik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maathuis</surname><given-names>FJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabala</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Tester</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> root non-selective cation channels mediate calcium uptake and are involved in growth</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>799</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>808</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desfeux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Female reproductive tissues are the primary target of <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation by the Arabidopsis floral-dip method</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>895</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>904</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of stretch-activated ion channels in pollen protoplasts</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>1398</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1406</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fasano</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Massa</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilroy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Ionic signaling in plant responses to gravity and touch</article-title>. <source>J Plant Growth Regul</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>88</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galaviz-Hernandez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stagg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>de Ridder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlessinger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaraja</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title><italic>Plac8</italic> and <italic>Plac9</italic>, novel placental-enriched genes identified through microarray analysis</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>89</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gietz</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>New yeast-<italic>Escherichia coli</italic> shuttle vectors constructed with in vitro mutagenized yeast genes lacking six-base pair restriction sites</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>527</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>534</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Functional analysis of a rice putative voltage-dependent Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> channel, <italic>OsTPC1</italic>, expressed in yeast cells lacking its homologous gene <italic>CCH1</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>496</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>500</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haswell</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyronnet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbier-Brygoo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Frachisse</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Two MscS homologs provide mechanosensitive channel activities in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> root</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>730</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>734</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayter</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Can Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> fluxes to the root xylem be sustained by Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>-ATPase in exodermal and endodermal plasma membrane?</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>4318</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>4325</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hellens</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyland</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullineaux</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>pGreen: a versatile and flexible binary Ti vector for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated plant transformation</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>832</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirschi</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The calcium conundrum. Both versatile nutrient and specific signal</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>2438</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2442</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunes</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochian</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Aluminum effects on calcium (<sup>45</sup>Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> translocation in aluminum-tolerant and aluminum-sensitive wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) cultivars: differential responses of the root apex verus mature root regions</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>93</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Okumura</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Anraku</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title><italic>MID1</italic>, a novel <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> gene encoding a plasma membrane protein, is required for Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx and mating</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>8259</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>8271</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Anraku</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Essential role for induced Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx followed by [Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>]<sub>i</sub> rise in maintaining viability of yeast cells late in the mating pheromone response pathway. A study of [Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup>]<sub>i</sub> in single <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> cells with imaging of fura-2</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>265</volume>: <fpage>13391</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>13399</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning in yeast by in vivo homologous recombination of the putative <italic>&alpha;</italic> 1 subunit of the voltage-gated calcium channel</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source> <volume>576</volume>: <fpage>291</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>296</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Izumi-Nakaseko</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi-Akahane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Essential, completely conserved glycine residue in the domain III S2-S3 linker of voltage-gated calcium channel <italic>&alpha;</italic> 1 subunits in yeast and mammals</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>282</volume>: <fpage>25659</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>25667</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Induction of curvature in maize roots by calcium or by thigmostimulation</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>762</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>768</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RGW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lunt</surname><given-names>OR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>The function of calcium in plants</article-title>. <source>Bot Rev</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>426</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagasawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Naruse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Molecular identification of a eukaryotic, stretch-activated nonselective cation channel</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>882</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>886</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiegle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Haseloff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tester</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Cell-type-specific calcium responses to drought, salt and cold in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> root</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>278</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Legu&eacute;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Blancaflor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wymer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Perbal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fantin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilroy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Cytosolic free Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> in Arabidopsis roots changes in response to touch but not gravity</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>789</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>800</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massa</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilroy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Touch modulates gravity sensing to regulate the growth of primary roots of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>435</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>445</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitsuhara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ugaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirochika</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohshima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Katayose</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Honkura</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Efficient promoter cassettes for enhanced expression of foreign genes in dicotyledonous and monocotyledonous plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>59</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional and physiological study of the response of Burma mangrove (<italic>Bruguiera gymnorhiza</italic>) to salt and osmotic stress</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>129</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mount</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadfield</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Transformation of lithium-treated yeast cells and the selection of auxotrophic and dominant markers</article-title>. <comment><italic>In</italic></comment> <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group>, <comment>ed</comment>, <article-title>Yeast Protocols: Methods in Cell and Molecular Biology</article-title>. <publisher-name>Humana Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Totowa, NJ</publisher-loc>, pp <fpage>139</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>145</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Differential regulation of two Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx systems by pheromone signaling in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>1527</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1538</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murashige</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Skoog</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>A revised medium for rapid growth and bioassays with tobacco tissue cultures</article-title>. <source>Physiol Plant</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>497</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsumi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuichi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishigami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plasma membrane protein crucial for Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> influx and touch sensing in roots</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>3639</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3644</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishigami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A mechanosensitive anion channel in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> mesophyll cells</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>1704</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1708</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelloux</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownlee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Calcium at the crossroads of signaling</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>S401</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>S417</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohmori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Molecular dissection of the hydrophobic segments H3 and H4 of the yeast Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> channel component Mid1</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>278</volume>: <fpage>9647</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>9654</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Telewski</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A unified hypothesis of mechanoperception in plants</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1466</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1476</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valvekens</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Montagu</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lijsebettens</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title><italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic>-mediated transformation of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> root explants by using kanamycin selection</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>5536</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5540</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>V&eacute;ry</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sentenac</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Cation channels in the Arabidopsis plasma membrane</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>175</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The pathway of calcium movement to the xylem</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>891</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>899</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Demidchik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Genes for calcium-permeable channels in the plasma membrane of plant root cells</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1564</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>309</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Broadley</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Calcium in plants</article-title>. <source>Ann Bot (Lond)</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>487</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>511</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yermiyahu</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Nir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Hayyim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kafkafi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Quantitative competition of calcium with sodium or magnesium for sorption sites on plasma membrane vesicles of melon (<italic>Cucumis melo</italic> L.) root cells</article-title>. <source>J Membr Biol</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>63</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
