<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">169045</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.169045</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>SYSTEMS BIOLOGY, MOLECULAR BIOLOGY, AND GENE REGULATION</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Target of Rapamycin Regulates Development and Ribosomal RNA Expression through Kinase Domain in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[OA]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Maozhi</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Shuqing</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Venglat</surname><given-names>Prakash</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Daoquan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>Gopalan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Datla</surname><given-names>Raju</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&ast;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Plant Biotechnology Institute, National Research Council of Canada, Saskatoon, Saskatchewan, Canada S7N 0W9</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&ast;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>raju.datla@nrc-cnrc.gc.ca</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the National Research Council of Canada Genomics and Health Initiative, Genome Canada, and Genome Prairie.</p></fn><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Raju Datla (<email>raju.datla@nrc-cnrc.gc.ca</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[OA]</label><p>Open Access articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.110.169045">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.110.169045</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>3</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>155</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1382</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>11</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2011 American Society of Plant Biologists</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p></p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Target of rapamycin (TOR) is a central regulator of cell growth, cell death, nutrition, starvation, hormone, and stress responses in diverse eukaryotes. However, very little is known about TOR signaling and the associated functional domains in plants. We have taken a genetic approach to dissect TOR functions in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) and report here that the kinase domain is essential for the role of TOR in embryogenesis and <italic>45S rRNA</italic> expression. Twelve new T-DNA insertion mutants, spanning 14.2 kb of TOR-encoding genomic region, have been characterized. Nine of these share expression of defective kinase domain and embryo arrest at 16 to 32 cell stage. However, three T-DNA insertion lines affecting FATC domain displayed normal embryo development, indicating that FATC domain was dispensable in Arabidopsis. Genetic complementation showed that the TOR kinase domain alone in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutant background can rescue early embryo lethality and restore normal development. Overexpression of full-length TOR or kinase domain in Arabidopsis displayed developmental abnormalities in meristem, leaf, root, stem, flowering time, and senescence. We further show that TOR, especially the kinase domain, plays a role in ribosome biogenesis by activating <italic>45S rRNA</italic> production. Of the six putative nuclear localization sequences in the kinase domain, nuclear localization sequence 6 was identified to confer TOR nuclear targeting in transient expression assays. Chromatin immunoprecipitation studies revealed that the HEAT repeat domain binds to <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter and the 5&#x2032; external transcribed spacer elements motif. Together, these results show that TOR controls the embryogenesis, postembryonic development, and <italic>45S rRNA</italic> production through its kinase domain in Arabidopsis.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p><italic>Target of rapamycin</italic> (<italic>TOR</italic>) encodes a large (280 kD) Ser/Thr protein kinase and plays a central role in regulation of cell growth and metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cafferkey et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kunz et al., 1993</xref>). This protein is structurally and functionally conserved in eukaryotic species ranging from yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) to human (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">De Virgilio and Loewith, 2006a</xref>). In yeast, TOR is encoded by two genes (<italic>TOR1</italic> and <italic>TOR2</italic>) that have 80% overall amino acid similarity and are also partially redundant in function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cafferkey et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kunz et al., 1993</xref>). Yeast TOR proteins interact with several other regulatory proteins to form two distinct complexes, TOR complex1 (TORC1) and TORC2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Kim et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Loewith et al., 2002</xref>). TORC1 consists of TOR1, LST8, KOG1, and Tco89, and regulates cell growth and metabolism in response to nutrients and energy requirements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Loewith et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Reinke et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Inoki et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Martin and Hall, 2005</xref>). Rapamycin, produced by <italic>Streptomyces hygroscopicus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Heitman et al., 1991</xref>), is an inhibitor of TORC1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Stan et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Zheng et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Kim et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Loewith et al., 2002</xref>). The yeast TORC2 complex consists of TOR2, LST8, AVO1-3, Bit6, Slm1p, and Slm2p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Loewith et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Fadri et al., 2005</xref>), and has been implicated in the regulation of cytoskeleton structure and activity, as well as spatial features of cell growth such as cell polarity. TORC2, however, is not inhibited by rapamycin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Loewith et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">De Virgilio and Loewith, 2006b</xref>).</p><p>In animals, including humans, there is only a single copy of <italic>TOR</italic>. However, as in yeast, the TOR protein occurs in two protein complexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Kim et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Martin and Hall, 2005</xref>). The core structure of TOR complexes consists of a catalytic subunit (TOR) and a regulatory subunit (LST8). This core dimer recruits Raptor (yeast KOG1) and PRAS40 to form TORC1, or Rictor (yeast AVO3) and SIN1 to form TORC2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Kim et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Wullschleger et al., 2006</xref>). As in yeast, the TORC1 complex in animals modulates a variety of cellular responses, such as translation initiation, ribosome biogenesis, and cell growth, and it is rapamycin sensitive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bjornsti and Houghton, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Wullschleger et al., 2006</xref>). S6K1 (p70 ribosomal protein S6 kinase1) and 4E-BP (translation initiation factor 4E binding protein) are substrates of TORC1 and phosphorylation of these proteins stimulates translation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Proud, 2004</xref>). TORC2 is rapamycin insensitive and is involved in the regulation of cytoskeleton structure, cell cycle, apoptosis, and transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Guertin et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Jones et al., 2009</xref>). AKT and SGK1 have been shown to be substrates for TORC2 in animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Guertin et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Jones et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>TOR proteins in diverse eukaryotes consist of highly conserved domains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). The N-terminal 1,200 residues consist of 20 HEAT repeats. These HEAT repeats have been implicated in protein-protein interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Andrade and Bork, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kunz et al., 2000</xref>). The focal adhesion target (FAT) domain, located at the C-terminal end of HEAT repeats has been also implicated in protein-protein interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bosotti et al., 2000</xref>). The FRB (FKBP12/rapamycin binding) domain is the binding site for FKBP12 (FK506 binding protein12) protein, which in turn is the target for rapamycin-mediated inhibition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Schmelzle and Hall, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Kim et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Loewith et al., 2002</xref>). The kinase domain contains a conserved lipid Ser/Thr kinase motif. A putative scaffolding domain, FATC, is located at the carboxy terminus of TOR protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Takahashi et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dames, 2010</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><italic>TOR</italic> kinase domain is essential for embryo development in Arabidopsis. A, A series of T-DNA insertion mutants from N to C terminal of <italic>TOR</italic> were genotyped and phenotyped. <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> (SALK_036379), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>4</italic> (SALK_007654), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>5</italic> (SALK_147473), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>6</italic> (SALK_017177), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>7</italic> (SALK_028697), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>8</italic> (SALK_016286), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>9</italic> (SALK_013925), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> (SALK_138622), and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic> (SALK_043130) knockout lines displayed similar embryo-defective phenotypes, while <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>12</italic> (SALK_056253), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>13</italic> (SALK_108347), and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>14</italic> (SALK_056209) showed normal embryo growth. &plus;, Defective embryo phenotype; &minus;, normal embryo phenotype; E.D., embryo defective. B, Sample images of siliques with developing seeds and embryos. The top image is a bright-field photograph of the silique showing developing seeds under 10&#x00D7; magnifications. Lower images are from developing embryos of <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>TOR</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> lines captured using Nomarski optics. Bars &equals; 0.01 mm unless indicated in figures.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_169045_wc_f1" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>One of the key functions of <italic>TOR</italic> is its involvement in ribosome biogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Li et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Wei et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Tsang et al., 2010</xref>). The rate of cell proliferation and growth directly depends on ribosome biogenesis. This requires coordination of the production of several ribosomal components, including four different rRNAs and about 130 ribosomal proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Michels and Hernandez, 2006</xref>). <italic>TOR</italic> has been implicated to play an important regulatory role in the expression of several of these components and also in the biogenesis of ribosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Li et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Michels and Hernandez, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Wei et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Tsang et al., 2010</xref>). In yeast and animals, inhibition of the TOR signaling pathway by nutrient starvation or rapamycin treatment results in a rapid down regulation of 18S, 5.8S, 25S, and 5S rRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Li et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Michels and Hernandez, 2006</xref>).</p><p>Loss of functions associated with <italic>TOR</italic> mutations in yeast is evidenced by small cell size, slow growth rate, hypersensitivity to temperature and osmotic stress, and defects in cell cycle and translation initiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Barbet et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Weisman and Choder, 2001</xref>). Knockouts of <italic>Drosophila TOR</italic> show reduced nucleolar size and lipid vesicle aggregation in the larval fat body (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Zhang et al., 2000</xref>). <italic>TOR</italic> deficiency in <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic><italic> elegans</italic> results in arrest at mid-to-late developmental stages of larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Long et al., 2002</xref>). In mice, the disruption of <italic>TOR</italic> causes early embryo lethality and also arrests the proliferation of embryonic stem cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Murakami et al., 2004</xref>).Together, these findings show that <italic>TOR</italic> plays a critical role in the growth and development of diverse eukaryotic species.</p><p>In contrast to the knowledge on TOR in other eukaryotes, very little is known about TOR signaling in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Menand et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Anderson et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Mahfouz et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Deprost et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Sormani et al., 2007</xref>). Unlike in yeast and animals, Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) TOR is insensitive to rapamycin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Sormani et al., 2007</xref>). The putative FKBP12 homologs in Arabidopsis do not bind or interact with rapamycin, and this failure to form the functional in vivo rapamycin-FKBP12 complex likely contributes to rapamycin insensitivity in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Sormani et al., 2007</xref>). Insensitivity to rapamycin has been a major impediment to making progress with determination of the biological effects of TOR activity in plants. Therefore, much less is known about the function of <italic>TOR</italic> in plants than in yeast and animal systems. The Arabidopsis genome contains a single copy of <italic>TOR</italic> and the loss-of-function mutations cause embryo lethality in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Menand et al., 2002</xref>). The TOR protein contains all the conserved regions found in other species: HEAT repeats, FAT domain, FRB domain, kinase domain, and the FATC domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Menand et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Mahfouz et al., 2006</xref>). However, it is not known which of the five domains are critical for embryo development or other regulatory functions of the TOR complexes. In this study, we characterize TOR functional domains required for plant growth and development and show that the kinase domain plays critical roles in development, nuclear localization, and rRNA expression in Arabidopsis.</p><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Characterization of 12 New T-DNA Insertion Lines Spanning 14.2 kb of the TOR-Encoding Genomic Region</title><p>TOR is a multidomain protein and these domains are implicated in different functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">De Virgilio and Loewith, 2006b</xref>). The Arabidopsis <italic>TOR</italic> gene spans 17.6-kb genomic region with 56 exons and 55 introns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Menand et al., 2002</xref>). An earlier study had shown embryo lethality in two T-DNA insertional mutants in the region preceding the FRB domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Menand et al., 2002</xref>). It is possible to identify mutations in different regions that produce truncated proteins for further functional analysis. Toward this, we screened SALK lines for additional insertional mutations and identified 12 new T-DNA insertion lines spanning 14.2 kb of TOR-encoding genomic region (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://signal.salk.edu/cgi-bin/tdnaexpress">http://signal.salk.edu/cgi-bin/tdnaexpress</ext-link>). The flanking sequences of these T-DNA lines were further confirmed by PCR and sequencing (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Materials and Methods S1</ext-link>). The sequencing results showed that all the left border flanking sequences of the 12 mutants are consistent with the information provided in the T-DNA Express database (see http://signal.salk.edu/cgi-bin/tdnaexpress; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>, the right border of T-DNAs was not detectable in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>6</italic> and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>12</italic>, possibly due to some DNA deletions or rearrangements. The other 10 lines showed the correct T-DNA right border flanking sequence (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl1"><label>Table I.</label><caption><title>Characterization of AtTOR T-DNA insertion mutants</title><p>F, Forward; R, reverse. If T-DNA insertion orientation (from RB to LB) is in accordance with TOR gene transcription orientation (from 5&#x2032; to 3&#x2032;), we designated this orientation as forward and in the other orientation (from 3&#x2032; to 5&#x2032;) designated as reverse.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">TOR Mutant</td><td align="center">SALK Lines</td><td align="center">Embryo Phenotypes</td><td align="center">Insertion Position/Domain/Orientation</td><td align="center">Distance to Transcription Initiation Site</td><td align="center">Right Border Sequence of T-DNA</td><td align="center">Left Border Sequence of T-DNA</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>bp</italic></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic></td><td>SALK_036379</td><td>Lethal</td><td>10th exon/HEAT/F</td><td align="char" char=".">3,604</td><td>No deletion</td><td>Correct position</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>4</italic></td><td>SALK_007654</td><td>Lethal</td><td>11th intron/HEAT/R</td><td align="char" char=".">4,016</td><td>No deletion</td><td>Correct position</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>5</italic></td><td>SALK_147473</td><td>Lethal</td><td>15th intron/HEAT/R</td><td align="char" char=".">5,766</td><td>No deletion</td><td>Correct position</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>6</italic></td><td>SALK_017177</td><td>Lethal</td><td>19th intron/HEAT/R</td><td align="char" char=".">6,795</td><td>Not detectable</td><td>Correct position</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>7</italic></td><td>SALK_028697</td><td>Lethal</td><td>19th intron/HEAT/R</td><td align="char" char=".">6,797</td><td>No deletion</td><td>Correct position</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>8</italic></td><td>SALK_016286</td><td>Lethal</td><td>28th intron/FAT/F</td><td align="char" char=".">9,870</td><td>No deletion</td><td>Correct position</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>9</italic></td><td>SALK_013925</td><td>Lethal</td><td>46th exon/FRB/F</td><td align="char" char=".">15,034</td><td>No deletion</td><td>Correct position</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic></td><td>SALK_138622</td><td>Lethal</td><td>47th exon/kinase/F</td><td align="char" char=".">15,159</td><td>No deletion</td><td>Correct position</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic></td><td>SALK_043130</td><td>Lethal</td><td>53 intron/Kinase/F</td><td align="char" char=".">16,572</td><td>No deletion</td><td>Correct position</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>12</italic></td><td>SALK_056253</td><td>Normal</td><td>55 exon/FATC/R</td><td align="char" char=".">17,093</td><td>Not detectable</td><td>Correct position</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>13</italic></td><td>SALK_108347</td><td>Normal</td><td>55th intron/FATC/R</td><td align="char" char=".">17,267</td><td>No deletion</td><td>Correct position</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>14</italic></td><td>SALK_056209</td><td>Normal</td><td>55 intron/FATC/R</td><td align="char" char=".">17,283</td><td>No deletion</td><td>Correct position</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>To further examine whether <italic>TOR</italic> insertion lines express truncated versions, we performed quantitative reverse transcription (RT)-PCR using the embryo samples to test <italic>TOR</italic> transcripts corresponding to upstream, downstream, and also the sequences that span the T-DNA insertion sites (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Materials and Methods S1</ext-link>). <italic>TOR</italic> transcription downstream of T-DNA insertion sites was not detectable in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>4</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>5</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>6</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>7</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>12</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>13</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>14</italic> but low expression was detectable in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>8</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>9</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>). These results are explainable on the basis of the orientation of the T-DNA insertion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>) because some transcripts can be produced in the forward T-DNA insertion orientation lines in which 35S promoter adjacent to T-DNA left border can potentially express the downstream coding sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Deprost et al., 2007</xref>). No expression was detected corresponding to <italic>TOR</italic> in the reverse T-DNA insertion orientation mutants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>). It should be noted in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>4</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>5</italic>, transcription of the sequence upstream to the insertion site was not evident (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>), indicating that truncated transcripts were not stable enough for detection in the three lines. However, the truncated versions of TOR transcripts, expressed under the control of native promoter, corresponding to upstream region of the T-DNA insertion sites, were detected in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>6</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>7</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>8</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>9</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>12</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>13</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>14</italic> lines (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>). The T-DNA insertions occurred in the introns of TOR genomic region in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>4</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>5</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>6</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>7</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>8</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>13</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>14</italic> lines. The RT-PCR analysis of these lines did not detect TOR transcription spanning the introns, suggesting no restoration of full-length transcript via splicing of T-DNA inserts from the respective introns (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Tables I</xref> and).</p><table-wrap id="tbl2"><label>Table II.</label><caption><title>Analysis of the transcription level and embryo phenotypes of AtTOR mutant</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">TOR Mutant</td><td align="center">Transcripts with Sequences from Upstream of the Insertion Site<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="center">Transcripts with Sequences from Downstream of the Insertion Site<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="center">Transcripts Spanning the Insertion Site</td><td align="center">Percentage of Aborted Seeds<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td align="center">Mutant Embryo Arrested Stage</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic></td><td>Not detected</td><td>0.07 (&#x00B1;0)</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">25.9 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,537)</td><td>16&ndash;32 cells</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>4</italic></td><td>Not detected</td><td>Not detected</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">25.2 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,511)</td><td>16&ndash;32 cells</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>5</italic></td><td>Not detected</td><td>Not detected</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">25.1 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,493)</td><td>16&ndash;32 cells</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>6</italic></td><td>0.76 (&#x00B1;0.05)</td><td>Not detected</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">24.9 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,498)</td><td>16&ndash;32 cells</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>7</italic></td><td>0.74 (&#x00B1;0)</td><td>Not detected</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">25.3 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,527)</td><td>16&ndash;32 cells</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>8</italic></td><td>0.82 (&#x00B1;0.03)</td><td>0.13 (&#x00B1;0.01)</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">24.8 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,522)</td><td>16&ndash;32 cells</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>9</italic></td><td>0.96 (&#x00B1;0.01)</td><td>0.09 (&#x00B1;0)</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">25.4 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,505)</td><td>16&ndash;32 cells</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic></td><td>1.05 (&#x00B1;0)</td><td>0.11 (&#x00B1;0.02)</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">25.1 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,517)</td><td>16&ndash;32 cells</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic></td><td>1.09 (&#x00B1;0)</td><td>0.14 (&#x00B1;0)</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">25.0 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,523)</td><td>16&ndash;32 cells</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>12</italic></td><td>1.07 (&#x00B1;0.02)</td><td>Not detected</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">0 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,579)</td><td>Normal embryos</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>13</italic></td><td>0.97 (&#x00B1;0.01)</td><td>Not detected</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">0 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,508)</td><td>Normal embryos</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tor</italic>-<italic>14</italic></td><td>1.01 (&#x00B1;0)</td><td>Not detected</td><td>Not detected</td><td align="center">0 (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,583)</td><td>Normal embryos</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>a</label><p>Values shown are mean number &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of <italic>TOR</italic> relative expression levels in 6 d after flower embryos against that of wild-type control. RNA was extracted from 6 DAF embryos and qualitatively analyzed by RT-PCR and then quantitatively analyzed by real-time PCR, and normalized against Actin2 expression.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn2"><label>b</label><p>Fifty siliques were used for each mutant line.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>The FATC Domain Is Dispensable in Arabidopsis</title><p>The FATC domain is essential for TOR functions in yeast and mammalian system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Takahashi et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dames, 2010</xref>). However, T-DNA insertions that are predicted to affect the FATC domain in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>12</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>13</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>14</italic> showed normal embryo development (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>), indicating that the truncated versions of TOR without FATC domain is functional and FATC domain is likely not essential for embryo development in Arabidopsis. In quantitative RT-PCR assays, we found no evidence of FATC domain transcript sequences downstream of the T-DNA insertions in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>12</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>13</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>14</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>). However, nearly normal levels of transcript from the upstream region were found (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>). Embryogenesis, vegetative growth, and reproductive development were also normal in these mutants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S3</ext-link>). These observations suggest that the FATC domain did not negatively impact the life cycle, indicating that this domain was not required for plant development under laboratory conditions. Multiple sequence alignment identified that the TOR FATC domain (80 amino acids at C terminal of TOR proteins) shows high conservation in yeast, mouse, and human (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>), while 22 additional residues (SSSAIPSNPIADHNNLLGGDSH) were found in the corresponding Arabidopsis FATC domain (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). Further, these additional residues are also found in the FATC domain of TOR proteins in diverse plant species, suggesting plant lineage diverged from the corresponding domain in yeast and animal species (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). Taken together, these observations likely reflect the functional diversities between plant and nonplant species of TOR proteins.</p></sec><sec><title>The Kinase Domain Is Required for Embryo Development</title><p>The insertions in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>4</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>5</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>6</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>7</italic> occurred in the HEAT repeats domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). A low level of transcript (approximately 7% of the wild-type level) downstream of T-DNA insertion site was evident in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>) due to the forward orientation of T-DNA insertion, but none was observed in the other four mutants. However, all these mutants showed embryo lethality (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Tables I</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">II</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). The T-DNA insertions occurred in the FAT and FRB domain in the lines <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>8</italic> and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>9</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), permitting low-level expression (13% and 9%, respectively; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>) because of the permissive orientation as in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>. However, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>8</italic> and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>9</italic> also cause embryo lethality (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). As for <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic>, despite their permissive orientation, the T-DNA insertion in kinase domain abolishes embryo development (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). Although low level of TOR transcription downstream of T-DNA insertion site were detected in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>8</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>9</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic> due to the forward T-DNA insertion orientation, they still exhibited the same embryo lethality as <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>4</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>5</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>6</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>7</italic> with the reverse T-DNA insertion orientation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>). Therefore, it is likely that low level of transcription downstream of T-DNA insertion site in these mutants is inadequate to support embryo development or these transcripts failed to translate to functional TOR protein. Nearly normal levels of transcription upstream of the T-DNA insertion site were detected in lines <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>6</italic> to <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>14</italic> but not in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>4</italic>, and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>5</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table II</xref>), indicating that production of <italic>TOR</italic> transcripts encompassing the HEAT, FAT, and FRB domains is insufficient for embryo development. However, <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> to <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic> lines share defective kinase domain and mutant embryo phenotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>), indicating that the kinase domain is a critical part of the TOR with respect to embryo development.</p><p>To further confirm that embryo-lethal phenotypes observed in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> to <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic> lines were the result of the respective T-DNA insertions, we crossed these lines independently with wild-type Arabidopsis (Columbia-0 [Col-0]). In the F2 population, the T-DNA cosegregated with embryo-lethal phenotypes, indicating that T-DNA insertions caused embryo-lethal phenotypes in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> to <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic> lines.</p></sec><sec><title>Kinase Domain Is Critical for TOR Functions in Vivo</title><p>To further assess the functional domains of TOR in vivo, we first assembled the full-length wild-type cDNA clone of <italic>TOR</italic> (7,446 bp) and 3 kb of the putative upstream promoter region. Expression constructs were generated with full-length cDNA and a series of truncated versions under the control of its native promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1"> Supplemental Materials and Methods S1</ext-link>). The <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> line, with the insertion closest to the 5&#x2032; end of the open reading frame among all other insertion mutations discussed in this study (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>), represents a mutant with near obliteration of <italic>TOR</italic> transcription. This line shows a strong embryo-defective phenotype with 88% (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,537) of the embryos arrested at the 16-cell stage and all of the remainder at the 32-cell stage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S5</ext-link>). The segregating mutant embryos displayed slower growth than the wild-type embryos (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S5</ext-link>). While the wild-type embryos were at the heart stage, the mutant embryos were only at dermatogen stage, suggesting that loss of <italic>TOR</italic> functions in these embryos affected the cell division and growth rates. The <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> allele, the earliest insertion in kinase domain, was selected to represent the kinase domain deletion. Examination of the <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> also identified similar growth defects in the segregating mutant embryos (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S5</ext-link>). However, more embryos (55%; <italic>n</italic> &equals; 2,517) progressed up to 32 cells and none beyond this stage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S5</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><italic>TOR</italic> kinase domain is critical for <italic>TOR</italic> functions in vivo. A, Functional complementation assay in <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> background that shows partial rescue of early embryo lethality with kinase domain in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> mutant embryos, while constructs without the kinase domain fail to rescue the early embryo lethality. &plus;&plus;, Complete rescue of early embryo lethality; &plus;, partial rescue of early embryo lethality; &minus;, no rescue of embryo lethality. All the complementation constructs are expressed under the control of 3-kb <italic>TOR</italic> native promoter. B, Representative Nomarski images of kinase domain alone (<italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic>) that shows partial complementation of <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> mutant embryos. Bars &equals; 0.01 mm unless indicated in figures. C, Functional complementation assay in <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> background shows that the kinase domain was able to rescue the <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutant embryo phenotype, while deletion constructs without the kinase domain failed to rescue embryo lethality. &plus;&plus;, Complete rescue of early embryo lethality; &minus;, constructs did not restore the mutant embryos. D, Representative Nomarski images of functional complementation of <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> defective embryos. <italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic> constructs completely complement the <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutant embryos. Bars &equals; 0.01 mm unless indicated in figures.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_169045_wc_f2" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>In the <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> mutant background, the full-length <italic>TOR</italic> cDNA (<italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>) completely rescued the embryo lethality to wild type and produced normal plants in T2 generation plants carrying both <italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> construct (Basta-selective marker for plant) and T-DNA insertion of <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S6</ext-link>), whereas the kinase domain construct (<italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic>) was able to rescue the embryo lethality from the early globular stage block to the late heart stage in T2 generation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A and B</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S6</ext-link>). The other deletion constructs lacking the kinase domain did not rescue the <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> embryos from globular stage arrest (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S6</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>), suggesting that the kinase domain though critical by itself is not sufficient to restore wild-type TOR functions. In the <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutant line, full-length <italic>TOR</italic> (<italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>) completely rescued the embryo lethality and produced normal plants in T2 generation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S7</ext-link>). Interestingly, transgenic plants containing the constructs that expressed: the kinase domain alone (<italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic>), deletion of N-terminal HEAT repeats (<italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR1433</italic>-<italic>2482</italic>), and deletion of both the HEAT repeats and FAT domain (<italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR1832</italic>-<italic>2482</italic>), fully rescued the <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutant and produced normal plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, C and D</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S7</ext-link>). These results suggest that kinase domain alone or in combination with HEAT and/or FAT domain deletions is sufficient to restore wild-type TOR functions in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutant background. The complementation of two partial TOR proteins to restore native functions is likely mediated through interaction and in vivo assembly of these peptides. To test potential interactions between different Arabidopsis TOR protein domains, we performed yeast two-hybrid assays with full-length protein, TOR kinase domain (TOR2031-2350), and TOR protein without kinase domain (TOR1-2031). These analyses showed that: TOR protein interacts with itself, TOR protein interacts with TOR2031-2350 (kinase domain), and TOR protein can also bind to TOR1-2031 (kinase and FATC domain deletion; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). Similar intragenic complementation phenotypes of <italic>TOR</italic> have also been observed in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Zhang et al., 2006b</xref>). Consistent with these observations, <italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR1</italic>-<italic>2031</italic> (kinase and FATC domain deletion) and pTOR:<italic>TOR<sup>&#x0394;2031</sup></italic><sup>-</sup><italic><sup>2350</sup></italic> (kinase domain deletion) constructs failed to rescue embryo-defective phenotypes of <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S7</ext-link>). Taken together, these results further demonstrate that the TOR kinase domain is essential for embryo development.</p></sec><sec><title>Perturbation of the TOR and Kinase Domain Functions Impairs Plant Development</title><p>To investigate the functions of <italic>TOR</italic> in other phases of Arabidopsis development, we generated transgenic lines with <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> construct using Basta resistance selection marker. These transgenic lines displayed a range of developmental phenotypes involving leaf, stem, root, and meristem (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, A and C</xref>). Based on <italic>TOR</italic> expression levels examined by real-time PCR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Tables S8</ext-link> and S9) and the severity of phenotypes, these lines were classified into strong, medium, weak, and normal groups.</p><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Phenotypic analysis of stable transgenic plants expressing full-length TOR (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>), TOR kinase domain (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR231</italic>-<italic>2350</italic>), and TOR without kinase domain (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>&#x0394;2031-2350). A to C, Phenotypes of full-length TOR overexpression lines (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>) at 15 and 30 DAG. Based on quantification of expression levels of TOR estimated by real-time PCR assay, we classified the transgenic plants into four groups: strong (A1), medium (A2), weak (A3), and normal (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S9</ext-link>). At medium expression levels, plants show early flowering (B) and altered leaf pattern phenotypes (C). <sc>d</sc> to I, Phenotypes of kinase domain overexpression lines (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR231</italic>-<italic>2350</italic>) at 30 DAG. Overexpression of the TOR kinase domain affects leaf number, color, shape of petiole (as shown in E and F), shoot architecture (as shown in G), root morphogenesis (H), and the shape of siliques (I). J and K, Transgenic lines with overexpression of <italic>TOR</italic> without the kinase domain (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>&#x0394;2031-2350) display early senescence phenotype in leaves (J) and dwarf growth (K).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_169045_wc_f3" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>The strong phenotype was defined as one with severe primary and lateral inflorescence meristem defects and shorter hypocotyls. Twenty nine of the 300 transgenic lines showed this strong phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Development of primary shoots and root meristems was arrested in these plants at the early vegetative stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>, plant number 1). The medium group (58/300) was defined as one where the shoot meristem had collapsed around 35 d after germination (DAG; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>, plant number 2). Additionally, the following changes in leaf patterning were observed: Leaf lamina was significantly larger, rounder, and thicker than the wild type and was noticeably wrinkled with severe changes in proximodistal and mediolateral axis. Short hypocotyls were also observed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>). The lines defined as the weak group (96/300; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>, plant number 3) displayed compact architecture with short petioles and early senescence of rosette leaves, reduced stem elongation, compressed internodes, and defects in lateral root initiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, B and C</xref>). The remaining lines (146/300) were phenotypically normal. To further examine whether <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> produced the functional protein in transgenic Arabidopsis, we transformed <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> construct into <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> and <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> backgrounds. Except displaying similar overexpression phenotypes, both <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutant embryos can be rescued by <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> in T2 generation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Tables S6</ext-link> and S7), suggesting that the <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> construct produced full-length functional TOR protein.</p><p>Since the kinase domain is critical for TOR in vivo function, we focused on whether overexpression of the kinase domain would show similar or different phenotypes as compared to transformants carrying full-length <italic>TOR</italic> (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>). We constructed <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic> construct (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>) using Basta resistance selection marker and produced independent transgenic lines. The overexpression lines with this construct (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S10</ext-link>) showed similar phenotypes of short hypocotyls and leaf petioles as observed in <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> lines (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>), but the <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic> lines also showed some distinct developmental phenotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, D and F</xref>). There were significant alterations in root morphogenesis and abnormal cell expansion in specialization zones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3H</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>). The pith cells in the root had an increased number of columns and this phenotype extended to the top part of the root (bracketed area) producing a tuberous root phenotype (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>). There were changes in proximal-distal axis; dark-green and asymmetric rosette leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, E&ndash;G</xref>); delayed senescence and flowering (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, E&ndash;G</xref>); altered phyllotactic pattern in the inflorescence stem; bent and longer siliques (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3I</xref>); defective primary meristem resulting in loss of apical dominance; and the simultaneous formation of axillary inflorescence shoots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3G</xref>). These phenotypes were observed in 96/300 lines. In comparison, 10/300 lines showed enlarged shoot apical meristem, often becoming fasciated, increased number of floral organs, and enlarged floral meristem, suggesting that TOR kinase domain likely mediates functions in meristem. We further introduced <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic> construct into <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> and <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> lines. In T2 generation, except displaying similar overexpression phenotypes, <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic> is able to restore the <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutant embryos to normal growth and partially rescue <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> to late heart stage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Tables S6</ext-link> and S7), indicating <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic> produced the same functional kinase domain protein as <italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic>.</p><p>To test the contributions of other <italic>TOR</italic> domains, a deletion derivative without the kinase domain was used to construct <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR<sup>&#x0394;2031-2350</sup></italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). Independent transgenic lines were made using this construct, again in the wild-type Arabidopsis background. These lines also displayed some phenotypes similar to full-length <italic>TOR</italic> overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3J</xref>): short leaf lamina petioles, compact and yellowing rosette leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3J</xref>); but some distinct phenotypes were also observed: dwarf plants, rapid ageing in rosette leaves and primary stem, and shorter overall lifespan (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3K</xref>).</p><p>To test any influence of <italic>TOR</italic> transgene on the expression of native genomic <italic>TOR</italic> gene, RT-PCR analysis was performed using specific 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032; primers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S8</ext-link>) that distinguish native and transgene expression in transgenic lines produced with <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>, <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic>, and <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR<sup>&#x0394;2031-2350</sup></italic> constructs. This analysis showed that the expression of endogenous <italic>TOR</italic> transcript levels (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S10</ext-link>) were very similar to wild-type controls, indicating that the overexpression phenotypes with these constructs are the outcome of the observed high expression levels of respective <italic>TOR</italic> transgenes.</p></sec><sec><title>The Kinase Domain Regulates rRNA Expression</title><p><italic>TOR</italic> has been implicated in the regulation of rRNA transcription in yeast and animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Li et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Wei et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Tsang et al., 2010</xref>). To determine if plant <italic>TOR</italic> is also involved in this process, we investigated whether transcription of <italic>pre</italic>-<italic>45SrRNA</italic>, consisting of 18S, 5.8S, and 25S rRNAs, was affected in the <italic>TOR</italic> mutants and in overexpression lines. Total RNA was isolated independently from embryos in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutants and <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>, <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>2031-2350, and <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR<sup>&#x0394;2031-2350</sup></italic> transgenic lines (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5</ext-link>). Using specific primers designed for 18S, 5.8S, and 25S rRNA regions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S8</ext-link>), quantitative analysis of expression levels was performed using real-time PCR-based assays. The expression levels of 18S, 5.8S, and 25S rRNA were significantly lower (less than 40%) in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutant embryos relative to the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). The rRNA levels were 8 times higher in <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> transgenic lines. The kinase domain overexpression lines (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>2031-2350) showed 6-fold greater level of rRNA expression relative to wild-type control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Notably, the positive influence of higher rRNA expression was abolished, if the kinase domain was deleted (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR<sup>&#x0394;2031-2350</sup></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). These results suggest that <italic>TOR</italic> regulates rRNAs transcript levels through the activity of its kinase domain.</p><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Analysis of rRNA expression levels in the embryos of wild type, mutants, and transgenic lines produced with TOR full-length and deletion derivatives. A, The rRNA levels are significantly reduced in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutant embryos. Error bars indicate &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> for triplicates. B, Up-regulation of <italic>45S rRNA</italic> levels in <italic>TOR</italic> and <italic>TOR</italic> kinase domain overexpression Arabidopsis lines. Error bars indicate &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> for triplicates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_169045_wc_f4" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The Kinase Domain of TOR Is Involved in Nuclear Localization</title><p>To further investigate TOR-mediated regulation of rRNA expression in Arabidopsis, we have examined TOR subcellular localization, using GFP translational fusion constructs (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic>) and onion (<italic>Allium cepa</italic>) epidermal cell-based transient expression system. The results revealed that TOR protein is present in both the cytoplasm and the nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). To map the nuclear localization sequences (NLSs) of TOR, we identified six putative NLSs using PSORT software: <sup>388</sup>PRKGRPL (NLS1); <sup>566</sup>RRRR (NLS2); <sup>1334</sup>PRSKRMD (NLS3); <sup>1671</sup>RKRK (NLS4); <sup>2077</sup>RPRK (NLS6); and a bipartite nuclear localization signal <sup>1506</sup>RRAKYDEAREYVERARK (NLS5; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>). To test which of these putative NLSs are involved in the nuclear targeting, we constructed the corresponding deletion mutants for expression in the onion epidermal cell-based transient expression system. Since these putative NLSs are distributed in different domains of <italic>TOR</italic> protein, the following independent constructs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>) were made: <italic>TOR1433</italic>-<italic>2482</italic> (NLS1, NLS2, and NLS3 deletions), <italic>TOR1832</italic>-<italic>2482</italic> (NLS1, NLS2, NLS3, NLS4, and NLS5 deletions), <italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic> (containing NLS6 motif), <italic>TOR1</italic>-<italic>2031</italic> (NLS6 deletion), and <italic>TOR<sup>&#x0394;2031-2350</sup></italic> (kinase domain deletion; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>). These derivatives were fused with GFP at C termini to determine nuclear targeting. Deletions involving the putative NLS1-5 motifs did not affect the nuclear localization. However, the loss of NLS6 region resulted in most of the GFP signal being retained in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>). This analysis suggests that the NLS6 motif (located in the kinase domain) of TOR is critical for nuclear localization. To further confirm that the GFP signal is not caused by the cleaved TOR protein, we fused GFP reporter at N terminal of TOR, TOR2031-2350, and <italic>TOR<sup>&#x0394;2031-2350</sup></italic> and tested in onion epidermal cell assay. These constructs displayed consistent localization pattern as their C-terminal GFP fusions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>), indicating that TOR protein wasn&#x2019;t cleaved in the onion epidermal cells.</p><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Characterization of amino acid sequences required for nuclear localization of <italic>TOR</italic>. A, Distribution of six putative NLSs in <italic>TOR</italic> and graphical representation of <italic>TOR</italic> deletion mutants fused with GFP for transient expression in onion epidermal cells. The ability of these constructs to target GFP to nucleus in onion epidermal cells is indicated. N.L., Nuclear localization; &plus;, nuclear localization; &minus;, cytoplasmic localization. B, NLS6 (RPRK motif) in the kinase domain is essential for <italic>TOR</italic> nuclear localization. Diagram of the NLS6 deletions of <italic>TOR</italic> kinase domain. 1, Deletion of <sup>2065</sup>FSRQLVVITSKQRPRKLTIHGNDGEDT<sup>2090</sup>; 2, deletion of <sup>2077</sup>RPRK; 3, RPRK. The nuclear localization of GFP was assessed in onion epidermal cells. &plus;, Nuclear localization; &minus;, cytoplasmic localization; N.L., nuclear localization. C, Representative images of <italic>TOR</italic> protein nuclear localization in onion epidermal cells with different GFP constructs. 1, Transient expression of full-length TOR fused at the C terminus with GFP (<italic>TOR</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic>); 2, TOR kinase domain fused at the C terminus with GFP (<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic>); 3, TOR kinase domain deletion mutant fused with GFP (<italic>TOR</italic>&#x0394;<italic>2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic>-<italic>GFP)</italic>; and 4, <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> as positive control. Bars &equals; 0.02 mm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_169045_wc_f5" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>To further define the regions of NLS6 required for nuclear localization, additional deletion mutants of this region as C-terminal GFP fusions were generated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>) using specific PCR primers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Materials and Methods S1</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). Transient onion cell expression studies showed deletions targeted in the RPRK motif, located in the kinase domain from amino acids 2,077 to 2,080, resulted in loss of nuclear localization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>). Furthermore, constructs involving fusion of the peptide RPRK to GFP at the N terminus or C terminus produced predominantly nuclear localization, suggesting that these four residues are sufficient for nuclear targeting (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>). These results provide evidence that the NLS6 within the kinase domain is required for targeting TOR to the nucleus.</p><p>We further asked whether N-terminal and C-terminal GFP fusion with TOR would affect TOR protein functions in plants. Both <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic> and <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic> constructs were introduced into <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> line. In the T2 generation, except displaying similar phenotypes as <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>), <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic> and <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic> were able to complement the <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> mutant embryos to normal growth (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S6</ext-link>), indicating that GFP fusion at the carboxy or amino end did not affect TOR functions in transgenic Arabidopsis lines.</p></sec><sec><title>TOR Directly Interacts with <italic>45S Ribosome RNA</italic> Promoter in Vivo</title><p>Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Tsang et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Xie et al., 2004</xref>) were performed to determine whether TOR directly binds to sequences within the <italic>45S</italic> ribosome promoter region. Since <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic> and <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic> showed similar localization in transient assays in onion epidermal system and same phenotypes as <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> in transgenic Arabidopsis lines, we selected <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic> transgenic Arabidopsis plants (10 DAG) to perform ChIP experiments. In this assay, <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> transgenic and wild-type lines were used as controls. Chromatin-associated proteins were cross-linked to the DNA with formaldehyde. The cross-linked chromatin was fragmented by sonication and then mixed with anti-GFP antibody to select and isolate DNA associated with the GFP-TOR fusion protein. PCR primer pairs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S11</ext-link>) were designed for amplifying 18 overlapping DNA fragments spanning the <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter and 5&#x2032;-external transcribed spacer elements (ETS) regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>). After immunoprecipitation (IP) with GFP antibody, the associated chromatin fragments extracted from <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic>, <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>, and wild-type control were analyzed by quantitative PCR amplification with the 18 primer sets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>). A mock IP without antibody was performed as a control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>). Specific PCR bands were displayed corresponding to primer pairs R6, R7, R12, R13, R14, R15, R17, and R18 only in IP chromatin samples of <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic> transgenic line and no detectable amplified DNA bands in <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> or wild-type control lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>), whereas the control experiment without antibody resulted in little or no detectable amplified DNA for any of the primer pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>). Furthermore, we selected five genes on different chromosomes of Arabidopsis to further validate the ChIP results. As shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figure S8</ext-link>, no detectable amplified DNA bands for any of these primer pairs in GFP-antibody-based IP chromatin samples of <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic>, <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>, and wild-type Arabidopsis, indicated that the observed interactions of AtTOR with <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter and 5&#x2032;-ETS regions are not due to random nonspecific binding to genomic sequences.</p><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>TOR interacts with the promoter and 5&#x2032;-ETS of the ribosome RNA gene and regulates ribosome rRNA expression in Arabidopsis. A, The organization of the <italic>45S rRNA</italic> gene in Arabidopsis and the location of 18 overlapping PCR fragments spanning <italic>45S rRNA</italic> genomic sequences designed for ChIP assay. Eighteen PCR primer sets are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S11</ext-link>. B, Mapping TOR binding regions in <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter and 5&#x2032;-ETS by ChIP assay. The ChIP assay was performed with GFP antibody using the samples derived from: 1, Wild type; 2, transgenic line produced with <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>; and 3, transgenic line produced with <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic> line. INPUT represents genomic DNA used as template to show the amplification of predicted size fragments with R1 to R18 primer set corresponding to 18 target genomic sequences (top section). In the IP chromatin samples recovered with GFP antibody, PCR amplification of genomic sequences was observed only with R6, R7, R12, R13, R14, R15, R17, and R18 primer sets in <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic> transgenic line (3), and no detectable amplified DNA bands in <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> (2) or wild-type control (1) lines (middle section). As negative control MOCK assay was performed after processing the same samples in ChIP assay but without antibody and this analysis show no amplification of target sequences (bottom section). The agarose gel was stained using GelRed dye solution. C, Quantification of TOR binding to the <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter and 5&#x2032;-ETS region. The R7 genomic region was set as the control region and the quantity of relative binding by TOR in other regions are shown in the bar graph as fold of enrichment compared with the control sample. Error bars indicate &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> for triplicates. D, DNA-binding domain is critical for the ability of TOR protein to bind the <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter. R6, R7, R12, R13, R14, R15, R17, and R18 primer pairs amplified specific PCR bands in the precipitated DNA samples from <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic> transgenic lines. No detectable bands were observed using these primer sets with wild-type or <italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic>&#x0394;1028-1050 transgenic plants. Samples used were wild type (1), <italic>TOR</italic> DNA-binding motif deletion (2), and <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic> transgenic line (3).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_169045_wc_f6" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Mapping the amplicons to the <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter region showed that TOR binding peaks occurred in the 5&#x2032;-ETS and the transcription initiation site for RNA polymerase I located within the 113-bp repeat containing TATAT<underline>A</underline>GGG (&plus;1 is underlined; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Doelling et al., 1993</xref>), and in the <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6C</xref>). These results suggested that TOR activates the expression of <italic>45S rRNA</italic> through binding to its promoter and 5&#x2032;-ETS region in Arabidopsis.</p></sec><sec><title>The Leu Zipper within the HEAT Domain Is Responsible for DNA Binding of TOR</title><p>We further considered whether TOR protein binds the <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter through DNA-binding motifs. Using PSORT software, we identified a putative DNA-binding (Leu zipper) sequence, <sup>1028</sup>LEVFGGTLDEHMHLLLPALIRL<sup>1050</sup>, within the TOR HEAT repeat domain. Transgenic plants with <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic><sup>&#x0394;1028-1050</sup> (Leu zipper deletion) construct (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>) were generated and ChIP assay was performed as noted above. Primer pairs R6, R7, R12, R13, R14, R15, R17, and R18 were employed for quantitative PCR analysis. Wild-type and <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic> transgenic Arabidopsis were used for negative and positive control, respectively. TOR protein without the DNA-binding motif (<italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR<sup>&#x0394;1028-1050</sup></italic>) did not produce amplified DNA fragments from the target regions while the samples from <italic>GFP</italic>-<italic>TOR</italic> transgenic plants showed specific PCR fragments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6D</xref>). These results suggested that TOR directly bound to <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter and 5&#x2032;-ETS region by its Leu zipper motif.</p></sec><sec><title>TOR Activates <italic>45S rRNA</italic> Promoter in a 5&#x2032;-ETS-Dependent Manner</title><p>Having established that TOR binds to the <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter and 5&#x2032;-ETS via the Leu zipper sequence within the HEAT repeat domain, we considered whether the promoter and/or the 5&#x2032;-ETS regions played more important roles in modulating transcription of <italic>45S rRNA</italic>. We therefore cloned two PCR fragments, a 2,885-bp fragment containing the <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Doelling et al., 1993</xref>) and a larger 4,162-bp fragment spanning both the promoter and 5&#x2032;-ETS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>), and fused them with GFP to generate two constructs <italic>P45S rRNA</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> and <italic>P45S rRNA</italic>:<italic>5</italic>&#x2032;-<italic>ETS</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7A</xref>). Transgenic plants harboring these GFP constructs were crossed with <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> transgenic plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7A</xref>). For each of the four lines, <italic>GFP</italic> and <italic>TOR</italic> transcript levels were examined with real-time PCR in 20 F2 generation plants. GFP RNA levels of the <italic>P45SrRNA</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> construct were 5 times higher in the <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> background compared to wild-type background (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). However, transgenic plants containing the <italic>P45SrRNA</italic>:<italic>5</italic>&#x2032;-<italic>ETS</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic> construct had 25 times higher GFP RNA levels in the <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> background, compared with wild-type background (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). These results show that TOR activates <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter and that the activation is significantly enhanced if 5&#x2032;-ETS is also present.</p><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Quantification of <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter activity in wild-type and <italic>TOR</italic> overexpression backgrounds. A, Diagram of GFP expression constructs produced by <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter with or without 5&#x2032;-ETS. These expression constructs were transformed into wild-type and <italic>TOR</italic> overexpression Arabidopsis backgrounds. 1, <italic>P45SrRNA</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> construct in wild-type Arabidopsis background; 2, <italic>P45SrRNA</italic>:<italic>5</italic>&#x2032;-<italic>ETS</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic> construct in wild-type Arabidopsis background; 3, <italic>P45SrRNA</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> construct in <italic>TOR</italic> overexpression background; 4, <italic>P45SrRNA</italic>:<italic>5</italic>&#x2032;-<italic>ETS</italic>-<italic>GFP</italic> in <italic>TOR</italic> overexpression background. B, Bar graph showing relative amounts of expressed GFP as determined by quantitative real-time PCR. The GFP expression with <italic>P45SrRNA</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> construct in wild-type Arabidopsis was used as control (value set as 1) and the relative GFP expression levels in other lines are shown in the bar graph as fold change compared to the wild-type control. The numbers 1, 2, 3, and 4 correspond to the constructs and background Arabidopsis lines as indicated in A. Quantities of GFP expression levels are relative to the amount of expression observed for construct 1. Error bars indicated &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> for triplicates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_169045_wc_f7" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this study, we have dissected functional domains of Arabidopsis TOR protein: the kinase domain that controls embryogenesis and the expression of rRNAs; a NLS, residing in the kinase domain that directs nuclear import of TOR protein; and the DNA-binding motif, residing in the HEAT repeat, which mediates the interaction between TOR protein and the promoter of <italic>45S rRNA</italic>. Plant TOR is insensitive to rapamycin and therefore genetic perturbations that alter the activity are required in delineating the functional aspects. Using insertional mutations in Arabidopsis, genetic complementation, and physical characterization of TOR-bound DNA from the chromatin, we have advanced our understanding of Arabidopsis <italic>TOR</italic>.</p><p>The spatial distribution of the 12 T-DNA insertions over 14.2-kb genome region and the embryo-lethal phenotypes of all but the FATC domain insertions allow us to conclude that the HEAT, FAT, and FRB domains are not sufficient for embryogenesis. Full rescue of the <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> embryo defect by complementation with the kinase domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S7</ext-link>) suggest the essentiality of the kinase domain. However, the kinase domain alone was not sufficient because it failed to achieve full restoration of embryogenesis in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> mutant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S6</ext-link>) that was defective for HEAT, FAT, FRB, kinase, and FATC. Remarkably, the kinase domain alone, in the absence of all other domains, was able to support the growth and development of embryo from 16 to 32 cell stage to late heart stage in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>. This established that TOR is not essential for the initial four or five cell divisions after fertilization. Whether HEAT, FAT, or FRB alone in combination with the kinase domain would suffice is unknown. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Menand et al. (2002)</xref> also showed that T-DNA insertion preceding FRB domain, which is predicted to disrupt kinase domain further downstream, causes embryo lethality. This suggests that all lesions involving expression of the downstream kinase domain result in a phenotype very similar to the <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> mutant, reflecting that kinase domain is essential for Arabidopsis embryogenesis. An intact kinase domain is also essential for TOR function in yeast cell growth and metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Alarcon et al., 1999</xref>), indicating that the function of kinase domain is critical and essential in diverse eukaryotic species.</p><p>The FATC domain of plant TOR is not essential for TOR function as evident from the normal life cycle of three independent insertion mutants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). Restoration of normal phenotype in <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> with kinase domain constructs without FATC domain further support this conclusion. However, the FATC domain is essential for TOR functions in yeast and mammalian system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Takahashi et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dames, 2010</xref>). It is possible that FATC domain plays a role that is not required for plant life cycle under the laboratory conditions employed in our study. Alternatively, its function is redundant to that of other unknown proteins. Our observations further indicate that the carboxy domain and the amino domain of TOR are quite permissive as GFP fusions at the carboxy or amino end did not abolish TOR function in Arabidopsis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figs. S6 and S7</ext-link>).This contrasts the observations with yeast TOR where N- or C-terminal GFP fusions abolish TOR function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Sturgill et al., 2008</xref>). These results show that TOR as a canonical eukaryotic protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">De Virgilio and Loewith, 2006a</xref>) does show some functional diversity.</p><p>So far, only one study has shown that overexpression of <italic>TOR</italic> (T-DNA activation-tagged lines) altered Arabidopsis development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Deprost et al., 2007</xref>). In those four T-DNA activation lines, however, the TOR expression level increased less than 2 times in two lines, and decreased around 50% in the other two lines in leaves relative to wild-type control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Deprost et al., 2007</xref>). It also should be noted that TOR expression levels are quite variable between leaves and roots in these four T-DNA activation lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Deprost et al., 2007</xref>). So far, likely due to the large size of <italic>TOR</italic> full-length transcript (approximately 7.5 kb), transgenic plants have not been successfully produced with this gene. In this study, we were able to overcome this bottleneck and generate transgenic lines with overexpression constructs using the full-length <italic>TOR</italic> cDNA coding sequence driven by strong constitutive promoter cauliflower mosaic virus 35S. The highest <italic>TOR</italic> expression level increased 80-fold in transgenic plants relative to wild-type control (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S9</ext-link>). The endogenous <italic>TOR</italic> gene expression levels are not affected in the overexpression lines, whereas the <italic>TOR</italic> as transgene show higher levels of expression (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S10</ext-link>). We also observed that <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>AtTOR</italic> can rescue the lethal phenotype in the segregating homozygous recessive mutant embryos after introducing it into <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> and <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> backgrounds, indicating the functional TOR protein was produced with our constructs in the transgenic lines.</p><p>In this study, although the transgenic lines of TOR kinase domain overexpression lines shared some phenotypes with full-length TOR lines, the phenotypes of delayed flowering, delayed senescence, and tuberous roots were found only in kinase domain overexpression lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, D&ndash;F</xref>). Interestingly, with kinase domain deletion construct that contain HEAT repeats, FAT, and FRB domains, the transgenic lines showed early senescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, J and K</xref>). Taken together these results suggest that higher activity of the kinase or HEAT-FAT-FRB domains confer contrasting outcomes, whereas with normal (wild-type) levels of <italic>TOR</italic> expression, their functions are coordinated to produce normal development. The overexpression lines may provide us with useful visual markers to further dissect the roles of different TOR domains.</p><p>Our work shows that TOR binds to <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter and activates expression and that enhanced activation requires the 5&#x2032;-ETS. The demonstration of the Leu zipper region of the HEAT domains as the DNA-binding domain, along with the observation that the kinase domain contains an active NLS, it is conceivable that the large TOR protein gains entry to the nucleus with the involvement of NLS-6 in the kinase domain and it activates rRNA expression by binding to the promoter via the HEAT domain&#x2019;s Leu zipper motif. Consistent with these observations, overexpression of kinase domain in wild-type plants produced higher levels of rRNA expression, indicating that the DNA-binding function of HEAT domain is required for this activation and kinase domain alone can interact with full-length or truncated TOR protein (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>) containing Leu zipper to restore TOR activity in Arabidopsis. Interestingly, high conservation of motifs especially corresponding to NLS-6 and Leu zipper DNA-binding domains was found in TOR proteins from diverse eukaryotes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figs. S9 and S10</ext-link>). The observation that truncated TOR can restore full TOR function insofar as embryogenesis is concerned, suggests that overexpression of kinase domain might recruit more TOR into the nuclei and activate rRNA transcription. This study showed that TOR protein is able to directly interact with the promoters of ribosome RNA genes to regulate rRNA expression as shown in human and murine cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Tsang et al., 2010</xref>), indicating that this function is conserved among diverse eukaryotic species.</p><p>We have found that rRNA levels were dramatically reduced in <italic>TOR</italic> mutant embryos. The reason why <italic>TOR</italic> mutant embryos fail to develop beyond the 16 to 32 cells stage might be due to a shortage of ribosomes to support protein synthesis. Ribosomal RNAs are the major components (approximately 65%) of ribosomes and the dosage of rRNAs is rate limiting for ribosome biogenesis, cell division, and cell growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Byrne, 2009</xref>). It is possible that the mutant embryos survive up to 16 to 32 cell stage by making use of maternally inherited ribosomes or a low level of ribosome assembly in the zygote.</p><p>Many developmental defects in different organs ranging from root, hypocotyl, stem, leaf, and meristem were observed in <italic>TOR</italic> overexpression lines. Ribosome biogenesis requires coordination of the ribosomal components that include four different rRNAs and approximately 130 ribosome proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Byrne, 2009</xref>). This coordinated program is likely distorted when rRNA levels are altered. Our data suggests that <italic>TOR</italic> plays a key role to control this coordination and to tightly regulate development in an ordered temporal and spatial pattern. These observations will provide framework for future investigations to address other functions of TOR signaling in plant developmental and signaling pathways.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Arabidopsis Growth and Transformation</title><p>Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) plants and plants were grown in growth chambers set at 22&#x00B0;C, with a 16-h/8-h light/dark cycle. Wild-type plants were of the ecotype Col. Transgenic plants were generated by the floral-dipping method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Zhang et al., 2006a</xref>). Transformation, growth, and screening of primary transformants were performed according to published protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Zhang et al., 2006a</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation and Characterization of T-DNA Insertion Lines</title><p>We obtained the following SALK lines from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center: <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> (SALK_036379), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>4</italic> (SALK_007654), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>5</italic> (SALK_147473), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>6</italic> (SALK_017177), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>7</italic> (SALK_028697), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>8</italic> (SALK_016286), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>9</italic> (SALK_013925), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> (SALK_138622), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>11</italic> (SALK_043130), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>12</italic> (SALK_056253), <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>13</italic> (SALK_108347), and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>14</italic> (SALK_056209). The knockout lines were identified and confirmed by PCR using primers designed from the T-DNA primer design Web site: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://signal.salk.edu/tdnaprimers.2.html">http://signal.salk.edu/tdnaprimers.2.html</ext-link>. These primers are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of DNA, Purification of Total RNA, and Cloning of <italic>TOR</italic> cDNA</title><p>Genomic DNA and total RNA were isolated from Arabidopsis (ecotype Col) samples using DNeasy plant mini kit (QIAGEN, cat. no. 69104) and RNeasy plant mini kit (QIAGEN, cat. no. 74904) following the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. A SMART RACE cDNA amplification kit (Clontech, cat. no. 634914) was used for cDNA amplification following the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. The full-length cDNA of the wild-type <italic>TOR</italic> (7.4 kb) and various truncated fragments were amplified by RT-PCR using the Advantage 2 polymerase mix kit (Clontech, cat. no. 639201) following the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. RT-PCR primer pairs for amplification of the full-length <italic>TOR</italic> gene from Arabidopsis were designed based on the cDNA sequence (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org">http://www.arabidopsis.org</ext-link>) of <italic>TOR.</italic> These primers were designed to introduce a <italic>Not</italic>I site at the 5&#x2032; end of forward primers and an <italic>Xma</italic>lI site at the 3&#x2032; end of reverse primers. Three overlapping fragments of the <italic>TOR</italic> gene were amplified and fused together by using restriction enzymes followed by ligation (<italic>Not</italic>I, <italic>Bsp</italic>EI, <italic>Blp</italic>I, and <italic>Xma</italic>lI) to generate the full-length clone (7.4 kb). The PCR products, with the 5&#x2032; <italic>Not</italic>I site and 3&#x2032; <italic>Xma</italic>lI site, were cloned into the TA cloning vector pCR2.1-TOPO (Invitrogen, cat. K450001). The recombinant clones were verified by DNA sequencing. Recombinant plasmids were digested with <italic>Not</italic>I and <italic>Xma</italic>I and cloned into p8GWN (see below) to generate the gateway system-based Entry vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Earley et al., 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Cloning p8GWN into Gateway Entry Vectors</title><p>The construction of the Gateway entry vector p8GWN is based on the pCR8/GW/TOPO (Invitrogen, cat. K2500-20) plasmid, comprising a TOPO AT cloning site flanked by attL1 and attL2 sites. To create p8GWN, a linker (forward primer: <underline>GCGGCCGC</underline>AAAAAA<underline>CCCGGG</underline>A, reverse primer: <italic><underline>CCCGGG</underline></italic>TTTTTT<underline>GCGGCCGC</underline>A, <italic>Not</italic>I and <italic>Xma</italic>lI sites underlined) was synthesized and directly inserted into pCR8/GW/TOPO. The resulting plasmid, p8GWN, was sequenced to confirm that the cloning sites were in frame between attL sequence and linker (attL1/<italic>Not</italic>I/AAAAAA/<italic>Xma</italic>lI/attL2). <italic>TOR</italic> and its truncated fragments were cloned into pCR2.1-TOPO (Invitrogen, cat no. K4500-01), sequenced, then removed by <italic>Not</italic>I and <italic>Xma</italic>I digestion, and then reinserted into the p8GWN <italic>Not</italic>I/<italic>Xma</italic>I cassette to generate Gateway entry vector constructs.</p></sec><sec><title>Generation of Overexpression Constructs</title><p>The Gateway system (Invitrogen) was employed for creating various expression constructs. Various plant, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, and yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) expression constructs were made by transferring the full-length and different deletion derivatives of <italic>TOR</italic> from p8GWN into the appropriate pEarleyGate vectors through LR recombination reactions in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Earley et al., 2006</xref>). The resulting plasmids were used to transform wild-type Arabidopsis plants (Col), <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>, <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> plants, and yeast.</p></sec><sec><title>Generation of PrRNA:5&#x2032;-ETS-GFP Constructs</title><p>A 813-bp GFP cDNA (Invitrogen) was PCR amplified using forward primer GFPF incorporating 5&#x2032; <italic>Asi</italic>sI and <italic>Not</italic>I sites (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>) and reverse primer GFPR incorporating a 3&#x2032; <italic>Asc</italic>I site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>) and inserted into pCR8/GW/TOPO using the TA cloning kit (Invitrogen, cat. K2500-20). Sequencing was performed to verify that the coding sequence was in frame and in the correct relative orientation between attL1 and attL2 sites. The <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter (2,885 bp), and the <italic>45S rRNA</italic> promoter plus 5&#x2032;-ETS sequences (4,162 bp), were amplified using forward primer PrRNAF incorporating a 5&#x2032; <italic>Asi</italic>sI site and reverse primers PrRNAR1 and PrRNAR2, respectively, incorporating 3&#x2032; <italic>Not</italic>I sites (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). The PCR products were cloned into the TA cloning vector pCR2.1-TOPO (Invitrogen, cat. K2000-01) for sequence verification. After digestion with <italic>Asi</italic>sI and <italic>Not</italic>I, the PCR products were subcloned into the <italic>Asi</italic>sI/<italic>Not</italic>I restriction sites upstream of the GFP coding region in the vector p8GWG to generate clones PrRNA:GFP and PrRNA:ETS-GFP. These recombinant constructs were transferred into pEarleyGate303 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Earley et al., 2006</xref>) through LR recombination reactions (as described above).</p></sec><sec><title>Generation of <italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>/Deletion Derivatives and Constructs for Complementation Assays</title><p>Based on the pCR8/GW/TOPO plasmid (Invitrogen, cat. K2500-20), a linker (<underline>GCGATCGC</underline>AAAAAA<underline>GCGGCCG</underline>CAAAAAA<underline>CCCGGG</underline>T, <italic>Asi</italic>sI, <italic>Not</italic>I site at the 5&#x2032; end, and <italic>Xma</italic>lI site at the 3&#x2032; end underlined) was synthesized and directly inserted into pCR8/GW/TOPO and sequenced to confirm the in-frame attL sequence with the linker (attL1/<italic>Asi</italic>sI/AAAAAA/<italic>Not</italic>I/AAAAAA/<italic>Xma</italic>lI/attL2). TOR and its deletion derivatives were digested with <italic>Not</italic>I and <italic>Xma</italic>I and cloned into the <italic>Not</italic>I/<italic>Xma</italic>lI sites. The 3-kb <italic>TOR</italic> promoter from Arabidopsis genomic DNA was amplified with oligo primers to introduce <italic>Asi</italic>sI at the 5&#x2032; end of forward primers and a <italic>Not</italic>I at the 3&#x2032; end of reverse primers (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>), and the respective PCR products verified by sequencing. The TOR promoter was fused with coding sequences of full-length TOR and its deletion derivatives having <italic>Asi</italic>sI and <italic>Not</italic>I compatible sites at the 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032;, respectively. These <italic>PTOR</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>/deletion constructs were inserted separately into pEarleyGate 303 destination vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Earley et al., 2006</xref>) through LR recombination reactions to generate the complementation vectors.</p></sec><sec><title>Mutagenesis Constructs</title><p>All the internal deletions were generated by PCR overlap mutagenesis using the TaKaRa long-range PCR system and Invitrogen mutagenesis kit (cat. no. 12397-014). The primers used in these experiments are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec><title>ChIP Assays</title><p>The ChIP assays were performed as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Tsang et al. (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Xie et al. (2004)</xref> with minor modifications (see below). Primers used in the ChIP assays are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S11</ext-link>. A total of 1.5 g of 10 DAG Arabidopsis whole-plant tissues were harvested, ground in liquid nitrogen, then fixed using 37 mL 1% formaldehyde solution for 30 min to cross-link proteins to DNA, followed by the addition of 2.5 mL 2M Gly to stop the cross-linking reaction. The cross-linked chromatin was fragmented by sonication. The resulting input sample is immunoprecipitated with GFP antibody (Invitrogen, 33-2600) that specifically recognizes the fusion proteins GFP-TOR or TOR-GFP, to enrich for DNA sequences that associate with the TOR protein in vivo. Chromatin preparation, preclearing and IP, collection, washes and elution of immune complexes, reverse cross-linking, and DNA cleanup were performed as described previously (http://www.epigenome-noe.net/researchtools/protocol.php?protid&equals;13). The quantity of the R7 PCR fragment was arbitrarily set at 100%. The qPCR machine used this value as control to quantify relative binding by TOR in other regions. The ChIP experiments were performed with three biological replicates. Gels were stained using GelRed dye solution (Biotium, cat. 41003).</p></sec><sec><title>GFP Transient Expression and Particle Bombardment in Plant Cells</title><p>Particle bombardment was performed as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Giglione et al. (2000)</xref>, with minor modifications (see below). The model Biolistic particle delivery system from Bio-Rad (PDS-1000/He) was used to deliver micron gold (Bio-RAD: cat no. 1652263)-coated pure plasmid DNA (purified with Qiagen mini-prep kits) spotted on microcarriers (Bio-RAD: cat no. 1652333) to transform onion (<italic>Allium cepa</italic>) epidermal cells incubated on Murashige and Skoog media. Both stopping screens (cat no. 1652336) and rupture disks 1,100 psi (cat no. 1652329) were from Bio-RAD. Bombardment parameters were as follows: vacuum, 25 inches Hg; distance to target, 6 cm; helium pressure, 1,300 p.s.i. Onion scales were incubated for 24 to 48 h in the growth chamber 16-h light/8-h dark at 24&#x00B0;C. Epidermal tissues were removed and layered in water on glass slides for microscopy. The 4&#x2032;,6-diamino-phenylindole staining of the onion samples was performed as described in McLean et al., (1990). The tissues were examined under a ZEISS SteRED Lumar V12 fluorescence microscope.</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative Real-Time PCR</title><p>Real-time PCR was performed as described by Mouritzen et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Mouritzen et al., 2005</xref>) with minor modifications. Total RNAs were isolated from Arabidopsis (ecotype Col) samples using RNeasy pPlant mMini kKit (QIAGEN: cCat. nNo. 74904) following manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. The QuantiTect RTReverse Transcription kKit (QIAGEN: cCat. nNo. 205311) was used for cDNA amplification following the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. Dyes were purchased from Applied Biosystems (PowerSYBR gGreen PCR master mix;. pPart nNo. 436759). AtACTIN2 was used as internal control. GenScript rReal-time PCR (TaqMan) pPrimer dDesign (https://www.genscript.com/ssl-bin/app/primer) was used for primer design. The sStep oOne rReal-time PCR system from Applied Biosystems was used for real-time PCR. Comparative CT eExperiments of sStep oOne v1.0 software was used for data analysis. Six6 specific primer pairs of the 5S, 18S, and 25S rRNAs for quantitative RT-PCR were used (Supplemental Table S8). We have used 45S rRNA 3 (specific primers: 25SRTR: 5&#x2032;-TCGAATCTTAGCGACAAAGGGC-3&#x2032;; 18SRTR: 5&#x2032;-CAATGATCCTTCCGCAGGTTCA-3&#x2032;; and 5.8RTR: 5&#x2032;-TTGTGACACCCAAGGCAGACGTG-3&#x2032; to synthesize the first strand of cDNA of rRNAs. We used rRNA-specific primers plus oligo dT derived first-strand cDNA as the template for quantitative RT-PCR analysis of rRNAs and mRNAs. Among 5.8S, 18S, and 25S rRNAs, they share similar expression pattern in mutant and overexpression lines. We therefore used the average values of 18S, 5.8S, and 25S rRNA to reflect <italic>45S rRNA</italic> expression in cells. To quantify the GFP expression level of P45SrRNA:GFP and P45SrRNA-5&#x2032;ETS:GFP in various transgenic Arabidopsis, we used GFP sequence-based GFPR primer (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>) plus oligo dT to synthesize the first strand of cDNA as the template to perform real-time PCR. The actin 2 (AT3g18780) and &#x03B2;-6-tublin (AT5g12250) genes were used as internal controls and to assess the efficiency of cDNA synthesis.</p></sec><sec><title>Yeast Two-Hybrid Assays</title><p>Based on the pCR8/GW/TOPO (Invitrogen, cat. K2500-20) plasmid, a linker (<underline>GGCCATGGAGGCC</underline>A<underline>GCGGCCG</underline>AAAAAA<underline>CCCGGG</underline>T, <italic>Sfi</italic>I, <italic>Not</italic>I site at the 5&#x2032; end, and <italic>Xma</italic>lI site at the 3&#x2032; end underlined) was synthesized and directly inserted into pCR8/GW/TOPO to generate P8GWY. The cDNAs of <italic>TOR</italic> and its deletion derivatives were generated by RT-PCR as described above, cloned them into P8GWY <italic>Not</italic>I/<italic>Xma</italic>I sites, then transferred them into pGADT7 (Ampicillin resistance) and pGBKT7 (Kanamycin resistance) vectors by using the <italic>Sfi</italic>I and <italic>Xma</italic>I restriction site in pGADT7 and pGBKT7, followed by transformation of the recommended plasmids into yeast host strains AH109 for interaction assays. All the yeast two-hybrid procedures were performed according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions (Clontech; cat. no. 630303).</p></sec><sec><title>Microscopy</title><p>For phenotyping mutant embryos, the ovules were cleared in chloral hydrate solution (8:1:2, chloral hydrate:glycerol:water; w/v/v). The embryos were viewed under Leica DMR compound microscope with differential interference contrast (Nomarski) optics. Images were captured using the Optronics Microfire camera and were edited in Abobe Photoshop CS.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figure S1</ext-link>.</bold> FATC domain shows high conservation among nonplant species while high diversity was found between plant and yeast/animal species.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figure S2</ext-link>.</bold> Yeast two-hybrid analysis of interactions of Arabidopsis TOR domains.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figure S3</ext-link>.</bold> Overexpression of kinase domain (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR2031</italic>-<italic>2350</italic>) phenocopies the short hypocotyl phenotype of full-length TOR overexpression lines (<italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic>) in low-expression transgenic lines.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figure S4</ext-link>.</bold> Root phenotypes of transgenic Arabidopsis TOR kinase domain overexpression lines.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figure S5</ext-link>.</bold> Agarose gel analysis of rRNAs in different TOR overexpression lines.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figure S6</ext-link>.</bold> Representative images of GFP N-terminal fusion with <italic>TOR</italic> and its truncated proteins&#x2019; subcellular nuclear and/or cytoplasmic localization in onion epidermal cells.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figure S7</ext-link>.</bold> GFP fusion at the carboxyl or amino end of <italic>AtTOR</italic> did not abolish <italic>AtTOR</italic> function in Arabidopsis.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figure S8</ext-link>.</bold> ChIP assay of genomic loci representing five Arabidopsis chromosomes.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figure S9</ext-link>.</bold> Conservation of putative NLS in kinase domain among yeast, animals, human, and different plant species.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Figure S10</ext-link>.</bold> Multiple alignment analysis of TOR protein DNA-binding domain region present in HEAT repeat.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.</bold> PCR primers used for confirmation of different T-DNA insertion lines.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>.</bold> RT-PCR primers used for detecting transcript sequences in different <italic>tor</italic> mutant lines.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S3</ext-link>.</bold> Phenotypic analysis of FATC domain T-DNA mutant lines.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>.</bold> PCR primers used for cloning and mutagenesis.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S5</ext-link>.</bold> Analysis of <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> and <italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> embryo phenotypes in comparison with embryos in wild type.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S6</ext-link>.</bold> Functional complementation assays in <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>3</italic> background.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S7</ext-link>.</bold> Functional complementation assays in <italic>TOR</italic>/<italic>tor</italic>-<italic>10</italic> background.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S8</ext-link>.</bold> Primers used for real-time PCR.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S9</ext-link>.</bold> Expression levels of <italic>TOR</italic> in the <italic>P35S</italic>:<italic>TOR</italic> (full-length protein-coding cDNA) transgenic lines.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S10</ext-link>.</bold> The endogenous TOR and transgene expression levels in various overexpression lines.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Table S11</ext-link>.</bold> PCR primers used for ChIP assay.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.169045/DC1">Supplemental Materials and Methods S1</ext-link>.</bold> Analysis of T-DNA lines.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Subbaiah Chalivendra, Michelle Alting-Mees, Adrian Cutler, and Don Palmer for critical reading and comments on the manuscript. We thank Dr. Christian Meyer for kindly providing the SALK_147817 T-DNA line and the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center for T-DNA insertion lines. This is publication number 50164 from the National Research Council of Canada.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alarcon</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardenas</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Protein kinase activity and identification of a toxic effector domain of the target of rapamycin TOR proteins in yeast</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>2531</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2546</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Veit</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis AtRaptor genes are essential for post-embryonic plant growth</article-title>. <source>BMC Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>HEAT repeats in the Huntington&#x2019;s disease protein</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>116</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbet</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Helliwell</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Stansfield</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuite</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>TOR controls translation initiation and early G1 progression in yeast</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>42</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bjornsti</surname><given-names>M-A</given-names></name><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The TOR pathway: a target for cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>348</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosotti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>FAT: a novel domain in PIK-related kinases</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>227</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A role for the ribosome in development</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>512</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>519</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cafferkey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergsma</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Koltin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sathe</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Faucette</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Livi</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Dominant missense mutations in a novel yeast protein related to mammalian phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase and VPS34 abrogate rapamycin cytotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>6012</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>6023</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dames</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Structural basis for the association of the redox-sensitive target of rapamycin FATC domain with membrane-mimetic micelles</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>7766</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>7775</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Virgilio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Loewith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006a</year>) <article-title>The TOR signalling network from yeast to man</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1476</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1481</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Virgilio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Loewith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006b</year>) <article-title>Cell growth control: little eukaryotes make big contributions</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>6392</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>6415</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deprost</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sormani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leterreux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicola&#x00EF;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robaglia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis TOR kinase links plant growth, yield, stress resistance and mRNA translation</article-title>. <source>EMBO Rep</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>864</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>870</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doelling</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaudino</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pikaard</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Functional analysis of Arabidopsis thaliana rRNA gene and spacer promoters in vivo and by transient expression</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>7528</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>7532</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Earley</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Opper</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Juehne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pikaard</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Gateway-compatible vectors for plant functional genomics and proteomics</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>616</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>629</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fadri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Daquinag</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The pleckstrin homology domain proteins Slm1 and Slm2 are required for actin cytoskeleton organization in yeast and bind phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate and TORC2</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1883</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1900</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giglione</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Serero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boisson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinnel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Identification of eukaryotic peptide deformylases reveals universality of N-terminal protein processing mechanisms</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>5916</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5929</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guertin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thoreen</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Burds</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalaany</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Moffat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Ablation in mice of the mTORC components raptor, rictor, or mLST8 reveals that mTORC2 is required for signaling to Akt-FOXO and PKCalpha, but not S6K1</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>859</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>871</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heitman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Movva</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Targets for cell cycle arrest by the immunosuppressant rapamycin in yeast</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>253</volume>: <fpage>905</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>909</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inoki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>K-L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Signaling by target of rapamycin proteins in cell growth control</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>100</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashrafi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Rictor/TORC2 regulates Caenorhabditis elegans fat storage, body size, and development through sgk-1</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e60</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarbassov</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Latek</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdjument-Bromage</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tempst</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabatini</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>mTOR interacts with raptor to form a nutrient-sensitive complex that signals to the cell growth machinery</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>175</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriquez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Deuter-Reinhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Movva</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Target of rapamycin in yeast, TOR2, is an essential phosphatidylinositol kinase homolog required for G1 progression</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>596</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Howald</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>HEAT repeats mediate plasma membrane localization of Tor2p in yeast</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>275</volume>: <fpage>37011</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>37020</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertram</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Nutrient regulates Tor1 nuclear localization and association with rDNA promoter</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>442</volume>: <fpage>1058</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1061</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loewith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacinto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wullschleger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crespo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonenfant</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppliger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenoe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Two TOR complexes, only one of which is rapamycin sensitive, have distinct roles in cell growth control</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>457</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>468</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Spycher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Avruch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>TOR deficiency in C. elegans causes developmental arrest and intestinal atrophy by inhibition of mRNA translation</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1448</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1461</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahfouz</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Delauney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> TARGET OF RAPAMYCIN interacts with RAPTOR, which regulates the activity of S6 kinase in response to osmotic stress signals</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>477</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>490</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The expanding TOR signaling network</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>158</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>166</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Eubanks</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Tissue-specific expression of divergent actins in soybean root</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>344</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menand</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Desnos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nussaume</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouchez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robaglia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Expression and disruption of the Arabidopsis TOR (target of rapamycin) gene</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>6422</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>6427</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michels</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Does Pol I talk to Pol II? Coordination of RNA polymerases in ribosome biogenesis</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1982</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1985</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mouritzen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Noerholm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomholt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfundheller</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolstrup</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>ProbeLibrary: a new method for faster design and execution of quantitative real-time PCR</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>316</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichisaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshiro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Edenhofer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonezawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>mTOR is essential for growth and proliferation in early mouse embryos and embryonic stem cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>6710</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>6718</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Proud</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Role of mTOR signalling in the control of translation initiation and elongation by nutrients</article-title>. <source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source> <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>244</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McCaffery</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Aronova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairclough</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iverson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wedaman</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>TOR complex 1 includes a novel component, Tco89p (YPL180w), and cooperates with Ssd1p to maintain cellular integrity in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>14752</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>14762</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmelzle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>TOR, a central controller of cell growth</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>262</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sormani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Menand</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ennar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecampion</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robaglia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Saccharomyces cerevisiae FKBP12 binds Arabidopsis thaliana TOR and its expression in plants leads to rapamycin susceptibility</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cafferkey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Livi</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Interaction between FKBP12-rapamycin and TOR involves a conserved serine residue</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>269</volume>: <fpage>32027</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>32030</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sturgill</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Diefenbacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautwein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>TOR1 and TOR2 have distinct locations in live cells</article-title>. <source>Eukaryotic Cell</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1819</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1830</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokunaga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hidayat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonezawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Carboxyl-terminal region conserved among phosphoinositide-kinase-related kinases is indispensable for mTOR function in vivo and in vitro</article-title>. <source>Genes Cells</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>765</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>775</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertram</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Drenan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Chromatin-mediated regulation of nucleolar structure and RNA Pol I localization by TOR</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>6045</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>6056</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>XFS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>mTOR binds to the promoters of RNA polymerase I- and III-transcribed genes</article-title>. <source>Cell Cycle</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>953</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>957</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms of regulation of RNA polymerase III-dependent transcription by TORC1</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2220</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2230</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weisman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Choder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The fission yeast TOR homolog, tor1&plus;, is required for the response to starvation and other stresses via a conserved serine</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>276</volume>: <fpage>7027</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>7032</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wullschleger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Loewith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>TOR signaling in growth and metabolism</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>484</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasschau</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lellis</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilberman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Genetic and functional diversification of small RNA pathways in plants</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>E104</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Stallock</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Regulation of cellular growth by the Drosophila target of rapamycin dTOR</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2712</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2724</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>QW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006a</year>) <article-title>Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of Arabidopsis thaliana using the floral dip method</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>641</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>646</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Billington</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006b</year>) <article-title>Drosophila target of rapamycin kinase functions as a multimer</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>172</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>362</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Florentino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crabtree</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>TOR kinase domains are required for two distinct functions, only one of which is inhibited by rapamycin</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>130</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
