<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">176776</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.176776</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>PLANTS INTERACTING WITH OTHER ORGANISMS</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Multiple Roles of WIN3 in Regulating Disease Resistance, Cell Death, and Flowering Time in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[C]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4"><sup>[OA]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Guan-Feng</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seabolt</surname><given-names>Savanna</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamdoun</surname><given-names>Safae</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>Gina</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Jin</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Hua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&ast;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Biological Sciences, University of Maryland Baltimore County, Baltimore, Maryland 21250</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&ast;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>hualu@umbc.edu</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the startup funds from the University of Maryland Baltimore County, by the National Science Foundation (grant no. RIG-0818651), and by the Florida Citrus Production Research Advisory Council to H.L. The <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> mutant was generated by H.L at the University of Chicago with support from the National Institutes of Health (grant no. R01GM54292) to Dr. Jean Greenberg.</p></fn><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Hua Lu (<email>hualu@umbc.edu</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[C]</label><p>Some figures in this article are displayed in color online but in black and white in the print edition.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn4"><label>[OA]</label><p>Open Access articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.111.176776">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.111.176776</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>7</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>156</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1508</fpage><lpage>1519</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2011 American Society of Plant Biologists</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p></p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The salicylic acid (SA) regulatory gene <italic>HOPW1-1-INTERACTING3</italic> (<italic>WIN3</italic>) was previously shown to confer resistance to the biotrophic pathogen <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic>. Here, we report that <italic>WIN3</italic> controls broad-spectrum disease resistance to the necrotrophic pathogen <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> and contributes to basal defense induced by flg22, a 22-amino acid peptide derived from the conserved region of bacterial flagellin proteins. Genetic analysis indicates that <italic>WIN3</italic> acts additively with several known SA regulators, including <italic>PHYTOALEXIN DEFICIENT4</italic>, <italic>NONEXPRESSOR OF PR GENES1</italic> (<italic>NPR1</italic>), and <italic>SA INDUCTION-DEFICIENT2</italic>, in regulating SA accumulation, cell death, and/or disease resistance in the Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) mutant <italic>acd6-1</italic>. Interestingly, expression of <italic>WIN3</italic> is also dependent on these SA regulators and can be activated by cell death, suggesting that <italic>WIN3</italic>-mediated signaling is interconnected with those derived from other SA regulators and cell death. Surprisingly, we found that <italic>WIN3</italic> and <italic>NPR1</italic> synergistically affect flowering time via influencing the expression of flowering regulatory genes <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS C</italic> and <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic>. Taken together, our data reveal that <italic>WIN3</italic> represents a novel node in the SA signaling networks to regulate plant defense and flowering time. They also highlight that plant innate immunity and development are closely connected processes, precise regulation of which should be important for the fitness of plants.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Successful defense against pathogens is crucial for plant growth and development. Plants have evolved sophisticated defense mechanisms against pathogen attacks. In addition to preformed physical and chemical barriers, plants have basal defense, triggered by perception of pathogen-associated molecular patterns, which are conserved molecules derived from many pathogens. More specific and robust defense responses can be induced when plant resistance proteins recognize their cognate pathogen effector proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Zipfel and Felix, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Chisholm et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Jones and Dangl, 2006</xref>). Such recognitions can subsequently lead to systemic acquired resistance, a form of long-lasting resistance to broad-spectrum pathogens at the whole plant level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Ryals et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Durrant and Dong, 2004</xref>).</p><p>During different periods of plant defense, the small molecule salicylic acid (SA) plays a central role in activating defense signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hammond-Kosack and Jones, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Ryals et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Tsuda et al., 2008</xref>). Genes regulating SA signaling networks can be grouped into three types, which affect three intricately interconnected subcircuits of the networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lu, 2009</xref>). The type I SA genes are directly involved in SA biosynthesis, including <italic>SA INDUCTION-DEFICIENT2</italic>/<italic>ENHANCED DISEASE SUSCEPTBILITY16</italic> (<italic>SID2/EDS16</italic>), which encodes isochorismate synthase for the synthesis of the majority of SA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Wildermuth et al., 2001</xref>) and genes in <italic>SID2</italic>-independent pathways for the minor production of SA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Chen et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lu et al., 2009</xref>). The type II SA genes are not directly involved in SA synthesis but influence SA levels through mechanisms that are not yet well understood. Examples of such SA regulators include <italic>ACCELERATED CELL DEATH6</italic> (<italic>ACD6</italic>), <italic>AGD2-LIKE DEFENSE1</italic>, <italic>EDS1</italic>, <italic>PHYTOALEXIN DEFICIENT4</italic> (<italic>PAD4</italic>), <italic>SID1/EDS5</italic>, <italic>HOPW1-1-INTERACTING3</italic> (<italic>WIN3</italic>)<italic>/AVRPPHB SUSCEPTIBLE3</italic> (<italic>PBS3</italic>)<italic>/GH3-LIKE DEFENSE GENE1</italic> (<italic>GDG1</italic>), and the <italic>MODIFIER OF SNC1</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Falk et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Jirage et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Nawrath et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lu et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Song et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Palma et al., 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Zhang et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Zhang and Li, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Goritschnig et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jagadeeswaran et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Nobuta et al., 2007</xref>). The type III SA genes act downstream of SA signaling, among which <italic>NONEXPRESSOR OF PR GENES1</italic> (<italic>NPR1</italic>) is the best-characterized SA signal transducer. The NPR1 protein translocates from the cytoplasm to the nucleus in response to the change of cellular redox and influences defense gene expression by interacting with transcription factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Cao et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Ryals et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Shah et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Fan and Dong, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Mou et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dong, 2004</xref>). Besides being the key defense signaling molecule, accumulating evidence indicates that SA regulates plant development, such as flowering time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Cleland and Tanaka, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Cleland and Ben-Tal, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Endo et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Wada et al., 2009</xref>). Consistent with this role of SA, light and phytochrome signaling, which are among the main factors contributing to the determination of flowering time, were shown to be part of the defense signaling networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Genoud et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Griebel and Zeier, 2008</xref>). Hence, studies from different fields of plant research clearly indicate an intimate relationship between plant development and innate immunity. However, our understanding of how these two processes are linked mechanistically is still in its infancy.</p><p>While little is known about the mechanisms by which many SA regulators act, information on how they interact to form distinct pathways within the networks is even scarcer. Biochemical and microarray approaches have proven useful to resolve some of the complexity of the defense networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Feys et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Bartsch et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Wang et al., 2008</xref>). Genetic analysis based on the unique Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) mutant, <italic>acd6-1</italic>, has also provided novel insights on the interactions among some SA regulators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Song et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lu et al., 2009</xref>). ACD6, a type II SA regulator with an ankyrin-repeat motif and a transmembrane domain, was shown to be a major determinant of fitness in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Todesco et al., 2010</xref>). The <italic>acd6-1</italic> mutant displays constitutive defense, severe cell death, and extreme dwarfism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rate et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Vanacker et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lu et al., 2003</xref>). Interestingly, the small size of <italic>acd6-1</italic> is sensitive to the change of defense levels in the plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lu et al., 2009</xref>). Such a feature of <italic>acd6-1</italic> makes it a useful tool to gauge the change of defense levels due to genetic interactions among some defense regulators.</p><p>The type II SA regulator WIN3 is one of the 19 members of the firefly luciferase family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Staswick et al., 2005</xref>). WIN3, also named PBS3, GDG1, and GH3.12, was previously shown to act upstream of SA signaling and to regulate resistance to the biotrophic pathogen <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jagadeeswaran et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Nobuta et al., 2007</xref>). The WIN3 protein conjugates amino acids to 4-substituted benzoates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Okrent et al., 2009</xref>), which can be used as precursors for SA biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Chen et al., 2009</xref>). In this report, we show that WIN3 regulates broad-spectrum disease resistance to both biotrophic and necrotrophic pathogens. Our genetic analysis indicates that WIN3 acts independently of PAD4 and NPR1 in regulating SA accumulation, disease resistance, and cell death in <italic>acd6-1</italic>. WIN3 also contributes to both SID2-dependent and -independent SA biosynthesis. Surprisingly, we found that WIN3 and NPR1 act synergistically in regulating flowering time, highlighting the interconnectedness of plant innate immunity and development.</p><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>WIN3 Contributes to Flg22-Induced Defense</title><p>WIN3 was previously shown to regulate basal defense against virulent <italic>P. syringae</italic> strains in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jagadeeswaran et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Nobuta et al., 2007</xref>). To further investigate this role of WIN3, we pretreated <italic>win3-1</italic> and wild-type control (Columbia [Col-0]) plants with a well-characterized elicitor of basal defense, flg22, a 22-amino acid peptide derived from the conserved region of bacterial flagellin proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Felix et al., 1999</xref>). Twenty-four hours after flg22 or water pretreatment, we infected the plants by infiltration with the virulent strain <italic>P. syringae</italic> pv <italic>maculicola</italic> ES4326 DG3 (<italic>Pma</italic>DG3; optical density at 600 nm [OD<sub>600</sub>] &equals; 0.0001). Compared with Col-0, <italic>win3-1</italic> showed more bacterial growth and severe disease symptoms in both flg22 and water pretreatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2007</xref>). Flg22 pretreatment induced disease resistance in both Col-0 and <italic>win3-1</italic>. Compared with Col-0, which had 62-fold reduction of bacterial growth in flg22- versus water-pretreated samples, <italic>win3-1</italic> only had 14-fold reduction of bacterial growth in flg22- versus water-pretreated samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). These data suggest that <italic>win3-1</italic> is less responsive to flg22 pretreatment. Consistent with these observations, we found that the <italic>win3-1</italic> seedlings were also less responsive to the inhibition of flg22 on root growth (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). Together, our data indicate a partial contribution of WIN3 in regulating flg22-induced defense.</p><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>WIN3 contributes to flg22-induced resistance to <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> infection. A, Bacterial growth assay. Twenty-five-day-old plants grown in 12-h-light/12-h-dark conditions were pretreated with 1 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> flg22 or water for 24 h before infection with <italic>Pma</italic>DG3 (OD<sub>600</sub> &equals; 0.0001). Bacterial growth was assessed 3 d after infection. Data represent average bacterial numbers in six samples &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc>. Statistical analysis was performed with Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test (StatView 5.0.1). Letters indicate significant differences among the samples (<italic>P</italic> &#x003C; 0.05). B, Disease symptoms. Infected leaves from plants in A were photographed 4 d after infection. These experiments were repeated twice with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_176776_wc_f1" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>WIN3 Regulates Disease Resistance against <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic></title><p>WIN3 is known to regulate resistance to the biotrophic pathogen <italic>P. syringae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jagadeeswaran et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Nobuta et al., 2007</xref>). To further investigate the breadth of disease resistance conferred by WIN3, we infected <italic>win3-1</italic> and Col-0 plants by spraying with <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>, a necrotrophic fungal pathogen. Compared with Col-0, <italic>win3-1</italic> exhibited more severe necrotic lesions on the leaves 2 d after the spray with <italic>Botrytis</italic> spores (10<sup>5</sup> spores mL<sup>&minus;1</sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Disease rating indicated that <italic>Botrytis</italic> susceptibility conferred by <italic>win3-1</italic> was comparable to two known <italic>Botrytis-</italic>susceptible mutants, <italic>jasmonic acid response1-1</italic> (<italic>jar1-1</italic>) and <italic>ethylene insensitive2-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Ferrari et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Genger et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>). It is worth noting that both WIN3 and JAR1 are members of the firefly luciferase family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Staswick et al., 2005</xref>). <italic>Botrytis</italic> susceptibility conferred by <italic>win3-1</italic> was further confirmed with a second <italic>WIN3</italic> allele, <italic>pbs3-1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>WIN3 regulates resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. A, Disease symptoms. Twenty-five-day-old plants grown in 12-h-light/12-h-dark conditions were sprayed with <italic>Botrytis</italic> spore suspension (2 &#x00D7; 10<sup>5</sup> spores mL<sup>&minus;1</sup>) and photographed for disease symptoms 2 d after inoculation. B, Disease rating. Disease symptoms were rated 2 d after inoculation according to the previously described scale (0 &equals; no disease to 6 &equals; extensive disease; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Genger et al., 2008</xref>). Data represent means of the ratings (<italic>n</italic> &#x003E; 12 plants per genotype) &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc>. Statistical analysis was performed with Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test (StatView 5.0.1). Letters indicate significant differences among the samples (<italic>P</italic> &#x003C; 0.05). The key for the genotypes is the same as shown in A. C, Camalexin accumulation. Camalexin was extracted from the infected plants at the indicated time points and quantified by HPLC. The experiments in A and B were repeated four times and that in C was repeated two times, and similar results were obtained. FW, Fresh weight.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_176776_wc_f2" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>In contrast to <italic>win3-1</italic>, <italic>acd6-1</italic>, a gain-of-function mutant with constitutive defense to <italic>P. syringae</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rate et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lu et al., 2003</xref>), displayed hyperresistance to <italic>Botrytis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A and B</xref>). <italic>win3-1</italic> partially suppressed <italic>Botrytis</italic> resistance in <italic>acd6-1</italic>. Camalexin is a phytoalexin that was previously shown to be important to <italic>Botrytis</italic> resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Ferrari et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Stefanato et al., 2009</xref>). However, we did not observe any significant difference in the levels of camalexin in <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> (7.1 &#x00B1; 0.1 &#x03BC;g g<sup>&minus;1</sup> fresh weight) and <italic>acd6-1</italic> (4.4 &#x00B1; 1.7 &#x03BC;g g<sup>&minus;1</sup> fresh weight). Further analyzing camalexin levels in a 48-h time course after <italic>Botrytis</italic> infection revealed no difference in the amount of camalexin and the kinetics of camalexin accumulation in Col-0 and <italic>win3-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>). These results suggest that WIN3-mediated resistance to <italic>Botrytis</italic> is camalexin independent.</p></sec><sec><title>WIN3 and Several SA Regulators Act Together to Affect <italic>acd6-1-</italic>Conferred Phenotypes</title><p>We previously used <italic>acd6-1</italic> as a genetic tool to understand the functional relationships between several SA regulators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Song et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lu et al., 2009</xref>). To elucidate the genetic interaction between WIN3 and other SA regulators, we crossed <italic>win3-1</italic> to several SA mutants, including <italic>pad4-1</italic>, <italic>npr1-1</italic>, and <italic>sid2-1</italic>, in the <italic>acd6-1</italic> background and assessed plant size and defense phenotypes. Like these other SA mutants, we found that <italic>win3-1</italic> suppressed small size, high SA accumulation, and constitutive defense in <italic>acd6-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs. 2&ndash;4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3"></xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4"></xref>). In addition, the triple mutants, <italic>acd6-1win3-1pad4-1</italic>, <italic>acd6-1win3-1npr1-1</italic>, and <italic>acd6-1win3-1sid2-1</italic>, were significantly larger than their respective double mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, A and B</xref>). Consistent with the change of plant size, free and glucosyl-conjugated SA (total SA) levels were drastically reduced in <italic>acd6-1win3-1pad4-1</italic> and <italic>acd6-1win3-1npr1-1</italic> compared with the respective double mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>). We also observed a small but significant decrease of total SA level in <italic>acd6-1win3-1sid2-1</italic> compared with <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> and <italic>acd6-1sid2-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>, inset in top panel).</p><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><italic>win3-1</italic> suppresses dwarfism and SA accumulation in <italic>acd6-1</italic> independently of <italic>pad4-1</italic>, <italic>sid2-1</italic>, or <italic>npr1-1</italic>. A, Twenty-five-day-old plants grown in 16-h-light/8-h-dark conditions. B, Plant size comparison. Plants from A were measured for their rosette diameters (<italic>n</italic> &#x003E; 12). C, SA quantitation. Total and free SA were extracted from plants shown in A and analyzed by HPLC. The inset in the top panel shows SA values of <italic>acd6-1sid2-1</italic> and <italic>acd6-1win3-1sid2-1</italic> to highlight the difference between the two samples. Statistical analysis was performed with Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test (StatView 5.0.1). Letters indicate significant differences among the samples (<italic>P</italic> &#x003C; 0.05). The key for the genotypes of all panels is shown at the bottom of the figure. These experiments were repeated twice with similar results. FW, Fresh weight. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_176776_wc_f3" alt-version="no"/></fig><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><italic>win3-1</italic> suppresses constitutive defense conferred by <italic>acd6-1</italic> independently of <italic>pad4-1</italic>, <italic>sid2-1</italic>, or <italic>npr1-1</italic>. A, Bacterial growth assay. Twenty-five-day-old plants grown in 12-h-light/12-h-dark conditions were inoculated with <italic>Pma</italic>DG3 (OD<sub>600</sub> &equals; 0.0001), and bacterial growth was assessed 3 d after infection. Data for bacterial growth represent averages of six samples &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc>. Statistical analysis was performed with Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test (StatView 5.0.1). Letters indicate significant differences among the samples (<italic>P</italic> &#x003C; 0.05). The number of bacteria inoculated at day 0 was similar in each genotype (data not shown). B, Expression of defense marker genes. Total RNA was extracted from uninfected 25-d-old plants for northern-blot analysis. Probes specific to <italic>PR1</italic>, <italic>PDF1;2</italic>, and <italic>WIN3</italic> were used to study the expression of these genes. <italic>EF1&#x03B1;</italic> was used as a loading control. The key for the genotypes is shown at the bottom of B. These experiments were repeated twice with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_176776_gs_f4" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>To see if changes in plant size and/or SA levels are correlated with the change in disease resistance, we infected these plants with <italic>Pma</italic>DG3. The triple mutants showed a similar susceptibility to <italic>win3-1</italic> but were significantly more susceptible than their respective double mutants, suggesting that <italic>win3-1</italic> and these SA mutants contribute additively to the suppression of <italic>acd6-1-</italic>conferred disease resistance.</p><p>We further examined the expression of defense marker genes in the absence of <italic>P. syringae</italic> infection. We used <italic>PR1</italic> as a marker for SA signaling and <italic>PDF1;2</italic> as a marker for ethylene and jasmonic acid signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Glazebrook et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Penninckx et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Reymond and Farmer, 1998</xref>). We found that expression of <italic>PR1</italic> was completely suppressed but that of <italic>PDF1;2</italic> was highly induced in the triple mutants compared with the double and single mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Such an expression pattern of <italic>PR1</italic> and <italic>PDF1;2</italic> is consistent with the antagonistic effect of SA on ethylene and jasmonic acid in <italic>acd6-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lu et al., 2009</xref>), further supporting a role of WIN3 in regulating SA levels. Together, our results from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref> suggest that WIN3 acts additively with PAD4, NPR1, and SID2 in regulating dwarfism, SA accumulation, and defense responses in <italic>acd6-1</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>WIN3 Modulates Cell Death in <italic>acd6-1</italic></title><p>The SA regulators PAD4, NPR1, and SID2 were shown before to modulate cell death in <italic>acd6-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lu et al., 2009</xref>). To see if WIN3 plays a role in regulating cell death, we examined <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> and related triple mutants for their cell death phenotype with trypan blue staining. We found that, like <italic>pad4-1</italic>, <italic>npr1-1</italic>, and <italic>sid2-1</italic>, <italic>win3-1</italic> also reduced the severity of cell death, in particular the large patches of cell death in <italic>acd6-1</italic>. In addition, the triple mutants <italic>acd6-1win3-1pad4-1</italic>, <italic>acd6-1win3-1npr1-1</italic>, and <italic>acd6-1win3-1sid2-1</italic> had much reduced cell death, compared with the corresponding double mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). These observations suggest that WIN3 acts additively with PAD4, NPR1, and SID2 in controlling cell death. However, residual cell death was still observed in these triple mutants even though their SA levels are less than those in the wild type, corroborating the notion that cell death conferred by <italic>acd6-1</italic> is only partially SA dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lu et al., 2009</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Suppression of cell death in <italic>acd6-1</italic> by <italic>win3-1</italic> is additive to the effect by <italic>pad4-1</italic>, <italic>sid2-1</italic>, or <italic>npr1-1</italic>. The fourth to sixth leaves of the indicated genotypes grown in 16-h-light/8-h-dark conditions were stained with trypan blue as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rate et al., 1999</xref>) and photographed with a dissecting microscope connected to an AxioCam MRc5 camera (Zeiss). Arrows indicate the minor cell death in <italic>acd6-1win3-1sid2-1</italic> and <italic>acd6-1win3-1npr1-1</italic>. No cell death was detected in <italic>pad4-1</italic>, <italic>sid2-1</italic>, and <italic>npr1-1</italic> (data not shown).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_176776_gs_f5" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>SA Signaling and Cell Death Synergistically Promote the Expression of <italic>WIN3</italic></title><p>Previous studies showed that expression of <italic>WIN3</italic> was inducible with <italic>P. syringae</italic> infection or SA treatment and requires multiple SA components (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jagadeeswaran et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2007</xref>). Consistent with these results, we found that <italic>WIN3</italic> transcripts were highly accumulated in <italic>acd6-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). The SA mutants <italic>pad4-1</italic>, <italic>npr1-1</italic>, and <italic>sid2-1</italic> partially suppressed the abundance of <italic>WIN3</italic> transcripts in <italic>acd6-1</italic>. In addition, we found that the small amount of <italic>WIN3</italic> transcripts detected in <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> was completely abolished in the triple mutants. These results further support that the full expression of <italic>WIN3</italic> requires functional PAD4, NPR1, and SID2.</p><p>Interestingly, we noticed that the level of <italic>WIN3</italic> transcripts in <italic>acd6-1</italic> was much higher than that in Col-0 induced by treatment with benzo(1,2,3)thiadiazole-7-carbothioic acid (BTH), a SA agonist (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). This result led us to speculate that activation of SA signaling alone is not enough to activate the high level of <italic>WIN3</italic> expression and that perhaps severe cell death in <italic>acd6-1</italic> also contributes to <italic>WIN3</italic> expression. To test this possibility, we used an inducible system, <italic>acd6-1nahG</italic>, to activate SA signaling and cell death. The transgene <italic>nahG</italic>, which encodes a bacterial SA hydroxylase, is known to completely suppress <italic>acd6-1-</italic>conferred phenotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rate et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Vanacker et al., 2001</xref>). SA signaling and cell death can be reactivated in <italic>acd6-1nahG</italic> with BTH treatment in the presence of light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Vanacker et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lu et al., 2003</xref>). Under this condition, we found that the abundance of <italic>WIN3</italic> transcripts was even higher in <italic>acd6-1nahG</italic> than in <italic>acd6-1</italic>. Although they expressed a similar level of <italic>PR1</italic> (a marker for SA signaling) to that in BTH-treated <italic>acd6-1nahG</italic>, BTH-treated Col-0 and <italic>nahG</italic> showed no cell death and expressed only weak or undetectable <italic>WIN3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). These results clearly indicate that activation of both SA signaling and cell death is necessary for the high expression of the <italic>WIN3</italic> gene. Thus, our data show that while <italic>WIN3</italic> is required for SA-mediated defense and cell death formation, the expression of this gene is likely under a feedback control by these two processes.</p><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Activation of <italic>WIN3</italic> expression by SA signaling and cell death. Twenty-five-day old plants grown in a 16-h-light/8-h-dark cycle were treated with 100 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> BTH or water for 24 h. Cell death was detected by trypan blue staining as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rate et al., 1999</xref>). Total RNA was extracted and analyzed in northern blotting. <italic>EF1&#x03B1;</italic> was used as a loading control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_176776_gs_f6" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>WIN3 and NPR1 Additively Regulate Flowering Time in <italic>acd6-1</italic></title><p>One of the noticeable phenotypes of the <italic>win3-1</italic> mutant was early flowering. To further investigate whether WIN3 plays a role in regulating Arabidopsis flowering, we recorded plant flowering time. In long-day condition (16 h of light/8 h of dark), Col-0 flowered about 22 d after planting and produced an average of 11 leaves at the time of the first appearance of flower buds. The <italic>win3-1</italic> mutant not only flowered earlier (about 17.6 d after planting) but also produced fewer leaves (about 8.5 leaves) at bolting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, A and B</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). While <italic>acd6-1</italic> flowered slightly earlier than Col-0 in one of the two experiments that we conducted, <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> showed the same early flowering as <italic>win3-1</italic>. Since <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> only accumulated 10% of total SA levels seen in <italic>acd6-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>), we concluded that <italic>WIN3</italic>-mediated early flowering is largely SA independent.</p><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>WIN3 and NPR1 act synergistically to regulate the transition to flowering in long-day conditions (16 h of light/8 h of dark). A, Leaf number quantitation. For each genotype (<italic>n</italic> &#x003E; 10), the number of leaves at the appearance of the first flower bud was counted. B, Flowering time measurement. For plants shown in A, the number of days post planting required for the appearance of the first flower bud was recorded. For A and B, statistical analysis was performed with Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test (StatView 5.0.1). Letters indicate significant differences among the samples (<italic>P</italic> &#x003C; 0.05). C, Gene expression in 16-d-old plants. D, Gene expression in 25-d-old plants. For C and D, plant tissue was harvested at 4 <sc>pm</sc> (10 h after light was on in the chamber). Total RNA was extracted from the indicated genotypes and reverse transcribed with the First-Strand cDNA Synthesis kit (Fermentas) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. RT-PCR of 25 and 30 cycles showed similar results of gene expression, and only the results from 30-cycle PCR are shown. <italic>ACTIN</italic> was used as a loading control. The RT-PCR product sizes are as follows: 591 bp for <italic>FLC</italic>, 529 bp for <italic>FT</italic>, and 513 bp for <italic>ACTIN</italic>. The sizes of the corresponding genomic fragments for the genes that can also be amplified with the RT-PCR primers are as follows: 5,592 bp for <italic>FLC</italic>, 2,150 bp for <italic>FT</italic>, and 588 bp for <italic>ACTIN</italic>. Note the absence of genomic fragments for <italic>FLC</italic> and <italic>FT</italic>, due to their large sizes that were not amplified from the genomic DNA template under the RT-PCR conditions. The key for the genotypes in all panels is placed to the right of B. These experiments were repeated two times with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_176776_gs_f7" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>We also observed an early-flowering phenotype in <italic>npr1-1</italic>. Strikingly, the <italic>acd6-1win3-1npr1-1</italic> triple mutant flowered earliest among all the plants tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, A and B</xref>). These results suggest that both WIN3 and NPR1 negatively regulate the transition to flowering, possibly in two independent pathways. Interestingly, <italic>acd6-1npr1-1</italic> flowered about the same time as Col-0, possibly due to the substantial expression of <italic>WIN3</italic> in <italic>acd6-1npr1-1</italic> that can antagonize early flowering conferred by <italic>npr1-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Unlike <italic>acd6-1npr1-1</italic>, <italic>npr1-1</italic> expressed undetectable <italic>WIN3</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>). In addition, our analysis of <italic>pad4-1</italic> and <italic>sid2-1</italic> mutants grown in long-day conditions did not reveal any significant difference in the flowering time in the single mutants and the double mutants in the <italic>acd6-1</italic> background compared with Col-0 and <italic>acd6-1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). However, in the presence of <italic>win3-1</italic>, the triple mutants <italic>acd6-1win3-1sid2-1</italic> and <italic>acd6-1win3-1pad4-1</italic> showed accelerated flowering, further supporting a role of <italic>win3-1</italic> in regulating floral transition.</p><p>In short-day conditions (8 h of light/16 h of dark), the <italic>win3-1</italic> and <italic>npr1-1</italic> mutants had overall delayed flowering with a largely similar pattern as seen in long-day conditions, with <italic>acd6-1win3-1npr1-1</italic> flowering the earliest (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). These results suggest a normal response to the change of light period in these plants. The fact that the single mutants <italic>win3-1</italic> and <italic>acd6-1</italic> had wild-type-like flowering time but the double mutant <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> flowered earlier than the two parental mutants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>) implies that <italic>win3-1</italic> also acts additively with <italic>acd6-1</italic> in regulating flowering time in short-day conditions.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1"><label>Table I.</label><caption><title>WIN3 and NPR1 act synergistically to regulate floral transition in short-day conditions (8 h of light/16 h of dark)</title><p>Flowering time is recorded as the days post planting at the appearance of the first flower bud for each genotype (<italic>n</italic> &#x003E; 10). Statistical analysis was performed with Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test (StatView 5.0.1). Letters indicate significant differences among the samples (<italic>P</italic> &#x003C; 0.05).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Genotype</td><td align="center">Flowering Time</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Col</td><td align="center">87.6 &#x00B1; 1.2 c</td></tr><tr><td><italic>win3-1</italic></td><td align="center">86.7 &#x00B1; 1.7 c</td></tr><tr><td><italic>acd6-1</italic></td><td align="center">90.4 &#x00B1; 2.5 c,d</td></tr><tr><td><italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic></td><td align="center">79.0 &#x00B1; 2.0 b</td></tr><tr><td><italic>acd6-1npr1-1</italic></td><td align="center">93.3 &#x00B1; 0.9 d</td></tr><tr><td><italic>acd6-1win3-1npr1-1</italic></td><td align="center">50.1 &#x00B1; 3.0 a</td></tr><tr><td><italic>npr1-1</italic></td><td align="center">74.3 &#x00B1; 1.7 b</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>To gain further insight into how WIN3 and NPR1 regulate the floral transition, we examined the expression of three genes promoting flowering time, <italic>CONSTANS</italic> (<italic>CO</italic>), <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>), and <italic>SUPPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CONSTANS1</italic> (<italic>SOC1</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Samach et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Wigge et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Yoo et al., 2005</xref>), and one flowering repressor, <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS C</italic> (<italic>FLC</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Michaels and Amasino, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Helliwell et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Searle et al., 2006</xref>). In 16-d-old plants grown in long-day conditions, we found that <italic>FLC</italic> transcripts were lower in the <italic>win3-1</italic> background and in <italic>npr1-1</italic> compared with Col-0 and <italic>acd6-1</italic>. On the other hand, <italic>FT</italic> transcript level remained constant in these plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7C</xref>). In 25-d-old plants grown in the same light regime, we observed a similar suppression of <italic>FLC</italic> expression. By contrast, <italic>FT</italic> transcripts were induced to a higher level in the presence of <italic>win3-1</italic> and in the <italic>npr1-1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7D</xref>). Expression of <italic>CO</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic>, however, remained unchanged in these mutants in both 16- and 25-d-old plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>). These results suggest that the early flowering conferred by <italic>win3-1</italic> and <italic>npr1-1</italic> mutants is via the regulation of <italic>FLC</italic> and <italic>FT</italic> but is independent of <italic>CO</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The type II SA regulator WIN3 was previously shown to regulate resistance to the biotrophic pathogen <italic>P. syringae</italic>. Data reported in this study indicate that WIN3 is also involved in controlling broad-spectrum disease resistance to the necrotrophic pathogen <italic>Botrytis</italic>. Genetic analysis indicated that WIN3 represents a new branch on SA signaling networks, acting together with PAD4, NPR1, and SID2 to regulate plant defense. Our data also revealed novel roles of WIN3 and NPR1 in influencing the transition from vegetative growth to reproductive growth, highlighting the interconnectedness of plant innate immunity and development.</p><sec><title>WIN3 Confers Resistance to Biotrophic and Necrotrophic Pathogens</title><p>Evidence from this report and previous studies indicate that WIN3 confers resistance to biotrophic and necrotrophic pathogens. SA is the key signaling molecule critical for broad-spectrum disease resistance. The susceptibility of the <italic>win3</italic> mutants to bacterial pathogens can be rescued by SA treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jagadeeswaran et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Nobuta et al., 2007</xref>), suggesting that WIN3 acts upstream of SA signaling. We further show here that, like the <italic>sid2</italic> mutant impaired in the major SA biosynthesis, the <italic>win3-1</italic> mutant is partially compromised in response to flg22-induced resistance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). In addition, our data demonstrated that suppression of <italic>acd6-1-</italic>conferred constitutive defense to <italic>P. syringae</italic> by <italic>win3-1</italic> was well correlated with the change of SA levels in <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figs. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref>). Thus, these data indicate that WIN3-conferred resistance to <italic>P. syringae</italic> is largely SA dependent.</p><p>We show here that WIN3 confers resistance to the necrotrophic fungal pathogen <italic>Botrytis</italic>. Our data indicate that such resistance is independent of the phytoalexin camalexin. Interestingly, we observed a correlation of reduced SA accumulation and enhanced <italic>Botrytis</italic> susceptibility in <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>). Since <italic>SID2</italic> contributes to the majority of SA biosynthesis, the fact that the SA level in <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> is only 10% of that in <italic>acd6-1</italic> but higher than that in <italic>acd6-1sid2-1</italic> suggests that WIN3 only partially affects <italic>SID2</italic>-mediated SA biosynthesis. In addition, an even lower SA level was observed in the triple mutant <italic>acd6-1win3-1sid2-1</italic> compared with <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> and <italic>acd6-1sid2-1</italic>, implying that WIN3 also contributes to SID2-independent SA biosynthesis. Since SID2 is not required for resistance to <italic>Botrytis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Govrin and Levine, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Ferrari et al., 2003</xref>), WIN3-mediated resistance to <italic>Botrytis</italic> is possibly through a SID2-independent SA pathway. Alternatively, since SID2-indepdendent SA accumulation is minor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>), it is also possible that WIN3 regulates defense against <italic>Botrytis</italic> in a SA-independent manner.</p></sec><sec><title>WIN3 Represents a Novel Branch in the SA Signaling Networks</title><p><italic>acd6-1</italic> is a small mutant whose size is inversely correlated with its defense levels. We have used this unique feature of <italic>acd6-1</italic> to assess interactions among several known defense genes in a genetic analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Song et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lu et al., 2009</xref>). Using a similar approach, we investigated in this study the interaction of WIN3 with several SA regulators. Our data indicate that WIN3 contributes to SID2-dependent and -independent SA biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>). Although further reduction of SA levels in <italic>acd6-1win3-1sid2-1</italic> was small, suppression of <italic>acd6-1-</italic>conferred disease resistance, cell death and dwarfism was more obvious in the triple mutant than in <italic>acd6-1sid2-1</italic>. One explanation could be that the WIN3-mediated, SID2-independent SA biosynthetic pathway plays a significant role in regulating disease resistance, cell death, and plant size in <italic>acd6-1win3-1sid2-1</italic>. Alternatively, a WIN3-mediated SA-independent pathway is required for these phenotypes conferred by <italic>acd6-1sid2-1</italic>. This interpretation of WIN3 function is supported by the biochemical activity of WIN3. WIN3 was shown to conjugate specific amino acids to its preferred benzoates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Okrent et al., 2009</xref>). Some of these benzoate substrates of WIN3 might be used as precursors for and/or signaling molecules to prime SA biosynthesis in a SID2-dependent and/or SID2-independent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Yalpani et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Ribnicky et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Chong et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Okrent et al., 2009</xref>). It is also possible that WIN3 substrates are engaged in physiological processes not affected by SA. Consistent with the latter notion, microarray analysis using a custom microarray to monitor the expression of 464 pathogen-responsive genes in several defense mutants, <italic>win3</italic>, <italic>sid2</italic>, <italic>eds5</italic>, and <italic>npr1</italic>, revealed that the number of genes affected by <italic>WIN3</italic> was greater than that affected by the major SA regulators, <italic>SID2</italic> and <italic>NPR1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Sato et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Wang et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>Previous genetic analysis with <italic>pad4-1</italic> and <italic>npr1-1</italic> mutants in the <italic>acd6-1</italic> background led us to conclude that NPR1 plays multiple roles in regulating SA-mediated defense, acting as a positive SA signal transducer and a positive and a negative regulator of SA accumulation. The negative role of NPR1 likely requires PAD4 to form a negative feedback loop in regulating SA levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lu et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). Our analysis of <italic>acd6-1win3-1npr1-1</italic> further corroborates multiple roles of NPR1 in regulating SA-mediated defense. Similar to <italic>pad4-1</italic>, <italic>win3-1</italic> greatly suppressed the high levels of SA in <italic>acd6-1npr1-1</italic>, suggesting that WIN3 is also part of a negative feedback loop of NPR1 in regulating SA accumulation. In addition, our data show that the suppression of <italic>acd6-1-</italic>conferred phenotypes by <italic>pad4-1</italic> and <italic>win3-1</italic> is additive, suggesting that WIN3 and PAD4 act in separate pathways (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). Together, these observations implicate more than one negative feedback loop involving NPR1 and PAD4, WIN3, and/or possibly other SA regulators to keep SA signaling networks in check. Interestingly, expression of <italic>WIN3</italic> is partially dependent on several SA regulators (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jagadeeswaran et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2007</xref>), possibly due to the effects of these SA regulators on SA accumulation and/or signaling. Together, these data suggest that WIN3 represents a novel node in the SA signaling networks. A model to summarize the role of WIN3 and other SA regulators in controlling SA signaling is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref>.</p><fig id="fig8"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>A model of action for WIN3. The SA signaling networks can be viewed in three interconnected regulatory subcircuits. WIN3 is a type II SA regulator that affects the accumulation of SA not by directly participating in SA biosynthesis but possibly through modifying precursors or signaling molecules for SA synthesis. WIN3 contributes to SID2-dependent and -independent pathways. WIN3 acts additively with another type II SA regulator, PAD4, to affect SA accumulation. Both WIN3 and PAD4 form positive signal amplification loops with SA. NPR1 can positively transduce SA signaling and affect SA accumulation. NPR1 can also negatively regulate SA levels, involving both WIN3 and PAD4. WIN3 and NPR1 act in separate pathways to regulate the floral transition by affecting the expression of <italic>FLC</italic> and <italic>FT</italic> genes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_176776_lw_f8" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>WIN3 and NPR1 Act Additively in Regulating the Transition to Reproduction</title><p>Previous studies implicate a positive role of SA in influencing flowering time. For instance, exogenous SA application accelerates the floral transition in many plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Cleland and Tanaka, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Cleland and Ben-Tal, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Endo et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Wada et al., 2009</xref>). UV-C treatment or infection with <italic>P. syringae</italic>, which potentially activate SA accumulation and/or signaling, also shortens flowering time in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Korves and Bergelson, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2004</xref>). In addition, some mutants with reduced SA levels demonstrate delayed flowering, while other mutants with increased SA levels show accelerated flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Jin et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">March-D&#x00ED;az et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>In contrast to the positive role of SA and some SA genes in regulating flowering time suggested by these previous studies, our data implicate a negative role of WIN3 and NPR1 in flowering time control. Although <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic> and <italic>acd6-1win3-1npr1-1</italic> accumulated much reduced SA levels compared with <italic>acd6-1</italic>, these plants flowered much earlier than <italic>acd6-1</italic> and Col-0, suggesting that WIN3 and NPR1 control of flowering time is largely SA independent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). The fact that <italic>acd6-1win3-1npr1-1</italic> flowered the earliest among all the plants tested under both long-day and short-day conditions suggests that WIN3 and NPR1 act in two independent pathways to regulate flowering time. A previous study showed that the SA-deficient mutant <italic>sid2-1</italic> flowered late in short-day conditions but not in long-day conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Mart&#x00ED;nez et al., 2004</xref>). Consistent with these results, we did not observe delayed flowering in <italic>sid2-1</italic> in long-day conditions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>).</p><p>How does WIN3 control flowering time? As discussed earlier, biochemical analysis of the WIN3 protein and gene expression profiling analysis by microarray with <italic>win3</italic> and other mutants disrupting SA signaling suggest the possibility that WIN3 acts in a SA-independent pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Wang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Okrent et al., 2009</xref>). Our data indicate that WIN3-mediated flowering is largely SA independent, possibly through the suppression of the major flowering repressor FLC and the activation of the positive flowering regulator FT. Since WIN3 is an enzyme that does not have a nucleus localization motif, it is less likely that WIN3 exerts a direct transcriptional control of <italic>FLC</italic> and <italic>FT</italic> genes. However, it is possible that in the absence of WIN3, accumulation of WIN3-preferred benzoate substrate(s) or their upstream compounds, and/or the lack of a certain product(s) downstream of benzoate production and/or modification, signal the control of expression of these flowering regulatory genes.</p><p>Like WIN3, NPR1 also regulates the expression of <italic>FLC</italic> and <italic>FT</italic>. As a transcription coregulator, NPR1 might function by interacting with transcription factors, such as members in the TGA protein family, to directly affect the expression of these flowering regulatory genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Zhang et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Despr&#x00E9;s et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Zhou et al., 2000</xref>). One such TGA protein is likely TGA4, which was shown to bind to the promoter of <italic>FT</italic> to control flowering time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Song et al., 2008</xref>). In addition, our data showed that higher expression of <italic>FT</italic> was only observed in 25-d-old but not in 16-d-old plants, suggesting that WIN3- and NPR1-regulated <italic>FT</italic> expression is also development related.</p><p>Multiple intrinsic and extrinsic factors are known to regulate plant flowering. Since <italic>win3-1</italic> and <italic>npr1-1</italic> mutants demonstrated a similar early flowering pattern in both long-day and short-day conditions, we speculate that WIN3 and NPR1 function independently of the photoperiod pathway. The biological clock is another main factor that determines flowering time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">McClung, 2001</xref>). Increasing evidence shows that the biological clock also controls the innate immunity in Arabidopsis. For instance, the component of the central oscillator of the Arabidopsis clock, CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED1, was recently shown to play a direct role in plant defense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Wang et al., 2011b</xref>). In addition, the expression of some defense genes is also known to be under the control of the biological clock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Wang et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">2011a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Sauerbrunn and Schlaich, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Weyman et al., 2006</xref>). However, we did not detect any change in the expression of the circadian clock-regulated gene <italic>CO</italic> in both <italic>win3</italic> and <italic>npr1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Su&#x00E1;rez-L&#x00F3;pez et al., 2001</xref>) compared with Col-0. In addition, we recently showed that expression of <italic>NPR1</italic> was not affected by the biological clock under our growth conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Wang et al., 2011a</xref>). Therefore, evidence from our studies did not support a role of the biological clock in regulating WIN3- and NPR1-mediated flowering time control. Further investigation should elucidate if WIN3 and NPR1 cross talk to other flowering pathways, such as the autonomous, hormone, and vernalization pathways, and uncover how these other flowering pathways are linked to plant innate immunity</p><p>To summarize the role of WIN3 and NPR1 in regulating SA-mediated defense and flowering time, we present the model in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8</xref>. In this model, we view the SA signaling networks in three interconnected regulatory subcircuits. WIN3 is a type II SA regulator that represents a novel node in the SA signaling networks. WIN3 contributes to SID2-dependent and -independent SA biosynthesis, possibly through its function in modifying benzoate substrates. Genetic analysis showed that WIN3 acts additively with another type II SA regulator, PAD4, to affect SA accumulation. Both WIN3 and PAD4 form positive signal amplification loops with SA. On the other hand, NPR1 has multiple roles in regulating SA defense. It cannot only positively transduce SA signaling and affect SA accumulation but also can negatively regulate SA levels. The negative role of NPR1 on SA accumulation likely involves both WIN3 and PAD4. In addition, the SA signaling networks cross talk with plant development, affecting the floral transition. While an increased SA level can lead to accelerated flowering, WIN3 and NPR1 are repressors of the floral transition through separate pathways to affect the expression of <italic>FLC</italic> and <italic>FT</italic> genes.</p><p>Taken together, we show that the SA regulator WIN3 plays multiple roles in controlling broad-spectrum disease resistance, cell death, and flowering time. The fact that two major SA regulatory genes, WIN3 and NPR1, are involved in determining the floral transition strongly supports the idea that plant innate immunity and development are intimately connected. Diseases, of course, can be devastating to crop plants, but disease resistance is also energetically costly. Under defense conditions, making an accelerated transition to the reproductive phase is crucial to the long-term fitness of plants. A better understanding of how plants adjust their growth and reproduction in response to pathogen attack should make it possible to positively manipulate overall crop yield.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Plant Materials</title><p>All Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) plants were grown in growth chambers with light intensity at 200 &#x03BC;mol m<sup>&minus;2</sup> s<sup>&minus;1</sup>, 60% humidity, and 22&#x00B0;C. Unless otherwise indicated, plant materials used in this paper are in the Col-0 background. Pathogen infection, flg22 and BTH treatments, and sample collection for RNA, SA, and camalexin analyses and cell death staining were done 6 h after light was on in the growth chamber. For each experiment, appropriate controls were included. Transgenic plant <italic>nahG</italic> and mutants (<italic>acd6-1</italic>, <italic>npr1-1</italic>, and the double mutants in the <italic>acd6-1</italic> background) were described before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rate et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lu et al., 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Song et al., 2004</xref>). <italic>win3-1</italic> was previously designated <italic>win3-T</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2007</xref>). <italic>acd6-1win3-1</italic>, <italic>acd6-1win3-1pad4-1</italic>, <italic>acd6-1win3-1sid2-1</italic>, and <italic>acd6-1win3-1npr1-1</italic> were made by genetic crosses and confirmed with cleaved amplified polymorphic sequence markers or other PCR markers corresponding to each single mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lu et al., 2009</xref>). The <italic>pbs3-1</italic> and <italic>pbs3-2</italic> seeds were provided by Mary Wildermuth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Nobuta et al., 2007</xref>). The <italic>fls2</italic> mutant (SALK_062054) was obtained from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center and confirmed with PCR primers At5g46330_937f (5&#x2032;-CAAGCACTCCGGATATACAAGAAC-3&#x2032;), At5g46330_1323r (5&#x2032;-CGGGATCTCGCCAGTCATT-3&#x2032;), and LBb1 (5&#x2032;-GCGTGGACCGCTTGCTGCAACT-3&#x2032;).</p></sec><sec><title>Bacterial and Fungal Infection</title><p><italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv <italic>maculicola</italic> ES4326 strain DG3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Guttman and Greenberg, 2001</xref>) was used to infect 25-d-old plants grown in a chamber with a 12-h-light/12-h-dark cycle. The infection was conducted by infiltrating bacterial solution with a 1-mL needleless syringe to the abaxial side of the fifth to seventh leaves. Bacterial culturing, infection, and growth analysis were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Greenberg et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lu et al., 2003</xref>). For flg22 treatment, 1 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> flg22 (GenScript USA) was infiltrated into the leaves 24 h prior to <italic>Pma</italic> infection.</p><p><italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> was provided by Tesfaye Mengiste at Purdue University. <italic>Botrytis</italic> culture and infection were performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Veronese et al., 2004</xref>). Briefly, <italic>Botrytis</italic> was cultured on a plate containing 4% potato dextrose agar at room temperature for 3 to 4 weeks. Spores were harvested and resuspended in a broth containing 1% Difco sabouraud maltose. The 25-d-old plants grown in a chamber with a 12-h-light/12-h-dark cycle were sprayed with 2 &#x00D7; 10<sup>5</sup> spores mL<sup>&minus;1</sup> and covered with a clear plastic dome to maintain high humidity. The disease rating was performed 2 d after the infection with a rating scale similar to one described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Genger et al., 2008</xref>). The rating scale was as follows: 0 &equals; no detectable lesions; 1 &equals; small rare lesions; 2 &equals; lesions on up to 10% of leaves; 3 &equals; lesions on up to 10% to 30% of leaves; 4 &equals; lesions on up to 30% to 60% of leaves; 5 &equals; lesions on up to 60% to 80% of leaves; and 6 &equals; less than 10% of green leaves remained.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Death Activation in <italic>acd6-1nahG</italic> and Cell Death Staining</title><p>To activate cell death, we sprayed 25-d-old <italic>acd6-1nahG</italic> and control plants, Col-0, <italic>acd6-1</italic>, and <italic>nahG</italic>, with 100 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> BTH or water. BTH was kindly provided by Robert Dietrich (Syngenta). The plants were grown in a chamber with a 16-h-light/8-h-dark cycle. Twenty-four hours after the treatments, leaves of all treated plants were collected for RNA analysis.</p><p>Trypan blue staining for cell death was performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rate et al., 1999</xref>). Stained leaves were examined with a Stemi SV 1.1 stereomicroscope (Zeiss), and photographs were taken with an AxioCam MRc5 camera (Zeiss) connected to the microscope.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA Analysis</title><p>Total RNA was isolated from infected leaves or whole mutant plants using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen). Northern blotting was performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lu et al., 2003</xref>). DNA templates for making radioactive probes were obtained by PCR with specific primers for each gene and labeled with [<sup>32</sup>P]dCTP in a PCR with a gene-specific antisense primer. For reverse transcription (RT)-PCR, total RNA was reverse transcribed into cDNAs using the First-Strand cDNA Synthesis kit (Fermentas) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. Primers specific for each gene were used in PCR to amplify the corresponding gene. These primers were designed to specifically amplify RT-PCR products and avoid the contamination from the PCR products amplified from genomic DNA template. The RT-PCR product sizes for these genes should be 300 bp for <italic>CO</italic>, 591 bp for <italic>FLC</italic>, 529 bp for <italic>FT</italic>, 536 bp for <italic>SOC1</italic>, and 513 bp for <italic>ACTIN</italic>. The sizes of the corresponding genomic fragments for these genes that can be amplified with the RT-PCR primers are 5,592 bp for <italic>FLC</italic>, 2,150 bp for <italic>FT</italic>, 2,275 bp for <italic>SOC1</italic>, and 588 bp for <italic>ACTIN</italic>. Due to their large sizes, the genomic DNA fragments for <italic>FLC</italic>, <italic>FT</italic>, and <italic>SOC1</italic> should not be amplified from genomic DNA under the conditions used for RT-PCR. For <italic>CO</italic>, the primers anchor on the junctions of two exons; therefore, no PCR product should be amplified with the genomic DNA template. Primers used for making radioactive probes and for RT-PCR are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec><title>SA and Camalexin Measurement</title><p>SA and camalexin were extracted as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lu et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Song et al., 2004</xref>). Briefly, 200 mg of leaf tissue from plants grown in a chamber with a 16-h-light/8-h-dark cycle was ground to fine powder with liquid nitrogen and extracted once with 1.5 mL of 90% methanol followed by one extraction with 1.5 mL of 100% methanol. For each sample, 500 ng of <italic>o</italic>-anisic acid (Sigma 169978) was added as the internal control during the first extraction. Each data point had three replicates. The methanol fraction was equally split into two microcentrifuge tubes and dried in the fume hood overnight. The pellet was dissolved by adding 500 &#x03BC;L of 100 m<sc>m</sc> sodium acetate (pH 5.5). To half of the duplicated samples, 40 units of &#x03B2;-glucosidase (Sigma G-0395) was added to digest glucosyl-conjugated SA (total SA) for 1.5 h at 37&#x00B0;C. All the samples were treated with an equal volume of 10% TCA and centrifuged at 10,000<italic>g</italic> for 10 min. The supernatant was extracted twice with 1 mL of extraction solvent (ethylacetate:cyclopentane:2-propanol 100:99:1, v/v). The top (organic) phase was collected in a microcentrifuge tube and dried in a fume hood overnight. The residual fraction was resuspended in 0.5 mL of 55% methanol by vortex and was passed through a 0.2-&#x03BC;m nylon spin-prep membrane (Fisher 07-200-389) via centrifugation for 2 min (14,000<italic>g</italic>) before being subjected to HPLC analysis. A Dionex AS50 HPLC instrument with an Acclaim 120 C18 reverse column (4.6 &#x00D7; 250mm) and an RF2000 fluorescence detector was used to separate and detect <italic>o</italic>-anisic acid, SA, and camalexin. The mobile phase included a gradient of methanol and 0.5% acetic acid. <italic>o</italic>-Anisic acid was detected at 4.9 min with 301-nm excitation/365-nm emission, SA was detected at 6.5 min with 301-nm excitation/412-nm emission, and camalexin was detected at 8.6 min with 318-nm excitation/385-nm emission. The standard curve was made from quantification of <italic>o</italic>-anisic acid, SA, and camalexin at concentrations of 50, 100, 250, 500, and 1,000 ng mL<sup>&minus;1</sup> and was used to calculate the final concentration in each sample with Excel software (Microsoft).</p></sec><sec><title>Flowering Time Determination and Plant Size Quantitation</title><p>To determine flowering time, the number of rosette leaves at bolting and/or the number of days post planting at the appearance of the first flower bud were counted for plants grown in long-day (16 h of light/8 h of dark) and short-day (8 h of light/16 h of dark) chambers. For size determination, 25-d-old plants grown in a long-day chamber were measured for rosette diameter.</p><p>Sequence data from this article can be found in the GenBank/EMBL data libraries under accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="At5g13320">At5g13320</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Figure S1</ext-link>.</bold> The <italic>win3-1</italic> mutant is less responsive to flg22 treatment in root growth assay.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Figure S2</ext-link>.</bold> The <italic>pbs3</italic> mutants are more susceptible to <italic>Botrytis</italic> infection.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Figure S3</ext-link>.</bold> <italic>WIN3</italic> expression in SA mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Figure S4</ext-link>.</bold> Expression of <italic>CO</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic> is constant in <italic>win3-1</italic> and <italic>npr1-1</italic> mutants in long-day conditions (16 h of light/8 h of dark).</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.</bold> Flowering time in plants grown in long-day conditions (16 h of light/8 h of dark).</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.176776/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>.</bold> Primer sets used in northern blotting and RT-PCR.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Drs. Jean Greenberg at the University of Chicago, Stephen Miller at the University of Maryland Baltimore County, John Larkin at Louisiana State University, and Mary Wildermuth at the University of California, Berkeley, for critical comments on the manuscript. We thank our colleagues at University of Maryland Baltimore County Dr. William LaCourse for sharing the use of his HPLC instrument, Dr. Charles Bieberich for sharing the use of his dissecting microscope, and Mr. Tim Ford for taking photographs for this publication.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gobbato</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bednarek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Debey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultze</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bautor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Salicylic acid-independent ENHANCED DISEASE SUSCEPTIBILITY1 signaling in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> immunity and cell death is regulated by the monooxygenase FMO1 and the Nudix hydrolase NUDT7</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1038</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1051</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Glazebrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Volko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis NPR1</italic> gene that controls systemic acquired resistance encodes a novel protein containing ankyrin repeats</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>63</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Biosynthesis of salicylic acid in plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Signal Behav</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>493</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>496</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chisholm</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Coaker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Staskawicz</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Host-microbe interactions: shaping the evolution of the plant immune response</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>803</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>814</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierrel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Atanassova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Werck-Reichhart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritig</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Saindrenan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Free and conjugated benzoic acid in tobacco plants and cell cultures: induced accumulation upon elicitation of defense responses and role as salicylic acid precursors</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>318</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>328</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Tal</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Influence of giving salicylic acid for different time periods on flowering and growth in the long-day plant <italic>Lemna gibba</italic> G3</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>290</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Effect of daylength on the ability of salicylic acid to induce flowering in the long-day plant <italic>Lemna gibba</italic> G3 and the short-day plant <italic>Lemna paucicostata</italic> 6746</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>424</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Despr&#x00E9;s</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaze</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fobert</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> NPR1/NIM1 protein enhances the DNA binding activity of a subgroup of the TGA family of bZIP transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>290</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>NPR1, all things considered</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>547</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>552</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durrant</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Systemic acquired resistance</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>209</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikegami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Beppu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Induction of flowering by inducers of systemic acquired resistance in the Lemna plant</article-title>. <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>185</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Feys</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>EDS1, an essential component of R gene-mediated disease resistance in Arabidopsis has homology to eukaryotic lipases</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>3292</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3297</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>In vivo interaction between NPR1 and transcription factor TGA2 leads to salicylic acid-mediated gene activation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1377</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1389</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Volko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Plants have a sensitive perception system for the most conserved domain of bacterial flagellin</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>276</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Plotnikova</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>De Lorenzo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis local resistance to <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> involves salicylic acid and camalexin and requires EDS4 and PAD2, but not SID2, EDS5 or PAD4</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>205</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feys</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moisan</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Direct interaction between the Arabidopsis disease resistance signaling proteins, EDS1 and PAD4</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>5400</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5411</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Genger</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurkowski</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Signaling pathways that regulate the enhanced disease resistance of Arabidopsis &#x201C;defense, no death&#x201D; mutants</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1285</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1296</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Genoud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchala</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00E9;traux</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome signalling modulates the SA-perceptive pathway in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>95</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glazebrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zook</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Crute</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Holub</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammerschmidt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Phytoalexin-deficient mutants of Arabidopsis reveal that <italic>PAD4</italic> encodes a regulatory factor and that four <italic>PAD</italic> genes contribute to downy mildew resistance</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>146</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>392</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goritschnig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The ubiquitin pathway is required for innate immunity in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>540</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>551</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Govrin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Infection of Arabidopsis with a necrotrophic pathogen, <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>, elicits various defense responses but does not induce systemic acquired resistance (SAR)</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>276</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Uncoupling salicylic acid-dependent cell death and defense-related responses from disease resistance in the Arabidopsis mutant <italic>acd5</italic></article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>156</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>350</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griebel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Light regulation and daytime dependency of inducible plant defenses in Arabidopsis: phytochrome signaling controls systemic acquired resistance rather than local defense</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>790</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>801</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guttman</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Functional analysis of the type III effectors AvrRpt2 and AvrRpm1 of Pseudomonas syringae with the use of a single-copy genomic integration system</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>155</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Resistance gene-dependent plant defense responses</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1773</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1791</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helliwell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis FLC protein interacts directly in vivo with SOC1 and FT chromatin and is part of a high-molecular-weight protein complex</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>192</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jagadeeswaran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Raina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosher</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Klessig</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Raina</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis GH3-LIKE DEFENSE GENE 1 is required for accumulation of salicylic acid, activation of defense responses and resistance to <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>234</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>246</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Oosten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The SUMO E3 ligase, AtSIZ1, regulates flowering by controlling a salicylic acid-mediated floral promotion pathway and through affects on FLC chromatin structure</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>530</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>540</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jirage</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tootle</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuber</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Feys</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Glazebrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> PAD4 encodes a lipase-like gene that is important for salicylic acid signaling</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>13583</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>13588</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dangl</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The plant immune system</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>444</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>329</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korves</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergelson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A developmental response to pathogen infection in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>339</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>347</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A key role for the Arabidopsis WIN3 protein in disease resistance triggered by <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> that secrete AvrRpt2</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1192</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1200</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Dissection of salicylic acid-mediated defense signaling networks</article-title>. <source>Plant Signal Behav</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>713</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>717</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rate</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>ACD6, a novel ankyrin protein, is a regulator and an effector of salicylic acid signaling in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> defense response</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2408</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2420</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Salimian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamelin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedorowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>LaCourse</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genetic analysis of <italic>acd6-1</italic> reveals complex defense networks and leads to identification of novel defense genes in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>412</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>March-D&#x00ED;az</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x00ED;a-Dom&#x00ED;nguez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano-Juste</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Le&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Florencio</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Histone H2A.Z and homologues of components of the SWR1 complex are required to control immunity in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>487</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Prats</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Le&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Salicylic acid regulates flowering time and links defence responses and reproductive development</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>217</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Circadian rhythms in plants</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>162</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Loss of FLOWERING LOCUS C activity eliminates the late-flowering phenotype of FRIGIDA and autonomous pathway mutations but not responsiveness to vernalization</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>941</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Inducers of plant systemic acquired resistance regulate NPR1 function through redox changes</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>944</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nawrath</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parinthawong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00E9;traux</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>EDS5, an essential component of salicylic acid-dependent signaling for disease resistance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, is a member of the MATE transporter family</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>286</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nobuta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Okrent</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoutemyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodibaugh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kempema</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wildermuth</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Innes</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The GH3 acyl adenylase family member PBS3 regulates salicylic acid-dependent defense responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>144</volume>: <fpage>1144</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1156</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okrent</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wildermuth</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis GH3.12 (PBS3) conjugates amino acids to 4-substituted benzoates and is inhibited by salicylate</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>284</volume>: <fpage>9742</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>9754</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>An importin alpha homolog, MOS6, plays an important role in plant innate immunity</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1129</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1135</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Regulation of plant innate immunity by three proteins in a complex conserved across the plant and animal kingdoms</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1484</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1493</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penninckx</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomma</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00E9;traux</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Concomitant activation of jasmonate and ethylene response pathways is required for induction of a plant defensin gene in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>2103</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2113</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rate</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuenca</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Guttman</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The gain-of-function <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> <italic>acd6</italic> mutant reveals novel regulation and function of the salicylic acid signaling pathway in controlling cell death, defenses, and cell growth</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1695</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1708</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reymond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Jasmonate and salicylate as global signals for defense gene expression</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>404</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>411</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ribnicky</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shulaev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Raskin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Intermediates of salicylic acid biosynthesis in tobacco</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>565</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>572</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryals</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weymann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jesse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> NIM1 protein shows homology to the mammalian transcription factor inhibitor I kappa B</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>439</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryals</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuenschwander</surname><given-names>UH</given-names></name><name><surname>Willits</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Systemic acquired resistance</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1809</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1819</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Onouchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ditta</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz-Sommer</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Distinct roles of CONSTANS target genes in reproductive development of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>288</volume>: <fpage>1613</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1616</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Spivey</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewdney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Denoux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Glazebrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A high-performance, small-scale microarray for expression profiling of many samples in Arabidopsis-pathogen studies</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>565</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>577</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauerbrunn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlaich</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>PCC1: a merging point for pathogen defence and circadian signalling in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>218</volume>: <fpage>552</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>561</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Turck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x00F6;ber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The transcription factor FLC confers a flowering response to vernalization by repressing meristem competence and systemic signaling in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>898</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>912</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Klessig</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Characterization of a salicylic acid-insensitive mutant (<italic>sai1</italic>) of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, identified in a selective screen utilizing the SA-inducible expression of the <italic>tms2</italic> gene</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>78</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A key role for ALD1 in activation of local and systemic defenses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>200</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>212</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Isolation of CONSTANS as a TGA4/OBF4 interacting protein</article-title>. <source>Mol Cells</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>559</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>565</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staswick</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Serban</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiryaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Suza</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Characterization of an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> enzyme family that conjugates amino acids to indole-3-acetic acid</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>616</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>627</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stefanato</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Abou-Mansour</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretschmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosbach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bochet</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00E9;traux</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoonbeek</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The ABC transporter BcatrB from <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> exports camalexin and is a virulence factor on <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>499</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>510</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su&#x00E1;rez-L&#x00F3;pez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheatley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Robson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Onouchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Valverde</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>CONSTANS mediates between the circadian clock and the control of flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>410</volume>: <fpage>1116</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1120</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Todesco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Traw</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Epple</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhns</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sureshkumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Natural allelic variation underlying a major fitness trade-off in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>465</volume>: <fpage>632</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>636</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Glazebrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Interplay between MAMP-triggered and SA-mediated defense responses</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>763</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>775</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanacker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rate</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A role for salicylic acid and NPR1 in regulating cell growth in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>216</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veronese</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Bluhm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmeron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mengiste</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The BOS loci of Arabidopsis are required for resistance to <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>558</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>574</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiraya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Salicylic acid and the flowering gene FLOWERING LOCUS T homolog are involved in poor-nutrition stress-induced flowering of Pharbitis nil</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source> <volume>167</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>452</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Battle</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011a</year>) <article-title>Circadian clock-regulated phosphate transporter PHT4;1 plays an important role in Arabidopsis defense</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant</source> <comment>(in press)</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasselmann</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenarz-Wyatt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Katagiri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Glazebrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The genetic network controlling the Arabidopsis transcriptional response to <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv. <italic>maculicola</italic>: roles of major regulators and the phytotoxin coronatine</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1408</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1420</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnaby</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>T&#x00F6;r</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldelari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DU</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011b</year>) <article-title>Timing of plant immune responses by a central circadian regulator</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>470</volume>: <fpage>110</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>114</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanouchi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Katayose</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Expression of the <italic>Pib</italic> rice-blast-resistance gene family is up-regulated by environmental conditions favouring infection and by chemical signals that trigger secondary plant defences</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>653</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>661</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weyman</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilchrist</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bostock</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A circadian rhythm-regulated tomato gene is induced by arachidonic acid and <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>248</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wigge</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Integration of spatial and temporal information during floral induction in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>1056</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1059</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wildermuth</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewdney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Isochorismate synthase is required to synthesize salicylic acid for plant defence</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>414</volume>: <fpage>562</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>565</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yalpani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Raskin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Pathway of salicylic acid biosynthesis in healthy and virus-inoculated tobacco</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>321</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>CONSTANS activates SUPPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CONSTANS 1 through FLOWERING LOCUS T to promote flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>770</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>778</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>MOS2, a protein containing G-patch and KOW motifs, is essential for innate immunity in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1936</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1942</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinkema</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Interaction of NPR1 with basic leucine zipper protein transcription factors that bind sequences required for salicylic acid induction of the PR-1 gene</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>6523</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>6528</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A putative nucleoporin 96 is required for both basal defense and constitutive resistance responses mediated by suppressor of npr1-1,constitutive 1</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1306</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1316</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Trifa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Klessig</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>NPR1 differentially interacts with members of the TGA/OBF family of transcription factors that bind an element of the PR-1 gene required for induction by salicylic acid</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>202</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Plants and animals: a different taste for microbes?</article-title> <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>360</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
