<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">153676</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.153676</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>ENVIRONMENTAL STRESS AND ADAPTATION TO STRESS</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Deregulated Copper Transport Affects Arabidopsis Development Especially in the Absence of Environmental Cycles<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[C]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4"><sup>[W]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Andr&eacute;s-Col&aacute;s</surname><given-names>Nuria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perea-Garc&iacute;a</surname><given-names>Ana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>Sergi</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Pe&ntilde;arrubia</surname><given-names>Lola</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&ast;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Departament de Bioqu&iacute;mica i Biologia Molecular, Universitat de Val&egrave;ncia, E&ndash;46100 Burjassot, Valencia, Spain</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&ast;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>penarrub@uv.es</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation (grant nos. BIO2008&ndash;02835 and CSD2007&ndash;00057 to L.P. and predoctoral Formaci&oacute;n del Personal Investigador fellowship to A.P.-G.), by Fondo Europeo de Desarrollo Regional funds from the European Union, and by the Fundaci&oacute; General de la Universitat de Val&egrave;ncia (to S.P.).</p></fn><fn id="fn2" fn-type="equal"><label>2</label><p>These authors contributed equally to the article.</p></fn><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Lola Pe&ntilde;arrubia(<email>penarrub@uv.es</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[C]</label><p>Some figures in this article are displayed in color online but in black and white in the print edition.</p></fn><fn id="fn4"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.110.153676">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.110.153676</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>5</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>153</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2010 American Society of Plant Biologists</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year></permissions><abstract><p>Copper is an essential cofactor for key processes in plants, but it exerts harmful effects when in excess. Previous work has shown that the Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) COPT1 high-affinity copper transport protein participates in copper uptake through plant root tips. Here, we show that COPT1 protein localizes to the plasma membrane of Arabidopsis cells and the phenotypic effects of transgenic plants overexpressing either <italic>COPT1</italic> or <italic>COPT3</italic>, the latter being another high-affinity copper transport protein family member. Both transgenic lines exhibit increased endogenous copper levels and are sensitive to the copper in the growth medium. Additional phenotypes include decreased hypocotyl growth in red light and differentially affected flowering times depending on the photoperiod. Furthermore, in the absence of environmental cycles, such as light and temperature, the survival of plants overexpressing <italic>COPT1</italic> or <italic>COPT3</italic> is compromised. Consistent with altered circadian rhythms, the expression of the nuclear circadian clock genes <italic>CIRCADIAN CLOCK-ASSOCIATED1</italic> (<italic>CCA1</italic>) and <italic>LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL</italic> (<italic>LHY</italic>) is substantially reduced in either <italic>COPT1-</italic> or <italic>COPT3</italic>-overexpressing plants. Copper affects the amplitude and the phase, but not the period, of the <italic>CCA1</italic> and <italic>LHY</italic> oscillations in wild-type plants. Copper also drives a reduction in the expression of circadian clock output genes. These results reveal that the spatiotemporal control of copper transport is a key aspect of metal homeostasis that is required for Arabidopsis fitness, especially in the absence of environmental cues.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Copper (Cu) is an essential micronutrient that participates as a redox catalytic cofactor in fundamental biological pathways. In higher plants, Cu is directly involved in a wide range of physiological processes, including photosynthesis, respiration, superoxide scavenging, cell wall metabolism, and perception of ethylene. A conserved family of high-affinity Cu transport proteins, denoted as the CTR family, mediates Cu acquisition in eukaryotic cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Puig and Thiele, 2002</xref>). Complementation assays using <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> strains defective in Cu uptake (<italic>ctr1&Delta;ctr3&Delta;</italic> yeast mutants) have allowed the identification of a family of six putative CTR high-affinity Cu transport proteins, know as COPT1 to -6, in the model plant Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sancenon et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Pe&ntilde;arrubia et al., 2010</xref>). COPT1 is the first COPT family member to have been identified and characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Kampfenkel et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Sancenon et al., 2004</xref>). Arabidopsis seedlings defective in <italic>COPT1</italic> expression display a significant decrease in Cu acquisition and accumulation, increased root length under Cu-limited conditions, and defects in mature pollen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Sancenon et al., 2004</xref>). These phenotypes are consistent with the <italic>COPT1</italic> expression in root tips and pollen grains, and they strongly suggest a predominant function for COPT1 in soil Cu acquisition and pollen development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Sancenon et al., 2004</xref>). The heterologous expression in yeast indicates that the COPT1 transporter is highly specific for Cu<sup>&plus;</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sancenon et al., 2003</xref>), similar to the Cu transporters of the CTR family from other eukaryotic organisms, and that it functions in transporting Cu<sup>&plus;</sup> toward the cytosolic compartment. After transport through the membrane, Cu is delivered to target subcellular compartments and cuproproteins by specific and conserved cytosolic metallochaperones (for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Puig et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Burkhead et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Puig and Pe&ntilde;arrubia, 2009</xref>).</p><p>At elevated concentrations, Cu leads to the generation of harmful reactive oxygen species, which cause oxidative damage to cells at the level of lipids, proteins, and nucleic acids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Halliwell and Gutteridge, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Drazkiewicz et al., 2004</xref>). Moreover, when in excess, Cu can replace other metal cofactors from their natural ligands in important metalloproteins, including magnesium in chlorophyll, thus further contributing to its cytotoxicity (for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Maksymiec, 1997; Pena et al., 1999</xref>). The widespread use of inappropriate agricultural practices (such as the excessive utilization of fungicides with elevated Cu concentrations), the production of industrial wastewaters, and mining activities have caused growing Cu contamination of cultivating soils and irrigating waters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">He et al., 2005</xref>). Symptoms of excess Cu in plants include chlorosis, fewer and smaller leaves, diminished root growth, and flowering and germination defects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">M&auml;rschner, 2002</xref>). When the environmental Cu concentration increases, Arabidopsis plants activate overlapping strategies that prevent the accumulation of damaging levels of Cu.</p><p>One of the mechanisms that Arabidopsis plants activate in response to the increase in environmental Cu consists of the transcriptional down-regulation of the expression of the high-affinity Cu transporter genes <italic>COPT1</italic> and <italic>COPT2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sancenon et al., 2003</xref>). Recent evidence indicates that the SPL7 (for SQUAMOSA promoter-binding-like) transcription factor activates the expression of the <italic>COPT1</italic> and <italic>COPT2</italic> transporter genes in response to Cu deficiency, probably through binding to the GTAC motifs within their promoter regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Yamasaki et al., 2009</xref>). Other SPL7 target genes induced upon Cu limitation include iron (Fe) superoxide dismutase <italic>FSD1</italic> and microRNA miR398, which mediates Cu/zinc (Zn) superoxide dismutases, <italic>CSD1</italic> and <italic>CSD2</italic>, mRNA down-regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abdel-Ghany et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Yamasaki et al., 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">2009</xref>). The substitution of <italic>CSD1</italic> and <italic>CSD2</italic> for its Fe counterpart, <italic>FSD1</italic>, is considered a hallmark strategy for replacing the dispensable Cu proteins by other metalloproteins, which, by using a different metal (usually Fe), perform a similar task. This strategy probably aims to save Cu for essential cuproproteins, such as plastocyanin, when scarce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Yamasaki et al., 2007</xref>). Cu deficiency mostly affects the plant reproductive structures of higher plants, which might be considered the most susceptible plant parts to Cu limitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Graham, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">M&auml;rschner, 2002</xref>). This fact has also been corroborated in transgenic plants defective in Cu acquisition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Sancenon et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>Mineral nutritional status, specifically an organic nitrogen metabolite, has been recently reported to affect the circadian clock in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Gutierrez et al., 2008</xref>). A wide variety of biological processes are subjected to circadian clock control that translates environmental, light and temperature, and endogenous cycles into integrated temporal signals to rhythmically schedule physiology and metabolism at the adequate timing. Oscillations in gene expression, protein synthesis and degradation, nucleo/cytoplasmic partitioning, and protein phosphorylation are at the molecular base of the biological rhythms (for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">McClung, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Harmer, 2009; Mas and Yanovsky, 2009</xref>). Although the main components of the circadian clock are not conserved among the different groups of organisms, the most common basis of the molecular mechanism of the clock in eukaryotes seems to consist of interlocked transcriptional/posttranslational feedback loops. The model proposed herein for the Arabidopsis clock comprises morning and evening oscillators that form a multiple-loop network (for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">McClung, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Harmer, 2009; Mas and Yanovsky, 2009</xref>). Among the main central clock components in Arabidopsis are the single Myb domain transcription factors CIRCADIAN CLOCK-ASSOCIATED1 (CCA1) and LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL (LHY; for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">McClung, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Harmer, 2009; Mas and Yanovsky, 2009</xref>). The LHY and CCA1 proteins bind to the same region of their target promoters, form homodimers or heterodimers, and colocalize within the nucleus, where they function synergistically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lu et al., 2009</xref>). The loss-of-function double mutants <italic>lhy cca1</italic> show short periods of free-running circadian rhythms, affected photoperiodic control of flowering time, modified hypocotyl length, and reduced plant height (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Mizoguchi et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Ito et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Niwa et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lu et al., 2009</xref>). Plants whose clock period matches to the environmental cycles show photosynthetic and competitive advantages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dodd et al., 2005</xref>). The transcriptional feedback loops have been shown to be interdependent of cytosolic rhythms, such as those of Ca<sup>2&plus;</sup> and cyclic ADP-Rib, leading to the consideration of the circadian system as an integral part of the entire cell signaling network, which optimizes plant responses to the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Hastings et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Harmer, 2009</xref>).</p><p>In this work, we describe how the COPT1 Cu transport protein localizes to the plasma membrane of Arabidopsis cells. Moreover, we show that the overexpression of the functional epitope-tagged COPT1 and COPT3 proteins in Arabidopsis causes an increase in endogenous Cu and that some of their phenotypes are reminiscent of altered circadian rhythms, such as those observed previously for plants defective in <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic>. Accordingly, expression analyses indicate that <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> mRNA levels significantly decrease as the endogenous content of Cu in Arabidopsis increases, which suggests that Cu homeostasis could affect, among other processes, the cellular circadian system.</p><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>The COPT1 Cu Transport Protein Localizes to the Plasma Membrane of Arabidopsis Cells</title><p>Although previous results indicate that the Arabidopsis COPT1 protein could function in Cu acquisition in the plasma membrane of specific plant cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Kampfenkel et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sancenon et al., 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">2004</xref>), the fact that certain CTR members are located at intracellular endosomal vesicles or vacuolar membranes in other eukaryotic organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bellemare et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Rees et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">van den Berghe et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bertinato et al., 2008</xref>) prompted us to address the subcellular localization of COPT1 in Arabidopsis cells. To that end, the coding sequence of the COPT1 protein was fused to GFP (<italic>COPT1-GFP</italic>) under the control of the constitutive cauliflower mosaic virus (CaMV) 35S promoter. Isolated Arabidopsis protoplasts transiently transformed with the <italic>COPT1-GFP</italic> construct were analyzed for green and red fluorescence, which are indicative of GFP and chlorophyll localization, respectively. Nontransformed protoplasts and the protoplasts transformed with a construct expressing only GFP were used as the negative and cytosolic positive controls, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). The negative control shows a signal in the chloroplasts that presents high endogenous fluorescence due to chlorophyll (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). In addition to the autofluorescence of chloroplasts, the COPT1-GFP-expressing cells display a specific signal on the cell surface that is absent in vacuoles, cytosol, and other discrete subcellular localizations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). The lypophilic styryl dye FM4-64, which becomes highly fluorescent upon binding to membranes, has been used at low temperatures as a marker to assess the plasma membrane colocalization with COPT1-GFP protein in Arabidopsis cells (Supplemental Fig. S1).</p><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Arabidopsis COPT1 protein localizes to the plasma membrane. Arabidopsis protoplasts transiently transformed with the <italic>COPT1-GFP</italic> construct and analyzed by confocal microscopy 16 h after transformation are shown. The nontransformed protoplasts were used as a negative control, while the protoplasts transformed with a plasmid expressing GFP alone were used as a positive control. Green and magenta fluorescences are indicative of GFP protein and chlorophyll localization, respectively. Images show representative protoplasts at the same scale, including the merges and the light fields.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp153676F01_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Arabidopsis Seedlings Overexpressing <italic>COPT1</italic> or <italic>COPT3</italic> Display Increased Endogenous Cu Content</title><p>To further understand the effect of deregulated Cu homeostasis on plant growth, transgenic plants overproducing either COPT1 or COPT3 were obtained. The coding sequences of the COPT1 and COPT3 transport proteins were tagged at their C-terminal regions with the human influenza virus hemagglutinin HA epitope (COPT1-HA and COPT3-HA constructs) to monitor protein levels. A heterologous complementation strategy with a <italic>ctr1&Delta;ctr3&Delta;</italic> yeast mutant strain, which is unable to grow on a medium containing glycerol as the only carbon source, has been used to test whether the COPT1-HA and COPT3-HA fusion proteins maintain their function in Cu transport in vivo. Yeast growth is restored when Glc or 100 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> is added to the medium, indicating that the <italic>ctr1&Delta;ctr3&Delta;</italic> growth defect on glycerol is a respiratory defect as a result of decreased Cu delivery to the mitochondrial cytochrome oxidase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). The lack of growth on the glycerol medium was restored when the yeast <italic>CTR1</italic> or Arabidopsis <italic>COPT1</italic> or <italic>COPT3</italic> gene was constitutively expressed in the yeast mutant strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Importantly, the expression of the COPT1-HA and COPT3-HA fusion proteins complemented the growth defect of the <italic>ctr1&Delta;ctr3&Delta;</italic> cells on glycerol similar to their untagged protein versions, indicating that the HA epitope does not interfere with the function of COPT1 and COPT3 in Cu transport in yeast. Once the functionality of the COPT1-HA and COPT3-HA fusion proteins had been verified, their coding sequences were cloned under the control of the constitutive CaMV35S promoter, and the <italic>CaMV35S</italic>:<italic>COPT1-HA</italic> and <italic>CaMV35S</italic>:<italic>COPT3-HA</italic> constructs were introduced by <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> transformation into the wild-type ecotype Columbia Arabidopsis plants (C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants). Several Arabidopsis transformed lines were analyzed by western blot using an antibody against the HA epitope. The lines with the highest levels of COPT1-HA and COPT3-HA protein (C1<sup>OE</sup> &num;1 and C3<sup>OE</sup> &num;3) were selected for further studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, B and C</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Obtaining and selection of <italic>COPT1-</italic> and <italic>COPT3</italic>-overexpressing Arabidopsis plants. A, Complementation of the growth phenotype of the <italic>S.</italic> <italic>cerevisiae</italic> <italic>ctr1&Delta;ctr3&Delta;</italic> mutant by the COPT1-HA and COPT3-HA constructs. Yeast cells transformed with an empty vector (<italic>p426GPD</italic>; negative control), a vector containing yeast <italic>CTR1</italic> or Arabidopsis <italic>COPT1</italic> and <italic>COPT3</italic> (positive controls), or the <italic>COPT1-HA</italic> and <italic>COPT3-HA</italic> constructs were assayed for growth on Glc, glycerol, or glycerol plus 100 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (Cu). Cells were spotted in 10-fold serial dilutions starting at <italic>A</italic><sub>600</sub> &equals; 0.1. B, Detection of COPT1-HA-fused protein in the transgenic plants. Western-blot analysis of the total protein extracts from leaves of the wild type (WT) and five independent transgenic C1<sup>OE</sup> lines. C, Detection of COPT3-HA-fused protein in the transgenic plants. Western-blot analysis of the total protein extracts from leaves of the wild type and five independent transgenic C3<sup>OE</sup> lines. The western blots shown in B and C were developed with commercial antibody against the HA epitope.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp153676F02_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>We first analyzed the expression of <italic>COPT1</italic> and <italic>COPT3</italic> mRNAs in the wild type and the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings grown on half-strength Murashige and Skoog medium (MS) or on the same medium supplemented with 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub>. Consistent with their overexpression, both mRNA levels significantly increased in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> lines compared with the wild-type seedlings grown on MS, and their expression remained high on 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, A and B</xref>). The C1<sup>OE</sup> seedlings displayed a 2.5-fold increase in the <italic>COPT1</italic> mRNA expression on MS and a 3.5-fold increase on Cu medium, as compared with the wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Given the low levels of the <italic>COPT3</italic> expression in the wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>) and the different oligonucleotide efficiencies in the real-time reverse transcription (RT)-PCR assays, it is hard to assess <italic>COPT3</italic> fold induction and to make comparisons with the <italic>COPT1</italic> levels. Because the Arabidopsis COPT1 and COPT3 proteins have been implicated in Cu transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Sancenon et al., 2004</xref>), we ascertained whether the overexpression of COPT1-HA and COPT3-HA alters the total content of Cu in the plant. A moderate increase in seedling Cu content was observed for the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> lines under both the MS and 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>). We further analyzed the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants by determining the mRNA levels of several genes regulated by Cu status. This analysis included the high-affinity Cu transporter <italic>COPT2</italic> gene and the Fe superoxide dismutase <italic>FSD1</italic> gene, whose expression is up-regulated upon Cu limitation, as well as the Cu/Zn superoxide dismutase <italic>CSD1</italic> and <italic>CSD2</italic> genes, which display the opposite pattern of expression, that is, they are down-regulated upon Cu limitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abdel-Ghany et al., 2005</xref>). Consistent with the increase noted in the endogenous Cu content, the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants displayed an increase of <italic>CSD1</italic> and <italic>CSD2</italic> mRNAs along with a decrease of the <italic>COPT2</italic> and <italic>FSD1</italic> transcript levels (Supplemental Fig. S2). These combined results demonstrate that the Arabidopsis plants overexpressing epitope-tagged versions of the COPT1 and COPT3 transport proteins display increased endogenous Cu levels, which are perceived by the plant Cu sensor system.</p><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Expression levels and endogenous Cu contents in <italic>COPT1-</italic> and <italic>COPT3-</italic>overexpressing Arabidopsis seedlings. A, Quantification by real-time RT-PCR of the <italic>COPT1</italic> mRNA expression levels from the wild-type (WT; plain bars) and C1<sup>OE</sup> (striped bars) seedlings grown on MS plates either without (MS; white bars) or with 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (Cu; gray bars) under 6 neutral days with photocycle and thermocycle. The <italic>UBQ10</italic> gene was used as a loading control. Values are means &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> of at least three technical replicates. a.u., Arbitrary units; R.E., relative expression. B, Quantification by real-time RT-PCR of the <italic>COPT3</italic> mRNA expression levels, as indicated in A, except C3<sup>OE</sup> (dotted bars). C, Cu content from the seedlings shown in A and B. Values are means &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> of at least three technical replicates. D.W., Dry weight. Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences with respect to the wild type (&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &ast;&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp153676F03_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title><italic>COPT</italic>-Overexpressing Arabidopsis Seedlings Are Sensitive to Elevated Cu Concentrations in the Environment</title><p>The phenotypic analysis of seed germination and seedling growth on plates revealed that the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings did not appreciably differ from the wild-type ones when they were grown on MS. In the presence of 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub>, however, the growth of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings was severely affected. More specifically, the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings grown on 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> displayed a dramatic inhibition in root growth, and additional lateral roots emerged near the crown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Furthermore, the growth of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings was impaired as the Cu concentration in the growth medium increased (data not shown). To accurately quantify the sensitivity of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants to environmental Cu, the root length of the wild-type, C1<sup>OE</sup>, and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings was measured in the presence of increasing concentrations of Cu in the medium.</p><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Cu sensitivity of <italic>COPT1-</italic> and <italic>COPT3-</italic>overexpressing Arabidopsis seedlings. A, Wild-type (WT), C1<sup>OE</sup>, and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings were grown vertically on MS plates either without (MS) or with 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (Cu) under 6 neutral days with photocycle and thermocycle. The inset shows an amplification of a representative C1<sup>OE</sup> seedling in Cu to show the root morphology. B, Quantification of the root length of the wild-type (white circles), C1<sup>OE</sup> (black squares), and C3<sup>OE</sup> (black triangles) seedlings grown vertically on MS plates containing 0, 10, 20, or 50 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub>, as indicated in A. Values are seedling means &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> (<italic>n</italic> &ge; 7) from three independent experiments. C, Quantification of the fresh weight (F.W.) of the wild-type and C1<sup>OE</sup> seedlings grown on MS plates containing 0 or 30 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> Cu, Fe, Zn, cadmium (Cd), or Ag sulfates, as indicated in A. Bars represent the percentage of fresh weight per seedling of the C1<sup>OE</sup> line with respect to the wild type as means &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> of at least three independent experiments. Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences with respect to MS (&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &ast;&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp153676F04_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4B</xref>, whereas wild-type root growth remained unaffected by concentrations up to 20 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub>, the root length of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings drastically shortened at a concentration of 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub>. Complete root growth inhibition was observed for the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings grown on MS supplemented with 50 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). To ascertain whether transgenic seedling sensitivity to Cu was specific, different metal salts were added to the growth medium and fresh weight was determined for the C1<sup>OE</sup> seedlings. As <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C</xref> depicts, the addition of 30 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> to MS lowered the fresh weight of the C1<sup>OE</sup> seedlings three times. However, a decrease in fresh weight as drastic as the one observed by Cu treatment was not observed when other metals (Fe, Zn, and cadmium) were added to the medium as sulfates at a concentration of 30 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>). Only silver (Ag), whose Ag<sup>&plus;</sup> ion is isoelectric to Cu<sup>&plus;</sup>, led to a significant decrease in fresh weight (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>). Taken together, these results indicate that the Arabidopsis seedlings overexpressing <italic>COPT1</italic> are specifically sensitive to Cu in the growth medium, and they highlight the need for a tight control of Cu homeostasis in higher plants.</p></sec><sec><title>Additional Phenotypes Associated with the <italic>COPT</italic>-Overexpressing Arabidopsis Plants</title><p>To further address the effects of the altered regulation of Cu homeostasis on plant physiology, we studied the fairly similar phenotypes observed for the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants grown on soil. The global size of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants was substantially smaller compared with the wild-type ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A;</xref> Supplemental Fig. S3A). Both the 4-week-old C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants grown on soil were around half the size of the wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). A closer view of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants revealed that the first pair of rosette leaves displayed a perpendicular orientation to the normal plane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B;</xref> Supplemental Fig. S3B). Moreover, the C1<sup>OE</sup> leaves presented an adaxial curvature instead of the abaxial curvature observed in the wild-type leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>). Reproductive organs in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants were also affected, as most flowers presented short petals and stamens protected by the sepals throughout flower development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5D;</xref> Supplemental Fig. S3C). This fact could account for the low fertility observed in the C1<sup>OE</sup> plant lines (data not shown). Furthermore, the flowering time of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants was slightly delayed in long-day conditions compared with the wild-type plants, as indicated by a higher leaf number at the time of flowering. Yet, the flowering time inverted in short-day conditions and was somewhat advanced in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). Moreover, the <italic>COPT</italic>-overexpressing hypocotyls were longer than the wild-type ones in white light, but the C1<sup>OE</sup> hypocotyls were shorter than the controls in both darkness and continuous red light (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). These additional phenotypes further highlight the importance of the spatiotemporal control of Cu homeostasis to ensure appropriate growth and development in higher plants. It is noteworthy that none of these phenotypes was observed when the Arabidopsis wild-type plants were grown on soil with elevated Cu levels, although some of them were rather reminiscent of plants with altered circadian rhythms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Mizoguchi et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Ito et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Niwa et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lu et al., 2009</xref>), suggesting potential alterations in the perception of light or circadian rhythms in the plants where Cu homeostasis is deregulated.</p><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Phenotypes of <italic>COPT1</italic>-overexpressing Arabidopsis plants grown on soil. A, Four-week-old wild-type (WT) and C1<sup>OE</sup> plants grown on soil. B, Two-week-old wild-type and C1<sup>OE</sup> plants grown on soil. Arrows point to the first pair of rosette leaves of the C1<sup>OE</sup> line. C, Fully expanded leaves from wild-type and C1<sup>OE</sup> plants. D, Flowers of wild-type and C1<sup>OE</sup> plants. Flowers are shown as either complete (left) or after eliminating frontal petals and sepals (right). Arrows point to the flower stamens. Images show representative plants, leaves, and flowers. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp153676F05_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1"><label>Table I.</label><caption><title>Phenotypic characterization of the COPT1- and COPT3-overexpressing plants</title><p>For plant height of the 4-week-old plants grown on soil under long-day conditions, values are averages of at least five plants with the corresponding <sc>sd</sc>. For rosette leaf number at the time of floral transition of the plants grown on soil under the indicated conditions, values are averages of at least six or 57 plants (for short and long days, respectively) with the corresponding <sc>sd</sc>. For hypocotyl length of 7-d-old seedlings grown at 23&deg;C on MS plates under the indicated continuous light conditions, values are averages of at least 16 seedlings, except for white light (five seedlings), with the corresponding <sc>sd</sc>. n.d., Not determined. Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences with respect to the wild type (&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &ast;&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Parameter</td><td align="center">Wild Type</td><td align="center">C1<sup>OE</sup></td><td align="center">C3<sup>OE</sup></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Plant height (cm)</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">19.00 &plusmn; 2.24</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">8.75 &plusmn; 3.73&ast;&ast;</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">8.00 &plusmn; 2.71&ast;&ast;</td></tr><tr><td>Leaf number at flowering time</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td>&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;Long day</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">12.34 &plusmn; 1.67</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">14.34 &plusmn; 1.71&ast;&ast;</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">13.28 &plusmn; 1.39&ast;&ast;</td></tr><tr><td>&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;Short day</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">56.00 &plusmn; 9.75</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">46.17 &plusmn; 6.27&ast;</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">43.25 &plusmn; 6.67&ast;&ast;</td></tr><tr><td>Hypocotyl length (mm)</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td>&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;White light</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">1.71 &plusmn; 0.44</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">4.58 &plusmn; 0.41&ast;&ast;</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">3.25 &plusmn; 0.50&ast;&ast;</td></tr><tr><td>&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;Dark</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">9.66 &plusmn; 0.91</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">7.31 &plusmn; 0.95&ast;&ast;</td><td align="center">n.d.</td></tr><tr><td>&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;&emsp;Red light</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">8.77 &plusmn; 0.85</td><td align="char" char="plusmn">5.17 &plusmn; 0.98&ast;&ast;</td><td align="center">n.d.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Given that light and temperature are classical environmental entrainment factors of the plant circadian rhythms, we tested the effect of the absence of light and temperature cycles on the development of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants. Both transgenic lines were grown on MS plates under neutral days with a synchronized photocycle and thermocycle (LDHC), or with either the photocycle (LLHC) or the thermocycle (LDHH) absent, or with both absent (LLHH). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref> and Supplemental Figure S4 show the data obtained under the LDHC and LLHH conditions, whereas Supplemental Figure S5 presents the data obtained under the LLHC and LDHH conditions. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref> and Supplemental Figure S5A show the seedlings grown for 6 d on MS plates either with or without 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub>. The growth of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings was more affected than that of the wild-type controls given the absence of environmental cycles; accordingly, the fresh weight per seedling further decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>). As stated, the root length of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings grown under LDHC conditions was greatly reduced by 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). In the absence of environmental cycles, however, the root length notably decreased in the COPT-overexpressing seedlings, even on MS (Supplemental Fig. S4), which further indicates a connection between Cu transport and daily cycles.</p><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Effects of the cycling conditions on the <italic>COPT1</italic>- and <italic>COPT3</italic>-overexpressing Arabidopsis seedlings. A, Wild-type (WT), C1<sup>OE</sup>, and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings grown vertically on MS plates either without (MS) or with 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (Cu) under 6 neutral days with photocycle and thermocycle (LDHC) or in the absence of both (LLHH). B, Quantification of the fresh weight (F.W.) of the wild-type (plain bars), C1<sup>OE</sup> (striped bars), and C3<sup>OE</sup> (dotted bars) seedlings grown on MS (white bars) or Cu (gray bars), as indicated in A. Values indicate fresh weight per seedling as means &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> (<italic>n</italic> &ge; 7) from three independent experiments. C, Quantification of the total chlorophyll content of the seedlings, as indicated in B. Values indicate the total chlorophyll content per fresh weight as means &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> of at least three independent experiments. D, Quantification of the lipid peroxidation of the seedlings, as indicated in B. Values are MDA contents per fresh weight as means &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> of at least two independent experiments. E, Quantification of total anthocyanin contents of the seedlings, as indicated in B. Values indicate total anthocyanin contents per fresh weight as means &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> of at least two independent experiments. Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences with respect to the wild type (&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &ast;&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp153676F06_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>In order to address whether the difficulties of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings to thrive in the absence of environmental inputs were caused by photooxidative damage, we determined total chlorophylls and anthocyanins as well as lipid peroxidation, measured as malondialdehyde (MDA) content, under the different photocycle and thermocycle conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6;</xref> Supplemental Fig. S5). When plants were grown under LLHH conditions and were compared with the LDHC conditions, a decrease in MDA content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6D</xref>) was accompanied by an increase in the total chlorophyll and anthocyanin contents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, C and E</xref>). However, no consistent differences in MDA and the chlorophyll or anthocyanin levels were observed among the wild-type and the COPT-overexpressing seedlings on MS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, C&ndash;E;</xref> Supplemental Fig. S5, D and E). A notable decrease in chlorophylls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6C</xref>; LLHH) or an increase in anthocyanins (Supplemental Fig. S5E; LLHC) was only detected under continuous conditions among the wild-type and the COPT-overexpressing seedlings in the Cu medium. These results mainly rule out a selective increase in photooxidative damage in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings as a primary cause of the observed difficulty of these plants to thrive in the absence of environmental inputs.</p></sec><sec><title>Alterations in Cu Content Influence the Expression of the Circadian Clock Components <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> in Arabidopsis</title><p>As already mentioned, the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings displayed an increased endogenous Cu content, which alters the expression of Cu-regulated genes, including <italic>COPT2</italic>, <italic>FSD1</italic>, <italic>CSD1</italic>, and <italic>CSD2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C;</xref> Supplemental Fig. S2). Furthermore, the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants exhibited certain phenotypes relating to altered circadian rhythms (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>) and found it difficult to thrive under constant environmental conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6;</xref> Supplemental Fig. S5). Taken together, these data prompted us to analyze the expression of the circadian clock components <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic>. Samples were harvested at dawn, Zeitgeber time 0 h, when the mRNA levels of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> show a peak of expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Mizoguchi et al., 2002</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>, the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings grown on MS and subjected to LDHC conditions exhibited a significantly reduced <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression when compared with the wild-type ones. As a result of this reduction, it is expected that circadian clock outputs, such as the expression of <italic>CONSTANS-LIKE1</italic> (<italic>COL1</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Mizoguchi et al., 2002</xref>) and <italic>LHCB1.1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Salom&eacute; et al., 2008</xref>) genes, should also be altered in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants. In addition to <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic>, the expression levels of the <italic>COL1</italic> and <italic>LHCB1.1</italic>, on both the MS and 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub>, indeed decreased if compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>).</p><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Regulation of the gene expression of circadian clock components and clock output genes in the <italic>COPT1-</italic> and <italic>COPT3-</italic>overexpressing Arabidopsis seedlings. Quantification by real-time RT-PCR of the <italic>CCA1</italic>, <italic>LHY</italic>, <italic>LHCB1.1</italic>, and <italic>COL1</italic> mRNA expression levels from the wild-type (WT; plain bars), C1<sup>OE</sup> (striped bars), and C3<sup>OE</sup> (dotted bars) seedlings grown on MS plates either without (MS; white bars) or with 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (Cu; gray bars) under 6 neutral days with photocycle and thermocycle. Samples were taken at Zeitgeber time 0 h. The <italic>UBQ10</italic> gene was used as a loading control. Values are means &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> of three technical replicates. a.u., Arbitrary units; R.E., relative expression. Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences with respect to the wild type (&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &ast;&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp153676F07_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>In order to further assess the role of Cu in the expression of the <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> genes, the wild-type seedlings were grown on MS and 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> under LDHC conditions, and the mRNA levels were analyzed in two diurnal cycles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>). The presence of Cu in the medium slightly decreased <italic>LHY</italic> mRNA but <italic>CCA1</italic> mRNA was reduced to about 50%, affecting the amplitude of their oscillations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>). When the <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression was analyzed at dawn (time for the peak of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression) in the wild-type seedlings grown at different Cu concentrations, we observed that <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression levels lowered in a dose-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>). The effect of Cu on the expression of these genes, particularly <italic>CCA1</italic>, is comparable to the regulation observed for the well-established Cu-regulated gene <italic>COPT2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig8"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Cu regulation of the circadian clock and Cu homeostasis genes in Arabidopsis seedlings. A, RT-PCR products from total RNA of the wild-type seedlings grown on MS plates either without (MS; white circles) or with 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (Cu; black squares) under 6 neutral days with photocycle and thermocycle. Samples were taken every 4 h during the following 48 h. The relative intensity of the electrophoretic band for each gene versus the <italic>18S</italic> band, used as a loading control, is represented. The experiments were repeated at least three times with similar results, and a representative experiment is shown. ZT, Zeitgeber time. The white and black bars at bottom indicate day and night, respectively. a.u., Arbitrary units; R.E., relative expression. B, RT-PCR products from total RNA of wild-type seedlings grown on MS plates with 0.2, 1, 10, or 50 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> under 6 neutral days with photocycle and thermocycle. Samples were taken at Zeitgeber time 0 h. <italic>18S</italic> rRNA was used as a loading control.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp153676F08_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>To ascertain whether Cu affects the circadian expression of the circadian clock components, the luciferase activity of the <italic>PLHY</italic>:<italic>luc</italic> seedlings, which fully recapitulate the rhythmic pattern of the expression of the endogenous <italic>LHY</italic> transcript (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Kim et al., 2003</xref>), was monitored at different environmental Cu statuses. After a 7-d entrainment to the LDHC cycles, the <italic>PLHY</italic>:<italic>luc</italic> seedlings were then released into either continuous light or dark at a constant temperature (25&deg;C). The analysis of the three luciferase activity cycles after being transferred into free-running conditions is shown either under continuous light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9A</xref>) or in the dark (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9B</xref>). Cu down-regulated the <italic>LHY</italic> expression by affecting the peak amplitude, which decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>). Error bars are not included in this figure for simplicity, but as Supplemental Figure S6A shows, the <sc>se</sc> of the mean of the MS and 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> data do not overlap at the oscillation peaks. Changes in the period, amplitude, and phase of the oscillations shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref> and Supplemental Figure S6 have been estimated and statistically analyzed (Supplemental Table S1). Whereas the <italic>LHY</italic> expression oscillation period remained unchanged after being transferred into free-running conditions, the amplitude significantly decreased (Supplemental Table S1; Supplemental Fig. S6A) and the phase was delayed (Supplemental Table S1; Supplemental Fig. S6A) on Cu medium compared with seedlings grown on MS. Moreover, the <italic>PLHY</italic>:<italic>luc</italic> seedlings, which had been entrained for 7 d to the LDHC cycles and transferred to continuous light, were subjected to Cu addition at different circadian oscillation phases (Supplemental Fig. S6B). Irrespective of the addition time, Cu modified the amplitude and the phase of the circadian <italic>LHY</italic> expression oscillation to a similar extent but did not affect its period (Supplemental Table S1; Supplemental Fig. S6B). Furthermore, when the <italic>PLHY</italic>:<italic>luc</italic> seedlings growing on plates with 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> were subjected to seven LDHC cycles and were then transferred to free-running light conditions in the presence of the specific Cu chelator bathocuproine disulfonic acid, the amplitude of oscillation increased, indicating the reversibility of the Cu effect (Supplemental Fig. S6C).</p><fig id="fig9"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Cu regulation of luciferase activity driven by the <italic>LHY</italic> promoter in Arabidopsis seedlings. A, Bioluminescence from the <italic>PLHY</italic>:<italic>luc</italic> seedlings grown on MS plates without (MS; white circles), with 5 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (gray circles), or with 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (black circles), entrained under 7 neutral days with photocycle and thermocycle, and transferred to continuous light. Bioluminiscence was measured every hour after transferring to continuous light. Values are seedling averages (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 4&ndash;7). White and gray bars at bottom indicate subjective day and night, respectively. B, Bioluminescence from <italic>PLHY</italic>:<italic>luc</italic> seedlings grown on MS plates either without (MS; white circles) or with 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (Cu; black circles), entrained under 7 neutral days with photocycle and thermocycle, and transferred to continuous dark. Bioluminiscence was measured every hour after transferring to continuous dark. Values are seedling averages (<italic>n</italic> &equals; 7&ndash;10). Gray and black bars at bottom indicate subjective day and night, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp153676F09_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>In order to further assess the role of Cu in the circadian clock, and in addition to <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic>, the expression of other genes considered to be outputs of the clock, such as <italic>COL1</italic> and <italic>LHCB1.1</italic>, was analyzed by real-time RT-PCR under free-running light conditions. Seedlings were grown over a 6-d period with LDHC cycles. After being transferred to continuous light conditions, samples were taken at Zeitgeber time 0 h during the subjective day in cycles 2 (LC2) and 3 (LC3). The results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10</xref> reflect that Cu also down-regulates the clock output genes <italic>COL1</italic> and <italic>LHCB1.1</italic>.</p><fig id="fig10"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Cu regulation of the gene expression of circadian clock components and clock output genes in the Arabidopsis seedlings. A, Quantification by real-time RT-PCR of the <italic>CCA1</italic>, <italic>LHY</italic>, <italic>LHCB1.1</italic>, and <italic>COL1</italic> mRNA expression levels from wild-type seedlings grown on MS plates either without (MS; white bars) or with 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (Cu; gray bars), entrained under 6 neutral days with photocycle and thermocycle, and transferred to continuous light. Samples were taken at Zeitgeber time 0 h on the subjective day for continuous light cycle 2 (LC2) and cycle 3 (LC3) after transferring. The <italic>UBQ10</italic> gene was used as a loading control. Values are technical replicate means &plusmn; <sc>sd</sc> (<italic>n</italic> &ge; 6) from two independent experiments. a.u., Arbitrary units; R.E., relative expression. Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences with respect to the wild type (&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &ast;&ast; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp153676F10_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Taken together, these results indicate that deregulated Cu homeostasis in <italic>COPT-</italic>overexpressing plants is detrimental for their growth, especially under continuous environmental conditions. One of the processes affected by Cu is the expression of the main components of the circadian clock <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> genes and their outputs.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The existence of tightly regulated Cu homeostasis networks in plants has been traditionally attributed to not only ensure Cu delivery to essential cuproproteins but to also avoid harmful effects of Cu when in excess. Despite this, very little is known about the specific effects of deregulated Cu homeostasis on plant physiology. Previous works have shown that Arabidopsis plants express a family of CTR-type Cu transport proteins, know as COPT1 to -6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Kampfenkel et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sancenon et al., 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">2004</xref>), and the COPT1 protein has been shown to function in plant Cu acquisition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Sancenon et al., 2004</xref>). Here, we ascertained COPT1 subcellular localization by expressing a GFP-tagged COPT1 protein in Arabidopsis protoplasts. Similar to other eukaryotic high-affinity Cu transporters of the CTR family, the COPT1 protein localizes to the plasma membrane of Arabidopsis cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1;</xref> Supplemental Fig. S1), which is not only consistent with its function in plant Cu acquisition but further reinforces its role in the cellular Cu uptake in Arabidopsis cells.</p><p>Several members of the Arabidopsis COPT family, including <italic>COPT1</italic> and <italic>COPT2</italic>, are transcriptionally down-regulated by Cu, whereas others, like <italic>COPT3</italic> and <italic>COPT5</italic>, are not regulated by Cu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sancenon et al., 2003</xref>). Both the COPT-mediated Cu transport activity and the Cu-inhibited expression of the COPT genes integrate a negative autoregulatory feedback loop (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Pe&ntilde;arrubia et al., 2010</xref>). In order to gain further insight into the specific role of Cu homeostasis in plant growth and plant development, we overexpressed the <italic>COPT1</italic> and <italic>COPT3</italic> genes in Arabidopsis driven by the constitutive <italic>CaMV35S</italic> promoter. Therefore, with the substitution of the native <italic>COPT1</italic> and <italic>COPT3</italic> regulatory regions for the constitutive <italic>CaMV35S</italic> promoter, we would expect not only the increased and ectopic expression of the genes but also the loss of the negative autoregulatory feedback loop. Consequently, the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants should display an increased and constitutive Cu transport activity toward the cytosol in most tissues. To easily determine the COPT1 and COPT3 protein levels and to select suitable lines, we tagged their protein sequences with the HA epitope at the C-terminal regions. Notably, the HA tag did not significantly interfere with the COPT1 and COPT3 protein functions in Cu transport, as shown by functional complementation experiments in yeast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). However, we cannot rule out that the HA epitope tag alters putative COPT1 posttranslational regulatory mechanisms, including Cu-induced endocytosis, degradation, and transport blockage, which have been previously described for other eukaryotic high-affinity Cu transporters of the CTR family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Ooi et al., 1996</xref>; Petris et al., 2003; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Guo et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Liu et al., 2007</xref>). In this sense, although the Cys residues at the yeast Ctr1 C terminus are dispensable for Cu transport, they have been postulated to serve as Cu sensors and to play a crucial role in preventing Cu uptake when intracellular Cu levels rise (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wu et al., 2009</xref>). Indeed, the lack of this regulatory mechanism in yeast cells expressing either a Ctr1 protein with an epitope tag or a deletion at its C terminus leads to sensitivity to Cu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wu et al., 2009</xref>). Therefore, the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants represent not only an increase but a modification in the Cu uptake pattern, which probably affects the regulation of COPT1 and COPT3 at the transcriptional and posttranslational levels and which would modify the content and the spatiotemporal distribution of the Cu transport in these plants.</p><p>Given the elevated specificity of the COPT transport proteins for the Cu<sup>&plus;</sup> ion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sancenon et al., 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">2004</xref>), the phenotypes observed for the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants should be highly Cu specific. In this sense, the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> lines are an excellent tool to study the effects of deregulated Cu transport on plant physiology. As expected, the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants display a moderate increase in endogenous Cu levels under both low and high Cu conditions in the medium when compared with the wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>). Notably, endogenous Cu in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants is biologically active and perceived by the Cu transcriptional factor SPL7, as suggested by the changes in the expression of the well-known Cu status markers (<italic>FSD1</italic> and <italic>COPT2</italic> for low Cu and <italic>CSD1</italic> and <italic>CSD2</italic> for high Cu; Supplemental Fig. S2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abdel-Ghany et al., 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Yamasaki et al., 2009</xref>). Root length is a highly sensitive parameter that is frequently used to test plant Cu sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Sancenon et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Andr&eacute;s-Col&aacute;s et al., 2006</xref>). Hence, the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> lines are more sensitive to the presence of Cu in the growth medium than the wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, A and B</xref>). Cu specificity is reflected in the decreased fresh weight of the C1<sup>OE</sup> plants, which is selectively caused by Cu<sup>&plus;</sup> and Ag<sup>&plus;</sup>, an isoelectric element to Cu<sup>&plus;</sup> that can partially mimic the effects of Cu (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>).</p><p>On the other hand, it is interesting to highlight that the phenotypes observed in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants are more exacerbated than expected by the endogenous Cu content of these plants. So, whereas the growth of the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings on MS (endogenous Cu content around 6 <italic>&mu;</italic>g g<sup>&minus;1</sup> dry weight) is affected under continuous environmental conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>; LLHH, compare C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> with the wild type on MS), the growth of the wild-type seedlings on 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> (endogenous Cu content around 32 <italic>&mu;</italic>g g<sup>&minus;1</sup> dry weight) remains mostly unaffected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>; LLHH, compare the wild type on MS and Cu). Furthermore, despite the endogenous Cu content of the wild-type seedlings in the 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> medium being around 32 <italic>&mu;</italic>g g<sup>&minus;1</sup> dry weight and approximately 45 <italic>&mu;</italic>g g<sup>&minus;1</sup> dry weight in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>), changes in gene expression (Supplemental Fig. S2), and particularly the visual phenotypes displayed by the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5;</xref> <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S3), are not observed in the wild-type seedlings grown on 20 to 25 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub>, despite their endogenous Cu content being around 100 <italic>&mu;</italic>g g<sup>&minus;1</sup> dry weight (data not shown). These results indicate that the observed phenotypic effects in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings are not solely due to their endogenous Cu content but are a result of the ectopic and deregulated Cu transport in these plants, which could drive the difficulty of C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants to thrive, especially in the absence of environmental inputs. Neither lipid peroxidation nor the anthocyanin content measured in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> seedlings indicates a drastic increase in the oxidative conditions of these plants compared with the wild-type ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, D and E;</xref> Supplemental Fig. S5, D and E), further suggesting additional alterations caused by deregulated Cu homeostasis, where environmental light and temperature cycles are involved.</p><p>Interestingly, some of the phenotypes displayed by the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants, including the number of rosette leaves at the reproductive transition and hypocotyl length (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>), are reminiscent of those obtained for the loss-of-function double mutant <italic>lhy cca1</italic>, which are nuclear components of the Arabidopsis circadian clock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Mizoguchi et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Ito et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Niwa et al., 2007</xref>). Accordingly, the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants show decreased expression levels of the <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> genes and of the circadian clock output genes <italic>LHCB1.1</italic> and <italic>COL1</italic> when compared with the wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). These data show that the increased and deregulated Cu transport occurring in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants modifies the expression of at least two crucial transcription factors that influence Arabidopsis chronobiology. Consequently, the results shown here indicate that the increased metal uptake strategies that aim to hyperaccumulate metals should take into account that deregulated metal homeostasis can affect other general and maybe interconnected cellular processes, such as the circadian system, as shown in this work. Nevertheless, the altered expression of circadian clock components cannot justify by itself the observed phenotypes in COPT-overexpressing plants grown on soil, since Arabidopsis mutants affected in circadian clock components (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Dodd et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">McClung, 2006</xref>) do not display all the phenotypes described in this work (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figs. 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5;</xref> Supplemental Fig. S3). These phenotypes could rather account for the Cu toxic effects when its transport is deregulated.</p><p>As a first approach to gain further insight into the Cu influence on <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> expression, their daily expression patterns have been shown to be Cu responsive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). Furthermore, the luciferase activity of the transgenic <italic>PLHY</italic>:<italic>luc</italic> plants, grown for 7 neutral days and then subjected to continuous light or dark, also reveals that the amplitude of the <italic>LHY</italic> circadian expression is Cu responsive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9B;</xref> Supplemental Table S1; Supplemental Fig. S6A). However, Cu has no effect on the <italic>LHY</italic> circadian oscillation period under the different conditions studied (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9;</xref> Supplemental Table S1; Supplemental Fig. S6), and the <italic>LHY</italic> oscillation phase is delayed by Cu (Supplemental Table S1; Supplemental Fig. S6A). Moreover, real-time RT-PCR corroborates that the wild-type seedlings display decreased levels of the Myb transcription factors <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> and the circadian clock targets <italic>LHCB1.1</italic> and <italic>COL1</italic> mRNAs under Cu treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10</xref>).</p><p>In addition to the role of the SPL7 transcription factor in Cu deficiency responses, other Arabidopsis SPL members have been shown to participate in flowering transition and fertility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Cardon et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Unte et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Wu and Poethig, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Gandikota et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Zhang et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Wang et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wu et al., 2009</xref>). It is interesting that two members of the <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic> SPL family, which are homologous to Arabidopsis SPL8, are regulated by the circadian clock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Riese et al., 2008</xref>). Furthermore, the <italic>AtSPL7</italic> expression cycles under the different diurnal and circadian conditions, as indicated in the data available in the Diurnal Oregon State University Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://diurnal.cgrb.oregonstate.edu/">http://diurnal.cgrb.oregonstate.edu/</ext-link>). Moreover, the <italic>AtSPL7</italic> target, miRNA398, displays a diurnal oscillatory pattern of accumulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Sire et al., 2009</xref>). The SPL genes present GTAC motifs within their promoters at a higher occurrence than in the randomly selected promoters, which have been suggested to mediate the autoregulation by possibly using a feedback loop based on protein interactions and transcriptional regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Wang et al., 2009</xref>). A single GTAC motif has recently been shown to be sufficient to confer the Cu responsiveness mediated by SPL7 to the <italic>miR398</italic> promoter in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Yamasaki et al., 2009</xref>). A bioinformatic search within the promoters of circadian clock genes performed with the PLACE Web Signal Scan (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.dna.affrc.go.jp/htdocs/PLACE/signalscan.html">http://www.dna.affrc.go.jp/htdocs/PLACE/signalscan.html</ext-link>) and the Patmatch program from The Arabidopsis Information Resource (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.arabidopsis.org">www.arabidopsis.org</ext-link>) was performed (data not shown). The presence of a GTAC motif within the <italic>LHY</italic> (&minus;160 to &minus;156 bp distance to the translational start site) and the <italic>CCA1</italic> (&minus;132 to &minus;128) 5&prime; untranslated regions suggests a possible explanation of how Cu influences the expression of the central oscillator components by down-regulating their expression via SPL7. Although the regulatory mechanism is far from being elucidated and further studies are necessary to understand the mechanisms that underlie the influence of Cu on the circadian clock in higher plants, taken together, these data suggest that members of the complex Arabidopsis SPL family of transcription factors may act as key integrators between Cu status and circadian responses in plants.</p><p>Chloroplasts indeed play a crucial role in the connection between metal homeostasis and the circadian clock. First, many critical metal-dependent processes take place in chloroplasts that constitute a major subcellular transition metal sink, where plastocyanin and Cu/Zn superoxide dismutase are the main chloroplastic cuproproteins. During chloroplast biogenesis, light and tissue signals promote the nuclear-chloroplastic coordinated synthesis of hundreds of chloroplast proteins, including different metalloproteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">L&oacute;pez-Juez, 2007</xref>). Presumably, metal requirements should be higher during the diurnal light phase in chloroplasts. Although little is known about the master switch regulators in the chloroplast biogenesis, the challenges that subcellular metal trafficking pose to the daily light/dark changes under intracellular redox conditions are emerging as a determinant process to fully understand dynamic aspects in transition metal homeostasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Puig and Pe&ntilde;arrubia, 2009</xref>). In this sense and under Cu deficiency, the chloroplastic Cu/Zn superoxide dismutase is substituted by the Fe superoxide dismutase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abdel-Ghany et al., 2005</xref>), which has already been shown to display a circadian expression pattern (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Kliebenstein et al., 1998</xref>). Interestingly, it has been recently shown that the regulation of the chloroplastic Fe storage protein, ferritin, is an output of the central oscillator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Duc et al., 2009</xref>), thus further suggesting that metal homeostasis is subjected to the circadian control in Arabidopsis. Furthermore, the different proteins that participate in plastid-to-nucleus retrograde signaling also affect the circadian clock (Hassidim et al., 2007; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Larkin and Ruckle, 2008</xref>).</p><p>The results we present here indicate that other than playing a role to ensure Cu availability while avoiding toxic effects, tightly spatiotemporally regulated Cu homeostasis is further required for Arabidopsis proper fitness in the absence of environmental cycles. The alterations in Cu homeostasis in the C1<sup>OE</sup> and C3<sup>OE</sup> plants down-regulate the circadian expression levels of the crucial circadian clock components in Arabidopsis. Thus, the control of Cu homeostasis, probably at both the spatial and temporal levels, could be important to fulfill the cell-specific and appropriate timing requirements of Cu daily intracellular traffic. In this sense, Cu homeostasis could participate in the integral cellular circadian system, possibly through the effect of Cu on the expression of circadian clock components, as shown in this work.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Plant Growth Conditions and Treatments</title><p>Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> ecotype Columbia) plants were grown on soil as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Andr&eacute;s-Col&aacute;s et al., 2006</xref>) for the indicated times. To grow seedlings on plates, seeds were surface sterilized, stratified for 2 d at 4&deg;C, and incubated on MS with 1% Suc, either supplemented or not with CuSO<sub>4</sub>, for the indicated times. MS plates contain 0.1 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub>, which is considered a concentration below the optimal Cu supply (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abdel-Ghany et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Yamasaki et al., 2009</xref>). Plants were grown under long-day (16 h of light-23&deg;C/8 h of dark-16&deg;C; LD), short-day (8 h of light-23&deg;C/16 h of dark-16&deg;C; SD), or neutral-day conditions with a synchronized photocycle and thermocycle (12 h of light-23&deg;C/12 h of dark-16&deg;C; LDHC) or in the absence of photocycle (LLHC), thermocycle (LDHH), or both (LLHH), as indicated. Fresh weight measurements were taken from five to 15 seedlings. Hypocotyl length was measured from the seedlings grown on MS plates without Suc. After 48 h at 4&deg;C in the dark, seedlings were exposed to white light for 3 h followed by incubation for 24 h in the dark at 23&deg;C. Then, seedlings were grown for 2 additional days at 23&deg;C at a fluence rate (1 <italic>&mu;</italic>mol m<sup>&minus;2</sup> s<sup>&minus;1</sup>) of continuous red light in an Intellus environmental controller (Percival Scientific), white light, or in the dark. The content of MDA, considered as a lipid peroxidation indicator, was measured following the protocol of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Buege and Aust (1978)</xref>. Anthocyanins were determined as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Fiorani et al., 2005</xref>) by measuring the <italic>A</italic><sub>536</sub> of 1 mL of supernatant diluted with 0.75 mL of water and 2 mL of chloroform. The chlorophyll content of the Arabidopsis seedlings was determined by the trichlorometric method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Parsons and Strickland, 1963</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Transgenic Plants Overexpressing COPT1 or COPT3</title><p>The complete <italic>COPT1</italic> and <italic>COPT3</italic> coding sequences were obtained from Arabidopsis genomic DNA by PCR using the following specific primers, which introduce the adequate restriction sites for cloning: COPT1-<italic>Xba</italic>I forward, 5&prime;-GC<underline>TCTAGA</underline>CCATGGATCATGATCACATGC-3&prime;; COPT1-<italic>Bgl</italic>II reverse, 5&prime;-GA<underline>AGATCT</underline>ACAAGCACAACCTGAGGGAGG-3&prime;; COPT3-<italic>Xba</italic>I forward, 5&prime;-GC<underline>TCTAGA</underline>ATGAACGGCATGAGTGGATC-3&prime;; COPT3-<italic>Bgl</italic>II reverse, 5&prime;-GA<underline>AGATCT</underline>ACAATGTGATTGAACCTCGG-3&prime;. The C terminus was tagged with the HA epitope through its insertion into the pPILY vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Ferrando et al., 2000</xref>) with the <italic>Xba</italic>I and <italic>Bgl</italic>II restriction enzymes. The function of the tagged protein was checked by yeast complementation as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sancenon et al., 2003</xref>). The tagged protein was cloned under the control of the constitutive CaMV35S promoter into the binary pBI121 vector with the <italic>Xba</italic>I and <italic>Sac</italic>I restriction enzymes. The C58 strain of <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> transformed with this construct was used to transform the Arabidopsis plants by following the floral dip protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Clough and Bent, 1998</xref>). Transgenic plants were selected by kanamycin resistance and by western-blot analysis with the total protein extracts from the leaves of adult plants, using a commercial anti-HA antibody (3F10; Roche).</p></sec><sec><title>Gene Expression Analysis by RT-PCR</title><p>Total RNA was isolated and reverse transcribed to cDNA as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Andr&eacute;s-Col&aacute;s et al., 2006</xref>) with p(dT)<sub>15</sub> (Roche) and the <italic>18S</italic> reverse primer (for primer sequences, see Supplemental Table S2). cDNA was used in the PCRs under the following conditions to maintain a linear response in the range of the cDNA concentrations used (for the primer-specific conditions, see Supplemental Table S2): cycles of three temperature segments of 30 s, except 50 s for the elongation of <italic>CCA1</italic>, <italic>TOC1</italic>, and <italic>HMA5</italic> (94&deg;C/hybridization temperature/72&deg;C). The PCR products were visualized on 2% agarose gels. Band intensities were quantified with the ImageJ 1.33a application (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>). The relative values of the mRNA levels for each sample were normalized in relation to <italic>18S</italic> rRNA as the internal control. The real-time PCRs were composed of 12.5 <italic>&mu;</italic>L of Power SYBR Green Master Mix (Applied Biosystems), 1.5 <italic>&mu;</italic>g of cDNA, and 0.3 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> primers for all the genes, except 0.9 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> for the reverse primer of <italic>ubiquitin10</italic> (<italic>UBQ10</italic>), in a 25-<italic>&mu;</italic>L total reaction volume (for the primer sequences, see Supplemental Table S3). The PCRs were carried out in a StepOnePlus Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems) under the following conditions: one cycle of 95&deg;C for 10 min, 40 cycles of 95&deg;C for 15 s, and 1 cycle of 60&deg;C for 1 min. The results correspond to the comparative cycle threshold method that compares the cycle threshold values of the samples with a reference sample (the wild type on MS). The relative values of the mRNA levels for each sample were normalized in relation to <italic>UBQ10</italic> as the internal control.</p></sec><sec><title>Bioluminescence and Statistical Analysis</title><p>The <italic>PLHY</italic>:<italic>luc</italic> plants were provided by Isabelle Carr&eacute;. Seedlings were grown as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Andr&eacute;s-Col&aacute;s et al., 2006</xref>) under neutral-day LDHC conditions for 6 d and were then transferred to white multiwell MS &plus; 3% Suc plates or to the same plates supplemented with 5 or 10 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> CuSO<sub>4</sub> or 100 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> bathocuproine disulfonic acid, as indicated. Then, 30 <italic>&mu;</italic>L of <sc>d</sc>-luciferin (Sigma) reaction substrate (0.42 mg mL<sup>&minus;1</sup>) was added to the wells, and the plates were sealed with Microseal B&prime; Film (Bio-Rad). After 1 additional day under LDHC conditions, the multiwell plates were released to free-running conditions at 25&deg;C. Bioluminescence was measured and expressed as relative light units with Luminoskan Ascent, and the data were processed with the Ascent software, version 2.6 (Thermo Scientific).</p><p>The period, amplitude, and phase of the oscillations were calculated with the BRASS analysis package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Locke et al., 2005</xref>; available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://millar.bio.ed.ac.uk/PEBrown/BRASS/BrassPage.htm">http://millar.bio.ed.ac.uk/PEBrown/BRASS/BrassPage.htm</ext-link>) using the FFT-NLLS algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Plautz et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>Statistical analysis (ANOVA, <italic>t</italic> test) was performed using the Jump-in software package (SAS Institute).</p></sec><sec><title>Metal Accumulation Measurements</title><p>Cu content was determined as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Andr&eacute;s-Col&aacute;s et al., 2006</xref>) at the Servei Central de Suport a la Investigaci&oacute; Experimental of the Universitat de Val&egrave;ncia. Lyophilized samples were digested with HNO<sub>3</sub> at 100&deg;C and diluted with milliQ<sub>PLUS</sub> water (Millipore). The Cu content of each sample was determined by graphite furnace atomic absorption spectrometry (Zeeman 4100ZL; Perkin-Elmer).</p></sec><sec><title>Subcellular Localization of the GFP Fusion Proteins</title><p>The complete <italic>COPT1</italic> coding sequence was obtained from Arabidopsis genomic DNA by PCR using the following specific primers, which introduce the adequate restriction sites for cloning: COPT1-<italic>Spe</italic>I forward, 5&prime;-GC<underline>TCTAGA</underline>CCATGGATCATGATCACATGC-3&prime;; COPT1-<italic>Sal</italic>I reverse, 5&prime;-GA<underline>AGATCT</underline>ACAAGCACAACCTGAGGGAGG-3&prime;. The C terminus was fused with the GFP reporter, and its expression was controlled by the constitutive CaMV35S promoter through its insertion into the transient expression vector pGFPau with the <italic>Spe</italic>I and <italic>Sal</italic>I restriction enzymes. The construct was used to transform Arabidopsis protoplasts as described previously from the fresh leaf tissue of 3-week-old plants grown on soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abdel-Ghany et al., 2005</xref>). After 16 h under continuous light at 23&deg;C in the wash solution, confocal images were obtained using a TCS SP Vertical Fluorescence Confocal Microscope (DM-R; Leica) equipped with argon ion (458 and 488 nm), helium-neon I (543 nm), and helium-neon II (633 nm) excitation laser systems and a 60&times; objective lens. The FM4-64 dye (Invitrogen) was added at a concentration of 50 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> and was incubated at 4&deg;C for 15 min before analyzing. The fluorescence signals were detected at 500 to 530 nm for GFP, 650 to 750 nm for chlorophyll, and 560 to 650 nm for FM4-64 after exciting at 488, 633, and 543 nm, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold> Arabidopsis COPT1 protein localizes to the plasma membrane.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S2.</bold> Gene expression pattern in <italic>COPT1-</italic> and <italic>COPT3-</italic>overexpressing Arabidopsis seedlings.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S3.</bold> Phenotype of the <italic>COPT3</italic>-overexpressing Arabidopsis plants grown on soil.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S4.</bold> Effects of the cycling conditions on the root length of the <italic>COPT1</italic>- and <italic>COPT3</italic>-overexpressing Arabidopsis seedlings.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S5.</bold> Effects of the cycling conditions on the <italic>COPT1-</italic> and <italic>COPT3</italic>-overexpressing Arabidopsis seedlings.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S6.</bold> Cu effects on the luciferase activity driven by the <italic>LHY</italic> promoter in Arabidopsis seedlings.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Table S1.</bold> Parameters of the luciferase activity oscillation.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Table S2.</bold> Oligonucleotides used in the RT-PCR reactions.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Table S3.</bold> Oligonucleotides used in the real-time RT-PCR reactions.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the Servei Central de Suport a la Investigaci&oacute; Experimental (Universitat de Val&egrave;ncia) for the atomic absorption spectrometer, sequencing, and confocal microscopy services and David Alabad&iacute; and Ver&oacute;nica Arana (Instituto de Biologia Molecular y Celular de Plantas, Val&egrave;ncia) for their help with the determination of hypocotyl length in red light. We also thank Isabelle Carr&eacute; (University of Warwick, UK) for providing the <italic>PLHY</italic>:<italic>luc</italic> plants, Tommaso Legnaioli and Paloma M&aacute;s (Centre de Recerca Agrigen&oacute;mica, Barcelona) for their advice with the bioluminiscence measurements, Fernando Aniento (Universitat de Val&egrave;ncia) for his advice with FM4-64 localization, and Joaqu&iacute;n Moreno (Universitat de Val&egrave;ncia) for his help in analyzing the circadian data and critical reading of the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Ghany</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller-Moule</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Niyogi</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shikanai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Two P-type ATPases are required for copper delivery in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> chloroplasts</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1233</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1251</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andr&eacute;s-Col&aacute;s</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sancenon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Navarro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&ntilde;arrubia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> heavy metal P-type ATPase HMA5 interacts with metallochaperones and functions in copper detoxification of roots</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>236</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellemare</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Morano</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaudoin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Langlois</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Labbe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Ctr6, a vacuolar membrane copper transporter in <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>277</volume>: <fpage>46676</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>46686</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertinato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Swist</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Plouffe</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>L&apos;Abbe</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Ctr2 is partially localized to the plasma membrane and stimulates copper uptake in COS-7 cells</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>409</volume>: <fpage>731</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>740</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buege</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aust</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>Microsomal lipid peroxidation</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>302</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>310</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burkhead</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Ghany</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Copper homeostasis</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>182</volume>: <fpage>799</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>816</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nettesheim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterisation of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SBP-box genes</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>237</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>104</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Floral dip: a simplified method for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>743</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Salathia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>K&eacute;vei</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>T&oacute;th</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibberd</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>AAR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Plant circadian clocks increase photosynthesis, growth, survival, and competitive advantage</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>630</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>633</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drazkiewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sk&oacute;rzy&nacute;ska-Polit</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupa</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Copper-induced oxidative stress and antioxidant defence in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Biometals</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>387</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duc</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobrr&eacute;aux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Briat</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaymard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Regulation of iron homeostasis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> by the clock regulator TIME FOR COFEE</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>284</volume>: <fpage>36271</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>36281</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrando</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Farras</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jasik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koncz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Intron-tagged epitope: a tool for facile detection and purification of proteins expressed in <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-transformed plant cells</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>553</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>560</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fiorani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Umbach</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Siedow</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The alternative oxidase of plant mitochondria is involved in the acclimation of shoot growth at low temperature: a study of Arabidopsis AOX1a transgenic plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1795</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1805</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gandikota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Birkenbihl</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardon</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The miRNA156/157 recognition element in the 3&prime; UTR of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SBP box gene <italic>SPL3</italic> prevents early flowering by translational inhibition in seedlings</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>683</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>693</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Male sterility in wheat plants deficient in copper</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>254</volume>: <fpage>514</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>515</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Petris</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Identification of methionine-rich clusters that regulate copper-stimulated endocytosis of the human Ctr1 copper transporter</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>17428</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>17433</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stokes</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Thum</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Obertello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Katari</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanurdzic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nero</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>et al (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Systems approach identifies an organic nitrogen-responsive gene network that is regulated by the master clock control gene CCA1</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>4939</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>4944</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halliwell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutteridge</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Oxygen toxicity, oxygen radicals, transition metals and disease</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>219</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>14</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The circadian system in higher plants</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>377</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hassidim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakir</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fradkin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Keren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Harir</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yerushalmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mutations in CHLOROPLAST RNA BINDING provide evidence for the involvement of the chloroplast in the regulation of the circadian clock in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>562</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Maywood</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>O&apos;Neill</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cellular circadian pacemaking and the role of cytosolic rhythms</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>R805</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>R815</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoffella</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Trace elements in agroecosystems and impacts on the environment</article-title>. <source>J Trace Elem Med Biol</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>140</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamichi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Niinuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>et al (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genetic linkages between circadian clock-associated components and phytochrome-dependent red light signal transduction in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>971</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>983</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kampfenkel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushnir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Babiychuk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Inze</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Montagu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization of a putative <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> copper transporter and its yeast homologue</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>28479</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>28486</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr&eacute;</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Light-regulated translation mediates gated induction of the Arabidopsis clock protein LHY</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>944</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kliebenstein</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Monde</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Last</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Superoxide dismutase in Arabidopsis: an eclectic enzyme family with disparate regulation and protein localization</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>637</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>650</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruckle</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Integration of light and plastid signals</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>593</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>599</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sitaram</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Burd</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Regulation of copper-dependent endocytosis and vacuolar degradation of the yeast copper transporter, Ctr1p, by the Rsp5 ubiquitin ligase</article-title>. <source>Traffic</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1375</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1384</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Southern</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozma-Bogn&aacute;r</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibberd</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Extension of a genetic network model by iterative experimentation and mathematical analysis</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&oacute;pez-Juez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Plastid biogenesis, between light and shadows</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>26</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Andronis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED1 and LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL function synergistically in the circadian clock of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>834</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>843</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maksymiec</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Effect of copper on cellular processes in higher plants</article-title>. <source>Photosynthetica</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>342</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&auml;rschner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Mineral Nutrition in Higher Plants</article-title>. <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Time for circadian rhythms: plants get synchronized</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>574</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>579</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Plant circadian rhythms</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>792</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>803</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheatley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanzawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carre</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title><italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>CCA1</italic> are partially redundant genes required to maintain circadian rhythms in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>641</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Onouchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouradov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Putterill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>et al (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Distinct roles of GIGANTEA in promoting flowering and regulating circadian rhythms in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>2255</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2270</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niwa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamichi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Niinuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genetic linkages of the circadian clock-associated genes, <italic>TOC1</italic>, <italic>CCA1</italic> and <italic>LHY</italic>, in the photoperiodic control of flowering time in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>925</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>937</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabinovich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dancis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonifacino</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Klausner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Copper-dependent degradation of the <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> plasma membrane copper transporter Ctr1p in the apparent absence of endocytosis</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>3515</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3523</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Strickland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>) <article-title>Discussion of spectrophotometric determination of marine-plant pigments, with revised equations for ascertaining chlorophyll-a and carotenoids</article-title>. <source>J Mar Res</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>156</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pena</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>A delicate balance: homeostatic control of copper uptake and distribution</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>1251</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1260</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pe&ntilde;arrubia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Andr&eacute;s-Col&aacute;s</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Regulation of copper transport in Arabidopsis thaliana: a biochemical oscillator</article-title>. <source>J Biol Inorg Chem</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>36</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petris</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Copper-stimulated endocytosis and degradation of the human copper transporter, hCtr1</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>278</volume>: <fpage>9639</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>9646</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plautz</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Straume</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanewsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowse</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Quantitative analysis of <italic>Drosophila period</italic> gene transcription in living animals</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>217</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Andr&eacute;s-Col&aacute;s</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Molina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&ntilde;arrubia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Copper and iron homeostasis in Arabidopsis: responses to metal deficiencies, interactions and biotechnological applications</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>290</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&ntilde;arrubia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Placing metal micronutrients in context: transport and distribution in plants</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>306</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of copper uptake and distribution</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Chem Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>180</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Mobilization of intracellular copper stores by the ctr2 vacuolar copper transporter</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>54221</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>54229</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zobell</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>SBP-domain transcription factors as possible effectors of cryptochrome-mediated blue light signalling in the moss <italic>Physcomitrella patens</italic></article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>227</volume>: <fpage>505</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>515</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salom&eacute;</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Circadian timekeeping during early Arabidopsis development</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>1110</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1125</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sancenon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mateu-Andres</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorcey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&ntilde;arrubia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> copper transporter COPT1 functions in root elongation and pollen development</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>15348</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>15355</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sancenon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Puig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pe&ntilde;arrubia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Identification of a copper transporter family in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>577</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>587</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sire</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Chapa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Moya</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>San Segundo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Diurnal oscillation in the accumulation of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> microRNAs, miR167, miR168, miR171 and miR398</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source> <volume>583</volume>: <fpage>1039</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1044</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unte</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pesaresi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandikota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leister</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title><italic>SPL8</italic>, an SBP-box gene that affects pollen sac development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1009</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1019</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van den Berghe</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Folmer</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Malingre</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>van Beurden</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Klomp</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Sluis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Merkx</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Klomp</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Human copper transporter 2 is localized in late endosomes and lysosomes and facilitates cellular copper uptake</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>407</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>59</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Czech</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>miR156-regulated SPL transcription factors define an endogenous flowering pathway in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>738</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>749</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Temporal regulation of shoot development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> by miR156 and its target <italic>SPL3</italic></article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>3539</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3547</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Copper transport activity of yeast Ctr1 is down-regulated via its C terminus in response to excess copper</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>284</volume>: <fpage>4112</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>4122</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Ghany</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shikanai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Regulation of copper homeostasis by micro-RNA in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>282</volume>: <fpage>16369</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>16378</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukazawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shikanai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>SQUAMOSA promoter binding protein-like7 is a central regulator for copper homeostasis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>361</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>SPL8, a local regulator in a subset of gibberellin-mediated developmental processes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>439</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
