<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">156943</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.156943</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>GENETICS, GENOMICS, AND MOLECULAR EVOLUTION</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>DTH8</italic> Suppresses Flowering in Rice, Influencing Plant Height and Yield Potential Simultaneously<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[OA]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Xiangjin</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Junfeng</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Hongnian</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Ling</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Saihua</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Chuanyuan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Zhenling</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Peisong</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Huqu</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>Jianmin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&ast;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>State Key Laboratory for Crop Genetics and Germplasm Enhancement, Jiangsu Provincial Center of Plant Gene Engineering, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China (X.W., J.X., H.G., L.J., S.C., C.Y., Z.Z., J.W.); Chinese National Center for Rice Improvement, China National Rice Research Institute, Hangzhou 310006, China (X.W., P.H.); Institute of Crop Science, National Key Facility for Crop Gene Resources and Genetic Improvement, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing 100081, China (H.Z., J.W.)</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&ast;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>wanjm@njau.edu.cn</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by grants from the 863 Program of China (grant nos. 2006AA100101, 2006AA10Z1A5, 2006BAD13B01, and 2009AA101101), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant nos. 30871497 and 30571142), Jiangsu Cultivar Development Program (grant no. BE2009301&ndash;3), Doctorial Foundation of Education Department (grant no. 20090097110011), and the 111 Project (grant no. B08025).</p></fn><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Jianmin Wan (<email>wanjm@njau.edu.cn</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[OA]</label><p>Open Access articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.110.156943">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.110.156943</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>8</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>153</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1747</fpage><lpage>1758</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2010 American Society of Plant Biologists</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p></p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The three most important agronomic traits of rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>), yield, plant height, and flowering time, are controlled by many quantitative trait loci (QTLs). In this study, a newly identified QTL, <italic>DTH8</italic> (QTL for days to heading on chromosome 8), was found to regulate these three traits in rice. Map-based cloning reveals that <italic>DTH8</italic> encodes a putative HAP3 subunit of the CCAAT-box-binding transcription factor and the complementary experiment increased significantly days to heading, plant height, and number of grains per panicle in CSSL61 (a chromosome segment substitution line that carries the nonfunctional <italic>DTH8</italic> allele) with the Asominori functional <italic>DTH8</italic> allele under long-day conditions. <italic>DTH8</italic> is expressed in most tissues and its protein is localized to the nucleus exclusively. The quantitative real-time PCR assay revealed that <italic>DTH8</italic> could down-regulate the transcriptions of <italic>Ehd1</italic> (for <italic>Early heading date1</italic>) and <italic>Hd3a</italic> (for <italic>Heading date3a</italic>; a rice ortholog of <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic>) under long-day conditions. <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> can also be down-regulated by the photoperiodic flowering genes <italic>Ghd7</italic> and <italic>Hd1</italic> (a rice ortholog of <italic>CONSTANS</italic>). Meanwhile, the transcription of <italic>DTH8</italic> has been proved to be independent of <italic>Ghd7</italic> and <italic>Hd1</italic>, and the natural mutation of this gene caused weak photoperiod sensitivity and shorter plant height. Taken together, these data indicate that <italic>DTH8</italic> probably plays an important role in the signal network of photoperiodic flowering as a novel suppressor as well as in the regulation of plant height and yield potential.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>As food for more than half of the world&apos;s population, rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) has always been a hot spot in plant science. Its yield is not only determined by spike number, grain weight, and number of grains per panicle but also affected by plant height and flowering time. Recent studies have shown much progress on exploring the mechanism for regulation of yield potential, plant height, and flowering time in rice. Some genes regulating the rice yield trait have already been identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Li et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Ashikari et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Fan et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Song et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Shomura et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Wang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Weng et al., 2008</xref>). The control of rice plant height is mostly related to the synthesis and regulation of the phytohormone, such as GA and brassinolide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Ashikari et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Yamamuroa et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Honga et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Sasaki et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Itoh et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Tanabe et al., 2005</xref>). Photoperiod determines flowering time as the most important environment signal in plants. Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), the model for long-day (LD) species, has been used to reveal how plants control flowering time induced by photoperiod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Corbesier et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Kobayashi and Weigel, 2008</xref>). A series of genes about phytochrome, clock, and flowering have been found and a signal network has been built up. In LD conditions, <italic>CONSTANS</italic> (<italic>CO</italic>) gene in Arabidopsis, being a transcription factor and regulated by <italic>GIGANTEA</italic> (<italic>GI</italic>) gene, which is one of the circadian clock genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Park et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Huq et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Sothern et al., 2002</xref>), activates the expression of <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Kardailsky et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Kobayashi et al., 1999</xref>). After the FT protein moves to the shoot apex, it binds to FD, which is another transcription factor, to trigger genes that determine floral organ identity and then induce flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abe et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Wigge et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Corbesier et al., 2007</xref>). Meanwhile, the short-day (SD) plant rice has a similar photoperiodic control of flowering pathway. Signals from light and circadian clocks are sent to <italic>OsGI</italic> (a rice ortholog of Arabidopsis <italic>GI</italic>) and <italic>OsGI</italic> regulates the expression of <italic>Heading date1</italic> (<italic>Hd1</italic>, a rice ortholog of Arabidopsis <italic>CO</italic>) and <italic>OsMADS51</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yano et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Hayama et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kim et al., 2007</xref>). When rice is in SD conditions, <italic>Hd1</italic> activates flowering by up-regulating <italic>Hd3a</italic> (a rice ortholog of Arabidopsis <italic>FT</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Kojima et al., 2002</xref>). And <italic>OsMADS51</italic> activates <italic>Hd3a</italic> through <italic>Early heading date1</italic> (<italic>Ehd1</italic>), in which <italic>Ehd1</italic> encodes a B-type response regulator and has no obvious counterpart in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Doi et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kim et al., 2007</xref>). By contrast, <italic>Hd1</italic> represses flowering by down-regulating <italic>Hd3a</italic> expression under LD conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Kojima et al., 2002</xref>). Additionally, <italic>RID1</italic>/<italic>OsID1</italic>/<italic>Ehd2</italic>, which is homologous to maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) <italic>Indeterminate1</italic> (<italic>ID1</italic>), promotes flowering in both SD and LD conditions by up-regulating <italic>Ehd1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Matsubara et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Park et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Wu et al., 2008</xref>). <italic>Ghd7</italic>, encoding a CCT domain protein, has been proven to have major effects on an array of traits in rice, including number of grains per panicle, plant height, and flowering time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Xue et al., 2008</xref>); it represses <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> expression and then delays flowering in LD conditions.</p><p>As one of the most common promoter elements found in a large number of genes in animals, fungi, and plants, the CCAAT box is recognized by the HAP complex, which consists of three subunits: HAP2 (NF-YA/CBF-B), HAP3 (NF-YB/CBF-A), and HAP5 (NF-YC/CBF-C; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Maity and de Crombrugghe, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Mantovani, 1999</xref>). In yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) and mammals, each of the HAP subunits is encoded by a single gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Mantovani, 1999</xref>), different from those in plants, in which all subunits are encoded by gene families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Gusmaroli et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">2002</xref>). The Arabidopsis genome encodes 10 AtNF-YA, 13 AtNF-YB, and 13 AtNF-YC subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Gusmaroli et al., 2002</xref>). The rice genome encodes 10 OsHAP2, 11 OsHAP3, and seven OsHAP5 subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Thirumurugan et al., 2008</xref>). Each subunit of the HAP complex contains an evolutionary conserved domain that mediates DNA binding or protein-protein interaction. Recent research suggests that the functional domain conserved within HAP2 and the CCT domain of CO share important residues, which are critical to the function of the CCT domain. CO might replace AtHAP2 in the HAP complex to form a trimetric CO/AtHAP3/AtHAP5 complex and flowering was delayed by overexpression of <italic>AtHAP2</italic> or <italic>AtHAP3</italic> in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Wenkel et al., 2006</xref>). Also, two NF-YB/ HAP3 genes, <italic>LEAFY COTYLEDON1</italic> and <italic>LEC1</italic>-<italic>LIKE</italic>, were shown to be important regulators of embryogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Lotan et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kwong et al., 2003</xref>). In rice, <italic>OsHAP3A</italic> or its homologs, <italic>OsHAP3B</italic> and <italic>OsHAP3C</italic>, were shown to control chloroplast biogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Miyoshi et al., 2003</xref>). However, the functions of other members of the <italic>NF</italic>-<italic>YB</italic>/<italic>HAP3</italic> gene families and all members of the <italic>NF</italic>-<italic>YA</italic>/<italic>HAP2</italic> and <italic>NF</italic>-<italic>YC</italic>/<italic>HAP5</italic> in Arabidopsis and rice are still unknown.</p><p>In this study, we identified a rice <italic>HAP3</italic> gene, <italic>DTH8</italic>, by map-based cloning. Our data showed that <italic>DTH8</italic> suppressed rice flowering under LD conditions and we surmise that it probably plays an important role in the regulation of plant height and yield potential in rice.</p><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>A Chromosome Segment of <italic>DTH8</italic> Has a Remarkable Effect on Flowering Time, Plant Height, and Yield</title><p>Quantitative trait loci (QTL) analysis for days to heading was conducted over 5 years in natural LD (NLD) conditions (daylength &gt; 14 h) based on a recombinant inbred line population (RIL), derived from two parents, cv Asominori (<italic>japonica</italic>) and cv IR24 (<italic>indica</italic>; Supplemental Fig. S1). One major QTL, <italic>DTH8</italic>, near marker R2976 on the short arm of chromosome 8 has been detected in all 5 years (Supplemental Table S1). Several chromosome segment substitution lines (CSSLs), such as CSSL8 and CSSL61, carrying a chromosome segment of IR24 on <italic>DTH8</italic> under the Asominori genetic background, showed earlier heading and its plant height, number of grains per panicle, yield, and dry weight per plant decreased significantly in NLD condition compared with Asominori (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S2; Supplemental Table S2), but no significant differences in these agronomic traits have been found in natural SD (NSD) conditions (daylength about 11.6 h; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; Supplemental Table S3). There was no difference in tiller number between CSSL61 and Asominori under either NLD or NSD conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; Supplemental Tables S2 and S3).</p><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Phenotypes of Asominori and CSSL61. A, Photos of Asominori and CSSL61, taken when CSSL61 reached maturity. B, Photos of Asominori and CSSL61, taken when Asominori reached maturity. C, Main panicles of Asominori and CSSL61. D, Grains from the main panicles of Asominori and CSSL61. A to D, Asominori and CSSL61 were grown under NLD conditions. E, Photos of Asominori and CSSL61, taken under NSD conditions. A to E, The left is Asominori and right is CSSL61. F, Days to heading of Asominori and CSSL61 in different daylength conditions. G, The genotype of CSSL61.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp156943F01_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1"><label>Table I.</label><caption><title>Phenotypes of Asominori, CSSL61, transgene-positive, and transgene-negative segregants in the T1 generation derived from T0 plants with single-copy transgenes under NLD conditions</title><p>Family 1 and 2 are the T1 plants derived from two independent T0 plants with single-copy transgene. Data are mean &plusmn; <sc>se</sc>. (&plus;) and (&minus;) indicate transgene-positive and transgene-negative, respectively.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Genotype</td><td align="center">No. of Plants</td><td align="center">No. of Days to Heading</td><td align="center">Plant Height in cm</td><td align="center">No. of Spikelets per Panicle</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Asominori</td><td align="char" char=".">20</td><td align="center">93.0 &plusmn; 1.3</td><td align="center">85.3 &plusmn; 3.2</td><td align="center">88.7 &plusmn; 10.9</td></tr><tr><td>CSSL61</td><td align="char" char=".">20</td><td align="center">80.0 &plusmn; 2.1</td><td align="center">71.3 &plusmn; 3.0</td><td align="center">59.2 &plusmn; 5.9</td></tr><tr><td><italic>P</italic> value (<italic>t</italic> test)</td><td></td><td align="center">2.21 &times; 10<sup>&minus;14</sup></td><td align="center">1.80 &times; 10<sup>&minus;8</sup></td><td align="center">3.21 &times; 10<sup>&minus;5</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Family 1 (&plus;)</td><td align="char" char=".">31</td><td align="center">89.8 &plusmn; 2.8</td><td align="center">81.6 &plusmn; 6.3</td><td align="center">90.9 &plusmn; 19.3</td></tr><tr><td>Family 1 (&minus;)</td><td align="char" char=".">12</td><td align="center">80.5 &plusmn; 3.4</td><td align="center">69.2 &plusmn; 7.4</td><td align="center">63.1 &plusmn; 12.2</td></tr><tr><td><italic>P</italic> value (<italic>t</italic> test)</td><td></td><td align="center">1.17 &times; 10<sup>&minus;7</sup></td><td align="center">3.65 &times; 10<sup>&minus;5</sup></td><td align="center">1.63 &times; 10<sup>&minus;6</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Family 2 (&plus;)</td><td align="char" char=".">33</td><td align="center">92.4 &plusmn; 1.4</td><td align="center">78.4 &plusmn; 4.2</td><td align="center">99.7 &plusmn; 11.6</td></tr><tr><td>Family 2 (&minus;)</td><td align="char" char=".">13</td><td align="center">80.0 &plusmn; 2.6</td><td align="center">65.6 &plusmn; 7.4</td><td align="center">56.6 &plusmn; 13.3</td></tr><tr><td><italic>P</italic> value (<italic>t</italic> test)</td><td></td><td align="center">5.08 &times; 10<sup>&minus;11</sup></td><td align="center">1.43 &times; 10<sup>&minus;5</sup></td><td align="center">1.29 &times; 10<sup>&minus;9</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title><italic>DTH8</italic> Encodes a Putative HAP3 Subunit of the CCAAT-Box-Binding Transcription Factor</title><p>An analysis of two secondary F2 populations, derived from the cross between CSSL8, CSSL61, and Asominori, showed that earlier heading and later heading plants of the two secondary F2 populations segregated as 62:164 and 56:150, respectively (<italic>&chi;</italic><sup>2</sup> &equals; 0.71, 0.52 &lt; <italic>&chi;</italic><sup>2</sup><sub>2,0.05</sub> &equals; 3.84, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05; Supplemental Fig. S3), which suggests that <italic>DTH8</italic> is a single Mendelian factor. Then, map-based cloning of <italic>DTH8</italic> was performed. A high-resolution linkage analysis demonstrated that <italic>DTH8</italic> is delimited within the interval between two insertion-deletion (Ind) markers, Ind8-47 and Ind8-15. This region was about 47 kb in the bacterial artificial chromosome contig OSJNBa0054L03 (http://www.gramene.org; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Map-based cloning of <italic>DTH8</italic>. A, Fine mapping of <italic>DTH8</italic>. B, Structure of <italic>DTH8</italic>. Vertical lines without labels represent single-base substitutions between Asominori and IR24. Small rectangular boxes and arrowheads represent deletions and insertions, respectively. C, <italic>DTH8</italic> cDNA and predicted amino acid sequence. Letters with an asterisk indicate 1-bp deletion IR24, and the amino acids with gray background represent the conserved domains for DNA binding or protein-protein interaction. F.S. and STOP represent frameshift mutation and create premature stop codon, respectively. D, A phylogenic tree of HAP3 protein families in rice, Arabidopsis, yeast (ScHAP3, NP_009532), and human (HsNF-B, L06145). The unrooted tree was generated based on the amino acid sequences of the conserved domain using the program DNAMAN. The scale represents the substitution percentage per site, and the similarity to <italic>DTH8</italic> in the conserved domain of each HAP protein is indicated in parentheses.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp156943F02_HT" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>The genome annotation software, RiceGAAS (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ricegaas.dna.affrc.go.jp">http://ricegaas.dna.affrc.go.jp</ext-link>), predicts 12 open reading frames (ORFs) in this region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). One of them, ORF4, encodes a putative HAP3/ NF-YB/CBF-A subunit of the CCAAT-box-binding transcription factor, and has been annotated as a flowering-time gene, <italic>Hd5</italic>, in the database (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>). There are 11 homologous genes (<italic>OsHAP3A</italic>&ndash;<italic>OsHAP3K</italic>) encoding HAP3 subunits in the genome of rice and ORF4 is named <italic>OsHAP3H</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Thirumurugan et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2D</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S4). Without any intron, the reading frame of <italic>OsHAP3H</italic> totals 894 bp, encoding a protein of 297 amino acids in cv Asominori (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, B and C</xref>). However, in cv IR24, 1-bp deletion was found in a position 322 bp away from start codon, causing a frameshift and premature termination of translation and leading to a mutant protein with only 125 amino acids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>).</p><p>To confirm that <italic>OsHAP3H</italic> is responsible for the phenotype of <italic>DTH8</italic>, the <italic>OsHAP3H</italic> cDNA from cv Asominori was expressed under CSSL61 background. The cDNA was inserted into pPZP2H-lac binary vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Fuse et al., 2001</xref>) and 13 independent transgenic T0 lines were generated, which were planted in NSD conditions. The segregation ratio between transgene-positive and transgene-negative plants in T1 families from T0 plants with single-copy transgene was about 3:1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). Perfect cosegregation between the transgene and the phenotype was also observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>): comparing with transgene-negative plants, days to heading, plant height, and number of grains per panicle of all transgene-positive plants increased significantly. Taken together, <italic>DTH8</italic>, which encodes a putative HAP3/NF-YB/CBF-A subunit of the CCAAT-box-binding transcription factor, has a large effect on flowering time, plant height, and yield potential in rice.</p><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Comparison of phenotype of the <italic>DTH8</italic> transformants and CSSL61 plants. A, Transgene-positive T1 plant (left) and CSSL61 plant (right). B, Transgene-positive T1 plant (left) and transgene-negative T1 plant (right). C, Main panicles of transgene-positive T1 plant (left) and transgene-negative T1 plant (right).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp156943F03_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Expression Pattern and Subcellular Localization of <italic>DTH8</italic></title><p>Quantitative real-time PCR (QRT-PCR) analyses were done with total RNA isolated from leaves, leaf sheaths, culms, young panicles, and roots from cv Asominori grown under NLD conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). The results revealed that <italic>DTH8</italic> was expressed in all examined tissues: The expressions were higher in roots, young panicles, and leaves than those in leaf sheaths and culms. To reconfirm the results above, the <italic>GUS</italic> gene driven by the <italic>DTH8</italic> promoter was transformed into rice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Staining of transgenic plants verified again the <italic>DTH8</italic> expression in the same tissues examined with QRT-PCR. The staining also showed more accumulation in roots, young panicles, and leaves, which matched the QRT-PCR findings.</p><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Expression pattern of <italic>DTH8</italic> and subcellular localization of its protein. A, Tissue-specific expression pattern revealed by QRT-PCR. RNA was isolated from leaves (L), leaf sheaths (S), culms (C), young panicles (P), and roots (R) from Asominori when it was heading in NLD conditions. B, GUS expression in different tissues driven by <italic>DTH8</italic> promoter under NLD conditions. a to f, Root, culm, node, leaf blade, leaf sheath, and young panicles. C, Nuclear localization of DTH8. a and e, Bright-field images of onion epidermal cells. b, Nuclear localization of DTH8-GFP fluorescence. c, The same cells stained with DAPI. d, The merged image of a, b, and c. f, Onion epidermal cells bombarded with the construct having GFP alone as the control. g, The merged image of e and f.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp156943F04_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Subcellular localization of DTH8 protein was carried out by fusing <italic>DTH8</italic> and <italic>GFP</italic>, which was driven by the cauliflower mosaic virus 35S promoter (<italic>35S</italic>::<italic>DTH8</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>) and delivered into onion (<italic>Allium cepa</italic>) epidermal cells by particle bombardment. The GFP signal was localized in the nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>), indicating that DTH8 is a nuclear protein. This result also supports the hypothesis that DTH8 acts as a subunit of the CCAAT-box-binding transcription factor.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>DTH8</italic> Suppresses Flowering by Down-Regulating <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic></title><p>To identify potential downstream genes that are regulated by <italic>DTH8</italic>, QRT-PCR was performed to analyze the expression levels of <italic>DTH8</italic> and seven flowering-related genes (<italic>Hd1</italic>, <italic>Ehd1</italic>, <italic>Hd3a</italic>, <italic>Ghd7</italic>, <italic>OsGI</italic>, <italic>OsMADS51</italic>, and <italic>RID1</italic>) in both Asominori and CSSL61. Leaf samples from 40-d-old plants grown under SD, LD, and NLD conditions were checked. No differences in <italic>DTH8</italic> expression were found between Asominori and CSSL61 under all three conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S5), suggesting that the natural mutation in the coding region does not significantly affect the expression of <italic>DTH8</italic>, and neither did the differences in <italic>OsGI</italic>, <italic>RID1</italic>, <italic>OsMADS51</italic>, and <italic>Ghd7</italic> expressions between Asominori and CSSL61 in all conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S5). For <italic>Hd1</italic>, the natural mutation of <italic>DTH8</italic> slightly induced its down expression in SD conditions but not under LD and NLD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S5). For <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> genes, this mutation led to a great reduction of transcription in CSSL61 under LD and NLD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S5). These results suggest that <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> possibly function downstream of <italic>DTH8</italic>, which suppresses rice flowering in LD condition by down-regulating <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic>. However, the expression of <italic>Ehd1</italic> was only slightly lower, whereas <italic>Hd3a</italic> expression was not changed at all in SD conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S5). This result was consistent with the observation that flowering time was not significantly different between Asominori and CSSL61 in SD conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; Supplemental Table S3).</p><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>The expression of <italic>DTH8</italic> and other flowering-time genes in Asominori and CSSL61. QRT-PCR was performed with total RNA from leaves of 40-d-old plants under SD and LD conditions. Samples were collected at the initiation of the light phase (ZT 0 h). These experiments were repeated at least three times.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp156943F05_LW" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Also, the diurnal expression patterns of <italic>DTH8</italic>, <italic>OsGI</italic>, <italic>Hd1</italic>, <italic>Ehd1</italic>, <italic>Hd3a</italic>, and <italic>Ghd7</italic> were checked in both Asominori and CSSL61 (Supplemental Fig. S6). The diurnal pattern of <italic>DTH8</italic> is similar to that of <italic>OsGI</italic> in both LD and SD conditions. As in the single measurements at the onset of the light phase, severe reductions in <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> mRNA were detected in both day and night cycles under LD conditions in Asominori. Meanwhile, little change was found in the diurnal patterns of <italic>OsGI</italic>, <italic>Hd1</italic>, <italic>Ehd1</italic>, <italic>Hd3a</italic>, and <italic>Ghd7</italic> expressions between Asominori and CSSL61 in both LD and SD conditions.</p></sec><sec><title>The Expression of <italic>DTH8</italic> Is Not Influenced by <italic>Hd1</italic> and <italic>Ghd7</italic></title><p>Previous studies show that the expression of <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> could be down-regulated by <italic>Ghd7</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Xue et al., 2008</xref>) and <italic>Hd3a</italic> can also be suppressed by <italic>Hd1</italic> under LD conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Kojima et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Hayama et al., 2003</xref>). In this study, our data showed that under LD conditions, <italic>DTH8</italic> could negatively influence the expression of <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> but not <italic>Hd1</italic> and <italic>Ghd7</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S5). To examine whether the expression of <italic>DTH8</italic> is influenced by <italic>Hd1</italic> and <italic>Ghd7</italic>, <italic>DTH8</italic> expression was examined in <italic>Hd1</italic> and <italic>Ghd7</italic> near-isogenic lines (NILs) grown for 40 d under LD conditions. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6A</xref> and Supplemental Figure S7A, the expression levels of <italic>DTH8</italic> and <italic>Ghd7</italic>, compared with those in Nipponbare, were not changed in NIL (<italic>hd1</italic>) grown under LD conditions. However, <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> were suppressed by <italic>Hd1</italic> in Nipponbare. Similarly, no changes were found in the levels of <italic>DTH8</italic> and <italic>Hd1</italic> mRNA in the <italic>Ghd7</italic> NILs under LD conditions. But the expressions of <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> were also suppressed by <italic>Ghd7</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S7B). These results indicate that <italic>DTH8</italic> suppresses rice flowering by down-regulating the expression of <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic>, and that the expression of <italic>DTH8</italic>, <italic>Hd1</italic>, or <italic>Ghd7</italic> is independent of each other under LD conditions.</p><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>The expression of <italic>DTH8</italic> and other flowering-time genes in the NILs of <italic>Hd1</italic> and <italic>Ghd7</italic> under LD conditions. A, The expression in cv Nipponbare (Nip) and NIL (<italic>hd1</italic>; carries <italic>hd1</italic> introgressed from cv Kasalath in a cv Nipponbare genetic background). B, The expression in NIL (<italic>Ghd7</italic>; carries functional <italic>Ghd7</italic> from Minghui63) and NIL (<italic>ghd7</italic>; carries nonfunctional <italic>ghd7</italic> from Zhenshan97). QRT-PCR was performed with total RNA from leaves of 40-d-old plants under LD conditions. Samples were collected at the initiation of the light phase (ZT 0 h). These experiments were repeated at least three times.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp156943F06_LW" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title><italic>DTH8</italic> Regulates the Stem Growth</title><p>During maturity, the average height of CSSL61 and transgene-negative plants was approximately 84% of Asominori and transgene-positive plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs. 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3B</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table I</xref>). The internode elongation patterns between CSSL61 and Asominori were compared (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S8) and the data showed that the panicles and internodes of CSSL61 were remarkably shorter than those of Asominori. Meanwhile, the diameter of stems between them was almost the same. To determine whether the dwarf phenotype of the CSSL61 results from defective cell division and/or cell elongation, longitudinal sections of internodes III and IV of CSSL61 culms were compared with their Asominori counterparts. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7, C, F, and G</xref>, the total cell number in the <italic>y</italic> axes in internodes III and IV of CSSL61 was not significantly less than that of Asominori, while the cell length of CSSL61 was significantly shorter. This result suggests that internode cell elongation is the main reason for the dwarf phenotype of CSSL61 and that <italic>DTH8</italic> probably plays an important role in stem growth and development.</p><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>The differences of the culms and scanning electron microscopic (SEM) observation of internodes between Asominori and CSSL61 plants. A, Main culms of Asominori (left) and CSSL61 (right) plants. Arrows indicate the positions of nodes. B, The differences of panicles and internodes of main culms between Asominori (left) and CSSL61 (right) plants. P, Panicle. Those from I to V indicate the corresponding internodes from top to bottom. C, Total cell number of internodes III and IV in <italic>y</italic> axis. D and E, SEM of transverse sections of the middle part of internode IV of Asominori (D) and CSSL61 (E) plants at the mature stage. F and G, SEM of longitudinal sections of the middle part of internode IV of Asominori (F) and CSSL61 (G) plants at the mature stage.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp156943F07_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Rice Varieties with Nonfunctional <italic>DTH8</italic> Have Weaker Sensitivity to Photoperiod</title><p>We investigated the diversity of the coding sequences of <italic>DTH8</italic> among 40 rice varieties from a wide geographic range in Asia (Supplemental Table S4). The <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles in these varieties were grouped into nine types and eight distinct proteins were identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). Frameshift mutations or premature stops caused by the deletions of some nucleotides were found in types 7, 8 (IR24), and 9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). So, the DTH8 proteins of these three allele types seem nonfunctional. For other types, the protein of type 2 is same as that of type 1 (Asominori), and types 3 to 6 just have several SNPs and indels that could cause single amino acid substitution, addition, or deletion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). Therefore, the proteins encoded by types 2 to 6 are probably functional. To confirm this, the <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles of type 4 (from cv Kasalath), type 5 (from cv 93-11), and type 6 (from cv IR64) were transformed into the CSSL61 (with nonfunctional <italic>DTH8</italic> allele from IR24) background. The results showed that all transgene-positive plants in the T1 families were tall and late heading with large panicles, whereas all transgene-negative plants have phenotypes with opposite features (Supplemental Fig. S9; Supplemental Table S5). We can thus separate the cultivars into two groups, functional and nonfunctional <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>; Supplemental Table S4). The photoperiod sensitivity (PS) of flowering time in these varieties was also analyzed using PS index (PS index &equals; [DTH<sub>NLD</sub> &minus; DTH<sub><sc>sd</sc></sub>]/DTH<sub>NLD</sub>; DTH, NLD, and SD represent days to heading, NLD, and SD conditions, respectively; Supplemental Table S4). The results showed that cultivars that carry the functional <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles tended to have larger PS indexes and that their flowering times were more sensitive to photoperiod, whereas those carrying nonfunctional <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles tended to show smaller PS indexes and less photoperiod-sensitive flowering times (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>; Supplemental Table S4).</p><fig id="fig8"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Different types of <italic>DTH8</italic> and their relationships with PS of flowering time. Type 1 is the genotype of cv Asominori. Polymorphic nucleotides in other cultivars are indicated by different colors. Deletion and insertion sites are indicated by white and black arrowheads, respectively. The number of cultivars and the mean value of PS index with each type of sequence (types from 1&ndash;9) are shown in the column at the right, with the numbers for loss-of-function types in red. The amino acid sequences of types 1 and 2 are identical. F.S. is frameshift and STOP is premature stop.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp156943F08_RGB" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><sec><title><italic>DTH8</italic> Has Pleiotropic Effects</title><p>Yield, plant height, and flowering time are the three most important agronomic traits in rice. Grain yield is mainly determined by factors such as spike/tiller number, number of grains per panicle, and grain weight. Recently, some genes related to yield have been cloned, e.g. <italic>MOC1</italic>, which initiates axillary buds and plays an important role in the control of rice tillering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Li et al., 2003</xref>); <italic>Gn1a</italic> controls the number of grains per panicle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Ashikari et al., 2005</xref>); <italic>GS3</italic>, <italic>GW2</italic>, and <italic>qSW5</italic>/<italic>GW5</italic> regulate grain size (grain length and grain width) and grain weight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Fan et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Song et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Shomura et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Weng et al., 2008</xref>); and <italic>GIF1</italic> controls rice grain filling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Wang et al., 2008</xref>). More genes for plant height in rice have been identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Ashikari et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Yamamuroa et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Sasaki et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Honga et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Itoh et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Tanabe et al., 2005</xref>). The molecular genetic pathway for flowering time has been under elucidation in rice since the isolation of many correlative genes or QTLs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yano et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Kojima et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Doi et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kim et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Wu et al., 2008</xref>). Although there are close correlations among yield, plant height, and flowering time, most of these genes were reported to be regulating only one of the three traits. Recently, one QTL, <italic>Ghd7</italic>, has been proven to have large pleiotropic effects on an array of traits, including grain number, flowering time, and plant height (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Xue et al., 2008</xref>). In this study, a rice <italic>HAP3</italic> gene, <italic>DTH8</italic>, was isolated by map-based cloning. Its large pleiotropic effects were likewise demonstrated. <italic>DTH8</italic> also delayed rice flowering by negatively influencing the expression of <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic>, being independent of <italic>Hd1</italic> under LD conditions. Simultaneously, it plays an important role in regulating plant height and grain number. Meanwhile, the differences between <italic>DTH8</italic> and <italic>Ghd7</italic> were also very obvious. Tiller number in <italic>Ghd7</italic> NILs with functional or nonfunctional alleles differed from each other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Xue et al., 2008</xref>); those between Asominori and CSSL61 are the same (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; Supplemental Tables S2 and S3). <italic>Ghd7</italic> regulates the height through total cell number in the <italic>y</italic> axes of internodes and it also influences culm thickness, whereas <italic>DTH8</italic> regulates height by altering cell elongation in the internodes, but keeps culm thickness stable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title><italic>DTH8</italic> Is a Novel Flowering Suppressor</title><p>Rice is a SD plant and most rice cultivars could be induced to flower more rapidly under SD conditions than under LD conditions. In SD conditions, signals from light and circadian clocks are received by <italic>OsGI</italic>, and it regulates the expression of <italic>Hd1</italic> and <italic>OsMADS51</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Izawa et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kim et al., 2007</xref>). <italic>Hd1</italic> induces rice flowering by up-regulating <italic>Hd3a</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Kojima et al., 2002</xref>), while <italic>OsMADS51</italic> promotes flowering by activating the expression of <italic>Hd3a</italic> through <italic>Ehd1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Doi et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kim et al., 2007</xref>). In LD conditions, the expression of <italic>Hd3a</italic> is suppressed by <italic>Hd1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Hayama et al., 2003</xref>), and <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> are also suppressed by <italic>Ghd7</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Xue et al., 2008</xref>), which accounts for the late flowering in rice. Additionally, <italic>RID1</italic>/<italic>OsID1</italic>/<italic>Ehd2</italic> promotes flowering under both SD and LD conditions by up-regulating <italic>Ehd1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Matsubara et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Park et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Wu et al., 2008</xref>). In this study, <italic>DTH8</italic> was found to delay rice flowering time by negatively influencing the expression of <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> in LD conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S5). But, under SD conditions, the expression of <italic>Hd3a</italic> and rice flowering time are not influenced by <italic>DTH8</italic>, and neither are the expressions of <italic>RID1</italic>, <italic>OsGI</italic>, <italic>Hd1</italic>, and <italic>Ghd7</italic> in LD conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S5). Meanwhile, the expression of <italic>DTH8</italic> is independent of <italic>Hd1</italic> and <italic>Ghd7</italic> in LD conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S7), suggesting that <italic>DTH8</italic> is a flowering suppressor by down-regulating the expression of <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> under LD conditions. There are many studies to have reported that <italic>Ehd1</italic> locates in the upstream of <italic>Hd3a</italic> and could promote its expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Doi et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kim et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Matsubara et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Park et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Wu et al., 2008</xref>). At the same time, some other reports show that the flowering suppressor could repress <italic>Hd3a</italic> expression by down-regulating <italic>Ehd1</italic> and then inhibits flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Xue et al., 2008</xref>). So we propose that <italic>DTH8</italic> is upstream of <italic>Ehd1</italic>, which in turn is upstream of <italic>Hd3a</italic> in the pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>). The diurnal expression pattern of <italic>DTH8</italic> is similar to that of <italic>OsGI</italic> in both LD and SD conditions (Supplemental Fig. S6), suggesting that <italic>DTH8</italic> probably locates downstream of <italic>OsGI</italic> in the pathway that regulates photoperiodic flowering time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>). Because there is no <italic>Ehd1</italic> ortholog in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Doi et al., 2004</xref>), the <italic>DTH8</italic>-<italic>Ehd1</italic>-<italic>Hd3a</italic> relation probably represents a distinct pathway that does not exist in Arabidopsis.</p><fig id="fig9"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>A proposed model for the initiation and integration of the flowering pathways in rice under LD conditions.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="pp156943F09_LW" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Previous research shows that <italic>Hd1</italic> and <italic>Ehd1</italic> regulate the expression of <italic>Hd3a</italic> through two different pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Doi et al., 2004</xref>). However, the results from this study showed that the expression of <italic>Ehd1</italic> is suppressed by <italic>Hd1</italic> in LD conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S7A). So <italic>Ehd1</italic> may be the integrator of different pathways in the regulation of flowering, which is down-regulated by <italic>Hd1</italic>, <italic>Ghd7</italic>, and <italic>DTH8</italic> but up-regulated by <italic>RID1</italic>. Then, the expression of <italic>Hd3a</italic> or its orthologs was activated by <italic>Ehd1</italic> and the transition from vegetative development to floral development in rice was induced under LD conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Possible Reason for the Pleiotropic Effects of <italic>DTH8</italic></title><p>The protein encoded by <italic>DTH8</italic> is a putative HAP3/NF-YB/CBF-A subunit of the HAP complex, OsHAP3H (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>), which binds to CCAAT box that is the cis-acting element in about 25% of eukaryotic promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Maity and de Crombrugghe, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Mantovani, 1999</xref>). The HAP complex consists of three subunits: HAP2/NF-YA/CBF-B, HAP3/NF-YB/CBF-A, and HAP5/NF-YC/CBF-C. Each subunit of the HAP complex contains a conserved domain that is responsible for DNA binding or protein-protein interaction. Although many genes encoding HAP subunits have been found so far (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Edwards et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Gusmaroli et al., 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Thirumurugan et al., 2008</xref>), only a few of them have been studied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Lotan et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Meinke, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">West et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kwong et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Miyoshi et al., 2003</xref>). In this study, a rice <italic>HAP3</italic> gene, <italic>DTH8</italic>, has been proven to play an important role in the regulation of flowering time, plant height, and yield potential. Because of the existence of multiple HAP2 and HAP5 subunit orthologs, the HAP complexes OsHAP2/DTH8/OsHAP5 should not be the only one that may bind to the CCAAT boxes in those genes working in different metabolic pathways. The genes controlling the number of primary branches and second branches are regulated by the OsHAP2/ DTH8/OsHAP5 complexes, which could influence the number of grains per panicle. Rice height was affected by DTH8 or OsHAP complexes mainly through the regulation of internode cell elongation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). According to previous reports, the control of rice height is mostly related to the synthesis and regulation of phytohormones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Ashikari et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Yamamuroa et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Sasaki et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Honga et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Itoh et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Tanabe et al., 2005</xref>). The OsHAP2/DTH8/OsHAP5 complexes may be involved in the biosynthesis or degradation of phytohormones.</p><p>In this study, we found that <italic>DTH8</italic> delayed rice flowering time by down-regulating the expression of <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> in LD conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). But the expressions of <italic>DTH8</italic>, <italic>Hd1</italic>, and <italic>Ghd7</italic> were not influenced by each other under LD conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figs. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6</xref>), suggesting that the down-regulation of <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> by <italic>DTH8</italic> may be independent of <italic>Hd1</italic> and <italic>Ghd7</italic> under these conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>). Recent research has shown that the conserved domain of HAP2 and the CCT domain of CO are similar to each other, where the most conserved residues are very important for the functioning of the CCT domain. CO could replace AtHAP2 in the HAP complex to form a trimetric complex, CO/AtHAP3/AtHAP5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Wenkel et al., 2006</xref>). In LD conditions, flowering was postponed by overexpression of <italic>AtHAP2</italic> or <italic>AtHAP3</italic> in Arabidopsis. Meanwhile, <italic>FT</italic> expression was going down while the level of <italic>CO</italic> remained stable. The mRNA abundance of <italic>AtHAP3a</italic> shows a diurnal rhythm and is regulated by the flowering-time gene <italic>GI</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Wenkel et al., 2006</xref>). The rice flowering genes <italic>Hd1</italic> and <italic>Ghd7</italic> also have the CCT domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Yano et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Xue et al., 2008</xref>) so they may be able to replace OsHAP2 in the HAP complex. Thus, we speculate that the down-regulation of <italic>Ehd1</italic> and <italic>Hd3a</italic> by <italic>DTH8</italic>, <italic>Hd1</italic>, and <italic>Ghd7</italic> might be mediated by forming the possible complexes Hd1/DTH8/OsHAP5 and Ghd7/DTH8/OsHAP5. Of course, more evidences are needed to test this hypothesis.</p></sec><sec><title>Relationship between <italic>DTH8</italic> and PS</title><p>A high degree of polymorphism in the <italic>DTH8</italic> sequences was identified, some of which cause frameshift mutations or create premature stop codons. The <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles in the core collection were grouped into nine types and eight distinct proteins were identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). All the cultivars were separated into groups with functional or nonfunctional <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles, depending on the results of transgenic analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S9; Supplemental Tables S4 and S5). Being a SD plant, the flowering time of rice is sensitive to variation in photoperiod induced by SD conditions and blocked by LD conditions. But with the long period of introduction and domestication, some rice varieties have become insensitive to photoperiod variation and flowering time of rice show little or even no difference when they are grown under either SD or LD conditions. Varieties with weak PS are usually grown in high-latitude area or in mid- and low-latitude area as early season rice.</p><p>The PS of flowering time for 40 varieties was also analyzed by looking at the PS index (Supplemental Table S4). The results showed that flowering times of cultivars that carry functional <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles are more sensitive to photoperiod, whereas those with nonfunctional <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles are less sensitive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>; Supplemental Table S4). However, there are still some exceptions, such as cv Jingnong1, cv XX-4, and cv 93-11. The flowering times of these varieties are weakly sensitive to photoperiod, even though they carry the functional <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles (Supplemental Table S5). The possible reason is that these cultivars may contain other unknown genes that can weaken their PS. The cultivars having nonfunctional <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles and showing weaker PS are grown as early season rice in mid- and low-latitude areas (Supplemental Table S5). Thus, it might be a better choice to breed rice cultivars with nonfunctional <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles in high-latitude areas or as early season rice in mid- and low-latitude areas. The cultivars with weaker PS would be able to adapt well to LD conditions. Similarly, while breeding single or late-season rice for the mid- or low-latitude areas, cultivars with functional <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles should be chosen because the flowering of these cultivars could be induced by the SD conditions and their grain yield could be increased by <italic>DTH8</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Plant Materials and Growth Conditions</title><p>A RIL and several CSSLs derived from two parents, cv Asominori (<italic>japonica</italic>) and cv IR24 (<italic>indica</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kubo et al., 1999</xref>; Supplemental Fig. S1), were grown in Nanjing NLD conditions (daylength &gt; 14 h). The materials that include Asominori, CSSL61, Nipponbare, NIL (<italic>hd1</italic>), NIL (<italic>Ghd7</italic>), and NIL (<italic>ghd7</italic>) for the expression of <italic>DTH8</italic> and other flowering genes were grown in NLD, LD (15 h light/9 h dark), and SD (9 h light/15 h dark) conditions. Asominori and CSSL61, for the analysis of diurnal expression patterns of flowering genes, were first grown in NLD conditions for 30 d and then transferred to LD or SD conditions for 10 d. The transgene-positive T0 and T1 plants were grown in NSD (about 11.6 h light/12.4 h dark) conditions (Hainan Province, China) and NLD conditions, respectively. The 40 varieties from Asia for genotyping the <italic>DTH8</italic> locus were grown under NLD and SD conditions.</p></sec><sec><title>Mapping for <italic>DTH8</italic></title><p>The RILs and several CSSLs derived from Asominori (<italic>japonica</italic>) and IR24 (<italic>indica</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Tsunematsu et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kubo et al., 1999</xref>) were used for primary mapping of the <italic>DTH8</italic> locus (Supplemental Fig. S1). The secondary F2 population containing 15,000 plants was constructed from the cross between CSSL61 and Asominori and 2,000 earliest plants were selected to fine map the <italic>DTH8</italic> locus, using the approach described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Zhang et al. (1994)</xref>. <italic>DTH8</italic> was first localized to a 2.3-cM interval between simple sequence repeat (SSR) markers RM22475 and RM5556, based on 200 earliest plants. After more than nine SSR or InDel markers were developed between RM22475 and RM5556, 40 recombinant plants were selected and <italic>DTH8</italic> was finally narrowed to the 47-kb region between Ind8-47 and Ind8-15 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). The molecular markers including SSR and InDel markers used for fine mapping <italic>DTH8</italic> are shown in Supplemental Table S6.</p></sec><sec><title>Vector Construction and Transformation</title><p>The full-length coding region of <italic>DTH8</italic> was isolated by PCR with primers 8 to 16 (Supplemental Table S7) from Asominori, Kasalath, 93-11, and IR64, then subcloned into the pPZP2H-lac binary vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Fuse et al., 2001</xref>). The resultant plasmid was introduced into CSSL61 by means of <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Hiei et al., 1994</xref>). The genotype of transgenic plants was determined by PCR amplification of the hygromycin phosphotransferase gene (<italic>hpt</italic>) and the analysis of hygromycin resistance.</p><p>A 2.5-kb sequence of <italic>DTH8</italic> promoter region was isolated by PCR amplification with primers Pro-14 (Supplemental Table S7) from Asominori and then subcloned into the pCAMBIA1381Z binary vector. The resulted plasmid was transformed into rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) through <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation, and the transgenic plants were analyzed by GUS staining assay as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Scarpella et al., 2003</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>RNA Extraction and QRT-PCR</title><p>Total RNA from leaves, leaf sheaths, culms, roots, and young panicles were isolated using an RNA extraction kit following the manufacturer&apos;s instruction (Beijing Dingguo Biotechnology Co. Ltd., <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dingguo.com">http://www.dingguo.com</ext-link>). First-strand cDNA was reverse transcribed from DNase I-treated RNA with oligo(dT) as the primer. Gene expression was measured by QRT-PCR and semiquantitative RT-PCR using <italic>Ubiquitin</italic> and <italic>Actin</italic> gene as internal controls. The QRT-PCR and semiquantitative PCR primers for <italic>Actin</italic>, <italic>DTH8</italic>, <italic>OsGI</italic>, <italic>Hd1</italic>, <italic>Hd3a</italic>, <italic>Ehd1</italic>, <italic>Ghd7</italic>, <italic>RID1</italic>, and <italic>OsMADS51</italic> are listed in Supplemental Table S8. The QRT-PCR was carried out in a total volume of 25 <italic>&mu;</italic>L containing 2 <italic>&mu;</italic>L of the reverse-transcribed product above, 0.2 <italic>&mu;</italic><sc>m</sc> of each primer and 1&times; SYBR green PCR master mix (TaKaRa Co. Ltd., <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.takara.com.cn">http://www.takara.com.cn</ext-link>). The PCR was performed with a Bio-Rad iCycler (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bio-rad.com/">http://www.bio-rad.com/</ext-link>) using the following program: 95&deg;C for 30 s, then 40 cycles of 95&deg;C for 5 s, 60&deg;C for 34 s. Changes in gene expression were calculated via the &Delta;&Delta;CT method. The semiquantitative PCR conditions were 95&deg;C for 3 min, then 26 cycles (cycle numbers for <italic>Actin</italic> were 26; <italic>DTH8</italic> and <italic>OsGI</italic> were 28; others were 30&ndash;35) of 95&deg;C for 30 s, 58&deg;C for 30 s, and 72&deg;C for 30 s.</p></sec><sec><title>Subcellular Localization</title><p>The <italic>DTH8</italic> ORF without a termination codon was cloned into the pA7-GFP vector, placing the <italic>DTH8</italic> gene upstream of the GFP coding sequence to create in-frame fusion of <italic>DTH8</italic> cDNA and GFP reporter gene. The fusion constructs, as well as the control (pA7-GFP), were transformed into onion (<italic>Allium cepa</italic>) epidermal cells by particle bombardment. The transformed onion epidermal cells were incubated at 22&deg;C on Murashige and Skoog plates in the dark for 48 h. Then, the cells were examined under confocal fluorescence microscopy.</p></sec><sec><title>Scanning Electron Microscopic Observation</title><p>Culms of Asominori and CSSL61 were harvested 10 d after flowering and fixed in 2.5% v/v glutaraldehyde. Then, the samples were post fixed in 2% w/v OsO4 for 2 h, dehydrated through an ethanol gradient, infiltrated, and embedded in butyl methyl methacrylate. The samples conducted with critical point dry and sputter coated with platinum and observed using a scanning electron microscope (S-3000N, Hitachi).</p><p>Sequence data from this article can be found in the GenBank/EMBL data libraries under accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="HM775396">HM775396</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="HM775397">HM775397</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S1</bold>. The flow chart of genetic study of <italic>DTH8</italic> in this article.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S2</bold>. Flowering times of Asominori and CSSLs carrying the chromosome segments including <italic>DTH8</italic> from the donor parent IR24 with Asominori background under NLD conditions.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S3</bold>. Distribution of days to heading under NLD conditions of two secondary F2 populations derived from the cross between CSSL8, CSSL61, and Asominori.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S4</bold>. Sequence alignment of the conserved domains of the HAP3 subunits from rice, Arabidopsis, yeast (ScHAP3, NP_009532), and human (HsNF-B, L06145).</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S5</bold>. The expressions of <italic>DTH8</italic> and other flowering genes in Asominori and CSSL61.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S6</bold>. Expressions of <italic>DTH8</italic>, <italic>OsGI</italic>, <italic>Hd1</italic>, <italic>Ehd1</italic>, <italic>Hd3a</italic>, and <italic>Ghd7</italic> in the cv Asominori and CSSL61 siblings during the diurnal cycle.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S7</bold>. The expression of <italic>DTH8</italic> and other flowering genes in the NILs of <italic>Hd1</italic> and <italic>Ghd7</italic> under LD conditions.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S8</bold>. Plant height phenotype of cv Asominori and CSSL61.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Figure S9</bold>. DTH8 alleles of type 4 (from cv Kasalath), type 5 (from cv 93-11), and type 6 (from cv IR64) were expressed driven by 35S in CSSL61 (with nonfunctional allele from IR24) background.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Table S1</bold>. <italic>DTH8</italic> was mapped over 5 years in NLD conditions based on a RIL population derived from two parents, cv Asominori (<italic>japonica</italic>) and cv IR24 (<italic>indica</italic>).</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Table S2</bold>. Phenotypes of Asominori and CSSLs carrying the chromosome segments including <italic>DTH8</italic> from the donor parent IR24 with Asominori background under NLD conditions.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Table S3</bold>. Phenotypes of Asominori and CSSL61 under NSD conditions.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Table S4</bold>. <italic>DTH8</italic> alleles and its PS of flowering time among 40 rice varieties from a wide geographic range of Asia.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Table S5</bold>. Phenotypes of transgenic and nontransgenic segregants in the T1 generation derived from T0 plants with single-copy gene grown under NLD conditions.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Table S6</bold>. The sequences of primers used for mapping <italic>DTH8</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Table S7</bold>. Primers for vector constructions in this article.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supplemental Table S8</bold>. Primers for QRT-PCR and semiquantitative RT-PCR in this article.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Professor A. Yoshimura for providing us the RIL and CSSL populations and genotype data; Professor M. Yano for the NILs of <italic>Hd1</italic>; and Professor Q.F. Zhang for the NILs of <italic>Ghd7</italic>.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Daimon</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichinoki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Notaguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>FD, a bZIP protein mediating signals from the floral pathway integrator FT at the shoot apex</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>1052</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1056</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Angeles</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Cytokinin oxidase regulates rice grain production</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>741</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>745</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Rice gibberellin-insensitive dwarf mutant gene Dwarf 1 encodes the alpha-subunit of GTP-binding protein</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>10284</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>10289</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbesier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Giakountis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrona</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gissot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title><italic>FT</italic> protein movement contributes to long-distance signaling in floral induction of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>316</volume>: <fpage>1030</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1033</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Izawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanouchi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimatani</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title><italic>Ehd1</italic>, a B-type response regulator in rice, confers short-day promotion of flowering and controls <italic>FT</italic>-like gene expression independently of Hd1</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>926</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>936</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>JAH</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Multiple genes encoding the conserved CCAAT-box transcription factor complex are expressed in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>1015</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1022</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>GS3, a major QTL for grain length and weight and minor QTL for grain width and thickness in rice, encodes a putative transmembrane protein</article-title>. <source>Theor Appl Genet</source> <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>1164</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1171</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Ti-plasmid vectors useful for functional analysis of rice genes</article-title>. <source>Plant Biotechnol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>222</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gusmaroli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantovani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Regulation of the CCAAT-binding NF-Y subunits in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>264</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>185</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gusmaroli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantovani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Regulation of novel members of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> CCAAT-binding nuclear factor Y subunits</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>48</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Adaptation of photoperiodic control pathways produces short-day flowering in rice</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>422</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>722</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Komari</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumashiro</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Efficient transformation of rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) mediated by <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> and sequence analysis of the boundaries of the T-DNA</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>282</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honga</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi-Tanakaa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Umemurab</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Uozub</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiokac</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatsutod</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshidac</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikaria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitanoa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A rice brassinosteroid-deficient mutant, ebisu dwarf (d2), is caused by a loss of function of a new member of cytochrome P450</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2900</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2910</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tepperman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>GIGANTEA is a nuclear protein involved in phytochrome signaling in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>9789</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>9794</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Otomo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Toyomasu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichihara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A rice semi-dwarf gene, <italic>Tan-Ginbozu</italic> (<italic>D35</italic>), encodes gibberellin biosynthesis enzyme, ent-kaurene oxidase</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>547</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Comparative biology comes into bloom: genomic and genetic comparison of flowering pathways in rice and Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>120</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kardailsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagenais</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Activation tagging of the floral inducer FT</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>1962</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1965</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title><italic>OsMADS51</italic> is a short-day flowering promoter that functions upstream of <italic>Ehd1</italic>, <italic>OsMADS14</italic>, and <italic>Hd3a</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>1484</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1494</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwabuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>A pair of related genes with antagonistic roles in mediating flowering signals</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>1960</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1962</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Move on up, it&apos;s time for change-mobile signals controlling photoperiod-dependent flowering</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>2371</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2384</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title><italic>Hd3a</italic>, a rice ortholog of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> <italic>FT</italic> gene, promotes transition to flowing downstream of <italic>Hd1</italic> under short-day conditions</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>1096</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1105</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Development of a series of Indica chromosome segment substitution lines in Japonica background of rice</article-title>. <source>Rice Genet Newsl</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>106</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>LEAFY COTYLEDON1-LIKE defines a class of regulators essential for embryo development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>18</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiroshi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Control of tillering in rice</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>422</volume>: <fpage>618</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>621</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lotan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>MAL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamagishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis LEAFY COTYLEDON1 is sufficient to induce embryo development in vegetative cells</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1195</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1205</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maity</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>de Crombrugghe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Role of the CCAAT-binding protein CBF/NF-Y in transcription</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>174</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>178</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mantovani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The molecular biology of the CCAAT-binding factor NF-Y</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>239</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>27</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanouchi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><name><surname>Minobe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Izawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title><italic>Ehd2</italic>, a rice ortholog of the maize <italic>INDETERMINATE1</italic> gene, promotes flowering by up-regulating <italic>Ehd1</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>1425</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1435</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meinke</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>A homeotic mutant of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> with leafy cotyledons</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>258</volume>: <fpage>1647</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1650</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Serizawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title><italic>OsHAP3</italic> genes regulate chloroplast biogenesis in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>532</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>540</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Choy</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Soh</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Control of circadian rhythms and photoperiodic flowering by the Arabidopsis <italic>GIGANTEA</italic> gene</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>1579</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1582</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Je</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Rice <italic>Indeterminate 1</italic>(<italic>OsId1</italic>) is necessary for the expression of <italic>Ehd1</italic> (<italic>Early heading date 1</italic>) regardless of photoperiod</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1018</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1029</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Swapan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khush</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Green revolution: a mutant gibberellin-synthesis gene in rice</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>416</volume>: <fpage>701</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>702</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Accumulation of phosphorylated repressor for gibberellin signaling in an F-box mutant</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>299</volume>: <fpage>1896</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1898</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scarpella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rueb</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The <italic>RADICLELESS1</italic> gene is required for vascular pattern formation in rice</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>645</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>658</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shomura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Izawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebitani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanegae</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Deletion in a gene associated with grain size increased yields during rice domestication</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1023</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1028</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A QTL for rice grain width and weight encodes a previously unknown RING-type E3 ubiquitin ligase</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>623</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>630</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sothern</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Orcutt</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Olszewski</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Koukkari</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title><italic>GIGANTEA</italic> and <italic>SPINDLY</italic> genes linked to the clock pathway that controls circadian characteristics of transpiration in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1005</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1022</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatsuto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A novel cytochrome P450 is implicated in brassinosteroid biosynthesis via the characterization of a rice dwarf mutant, <italic>dwarf11</italic>, with reduced seed length</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>776</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>790</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thirumurugan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Serizawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Identification, characterization and interaction of <italic>HAP</italic> family genes in rice</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source> <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>289</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsunematsu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harushima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>RFLP framework map using recombinant inbred lines in rice</article-title>. <source>Breed Sci</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>284</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Control of rice grain-filling and yield by a gene with a potential signature of domestication</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1370</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1374</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Isolation and initial characterization of <italic>GW5</italic>, a major QTL associated with rice grain width and weight</article-title>. <source>Cell Res</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1199</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1209</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wenkel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Turck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gissot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Gourrierec</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Samach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>CONSTANS and the CCAAT box binding complex share a functionally important domain and interact to regulate flowering of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>2971</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2984</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>MAL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Danao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>LEAFY COTYLEDON1 is an essential regulator of late embryogenesis and cotyledon identity in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1731</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1745</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wigge</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Integration of spatial and temporal information during floral induction in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>1056</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1059</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name><name><surname>Mary</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title><italic>RID1</italic>, encoding a Cys2/His2-type zinc finger transcription factor, acts as a master switch from vegetative to floral development in rice</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>12915</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>12920</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Natural variation in <italic>Ghd7</italic> is an important regulator of heading date and yield potential in rice</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>761</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>767</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamuroa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatsuto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Loss of function of a rice brassinosteroid insensitivel homolog prevents internode elongation and bending of the lamina joint</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1591</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1606</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Katayose</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanouchi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Monna</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Umehara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title><italic>Hd1</italic>, a major photoperiod sensitivity quantitative trait locus in rice, is closely related to the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowering line gene <italic>CONSTANS</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>2473</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2483</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QF</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>BZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>XK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Saghai Maroof</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Using bulked extremes and recessive class to map genes for photoperiod-sensitive genic male sterility in rice</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>8675</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>8679</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
