<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">217703</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.217703</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>GENES, DEVELOPMENT, AND EVOLUTION</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Brassinosteroid Regulates Seed Size and Shape in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[OPEN]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Wen-Bo</given-names></name><ext-link ext-link-type="orcid" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8383-143X"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Hui-Ya</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Yu-Wei</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Sheng-Wei</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Zhi-Yong</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Wen-Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Key Laboratory of Plant Molecular Physiology, Institute of Botany, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100093, China (W.-B.J., H.-Y.H., Y.-W.H., S.-W.Z., W.-H.L.)</aff><aff id="aff2">Graduate University of the Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, China (H.-Y.H., Y.-W.H.); and</aff><aff id="aff3">Department of Plant Biology, Carnegie Institution for Science, Stanford, California 94305 (Z.-Y.W.)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>whlin@ibcas.ac.cn</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the National Basic Research Program of China (grant no. 2009CB941503), the Ministry of Agriculture of China (grant no. 2009ZX08009&#x2013;022B), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant no. 31171614), and the National High Technology Research and Development Program of China (grant no. 2012AA101108).</p></fn><fn id="afn1"><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Wen-Hui Lin (<email>whlin@ibcas.ac.cn</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[OPEN]</label><p>Articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.113.217703">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.113.217703</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>08</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>06</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>162</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1965</fpage><lpage>1977</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>03</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>06</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2013 American Society of Plant Biologists. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p/></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="PP_217703_ic1.gif"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><italic>Brassinosteroid regulates Arabidopsis seed size and shape by transcriptionally modulating specific seed developmental pathways.</italic></p></abstract><abstract><p>Seed development is important for agriculture productivity. We demonstrate that brassinosteroid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>) plays crucial roles in determining the size, mass, and shape of Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) seeds. The seeds of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-deficient mutant <italic>de-etiolated2</italic> (<italic>det2</italic>) are smaller and less elongated than those of wild-type plants due to a decreased seed cavity, reduced endosperm volume, and integument cell length. The <italic>det2</italic> mutant also showed delay in embryo development, with reduction in both the size and number of embryo cells. Pollination of <italic>det2</italic> flowers with wild-type pollen yielded seeds of normal size but still shortened shape, indicating that the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> produced by the zygotic embryo and endosperm is sufficient for increasing seed volume but not for seed elongation, which apparently requires <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> produced from maternal tissues. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> activates expression of <italic>SHORT HYPOCOTYL UNDER BLUE1</italic>, <italic>MINISEED3</italic>, and <italic>HAIKU2</italic>, which are known positive regulators of seed size, but represses <italic>APETALA2</italic> and <italic>AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR2</italic>, which are negative regulators of seed size. These genes are bound in vivo by the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-activated transcription factor BRASSINAZOLE-RESISTANT1 (BZR1), and they are known to influence specific processes of integument, endosperm, and embryo development. Our results demonstrate that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulates seed size and seed shape by transcriptionally modulating specific seed developmental pathways.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">BR</term><def id="def1"><p>brassinosteroid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">Col-0</term><def id="def2"><p>ecotype Columbia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">Ws</term><def id="def3"><p>ecotype Wassilewskija</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">DAP</term><def id="def4"><p>d after pollination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">BRZ</term><def id="def5"><p>brassinazole</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">ChIP</term><def id="def6"><p>chromatin immunoprecipitation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">qPCR</term><def id="def7"><p>quantitative PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8">RT</term><def id="def8"><p>reverse transcription</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>Seed development in flowering plants is a complicated process controlled by a complex network. The double fertilization in the embryo sac generates two zygotic products, the embryo and endosperm. The embryo gives rise to the daughter plant while the endosperm provides nutrients for embryo during embryogenesis and germination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lopes and Larkins, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Faure et al., 2002</xref>). Seed coats, which enclose the embryo and endosperm, are differentiated from maternally derived integuments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Haughn and Chaudhury, 2005</xref>), and the final seed size and weight are coordinately determined by the growth of the endosperm, embryo, and integument (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Berger et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Zhou et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>The molecular mechanisms of seed development have been studied extensively, and many genes involved in seed development have been identified. These include <italic>SHORT HYPOCOTYL UNDER BLUE1</italic> (<italic>SHB1</italic>), <italic>HAIKU1</italic> (<italic>IKU1</italic>), <italic>MINISEED3</italic> (<italic>MINI3</italic>), and <italic>HAIKU2</italic> (<italic>IKU2</italic>), which promote the development of endosperm and embryo and positively regulate the seed size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Garcia et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Luo et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Zhou et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). IKU1, MINI3, and IKU2 successively act in the same pathway that is required to expand the seed cavity and to induce the endosperm growth in the early phase of seed development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Luo et al., 2005</xref>). IKU1 directly interacts with MINI3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). SHB1 is a positive regulator of seed development and may activate <italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>IKU2</italic>. SHB1 has also been shown to enhance the embryo cell proliferation and expansion through an unknown IKU2-independent pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Zhou et al., 2009</xref>). By contrast, APETALA2 (AP2) inhibits integument growth and the development of embryo and endosperm and reduces the seed size. AP2 determines seed weight and seed size by coordinating the growth of endosperm, embryo, and maternal integuments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Jofuku et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Ohto et al., 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">2009</xref>). In addition, <italic>AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR2</italic> (<italic>ARF2</italic>) determines seed mass and seed size through regulating integument growth. Deficiency of ARF2 results in the dramatically increased seed size and weight due to the extra cell division in the integuments, which leads to the formation of enlarged seed coats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Schruff et al., 2006</xref>). The cytochrome P450 CYP78A5 (KLUH [KLU]) has been shown to act as a maternal regulator of seed size by stimulating the integument cell proliferation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Ito and Meyerowitz, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Adamski et al., 2009</xref>). Additional factors, including FERTILIZATION INDEPENDENT SEED2 (FIS2), AINTEGUMENTA (ANT), RETARDED GROWTH OF EMBRYO1 (RGE1), ARABIDOPSIS HIS KINASE2 (AHK2), AHK3, and AHK4, and CYTOKININ INDEPENDENT1 (CKI1), regulate the seed weight and size through epigenetic regulation of endosperm development and paternal imprinting, regulation of embryo proliferation, endosperm, and integument development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Sun et al., 2010a</xref>).</p><p>Brassinosteroid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>), a kind of steroid hormone, plays important roles in plant growth and development, such as stem elongation, leaf expansion, vascular differentiation, stress tolerance, senescence, and stomatal development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Clouse and Sasse, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Gudesblat et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kim et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Wang et al., 2012</xref>). An important role for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> in plant reproductive growth and seed development has been suggested by the studies of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-deficient and -insensitive mutants of Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic>), tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>), and rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Fujioka and Yokota, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Nomura et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Ye et al., 2010</xref>). In Arabidopsis, the weak <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-deficient mutant <italic>de-etiolated2</italic> (<italic>det2</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Fujioka et al., 1997</xref>) has lower fertility compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Ye et al., 2010</xref>), and the strong <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-deficient mutants <italic>dwarf4</italic> (<italic>dwf4</italic>) and <italic>constitutive photomorphogenesis and dwarfism</italic> (<italic>cpd</italic>) are completely male sterile (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Choe et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Ye et al., 2010</xref>). Rice mutants with defects in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> biosynthesis or signaling also show reduced seed length (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Hong et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Tanabe et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Morinaka et al., 2006</xref>). Overexpression of a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> biosynthetic gene in rice increases seed filling and seed size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Wu et al., 2008</xref>). The BR-deficient mutant <italic>lk</italic> of pea has irregularly shaped seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Nomura et al., 2007</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> acts through the cell surface receptor BRASSINOSTEROID INSENSITIVE1 (BRI1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kim et al., 2009</xref>) and transcription factors BRASSINAZOLE-RESISTANT1 (BZR1) and BRI1-EMS-SUPPRESSOR1 (BES1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Wang et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Yin et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">He et al., 2005</xref>) to control a large number of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-responsive genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Sun et al., 2010b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Yu et al., 2011</xref>). Although it has been reported that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> affects seed size and shape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Hong et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Takahashi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Tanabe et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Morinaka et al., 2006</xref>), the molecular mechanism of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulation of seed development has remained unclear.</p><p>To understand the mechanisms by which <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> controls seed size and shape, we analyzed the seed development in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-deficient and -insensitive mutants and the effects of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> on genes known to control various aspect of seed development. Our studies indicated that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> increased seed size by affecting the integument, endosperm, and embryo development, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-activated BZR1 directly regulated several genes known to control the seed size. We further showed that the seed shape would be determined largely by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signal of maternal tissues, whereas <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> produced by the embryo and endosperm seemed sufficient to increase seed size, providing evidence for a mode of localized actions of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> in seed development.</p><sec id="s1" sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-Deficient and -Insensitive Mutants Have Small Seeds</title><p>To evaluate the effects of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> on seed growth, we analyzed the size and weight of seeds of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-deficient mutant <italic>det2</italic> and the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> receptor mutant <italic>bri1-5</italic> (a weak allele of <italic>bri1</italic> mutant; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Fujioka et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Wang et al., 2001</xref>). The mature dry seeds of <italic>det2</italic> and <italic>bri1-5</italic> were smaller than wild-type seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, A&#x2013;E</xref>), and the embryos from mature <italic>det2</italic> seeds were significantly smaller than those of the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, F and G</xref>). The <italic>det2</italic> seeds were 17% lighter than the wild type (ecotype Columbia [<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>]; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1H</xref>), and the seeds of <italic>bri1-5</italic> were about 10% lighter than the wild-type seeds (ecotype Wassilewskija [<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ws</xref>]; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1H</xref>). The seeds of <italic>det2</italic> and <italic>bri1-5</italic> had shorter length but slightly bigger width compared with the wild-type controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, I&#x2013;J</xref>). The seeds of <italic>bzr1-1D</italic>, a gain-of-function mutant of the <italic>BZR1</italic> gene, were not bigger or heavier than the seeds of wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, A, C, H, I, and K</xref>); the <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> mutant also showed a short-hypocotyl phenotype, which is thought to be due to feedback inhibition of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Wang et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">He et al., 2005</xref>). These results suggested that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> positively regulated seed size and was involved in seed shape determination.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-deficient mutants and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-insensitive mutants have small seeds. Mature seeds of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> (A), <italic>det2</italic> (B), <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> (C), <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ws</xref> (D), and <italic>bri1-5</italic> (E). Mature embryos of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> (F) and <italic>det2</italic> (G). Seed weight per 1,000 mature dried seeds (H), seed length and seed width (I), the ratio of length to width (J), and seed area (K) of mature dried seeds of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>, <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>bzr1-1D</italic>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ws</xref>, and <italic>bri1-5</italic>. Hypocotyl cell length and width of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> and <italic>det2</italic> (&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Average cell numbers from three columns in the central region of the hypocotyl (L), plus the embryonic (Em) root (left) and the cotyledon (right) of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> and <italic>det2</italic> (&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; M). Bars = 750 &#x00B5;m (A&#x2013;E) and 50 &#x00B5;m (F and G). Values that differ at the 0.05 significance level are labeled with different letters.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_217703_f1"></graphic></fig><p>To investigate the cellular basis for the altered seed size and shape of <italic>det2</italic>, we examined the cell size and number of the embryonic shoot or hypocotyl and embryonic root apex in mature <italic>det2</italic> and wild-type seeds using scanning electron microscopy. The results showed that the cell length of <italic>det2</italic> hypocotyls was reduced by 23% compared with the wild type, and cell width was not obviously altered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, L</xref>). In addition, the numbers of cells in the epidermal cell files from the base of cotyledon junction to the embryonic root apex, and along the axis of cotyledon, were smaller in <italic>det2</italic> mutant than in the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, M</xref>). Microscopic analysis further showed that the integument cells of <italic>det2</italic> mutants were significantly shorter than the wild type (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). These results indicated that the decrease in seed size and seed weight in <italic>det2</italic> was correlated with reduced embryo cell size and number and decreased integument cell length.</p><p>The sections of ovaries also showed that the endosperm cellularization of <italic>det2</italic> was delayed. The endosperm cellularization of the wild type began at 5 d after pollination (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref>) when embryos were at the early-heart stage, whereas <italic>det2</italic> endosperm cellularization was initiated at late 6 to 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref>, when embryos were close to the middle-heart stage. Endosperm cellularization of <italic>det2</italic> and wild-type seeds was finished at 9 and 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref>, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). These results indicate that the reduced seed cavity and endosperm volume, delayed embryo development, decreased embryo cell size and number, and reduced integument cell length possibly contributed to the reduced seed size of <italic>det2</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Tissue-Specific Effects of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> on Seed Size and Shape</title><p>Seed is a complex organ that contains both maternal tissues (integument) and zygotic tissues (embryo and endosperm). Control of seed size involves complex interactions among the zygotic embryo and endosperm, the maternally derived seed coat, and the parent plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Schruff et al., 2006</xref>). To dissect the effects of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> synthesis and signaling in specific tissues on seed size and shape, we performed reciprocal crosses of the wild type with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-deficient and -insensitive mutants to create seeds that contain wild-type embryo and endosperm but mutant integuments. To avoid the volume effect of siliques to seed shape, we compared the ovaries shape in the very early stages after fertilization. After hand pollination, the ovaries in early-, middle-, and mature-heart stages were cleared and analyzed respectively under differential contrast microscopy. The heart shape embryos indicated the same angles of the photography, especially in middle-heart stage. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Figure S2</ext-link>, <italic>det2</italic>&#x2013;/&#x2013;, <italic>dwf4</italic>&#x2013;/&#x2013;, and <italic>bri1</italic>&#x2013;/&#x2013; ovaries produced by hand pollinating the corresponding pollens to self pistils were smaller and shorter than the wild type. On average, the <italic>det2-1</italic> seeds were 16% lighter than those of the wild type, and the <italic>dwf4</italic> (&#x2013;/&#x2013;) and the <italic>bri1-116</italic> (&#x2013;/&#x2013;) seeds were 17% and 18% lighter than those of the wild type, respectively. The ovaries from the <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>dwf4</italic>, and <italic>bri1</italic>-<italic>116</italic> mutant plants pollinated with wild-type pollen, resulting in wild-type embryos and endosperm but mutant integuments, were bigger but of same round shape compared with those from self-pollinated mutant plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2, A&#x2013;G</ext-link>). Consistent with these observations of developing ovaries, the <italic>det2</italic> (+/&#x2013;), <italic>dwf4</italic> (+/&#x2013;), and <italic>bri1-116</italic> (+/&#x2013;) mature seeds produced from <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>dwf4</italic>, or <italic>bri1-116</italic> pistils pollinated with wild-type pollens had similar seed weight and seed area as wild-type seeds, which showed rescue of the seed size but not the seed shape by the wild-type alleles from the pollens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, B&#x2013;E</xref>). By contrast, the ovaries and seeds produced by wild-type plants pollinated by the mutant pollens are almost the same size and shape of the wild type, consistent with the recessive nature of these mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A&#x2013;E</xref>). These results indicated that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> produced by the embryo and endosperm increased the seed size but had little effect on seed shape, whereas <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signaling in the integument contributed to the elongated shape of Arabidopsis seeds. The inability of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> produced in the embryo and endosperm to rescue the seed shape suggested that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> had limited mobility, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> synthesized in these internal seed organs had little effect on the integument cells.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulates seed size and shape. Cleared seeds of the plants from reciprocal crosses between <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> and <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>dwf4</italic>, and <italic>bri1-116</italic> (shown <italic>116</italic>) in middle-heart stage were imaged with differential contrast optics. Bar = 60 &#x00B5;m. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> <italic>det2</italic> indicates <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> pistils pollinated with <italic>det2</italic> pollen and so on (A). Seed length and seed width (B), the ratio of length to width (C), and seed area (D) from seeds of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> <italic>det2</italic>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> <italic>dwf4</italic>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> <italic>116</italic>, <italic>det2 det2</italic>, <italic>det2</italic> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>, <italic>dwf4 dwf4</italic>, <italic>dwf4</italic> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>, <italic>bri1-116 bri1-116</italic>, and <italic>bri1-116</italic> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> in middle-heart stage. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> <italic>det2</italic> indicates <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> pistils pollinated with <italic>det2</italic> pollen and so on. Seed weight per 1,000 mature seeds from seeds of these reciprocal crosses (E). Values that differ at the 0.05 significance level are labeled with different letters.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_217703_f2"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s4"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> Treatment Increases Seed Size and Affects Seed Shape</title><p>Application of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> to the inflorescence of the wild type and <italic>det2</italic> mutants resulted in enhanced seed weight in both the wild type and <italic>det2</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). But the seed weight of the <italic>det2</italic> mutant under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment was lower than wild-type seeds without <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment, indicating the exogenetic <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> could not fully rescue <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> deficiency in the <italic>det2</italic> mutant. The seed area of the <italic>det2</italic> mutant was recovered to wild-type level under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment, and there was no significant difference of seed area between the wild type and <italic>det2</italic> mutant after BR treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). For seed shape, ratio of seed length to width of wild-type plant was not changed by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment, and that of <italic>det2</italic> mutant was enhanced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). The length/width ratio of the <italic>det2</italic> mutant under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment was lower than the wild type, suggesting that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment could not fully rescue seed shape. The explanation of partial rescue would be the efficiency of extrinsic <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment. Above all, we still could conclude that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> directly regulated seed size and affected seed shape.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> increases seed size and affects seed shape, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulates the expression levels of seed size-related genes through directly binding to their promoters by BZR1. A, Statistics of seed weight, seed area, and the ratio of seed length to width indicated that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment resulted in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> seeds with enhanced weight and det2 seeds with rescued seed area and partially rescued seed weight/ratio of seed length to width. Values that differ at the 0.05 significance level are labeled with different letters. The inflorescence of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> and det2 mutants was dipped with 10 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> 24-epibrassinolide (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>) or mock solution once a day. The inflorescence was dipped 10 s and then grew normally. B, Expression levels of the above-mentioned genes in siliques 4 to 5 d after hand pollination of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> with mock solution or 10 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> 24-epibrassinolide (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>) treatment and <italic>det2</italic> with mock solution or 10 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> 24-epibrassinolide (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>) treatment for 3 h as determined by quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">RT</xref>-PCR analysis. C, Expression levels of the above-mentioned genes in siliques 4 to 5 d after hand pollination of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> with mock solution or 1 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">BRZ</xref> treatment and <italic>det2</italic> with mock solution or 1 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">BRZ</xref> treatment for 3 h as determined by quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">RT</xref>-PCR analysis. D, Expression levels of <italic>SHB1</italic>, <italic>IKU1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, <italic>IKU2</italic>, <italic>AP2</italic>, <italic>ARF2</italic>, <italic>HSF15</italic>, and <italic>KLU</italic> in siliques 4 to 5 d after hand pollination of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>, <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>bzr1-1D</italic>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ws</xref>, and <italic>bri1-5</italic> as determined by quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">RT</xref>-PCR analysis. E, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">ChIP</xref> analysis revealed that BZR1 binds to the promoters of <italic>SHB1</italic>, <italic>IKU1</italic>, <italic>IKU2</italic>, <italic>AP2</italic>, and <italic>ARF2</italic>. Means were calculated from three biological samples, and each biological sample was examined in triplicate. Error bars indicate <sc>sd</sc>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_217703_f3"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s5"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> Regulates the Expression of Seed Size-Related Genes</title><p>Previous studies indicated that seed size is coordinately determined by the growth of the endosperm, embryo, and integument (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Berger et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Zhou et al., 2009</xref>), and several genes involved in these processes have been identified. We thus analyzed whether any of the genes known to regulate seed size or shape were regulated by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>. The expression levels of these genes in the wild type plant and <italic>det2</italic> mutant under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment or brassinazole (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">BRZ</xref>), a triazole compound that specifically blocks brassinolide biosynthesis by inhibiting <italic>DWF4</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Asami et al., 2001</xref>), were first analyzed. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>, the expression levels of the <italic>SHB1</italic>, <italic>IKU1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, <italic>IKU2</italic>, <italic>HEAT SHOCK FACTOR15</italic> (<italic>HSF15</italic>), and <italic>KLU</italic> genes, which were positive regulators of seed size, were significantly increased after 3 h of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment and obviously reduced by 3 h of treatment with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> biosynthetic inhibitor <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">BRZ</xref> in both wild-type and <italic>det2</italic> siliques (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, B and C</xref>). Then the transcription level of these genes were analyzed in <italic>det2</italic> and <italic>bri1-5</italic> siliques at 4 to 5 d after hand pollination. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3D</xref>, the expression levels of positive regulators of seed size were significantly reduced in the <italic>det2</italic> and <italic>bri1-5</italic> mutants but slightly increased or unaffected in the <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> mutant. The transcript levels of the <italic>AP2</italic> and <italic>ARF2</italic> genes, which were negative regulators of seed size, were decreased by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment and increased by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">BRZ</xref> treatment in wild-type and <italic>det2</italic> siliques (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, B and C</xref>), as well as enhanced in the <italic>det2</italic> and <italic>bri1-5</italic> mutants but slightly decreased in the <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3D</xref>). In addition, the expressions of <italic>FIS2</italic>, <italic>ANT</italic>, <italic>RGE1</italic>, <italic>AHK1</italic>, <italic>AHK3</italic>, <italic>AHK4</italic>, and <italic>CKI1</italic>, which are all related to seed size, were changed under altered <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> levels (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>). These results suggested that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> increased seed size by activating the expressions of many genes that possibly increase seed size and repressing the genes that inhibit seed growth.</p><p>Previous genome-wide studies have identified direct target genes of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-signaling transcription factors BZR1 and BZR2/BES1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Wang et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Yin et al., 2002</xref>); the data suggest that those important seed development-regulating genes mentioned above (<italic>SHB1</italic>-<italic>MINI3</italic>-<italic>IKU2</italic>, <italic>AP2</italic>, and <italic>ARF2</italic>) are direct targets of BZR1 but not BES1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Sun et al., 2010b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Yu et al., 2011</xref>), so we further performed BZR1 chromatin immunoprecipitation (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">ChIP</xref>) followed by quantitative PCR (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">qPCR</xref>) analysis to confirm the direct involvement of BZR1 in the regulation of seed development-related genes. The results showed that in vivo BZR1 bound to the promoters of <italic>SHB1</italic>, <italic>IKU1</italic>, <italic>IKU2</italic>, <italic>AP2</italic>, and <italic>ARF2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3E</xref>). Although MINI3 was not a direct target of BZR1, its interacting protein IKU1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Wang et al., 2010</xref>) was a direct target of BZR1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3E</xref>). It has been reported that SHB1 regulates the expression of <italic>MINI3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Zhou et al., 2009</xref>), so it was deduced that BZR1 indirectly regulated <italic>MINI3</italic> through <italic>IKU1</italic> or <italic>SHB1</italic>. Additional genes involved in regulating seed size, including <italic>KLU</italic>, <italic>HSF15</italic>, <italic>FIS2</italic>, <italic>RGE1</italic>, <italic>ANT</italic>, <italic>AHK1</italic>, <italic>AHK3</italic>, <italic>AHK4</italic>, and <italic>CKI1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Sun et al., 2010b</xref>), were all confirmed to be direct targets of BZR1 by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">ChIP</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">qPCR</xref> detection (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>). These results suggested that BZR1 directly mediated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulation of genes involved in seed development.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title><italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>SHB1</italic> Act Downstream of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> in Regulating Seed Size</title><p>To further investigate whether the reduced expression of <italic>SHB1</italic>, <italic>IKU1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic> in the <italic>det2</italic> mutant were responsible for the small-seed phenotype, we analyzed the genetic interactions of these genes with <italic>det2-1</italic>. Overexpression of <italic>MINI3</italic> in the <italic>det2</italic> mutant resulted in obviously heavier seeds, although the seed length, width, ratio of length to width, and seed area were not significantly affected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, A&#x2013;E</xref>). Overexpression of <italic>MINI3</italic> in wild-type plant also resulted in heavier seeds, while other seed traits were unaffected (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). These results suggested that <italic>MINI3</italic> possibly acted downstream of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> and mediated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulation of seed weight but not seed shape.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Increased <italic>MINI3</italic> expression can partially restore the seed phenotypes of the <italic>det2</italic> mutant, and <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> also can partially restore the seed phenotypes of the <italic>bri1-5</italic> mutant. A, Overexpression of <italic>MINI3</italic> in <italic>det2</italic> mutants produces larger seeds compared with the <italic>det2</italic> mutant. Mature dried seeds from MINI3 overexpression (OE) 1<italic>/det2</italic>, MINI3 OE 2<italic>/det2</italic>, MINI3 OE 3<italic>/det2</italic>, <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic>, and <italic>bri1-5 shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> were shown. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> and <italic>det2</italic> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ws</xref> and <italic>bri1-5</italic> data are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, and all the seeds came from parallel experiments. Bar = 750 &#x00B5;m. Seed weight per 1,000 mature dried seeds (B), seed length and seed width (C), the ratio of length to width (D), and seed area of mature dried seeds (E) of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>, <italic>det2</italic>, MINI3 OE 1<italic>/det2</italic>, MINI3 OE 2<italic>/det2</italic>, and MINI3 OE 3<italic>/det2</italic> were shown. Seed weight per 1,000 mature dried seeds (F), seed length and seed width (G), the ratio of length to width (H), and seed area of mature dried seeds (I) of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ws</xref>, <italic>bri1-5</italic>, <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic>, and <italic>bri1-5 shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> were shown. Values that differ at the 0.05 significance level are labeled with different letters.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_217703_f4"></graphic></fig><p>The <italic>shb1-Dominant</italic> (<italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic>) mutant produces heavier seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Zhou et al., 2009</xref>). We crossed <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> with <italic>bri1-5</italic>, which are both in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ws</xref> background. Analysis of more than 10 <italic>bri1-5 shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> double mutant individuals showed increased seed mass and seed area compared with those of <italic>bri1-5</italic> or the wild type and no obvious difference when compared with <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, F&#x2013;I</xref>). The seed length of <italic>bri1-5 shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> was larger than that of <italic>bri1-5</italic> and shorter than <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic>, while the seed width of <italic>bri1-5 shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> was larger than either <italic>bri1-5</italic> or <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4G</xref>). The ratio of length to width of <italic>bri1-5 shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> was not obviously different from that of <italic>bri1-5</italic> and was significantly smaller than that of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ws</xref> or <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4H</xref>). These results showed that <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> can partially restore the seed weight and seed size of the <italic>bri1-5</italic> mutant, consistent with <italic>SHB1</italic> acting downstream of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> in promoting seed size. However, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>&#x2019;s effect on seed shape was independent of <italic>SHB1</italic>.</p><p>Genetic studies by crossing the <italic>shb1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> mutants with <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> mutants were performed to further test whether <italic>SHB1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic> acted downstream of BZR1 and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signal. The mass and area of seeds produced from <italic>shb1 bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>mini3 bzr1-1D</italic>, and <italic>iku2 bzr1-1D</italic> were all significantly lower than those of <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> mutants and had no obvious difference from those of <italic>shb1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, A, B, and E</xref>). The other seed traits, including the ratio of length to width, in <italic>shb1 bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>mini3 bzr1-1D</italic>, and <italic>iku2 bzr1-1D</italic> were also similar to that of <italic>shb1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> mutants, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5,C and D</xref>). These genetic results were consistent with <italic>SHB1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic> acting downstream of BZR1.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><italic>SHB1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic> act downstream of <italic>BZR1</italic>. A, Mature dried seeds of <italic>shb1</italic>, <italic>shb1 bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, <italic>mini3 bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>iku2</italic>, and <italic>iku2 bzr1-1D</italic> were shown. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> and <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> data are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, and all the seeds came from parallel experiments. Bar = 750 &#x00B5;m. Seed weight per 1,000 mature dried seeds (B), seed length and seed width (C), the ratio of length to width (D), and seed area of mature dried seeds (E) of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>, <italic>bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>shb1</italic>, <italic>shb1 bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, <italic>mini3 bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>iku2</italic>, and <italic>iku2 bzr1-1D</italic>. Values that differ at the 0.05 significance level are labeled with different letters.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_217703_f5"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s7"><title><italic>AP2</italic> and <italic>ARF2</italic> Are Negative Regulators of Seed Size Acting Downstream of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref></title><p>It is reported that AP2 negatively regulates seed size and mass. The weak (<italic>ap2-5</italic>) and strong (<italic>ap2-6</italic>) allele of <italic>AP2</italic> mutants produced larger seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Jofuku et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Ohto et al., 2005</xref>). Double mutants of <italic>det2</italic> with <italic>ap2-5</italic> and <italic>ap2-6</italic> were generated and analyzed to investigate whether the increased expression of <italic>AP2</italic> in <italic>det2</italic> was responsible for the small-seed phenotype of <italic>det2</italic>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>, mutations in <italic>AP2</italic> suppressed the small-seed phenotype of <italic>det2</italic>. Seed mass and seed area of <italic>ap2-5 det2</italic> was significantly larger than that of the <italic>det2</italic> mutant and similar to the <italic>ap2-5</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, B and E</xref>). The <italic>ap2-5 det2</italic> seeds had notably increased length and width but unchanged ratio of length to width compared with <italic>det2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, C and D</xref>). Seeds from <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> were dramatically heavier and larger than <italic>det2</italic> and were not obviously different from those of <italic>ap2-6</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, A, B, and E</xref>). By contrast, the seed shape of <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> was similar to <italic>det2</italic> but different from <italic>ap2-6</italic>. The seed length and width of <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> were notably increased, but their ratio remained the same compared with <italic>det2</italic>. The seed length of <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> was shorter than that of <italic>ap2-6</italic>, but the seed width was increased compared with that of <italic>ap2-6</italic>. There was no significant difference in seed shape between <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> and <italic>det2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, C and D</xref>). These results indicated that seed weight and seed size of the <italic>ap2 det2</italic> double mutant were similar to the single <italic>ap2</italic> mutants, whereas the seed shape of double mutants was similar to <italic>det2</italic> but notably different from <italic>ap2</italic>, suggesting that <italic>AP2</italic> acted downstream of <italic>DET2</italic> and played a negative role in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulation of seed size. On the other hand, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-mediated seed shape regulation was independent of <italic>AP2</italic>.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>The <italic>AP2</italic> mutation in <italic>det2</italic> mutants suppressed the small seed phenotype of <italic>det2</italic>, and <italic>AP2</italic> acts downstream of <italic>BZR1</italic>. A, Mature dried seeds from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>, <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>ap2-5</italic>, <italic>ap2-5 det2</italic>, <italic>ap2-5 bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>ap2-6</italic>, <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic>, and <italic>ap2-6 bzr1-1D</italic> were shown. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>, <italic>det2</italic>, and <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> data are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, and all the seeds came from parallel experiments. Bar = 750 &#x00B5;m. Seed weight per 1,000 mature dried seeds (B), seed length and seed width (C), the ratio of length to width (D), and seed area of mature dried seeds (E) of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>, <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>ap2-5</italic>, <italic>ap2-5 det2</italic>, <italic>ap2-5 bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>ap2-6</italic>, <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic>, and <italic>ap2-6 bzr1-1D</italic>. Values that differ at the 0.05 significance level are labeled with different letters.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_217703_f6"></graphic></fig><p>To investigate whether <italic>AP2</italic> acted downstream of <italic>BZR1</italic> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signal, we performed double mutation analysis combining <italic>ap2-6</italic> with <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> mutants. Seeds produced from <italic>ap2-5 bzr1-1D</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Huang et al., 2012</xref>) and <italic>ap2-6 bzr1-1D</italic> double mutants were significantly heavier and larger than those of <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> mutants and were not obviously different than those of <italic>ap2-5</italic> and <italic>ap2-6</italic> mutants, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, A, B, and E</xref>). Other seed traits, such as seed length and width and the ratio of length to width, in <italic>ap2-5 bzr1-1D</italic> and <italic>ap2-6 bzr1-1D</italic> double mutants resembled those of <italic>ap2-5</italic> and <italic>ap2-6</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, C and D</xref>). These data were consistent with <italic>AP2</italic> acting downstream of <italic>BZR1</italic>.</p><p>It has been shown previously that the embryos of <italic>ap2</italic> mutants have larger cell size and a greater number of cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Jofuku et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Ohto et al., 2005</xref>). Analysis showed that the embryo cell length of <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> was significantly larger than that of the <italic>det2</italic> mutant and similar to the <italic>ap2-6</italic> mutant, but there was no obvious difference in cell width between <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> double mutants and <italic>ap2-6</italic> mutants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Figs. S1 and S5</ext-link>). The embryo shoot and embryo root apex or cotyledon of <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> double mutants produced more cells than <italic>det2</italic> mutants, and the cell number of <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> double mutants was similar to that of the <italic>ap2-6</italic> mutants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Figs. S1 and S5</ext-link>). These results indicated that <italic>AP2</italic> mutation rescued the phenotypes of smaller cell size and fewer cell numbers of the <italic>det2</italic> mutant, suggesting that the increased expression of <italic>AP2</italic> in <italic>det2</italic> contributed to the small-seed phenotype and that <italic>AP2</italic> was involved in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulation of embryo cell size and number.</p><p><italic>AP2</italic> affects seed cavity, endosperm size, and endosperm cellularization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Ohto et al., 2009</xref>). Our observation showed that the seed cavity and endosperm size of <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> was larger than those of <italic>det2</italic> at the same stage and was similar to that of <italic>ap2-6</italic>. The seed development of <italic>ap2-6</italic> and <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> started more slowly than the wild type in the first 5 d, but the growth speed increased soon after, giving rise to a cavity size similar to the wild type after 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref>. The final embryo sizes of <italic>ap2-6</italic> and <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> were bigger than those of the wild type (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>). Similar to <italic>ap2-6</italic>, <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> initiated endosperm cellularization when embryos were at the middle-heart stage at approximately 6 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref> and completed cellularization when embryos were at the late-heart stage at approximately 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>). These results indicated that <italic>AP2</italic> was epistatic to <italic>det2</italic> and played an important role in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulation of seed cavity, endosperm, and embryo development.</p><p><italic>ARF2</italic> is a negative regulator of seed size and mass. Loss-of-function mutant <italic>arf2-8</italic> has increased seed size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Schruff et al., 2006</xref>). We crossed <italic>arf2-8</italic> with <italic>det2</italic> to test whether the increased expression of <italic>ARF2</italic> in <italic>det2</italic> was responsible for the smaller seed size of <italic>det2</italic>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref>, the seed weight and seed area of <italic>arf2-8 det2</italic> were notably larger than those of <italic>det2</italic> or the wild type and not obviously different to <italic>arf2-8</italic>. The seed length of <italic>arf2-8 det2</italic> was larger than that of <italic>det2</italic> but shorter than that of <italic>arf2-8</italic>, and the seed width was increased compared with <italic>det2</italic> or <italic>arf2-8</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7C</xref>). There was no significant difference in the ratio of length to width compared with <italic>det2</italic>; however, the ratio was significantly lower than the wild type or <italic>arf2-8</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7D</xref>). These results indicated that the seed weight and seed size of <italic>arf2-8 det2</italic> double mutants resembled <italic>arf2-8</italic> phenotypes, and <italic>ARF2</italic> acted downstream of <italic>DET2</italic> as a negative regulator of seed size. On the other hand, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulation of seed shape was independent of <italic>ARF2</italic>.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>The <italic>ap2-8 det2</italic> double mutants displayed <italic>arf2-8</italic> phenotypes. A, Mature dried seeds from <italic>arf2-8</italic> and <italic>arf2-8 det2</italic> were shown. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> and <italic>det2</italic> data are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>, and all the seeds came from parallel experiments. Bar = 750 &#x00B5;m. Seed weight per 1,000 mature dried seeds (B), seed length and seed width (C), the ratio of length to width (D), and seed area of mature dried seeds (E) of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref>, <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>arf2-8</italic>, and <italic>arf2-8 det2</italic>. Values that differ at the 0.05 significance level are labeled with different letters.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_217703_f7"></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s8" sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Seed size is a major agricultural trait, and our study demonstrated an important role of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> in promoting seed development. Our studies showed that deficiency of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> biosynthesis and signal transduction led to smaller seed size and abnormal seed shape in Arabidopsis. The effects of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> on seed size and seed shape were attributed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> actions in the embryo/endosperm and maternal tissues, respectively. While <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> was known to increase cell size and cell division in general, our molecular analysis provided evidence that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> modulated specific developmental regulators of seed development. Thus, our study linked <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signal to developmental pathways that controlled seed size and shape. This knowledge not only provided insight into the molecular mechanism of hormonal regulation of seed development but also potential means for improving grain yield.</p><sec id="s9"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> Plays Crucial Roles in Regulating Seed Size and Seed Mass</title><p>The positive effect of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> on seed growth has been observed in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-deficient mutant and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-overproducing rice plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Wu et al., 2008</xref>). Our analysis of Arabidopsis <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> mutants showed similar requirements of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> for normal seed development. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-deficient mutant <italic>det2</italic> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-insensitive mutant <italic>bri1</italic> both had reduced seed size, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> treatment obviously increased the <italic>det2</italic> seed weight, area, and ratio of seed length to width, although the enhanced seed weight and length/width ratio are still not as normal as the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). We further showed that the reduced seed size of <italic>det2</italic> was mainly due to reduced embryo cell size and cell number and smaller integument cell size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). In flowering plants, the embryo and the endosperm, which are enclosed by maternal seed integument, are derived from double fertilization, and the development of these three components are finely coordinated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Garcia et al., 2003</xref>). Our studies suggested that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulated seed size by coordinating the growth of the embryo and integument through independent mechanisms that depend on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> produced in each tissue. Pollinating <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-deficient or -insensitive mutants with wild-type pollen, which resulted in a functional wild-type embryo in the mutant integument, rescued the size but not shape of the seed, suggesting that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> produced in the embryo and endosperm were sufficient for increasing seed size, but the elongated seed shape required <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> production and signaling in the integument. This observation also suggested that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> could not move far from the source cells that synthesize it. Consistent with such independent action of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> in embryo/endosperm on seed size and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> action in the integument determining seed shape, altering several <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-regulated genes suppressed the small-seed phenotype of <italic>det2</italic> but not the seed shape. Our results suggested that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulated seed size and seed shape through independent actions of distinct downstream genes acting separately in the embryo/endosperm and the integument.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> Activates the <italic>SHB1-MINI3</italic>-<italic>IKU2</italic> Pathway and Represses <italic>AP2</italic> and <italic>ARF2</italic> to Increase Seed Size, though Directly Binding Their Promoters by BZR1</title><p>BZR1 is a very important transcription factor in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signaling transduction pathway, and <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> is a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signal-enhanced mutant. There is no significant difference in seed weight, area, and shape between <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> and the wild type. We statistically analyzed <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> seed phenotypes in different grow places and found that the <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> seed area and weight might be slightly lower than the wild type under poor conditions in some instances, which could be explained by feedback inhibition to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> biosynthesis genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">He et al., 2005</xref>), too many seeds per silique (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Huang et al., 2012</xref>), or the putative function of BZR1/BES1 in seed development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Yu et al., 2011</xref>). We did not analyze <italic>bes1-<sc>d</sc></italic> in this work because many important seed development-regulating genes, such as <italic>SHB1</italic>-<italic>MINI3</italic>-<italic>IKU2</italic>, <italic>AP2</italic>, and <italic>ARF2</italic>, were not identified as direct target genes of BES1. BES1 possibly regulates seed development through targeting other seed development-regulating genes, such as <italic>KLU</italic> and <italic>AHK4</italic>, which are the target genes of both BZR1 and BES1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Sun et al., 2010b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Yu et al., 2011</xref>), and regulates their expressions, which might be worth investigation in the future.</p><p>Our results showed that the expression of many genes involved positive regulation of seed size, especially the components in the SHB1-MINI3-IKU2 pathway, were activated by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>, mostly through direct regulation by BZR1. Genetics interactions provided further evidence that <italic>SHB1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic> genes were positive factors for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulation of seed size. Overexpression of <italic>MINI3</italic> and dominant mutation of <italic>SHB1</italic> partly suppressed the small-seed phenotype of <italic>det2</italic>. Consistent with a role downstream of BR, the <italic>shb1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, or <italic>iku2</italic> mutants showed normal expressions of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> biosynthetic genes <italic>DWF4</italic> and <italic>CPD</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S7</ext-link>). The suppression of the seed size but not seed shape of <italic>det2</italic> by <italic>MINI3</italic> overexpression and <italic>shb1</italic>-<italic>D</italic> was consistent with previous studies showing that the <italic>SHB1-MINI3-IKU2</italic> pathway regulated endosperm and embryo but not integument development to affect seed size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Zhou et al., 2009</xref>). Our molecular experiments indicated that BZR1 bound to the promoter region of <italic>SHB1</italic>, which might, in turn, activate the expressions of <italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>IKU2</italic>. BZR1 also binds to the promoter region of <italic>IKU1</italic>, which can interact with MINI3 at the protein level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). The expression of <italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>IKU2</italic> is altered in <italic>iku1</italic> and <italic>mini3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Luo et al., 2005</xref>), indicating BZR1 might target and regulate IKU1 and thus affect MINI3, which led to <italic>IKU2</italic> activation too. The molecular and genetic data together supported that the SHB1-MINI2-IKU2 pathway acted downstream of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signaling to positively regulate embryo development and seed size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>).</p><fig id="fig8" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Hypothetical model for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>-regulated seed development. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulates embryo and endosperm development to determine seed size through binding to the promoter region of <italic>SHB1</italic> by BZR1, which further regulates the expression of <italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>IKU2</italic>, or through BZR1 binding to the promoter region of <italic>IKU1</italic>, which interacts with MINI3 to regulate the expression of <italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>IKU2</italic>, or alternatively, through BZR1 binding to the promoter of <italic>IKU2</italic>, and regulates the expression of <italic>IKU2</italic>. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulates integuments, endosperm, and embryo development through BZR1 binding to the <italic>AP2</italic> promoter and then affects seed size. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> also modulates the integument development through BZR1 binding to the promoter of <italic>ARF2</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_217703_f8"></graphic></fig><p>Our studies showed that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> also suppressed the expression of genes that negatively regulated seed size, including <italic>AP2</italic> and <italic>ARF2</italic>. These two genes were direct targets of BZR1 and both of them expressed in high level in <italic>det2</italic> and <italic>bri1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3D</xref>). The loss-of-function mutations of <italic>AP2</italic> and <italic>ARF2</italic> increased seed size and suppressed the small-seed phenotype of <italic>det2</italic>, indicating that the elevated expression levels of these genes contributed to the small-seed phenotype of <italic>det2</italic>.</p><p>We confirmed that AP2 expression was repressed by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Huang et al., 2012</xref>), and our results showed that AP2 might also regulate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> synthesis or signaling. The expression levels of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> biosynthetic genes <italic>DWF4</italic> and <italic>CPD</italic> were decreased in the <italic>ap2</italic> mutants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S7</ext-link>). Due to feedback regulation, expression levels of <italic>CPD</italic> and <italic>DWF4</italic> were increased in <italic>det2</italic> and decreased in <italic>bzr1-1D</italic>. The <italic>ap2</italic> mutations reduced <italic>CPD</italic> and <italic>DWF4</italic> expression in the <italic>det2</italic> background but not in the <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> background (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S7</ext-link>). AP2 might negatively regulate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signaling. The reduced expression of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> biosynthetic genes in the <italic>ap2</italic> mutant could be due to feedback inhibition by enhanced <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signal. Alternatively, AP2 might positively regulate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> biosynthetic genes directly and thus would form another feedback loop, as <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> inhibition of AP2 expression would lead to reduced <italic>CPD</italic> and <italic>DWF4</italic> expression again. In contrast to AP2, ARF2 seems not to affect the expression of <italic>CPD</italic> and <italic>DWF4</italic>, suggesting that AP2 and ARF2 act through distinct pathways, which is consistent with the reports that <italic>AP2</italic> influences development of maternal integuments, the zygotic embryo, and endosperm to repress seed size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Ohto et al., 2009</xref>) and <italic>ARF2</italic> represses seed size by regulating the development of integuments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Schruff et al., 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> and Other Signals Coregulate Seed Size</title><p>In addition to the SHB1-MINI3-IKU2 pathway, several other pathways affecting seed size were regulated by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>. <italic>KLU</italic> expresses in the inner integument of developing ovules and promotes cell proliferation in integuments to determine the growth potential of seed coat and seed. The <italic>klu</italic> mutant has smaller seeds, and by contrast, overexpression of the <italic>KLU</italic> gene results in significantly enlarged seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Adamski et al., 2009</xref>). The expression level of <italic>KLU</italic> was up-regulated by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>, and <italic>KLU</italic> was a direct target of BZR1. These results suggested that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> might positively regulate integument development through BZR1 activating <italic>KLU</italic>. <italic>FIS2</italic> also regulates seed development through the epigenetic regulation pathway of endosperm development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Pien and Grossniklaus, 2007</xref>). Our results confirmed that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> activated <italic>FIS2</italic> by BZR1 targeting <italic>FIS2</italic>. <italic>RGE1</italic> and <italic>ANT</italic>, two BZR1 target genes induced by BR, positively regulate embryo proliferation. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> might regulate seed development through regulation of embryo proliferation through BZR1 targeting and regulating <italic>RGE1</italic> and <italic>ANT</italic>.</p><p>Recent studies reported that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> and gibberellins regulate common cellular activities and developmental processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bai et al., 2012</xref>), and BZR1 interacts with phytochrome-interacting factor4 to control a core transcription network, which indicate that plant growth can be coregulated by the steroid and environmental signals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Oh et al., 2012</xref>). Our results showed that the important genes for cytokinin signaling, <italic>AHK</italic> and <italic>CKI1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Riefler et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Deng et al., 2010</xref>), were the target genes of BZR1 and were regulated by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> and cytokinin might cross talk to coregulate seed development, but the detailed mechanism needs further investigation.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> Regulates Seed Shape through Unknown Maternal Tissue Factors after Fertilization</title><p>Our results showed that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> might have a major effect on seed shape. The ratio of length to width in wild-type seed ranged from 1.5 to 1.7, depending on growth conditions and metrical methods, which resembles the golden ratio of 1.61803399 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Cervantes et al., 2010</xref>), and this ratio was notably lower in <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>dwf4</italic>, or <italic>bri1-116</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). Cross pollination of these mutants with wild-type pollen, restoring <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> signaling in the embryo and endosperm, rescued seed size/mass to that of the wild type but did not rescue the seed shape. Before pollination, the ovule shape, including length, width, and area, of <italic>det2</italic> was not significantly different from the wild type (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S8</ext-link>), indicating the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulated seed shape after fertilization. Although the <italic>SHB1</italic>-<italic>MINI3</italic>-<italic>IKU2</italic> pathway, <italic>AP2</italic>, and <italic>ARF2</italic> mediated the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> control of seed weight and seed size, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulation of seed shape was independent of these genes. Therefore, the mechanism for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulation of seed shape was different from that of seed size. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> synthesis and signaling in the maternal tissues, such as integument, determined the seed shape, whereas the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> produced in the embryo/endosperm had little effect on seed shape. Such distinct cell type-specific effects of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> suggested that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> did not transport over long distance from source cells (for our case, from zygote to integument cells) and thus can function as a local signal in morphogenesis, which was consistent with previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Symons et al., 2008</xref>), and also in accord with the recent finding of a role of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> in regulating organ boundary formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bell et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Gendron et al., 2012</xref>). Our study indicated that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref> regulated distinct pathways in specific cell types to control the seed size and shape. Further study of these pathways at the molecular and developmental levels would be important for increasing grain yield.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s13" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s14"><title>Plant Materials and Growth Conditions</title><p>The <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>dwf4</italic>, <italic>bri1-116</italic>, <italic>bzr1-1D</italic>, <italic>shb1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, <italic>iku2</italic>, <italic>ap2-5</italic>, <italic>ap2-6</italic>, and <italic>arf2-8</italic> mutants and transgenic Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) plants are with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> background. <italic>bri1-5</italic> and <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> mutants are with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">Ws</xref>. Plants were grown at 23&#x00B0;C, and seeds were harvested when the plant was completely mature. At later developmental stages, the plants were also fitted with a plastic well to catch all seeds released by dehiscing siliques. Isolated siliques of 4 to 5 d after hand-pollination of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> and <italic>det2</italic> were dipped with mock solution or 10 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> 24-epibrassinolide (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">BR</xref>) treatment and mock solution or 1 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">BRZ</xref> for 3 h as determined by quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) analysis. All siliques were cut in the same length of center joint position for easily absorbing the solutions.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Measurement of Seed Weight, Seed Length, Seed Width, and Seed Area</title><p>For seed weight, plants were grown concurrently under identical conditions and seeds were harvested when the plant was mature. One thousand seeds per genotype were dried at 24&#x00B0;C for 7 d and weighed. Data are presented as means &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> from at least three independent experiments. For seed length and width, dried seeds were photographed using a Zeiss Axio Imager A1 microscope and then measured by ImageJ software. The measured seed length and width were used to calculate the ratio of length to width. ImageJ software was used to calculate the seed area. Young seeds at early-heart or middle-heart stage were cleared in Hoyer&#x2019;s solution overnight and photographed using a Leica differential interference contrast microscope, followed by using ImageJ software to calculate the seed dimensions.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Developmental Alteration Analysis</title><p>To examine the developmental alterations of <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>ap2-6</italic>, and <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> mutants, flowers of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> and <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>ap2-6</italic>, and <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> mutants were hand pollinated, and the developing seeds were harvested at different days after pollination. The siliques were dissected under an Olympus SZX9 microscope to isolate the young seeds, and then these young seeds were cleared in Hoyer&#x2019;s solution overnight and photographed using a Leica differential interference contrast microscope. To investigate the endosperm development, young seeds were fixed in formaldehyde-acetic acid solution overnight at 4&#x00B0;C and dehydrated through an ethanol series (50% (v/v), 70% (v/v), 80% (v/v), 90% (v/v), and 100% (v/v), each for 30 min). The samples were then embedded in LR White (Sigma-Aldrich). Sections were stained with 0.1% (w/v) toluidine blue O in distilled water. Stained sections were photographed using a Zeiss Axio Imager A1 microscope.</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Scanning Electron Microscopy Analysis</title><p>Mature dried seeds were imbibed for 1 h and dissected under an Olympus SZX9 microscope to isolate the mature embryos. The embryos were incubated for 12 h in buffer that contains 50 m<sc>m</sc> sodium phosphate (pH 7.0), 10 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 1% Triton X-100, and 1% dimethyl sulfoxide at 37&#x00B0;C and fixed for 24 h in formaldehyde-acetic acid (10% formalin, 5% acetic acid, 45% ethanol, and 0.01% Triton X-100). After fixation, the samples were dehydrated through an ethanol series (70%, 85%, 95%, and 100%, each for 30 min) and then dehydrated through an ethanol and isopentyl acetate series (75% ethanol and 25% isopentyl acetate, 50% ethanol and 50% isopentyl acetate, 25% ethanol and 75% isopentyl acetate, and 100% isopentyl acetate, each for 30 min). The embryos were then dried using a Hitachi Critical Point Dryer. The individual embryos were mounted on scanning electron microscopy stubs, sputter coated with platinum using the Hitachi Ion Sputter, and examined under a Hitachi S-4800 scanning electron microscope. Around 50 embryos were photographed, and the cell length and width were determined using ImageJ software. Data are presented as the average of three independent experiments.</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Total RNA Isolation and Quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">RT</xref>-PCR Analysis</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from siliques 4 to 5 d after hand pollination using the TRIzol RNA extraction kit (Invitrogen). The first-strand complementary DNA was synthesized by using moloney murine leukemia virus reverse transcriptase (Promega) and used as templates for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">RT</xref>-PCR analysis. Quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">RT</xref>-PCR analyses were carried out on Mx3000P (Stratagene) by using the SYBR Green reagent (Toyobo) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. The primer sequences for quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">RT</xref>-PCR were listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>. Data were calculated from three biological replicates, and each biological replicate was examined in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Reciprocal Crosses and Double Mutant Analysis</title><p>The reciprocal crosses between <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">Col-0</xref> and <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>dwf4</italic>, and <italic>bri1-116</italic> were performed with flowers at identical positions (11th to 14th flowers) on secondary inflorescences. A series of double mutants of <italic>det2</italic> with mutants showing large-seed-size <italic>ap2-5</italic>, <italic>ap2-6</italic>, and <italic>arf2-8</italic> were generated, and the mutant of <italic>bri1-5</italic> with the mutant showing large-seed-size <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> was also generated. A succession of double mutants of <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> with mutants showing small-seed-size <italic>shb1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> and with mutants showing large-seed-size <italic>ap2-5</italic> and <italic>ap2-6</italic> were generated. The transfer DNA-specific primer for <italic>shb1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> is T-DNA-1 and for <italic>arf2-8</italic> is T-DNA-2. For <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> genotyping, the transfer DNA-specific primer is T-DNA-3. For <italic>ap2-5</italic> genotyping, the PCR fragment from the wild type but not from <italic>ap2-5</italic> can be cut by <italic>Sac</italic>II. For <italic>ap2-6</italic> genotyping, the PCR fragment from the wild type but not from <italic>ap2-6</italic> can be cut by <italic>Pst</italic>I. For <italic>det2</italic> genotyping, <italic>Mnl</italic>I cuts the PCR fragment amplified from the wild type but not det2. For <italic>bri1-5</italic> genotyping, <italic>Pst</italic>I cuts the PCR fragment amplified from the wild type but not bri1-5. For <italic>bzr1-1D</italic> genotyping, the PCR fragment from the wild type but not from bzr1-1D can be cut by <italic>Cfr</italic>10I. The primer sequences for mutants screening were listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Table S3</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">ChIP</xref> Analysis</title><p>For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">ChIP</xref> experiments, Arabidopsis wild-type and <italic>pBZR1</italic>::<italic>BZR1-cyan fluorescent protein</italic> (<italic>CFP</italic>) transgenic Arabidopsis plants were grown at 23&#x00B0;C under 16-h-light and 8-h-dark conditions. Siliques at 4 to 5 d were cross linked for 15 min in 1% formaldehyde by vacuum filtration. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">ChIP</xref> analysis was performed by using an affinity-purified anti-GFP polyclonal antibody, and quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">RT</xref>-PCR was performed using SYBR Green reagent (Toyobo). Results were presented as the ratio of the amount of DNA immunoprecipitated from BZR1-CFP samples to that of the wild-type samples. The <italic>PROTEIN PHOSPHATASE2A</italic> (<italic>PP2A</italic>) and <italic>CO-FACTOR FOR NITRATE, REDUCTASE AND XANTHINE DEHYDROGENASE5</italic> (<italic>CNX5</italic>) genes were used as the negative control, and the <italic>DWF4</italic> gene was used as the positive control. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">ChIP</xref> experiments were performed three times, from which the means and <sc>sd</sc>s were calculated. The primer sequences for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">ChIP</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">qPCR</xref> were listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>.</p><p>Sequence data from this article can be found in the Arabidopsis Genome Initiative database under accession numbers <italic>UBIQUITIN10</italic> (At4G05320), <italic>DET2</italic> (At2G38050), <italic>BRI1</italic> (At4G39400), <italic>DWF4</italic> (At3G50660), <italic>BZR1</italic> (At1G75080), <italic>SHB1</italic> (At4G25350), <italic>IKU1</italic> (At2g35230), <italic>MINI3</italic> (At1G55600), <italic>IKU2</italic> (At3G19700), <italic>AP2</italic> (At4G36920), <italic>ARF2</italic> (At5G62000), <italic>KLU</italic> (At1G13710), <italic>HSF15</italic> (At4G18870), <italic>FIS2</italic> (At2G35670), <italic>ANT</italic> (At4G37750), <italic>RGE1</italic> (At1G49770), <italic>AHK1</italic> (At2G17820), <italic>AHK3</italic> (At1G27320), <italic>AHK4</italic> (At2G01830), and <italic>CKI1</italic> (At2G47430).</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> Integument cell size and endosperm cellularization of Col, <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>ap2-6</italic>, and <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> mutant plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> BR regulates seed size and shape.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S3.</bold></ext-link> BR regulates the expression levels of seed size-related genes through BZR1&#x0027;s targeting their promoters.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S4.</bold></ext-link> Overexpression <italic>MINI3</italic> in Col does not result in the changed seed size.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S5.</bold></ext-link> Seed phenotypes of <italic>det2</italic> mutants are rescued by <italic>AP2</italic> mutation.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S6.</bold></ext-link> Seed development in Col, <italic>det2</italic>, <italic>ap2-6</italic>, and <italic>ap2-6 det2</italic> mutant plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S7.</bold></ext-link> Expression levels of <italic>DWF4</italic> and <italic>CPD</italic> in single and double mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S8.</bold></ext-link> The <italic>det2</italic> ovule before pollination is similar to that of Col.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S1.</bold></ext-link> Overexpression of <italic>MINI3</italic> in Col resulted in heavier seeds and unaltered seed size.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S2.</bold></ext-link> The primer sequences for qRT-PCR analysis.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S3.</bold></ext-link> The primer sequences for mutants screening.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.217703/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S4.</bold></ext-link> The primer sequences for ChIP-qPCR analysis.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank John J. Harada (University of California, Davis) for providing the seeds of <italic>ap2-5</italic> and <italic>ap2-6</italic>, Min Ni (University of Minnesota) for providing the seeds of <italic>shb1</italic>, <italic>shb1-D</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic>, Jennifer L. Nemhauser (University of Washington) for providing the seeds of <italic>arf2-8</italic>, and Hong-Wei Xue (Shanghai Institute of Plant Physiology, CAS), Ming-Yi Bai and Jia-Ying Zhu (Department of Plant Biology, Carnegie Institution for Science), and Dale McAninch (Adelaide University) for language editing.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adamski</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Anastasiou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x2019;Neill</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Local maternal control of seed size by <italic>KLUH</italic>/<italic>CYP78A5</italic>-dependent growth signaling</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>20115</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20120</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatsuto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Selective interaction of triazole derivatives with DWF4, a cytochrome P450 monooxygenase of the brassinosteroid biosynthetic pathway, correlates with brassinosteroid deficiency in planta</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>276</volume>: <fpage>25687</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25691</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zentella</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Brassinosteroid, gibberellin and phytochrome impinge on a common transcription module in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>810</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>817</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Husbands</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaganatha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jablonska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangeon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Neff</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Girke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> lateral organ boundaries negatively regulates brassinosteroid accumulation to limit growth in organ boundaries</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>21146</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>21151</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Grini</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnittger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Endosperm: an integrator of seed growth and development</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>664</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>670</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cervantes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Javier Mart&#x00ED;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardanuy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>de Diego</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tocino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Modeling the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seed shape by a cardioid: efficacy of the adjustment with a scale change with factor equal to the Golden Ratio and analysis of seed shape in ethylene mutants</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source> <volume>167</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>410</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dilkes</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatsuto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldmann</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The <italic>DWF<sub>4</sub></italic> gene of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> encodes a cytochrome P450 that mediates multiple 22&#x03B1;-hydroxylation steps in brassinosteroid biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>243</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clouse</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasse</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>BRASSINOSTEROIDS: essential regulators of plant growth and development</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>451</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> histidine kinase CKI1 acts upstream of histidine phosphotransfer proteins to regulate female gametophyte development and vegetative growth</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1232</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1248</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rotman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortun&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Fertilization in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> wild type: developmental stages and time course</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>481</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>488</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatsuto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuriyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis deetiolated2</italic> mutant is blocked early in brassinosteroid biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1951</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1962</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Biosynthesis and metabolism of brassinosteroids</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>164</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Saingery</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambrier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x00FC;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis <italic>haiku</italic> mutants reveal new controls of seed size by endosperm</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>1661</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1670</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gendron</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenkel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Brassinosteroids regulate organ boundary formation in the shoot apical meristem of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>21152</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>21157</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gudesblat</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider-Pizo&#x0144;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Betti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayerhofer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanhoutte</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dongen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhiponova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>SPEECHLESS integrates brassinosteroid and stomata signalling pathways</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>548</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>554</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haughn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genetic analysis of seed coat development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>472</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>477</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Gendron</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gampala</surname><given-names>SSL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gendron</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>BZR1 is a transcriptional repressor with dual roles in brassinosteroid homeostasis and growth responses</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>307</volume>: <fpage>1634</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1638</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatsuto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The Rice <italic>brassinosteroid-deficient dwarf2</italic> mutant, defective in the rice homolog of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> DIMINUTO/DWARF1, is rescued by the endogenously accumulated alternative bioactive brassinosteroid, dolichosterone</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>2243</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2254</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="other"><bold>Huang HY, Jiang WB, Hu YW, Wu P, Zhu JY, Liang WQ, Wang ZY, Lin WH</bold> (2012) BR signal influences <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ovule and seed number through regulating related genes expression by BZR1. Mol Plant <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>456</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>469</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of a gene encoding a cytochrome P450, <italic>CYP78A9</italic>, induces large and seedless fruit in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1541</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1550</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jofuku</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Omidyar</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamuro</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Control of seed mass and seed yield by the floral homeotic gene <italic>APETALA2</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>3117</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3122</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Burlingame</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Brassinosteroid signal transduction from cell-surface receptor kinases to nuclear transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1254</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1260</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Michniewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergmann</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Brassinosteroid regulates stomatal development by GSK3-mediated inhibition of a MAPK pathway</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>482</volume>: <fpage>419</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>422</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Larkins</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Endosperm origin, development, and function</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1383</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1399</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>MINISEED3</italic> (<italic>MINI3</italic>), a WRKY family gene, and <italic>HAIKU2</italic> (<italic>IKU2</italic>), a leucine-rich repeat (<italic>LRR</italic>) <italic>KINASE</italic> gene, are regulators of seed size in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>17531</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17536</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morinaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Inukai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Agetsuma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Morphological alteration caused by brassinosteroid insensitivity increases the biomass and grain production of rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>141</volume>: <fpage>924</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>931</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatsuto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Roles of brassinosteroids and related mRNAs in pea seed growth and germination</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>1680</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1688</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Interaction between BZR1 and PIF4 integrates brassinosteroid and environmental responses</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>802</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>809</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohto</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Control of seed mass by <italic>APETALA2</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>3123</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3128</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohto</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Floyd</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Effects of APETALA2 on embryo, endosperm, and seed coat development determine seed size in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Sex Plant Reprod</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>289</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pien</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Polycomb group and trithorax group proteins in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1769</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>382</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riefler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Strnad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schm&#x00FC;lling</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cytokinin receptor mutants reveal functions in shoot growth, leaf senescence, seed size, germination, root development, and cytokinin metabolism</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>54</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schruff</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Spielman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenby</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The <italic>AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR 2</italic> gene of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> links auxin signalling, cell division, and the size of seeds and other organs</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>261</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shantharaj</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year><comment>a</comment>) <article-title>Transcriptional and hormonal signaling control of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seed development</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>611</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>620</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year><comment>b</comment>) <article-title>Integration of brassinosteroid signal transduction with the transcription network for plant growth regulation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>765</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>777</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Symons</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Brassinosteroid transport</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>shk1-D</italic>, a dwarf <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutant caused by activation of the <italic>CYP72C1</italic> gene, has altered brassinosteroid levels</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>22</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatsuto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A novel cytochrome P450 is implicated in brassinosteroid biosynthesis via the characterization of a rice dwarf mutant, <italic>dwarf11</italic>, with reduced seed length</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>776</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>790</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The VQ motif protein IKU1 regulates endosperm growth and seed size in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>670</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>679</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Brassinosteroid signaling network and regulation of photomorphogenesis</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Genet</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>701</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>724</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gendron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vafeados</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Asami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Nuclear-localized BZR1 mediates brassinosteroid-induced growth and feedback suppression of brassinosteroid biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>505</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>513</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>BRI1 is a critical component of a plasma-membrane receptor for plant steroids</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>410</volume>: <fpage>380</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>383</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Trieu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwok</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatsuto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Brassinosteroids regulate grain filling in rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2130</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2145</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Brassinosteroids control male fertility by regulating the expression of key genes involved in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> anther and pollen development</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>6100</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6105</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Mora-Garcia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Asami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>BES1 accumulates in the nucleus in response to brassinosteroids to regulate gene expression and promote stem elongation</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>191</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zola</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluru</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Foudree</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluru</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A brassinosteroid transcriptional network revealed by genome-wide identification of BESI target genes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>634</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>646</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>SHORT HYPOCOTYL UNDER BLUE1 associates with <italic>MINISEED3</italic> and <italic>HAIKU2</italic> promoters in vivo to regulate <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seed development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>117</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
