<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">219238</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.219238</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>SIGNALING AND RESPONSE</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cross-Repressive Interactions between SOC1 and the GATAs GNC and GNL/CGA1 in the Control of Greening, Cold Tolerance, and Flowering Time in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[OPEN]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>Ren&#x00E9;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bastakis</surname><given-names>Emmanouil</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Schwechheimer</surname><given-names>Claus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Department of Plant Systems Biology, Center for Life and Food Sciences, Technische Universtit&#x00E4;t M&#x00FC;nchen, 85354 Freising, Germany</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>claus.schwechheimer@wzw.tum.de</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaff (grant nos. SCHW751/9&#x2013;1 and SCHW751/10&#x2013;1 to C.S.).</p></fn><fn id="afn1" fn-type="present-address"><label>2</label><p>Present address: Max-Planck-Institute for Plant Breeding Research, 50829 Cologne, Germany.</p></fn><fn id="afn2"><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Claus Schwechheimer (<email>claus.schwechheimer@wzw.tum.de</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[OPEN]</label><p>Articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.113.219238">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.113.219238</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>08</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>06</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>162</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1992</fpage><lpage>2004</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>04</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>06</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2013 American Society of Plant Biologists. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p/></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="PP_219238_ic1.gif"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><italic>The transcription factor SOC1 is regulated by two GATA transcription factors for the control of flowering while the GATAs are controlled by SOC1 to control greening and cold tolerance.</italic></p></abstract><abstract><p>The paralogous and functionally redundant GATA transcription factors GNC (for GATA, NITRATE-INDUCIBLE, CARBON-METABOLISM INVOLVED) and GNL/CGA1 (for GNC-LIKE/CYTOKININ-RESPONSIVE GATA FACTOR1) from Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) promote greening and repress flowering downstream from the phytohormone gibberellin. The target genes of GNC and GNL with regard to flowering time control have not been identified as yet. Here, we show by genetic and molecular analysis that the two GATA factors act upstream from the flowering time regulator <italic>SUPPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CONSTANS1</italic> (<italic>SOC1</italic>) to directly repress <italic>SOC1</italic> expression and thereby repress flowering. Interestingly, this analysis inversely also reveals that the MADS box transcription factor SOC1 directly represses <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> expression to control cold tolerance and greening, two further physiological processes that are under the control of SOC1. In summary, these findings support the case of a cross-repressive interaction between the GATA factors GNC and GNL and the MADS box transcription factor SOC1 in flowering time control on the one side and greening and cold tolerance on the other that may be governed by the various signaling inputs that are integrated at the level of <italic>SOC1</italic> expression.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">L<italic>er</italic></term><def id="def1"><p>Landsberg <italic>erecta</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">qRT</term><def id="def2"><p>quantitative real-time</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">ChIP</term><def id="def3"><p>chromatin immunoprecipitation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">H3K9Ac</term><def id="def4"><p>K9-acetylated histone 3</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">H3K9me2</term><def id="def5"><p>K9-dimethylated histone 3</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">HA</term><def id="def6"><p>hemagglutinin</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>Throughout evolution, plants have acquired the ability to adapt their growth and flowering to their environmental conditions to guarantee optimal reproductive success in their individual growth environments. Various signaling pathways are known that are integrated to control flowering time in response to light quality, daylength, temperature, and nutrient availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Parcy, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Franks et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Izawa, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Turck et al., 2008</xref>). In Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), genetic studies have identified the transcription factors <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>), <italic>LEAFY</italic>, and <italic>SUPPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CONSTANS1</italic> (<italic>SOC1</italic>) as major integrators of flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Nilsson et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Samach et al., 2000</xref>). FT protein was shown to act as the florigen that moves from the leaves in inductive conditions to the shoot apical meristem, where it promotes the transition from vegetative to reproductive meristem identity by forming a complex with the bZIP transcription factor FLOWERING LOCUS D (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Corbesier et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Mathieu et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Taoka et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>Under inductive long days, expression of the MADS box transcription factor <italic>SOC1</italic> is essential for floral induction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Samach et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Yoo et al., 2005</xref>). Under short days, SOC1 appears also to be the major integrator of flowering time stimulation in response to the phytohormone GA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bl&#x00E1;zquez and Weigel, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Moon et al., 2003</xref>). <italic>SOC1</italic> expression is furthermore repressed by the MADS box transcription factor FLOWERING LOCUS C, which controls flowering in response to long cold periods (vernalization) and acts together with the MADS box transcription factor SHORT VEGETATIVE PHASE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Hartmann et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Li et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Tao et al., 2012</xref>). Additionally, <italic>SOC1</italic> expression is controlled by an age-dependent regulatory system that involves SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN-LIKE (SPL) transcription factors and their antagonistic microRNA regulator miRNA156 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Wang et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p><italic>SOC1</italic> expression and flowering are also repressed in response to short periods of cold that plants experience, such as during a cold spring season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Seo et al., 2009</xref>). During such cold periods, <italic>SOC1</italic> expression is reduced and the concomitant delay in flowering correlates with an increase in the expression of cold-regulated genes such as <italic>C-REPEAT/DROUGHT-RESPONSIVE ELEMENT-BINDING FACTOR</italic> (<italic>CBF</italic>) and cold-response marker genes such as <italic>COLD-REGULATED15a (COR15a</italic>) and <italic>COR15b</italic>. Inversely, <italic>SOC1</italic> overexpression results in the inverse regulation of cold-regulated genes, and this supports experimental data that indicate that SOC1 is a direct regulator of cold-regulated genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Seo et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>GAs have been implicated in a variety of growth responses in plants, including the control of flowering time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hisamatsu and King, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Itoh et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Schwechheimer, 2011</xref>). GAs are perceived by the GIBBERELLIC ACID-INSENSITIVE DWARF1 GA receptors, which in turn bind to and induce the degradation of DELLA repressors such as GIBBERELLIC ACID INSENSITIVE (GAI) and REPRESSOR OF <italic>ga1-3</italic> (RGA) from Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Ueguchi-Tanaka et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Griffiths et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Willige et al., 2007</xref>). DELLA proteins repress a broad range of different transcription factor activities, including that of the PHYTOCHROME INTERACTING FACTORS (PIFs), basic helix-loop-helix transcription factors that integrate GA as well as light signaling by interacting with DELLAs, and the phytochrome light receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">de Lucas et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Feng et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Gallego-Bartolom&#x00E9; et al., 2010</xref>). Inversely, GA responses appear completely derepressed in mutants deficient in the function of the GlcNAc transferase SPINDLY (SPY; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Jacobsen and Olszewski, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Wilson and Somerville, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Silverstone et al., 2007</xref>).</p><p>In long-day-grown wild-type plants, flowering is typically only moderately promoted by GA, because growth conditions in laboratory experiments are adjusted to guarantee a short generation time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Reeves and Coupland, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Galv&#x00E3;o et al., 2012</xref>). <italic>DELLA</italic> gene loss-of-function mutants with a constitutive GA response or <italic>spy</italic> mutants do not flower much faster than the wild type when grown under long days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Achard et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Tseng et al., 2004</xref>). Based on the observation that the Landsberg <italic>erecta</italic> (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">L<italic>er</italic></xref>) allele of the GA biosynthesis mutant <italic>ga1-3</italic> displays only a comparatively minor delay in flowering under long-day conditions, GA has for a long time been thought to be of minor importance for floral induction under long days. In contrast, <italic>ga1-3</italic> mutants failed to flower even after 5 to 6 months in short-day conditions, and this has given rise to the long-standing hypothesis that, in Arabidopsis, GA is essential for flowering only under short days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Wilson et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Reeves and Coupland, 2001</xref>). Several recent studies, however, report a strong flowering time delay also under long days in <italic>ga1</italic> mutants and other Arabidopsis GA pathway mutants when examined in the Columbia ecotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Willige et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hisamatsu and King, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Galv&#x00E3;o et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Porri et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>Plants use GAs also to control plant growth in response to abiotic stress such as cold, salt, and oxidative stress as well as biotic stress caused by pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Achard et al., 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">2008b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Navarro et al., 2008</xref>). The growth constraint resulting from the exposure to cold temperature correlates with and can be explained by a cold-induced stabilization of the DELLAs and results in increased cold tolerance in Arabidopsis seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Achard et al., 2008a</xref>). The identities of the genes that confer cold tolerance downstream of the DELLAs have not been revealed as yet.</p><p>We have previously identified the two functionally paralogous GATA family transcription factors <italic>GNC</italic> (for <italic>GATA, NITRATE-INDUCIBLE, CARBON-METABOLISM INVOLVED</italic>) and <italic>GNL/CGA1</italic> (for <italic>GNC-LIKE/CYTOKININ-RESPONSIVE GATA FACTOR1</italic>) from Arabidopsis as critical transcription targets downstream from GA, DELLAs, and PIFs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Naito et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> expression is repressed in response to GA and increased in mutants with a block in GA signaling, such as <italic>ga1</italic> and <italic>gid1abc</italic>. In agreement with the repressive activity of GAs on <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> expression, <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> overexpression plants, where <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> regulation is uncoupled from GA control, resemble <italic>ga1</italic> or <italic>gid1abc</italic> mutants at the phenotypic and global gene expression levels. Similar to the GA pathway mutants, <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> overexpressors are dark-green dwarfs with a delay in germination and flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). PIF3 is at least one member of the PIF family of transcription factors that controls <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> expression. As recently reported, the greening phenotype of <italic>gnc</italic> and <italic>gnl</italic> mutants may be explained by their role in directly and indirectly regulating the expression of chlorophyll biosynthetic genes and chloroplast development, growth, and division (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hudson et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Chiang et al., 2012</xref>). <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> have also been identified as transcription repression targets of the floral homeotic genes APETALA3 and PISTILLATA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Mara and Irish, 2008</xref>). In the context of the role of GNC and GNL in regulating chlorophyll biosynthesis, it has been proposed that repression of the two GATAs is at least in part responsible for the nongreening of petals and stamens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Mara and Irish, 2008</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we show that GNL, as a representative GATA factor for the two functionally homologous GATAs GNC and GNL, represses flowering downstream from GA signaling and upstream from <italic>SOC1</italic>. We further show that <italic>GNL</italic> overexpression results in a decrease in <italic>SOC1</italic> expression and that both GATAs can directly bind to the <italic>SOC1</italic> promoter, suggesting that GNL may be a direct transcriptional repressor of <italic>SOC1</italic> expression. Interestingly, we also find that GNC and GNL promote two other SOC1-dependent physiological responses downstream from SOC1, greening and cold tolerance, and that SOC1 can directly bind to the promoters of both GATAs. We thereby present a case for a cross-repressive interaction of GNC and GNL on the one side and SOC1 on the other in the control of flowering time, greening, and cold tolerance.</p><sec id="s1" sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2"><title><italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> Repress Flowering Downstream from GA Signaling</title><p>We have previously established that the GATA transcription factors GNC and GNL repress GA responses downstream from GA, DELLAs, and PIFs in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). The role for GNC and GNL in the control of flowering time is already suggested by a subtle acceleration in flowering in long-day-grown as well as short-day-grown <italic>gnc gnl</italic> mutants when compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, A and B</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Fig; S1</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). The repressive role of the two GATAs, however, is much more apparent in the GA-deficient <italic>ga1</italic> background, where the loss of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> in <italic>ga1 gnc gnl</italic> resulted in the partial suppression of the flowering time delay of the <italic>ga1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, D&#x2013;F</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). Here, we found that <italic>ga1 gnc gnl</italic> mutants (99.7 &#x00B1; 7.1 leaves; 79.8 &#x00B1; 5.7 d) flower about 1 month earlier than <italic>ga1</italic> (118.9 &#x00B1; 9.1 leaves; 118.7 &#x00B1; 10 d) when grown under long-day growth conditions. Since <italic>ga1 gnc gnl</italic> flowers still much later than the wild type (12.3 &#x00B1; 1.1 leaves; 23.1 &#x00B1; 1.1 d) or <italic>ga1</italic> mutants after GA treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, D, E, and G</xref>), these findings suggest that other regulators in addition to GNC and GNL must repress flowering in the absence of GA. One the one side, such regulators could be functionally homologous GATA factors closely related to GNC and GNL or, on the other side, other unrelated proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>GNC and GNL repress flowering downstream from the GA signaling pathway. A, D, G, and H, Representative photographs of Arabidopsis plants grown for 5 or 6 weeks (w) under long-day conditions. Plants shown in G were watered twice per week with 1 &#x00B5;<sc>m</sc> GA<sub>3</sub>. B, E, and I, Flowering time analysis (total rosette leaf number) of long-day-grown plants shown in A, D, G, and H. C, F, and J, Results of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR analyses for the flowering time regulators <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic> performed with 10-d-old seedlings. Fold change was calculated relative to wild-type levels. Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> tests were performed in comparison with the wild type unless indicated otherwise: a = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.05, b = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.01, c = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.001; n.s., not significant. Bars = 5 cm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_219238_f1"></graphic></fig><p>In line with the proposed role of the two GATAs as repressors of flowering, we found that the overexpression of either <italic>GNC</italic> (<italic>GNC</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>) or <italic>GNL</italic> (<italic>YELLOW FLUORESCENT PROTEIN</italic> [<italic>YFP</italic>]:<italic>GNL</italic>) results in a strong delay in flowering in the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, A and B</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). In order to understand at which stage of flowering time regulation the <italic>GATA</italic> transgenes are active, we introduced <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic>, which in our hands is the genetically more stable of the two GATA transgenes, into the <italic>spy</italic> and the <italic>rga gai</italic> DELLA gene loss-of-function backgrounds. Also in the early flowering <italic>spy</italic> mutant, which mimics the phenotype of a constitutive GA response mutant, we observed a strong delay in flowering in the presence of <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, H and I</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Jacobsen and Olszewski, 1993</xref>). Flowering time was also strongly delayed in the <italic>rga gai</italic> loss-of-function mutant that normally flowers early, specifically in short-day conditions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2, A and B</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Dill and Sun, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cheng et al., 2004</xref>). Since our previous analysis of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> regulation had shown that the two <italic>GATAs</italic> are targets of PIF3, we also analyzed <italic>GNL</italic> overexpression in a <italic>PIF3</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> overexpression line. Also in this background, flowering was strongly delayed, indicating that <italic>GNL</italic> represses flowering downstream from its transcriptional regulator PIF3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2, C and D</ext-link>). In summary, these findings confirm the role of <italic>GNL</italic> as a repressor of flowering downstream from GA, DELLA, and PIF3. Since all our experiments at present suggest that GNC and GNL are functionally redundant, we speculate that these observations also hold true for <italic>GNC</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>SOC1 Is an Essential Flowering Time Integrator Downstream from GNC and GNL</title><p>Different flowering time pathways converge on the regulation of the two positive flowering time regulators <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic>. To understand the contribution of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic> expression to the flowering time phenotypes of the genotypes described above, we performed quantitative real-time (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>)-PCR using 10-d-old seedlings to assess their transcript abundance in the presence of the <italic>GATA</italic> overexpression constructs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>). While the abundance of <italic>FT</italic> is not significantly altered by the presence or absence of the GATAs, the abundance of <italic>SOC1</italic> is strongly repressed when either <italic>GNC</italic> or <italic>GNL</italic> is overexpressed. Furthermore, the reduced transcript abundance of <italic>SOC1</italic> also correlates with the late-flowering phenotype of the <italic>spy YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> and <italic>PIF3</italic>:<italic>MYC YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> genotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1J</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2D</ext-link>). Inversely, <italic>SOC1</italic> transcript levels are increased in <italic>ga1 gnc gnl</italic> when compared with <italic>ga1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1F</xref>).</p><p>Since these findings invited the hypothesis that GNC and GNL may be regulators of <italic>SOC1</italic> expression, we became interested in examining the relationship between <italic>SOC1</italic> and the GATAs in more detail. To this end, we introduced the <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> overexpression transgene into a <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> overexpression background. Flowering is strongly delayed in <italic>soc1</italic> loss-of-function mutants (32.7 &#x00B1; 2.8 leaves) and slightly accelerated in a <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> overexpression line (10.2 &#x00B1; 0.7 leaves) when compared with the wild type (12.7 &#x00B1; 1.0 leaves; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A and B</xref>). Interestingly, and unlike what we had observed when we introduced <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> into the GA pathway mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> overexpression does not delay flowering in the <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> background, where SOC1 expression is under the control of the 35S cauliflower mosaic virus promoter and thus uncoupled from its native transcriptional regulation (10.6 &#x00B1; 0.9 leaves; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A and B</xref>). This suggests that <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> promotes flowering downstream from <italic>GNL</italic>. Using promoter-GUS lines for <italic>SOC1</italic> (<italic>SOC1<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic>), <italic>GNC</italic> (<italic>GNC<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic>), and <italic>GNL</italic> (<italic>GNL<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic>), we could show in subsequent experiments that the three genes are coexpressed in the leaves of 10-d-old seedlings and that the overexpression of <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> represses <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> expression in this tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>GNC and GNL act upstream of <italic>SOC1</italic>. A, Representative photographs of 3- and 5-week-old (w) Arabidopsis plants. B, Flowering time analysis (total rosette leaf number) of long-day-grown plants shown in A. C, GUS expression in the first pair of true leaves in 10-d-old long-day-grown (LD) and short-day-grown (SD) Arabidopsis seedlings expressing <italic>GNC<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic>, <italic>GNL<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic>, and <italic>SOC1<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> in the wild type and the <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> overexpression background. Arrows indicate expression differences between the <italic>GUS</italic> transgenes. Note that <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> overexpression results in a dwarfed seedling phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). D, Schematic representation of the <italic>SOC1</italic> genomic locus. Black boxes, exons; gray boxes, untranslated regions; underlined roman numbers, promoter regions containing GATA boxes (vertical lines); gray lines, predicted nucleosome-binding regions. E and F, Fold enrichment (<italic>GNC</italic>:<italic>GFP/</italic>wild type [E] and <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic>/wild type [F]) of promoter fragment amplification after <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ChIP</xref>-PCR with anti-GFP. G and H, Fold enrichment after <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ChIP</xref> with anti-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">H3K9Ac</xref> and anti-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">H3K9me2</xref> and promoter fragment amplification by PCR when compared with the wild type. I, Representative photographs of 6-week-old Arabidopsis plants. J, Flowering time analysis (total rosette leaf number) of long-day-grown plants shown in I. Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> tests were performed in comparison with the wild type unless indicated otherwise: a = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.05, b = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.01, c = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.001; n.s., not significant. Bars = 5 cm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_219238_f2"></graphic></fig><p>Since we could identify various GATA boxes in the promoter of <italic>SOC1</italic>, we reasoned that GNL and possibly also GNC may regulate <italic>SOC1</italic> expression directly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2D</xref>). To test this hypothesis, we performed chromatin immunoprecipitation (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ChIP</xref>) for GNC:GFP and YFP:GNL and, indeed, detected a strong binding of both GATA factors to two GATA boxes (boxes I and II) in the first intron and exon of the <italic>SOC1</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, E and F</xref>). In support of a model where the decrease in <italic>SOC1</italic> transcript abundance in the <italic>GNC</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> or <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> overexpressors is the result of transcriptional repression, we further detected decreased abundance of K9-acetylated histone 3 (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">H3K9Ac</xref>), a marker for active chromatin, and increased abundance of K9-dimethylated histone 3 (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">H3K9me2</xref>), a marker for inactive chromatin, at two promoter regions, Hb and Hc, that are proximal to the ATG start codon of <italic>SOC1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, G and H</xref>). At the same time, binding of the two histone H3 variants to a more remote site, Ha, was unaltered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, G and H</xref>). A similar H3-variant chromatin-binding preference was observed when we tested <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">H3K9Ac</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">H3K9me2</xref> binding to the <italic>SOC1</italic> promoter in the GA-insensitive <italic>gai-1D</italic> mutant, where <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> expression is increased as a consequence of DELLA protein stabilization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, G and H</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). Since this analysis may suffer from the criticism that the observed promoter binding is the result of an off-target amplification of the overexpressed <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic>, we established also a <italic>GNL<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GNL</italic>:<italic>HA</italic> transgene that complemented the <italic>gnc gnl</italic> mutant phenotype (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4, A and B</ext-link>). We then tested binding of the hemagglutinin (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HA</xref>)-tagged GNL protein to promoter boxes IV (negative control) and I (positive control) and could in both cases confirm the negative (IV) as well as the positive (I) binding of GNL:<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HA</xref> to the predicted target sites in the <italic>SOC1</italic> promoter (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4C</ext-link>).</p><p>Since our experiments indicated that GNC and GNL are direct transcriptional repressors upstream from <italic>SOC1</italic>, we also expected that the late-flowering phenotype of <italic>soc1</italic>, unlike the late-flowering phenotype of the <italic>ga1</italic> mutant, is not suppressed in a <italic>soc1 gnc gnl</italic> triple mutant. Indeed, we found no significant difference in the late flowering of <italic>soc1 gnc gnl</italic> (32.4 &#x00B1; 2.1 leaves) when compared with the <italic>soc1</italic> single mutant (32.9 &#x00B1; 2.2 leaves). Therefore, we concluded that <italic>SOC1</italic> is critical for flowering time control downstream from <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, I and J</xref>). In line with a role of GA upstream of <italic>SOC1</italic> in the control of flowering, we also noted that the flowering time delay of the <italic>soc1</italic> mutant cannot be suppressed by GA treatments that are sufficient to accelerate flowering in the wild type, suggesting that SOC1 is essential to promote flowering downstream from GA (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5, A and B</ext-link>). In summary, these findings suggest that GNC and GNL are direct repressors of <italic>SOC1</italic> and that the <italic>GNC</italic>- and <italic>GNL</italic>-dependent repression of <italic>SOC1</italic> transcript abundance correlates with activating and repressive chromatin changes at the <italic>SOC1</italic> promoter and with the late-flowering phenotype of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> overexpressors. Thus, <italic>SOC1</italic> is the essential flowering time integrator downstream from <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title><italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> Promote Greening Downstream from <italic>SOC1</italic></title><p>A reduction in chlorophyll content had been the original phenotype associated with the <italic>gnc</italic> mutant in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bi et al., 2005</xref>). Both <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> have recently been characterized as positive regulators of chlorophyll biosynthesis and chloroplast division (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hudson et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Chiang et al., 2012</xref>). <italic>gnc gnl</italic> loss-of-function mutants are light green; conversely, <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> overexpression lines show increased greening and chlorophyll accumulation. Interestingly, we observed that the <italic>soc1 gnc gnl</italic> triple mutant is visibly less green and contains less chlorophyll than the dark-green <italic>soc1</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>). When compared with <italic>soc1</italic> and the wild type, this reduction in chlorophyll accumulation of the <italic>soc1 gnc gnl</italic> triple mutant also correlated with a decrease in the transcript abundance of the three <italic>PROTOCHLOROPHYLLIDE OXYDOREDUCTASE</italic> (<italic>POR</italic>) genes <italic>PORA</italic>, <italic>PORB</italic>, and <italic>PORC</italic>, the gene products of which control a critical step in chlorophyll biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Thomas, 1997</xref>). While our analysis of flowering time control had suggested that <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> function upstream of <italic>SOC1</italic>, the greening phenotype suggested a role of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> downstream from <italic>SOC1</italic> in the control of chlorophyll biosynthesis. This antagonism in the genetic interaction between the <italic>GATAs</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic> with regard to greening and flowering time control, respectively, was further supported by the greening phenotype of the <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> background. While we had observed that the <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> overexpressor cannot delay flowering in the early-flowering <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> background, we found that the overexpression of <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> resulted in a stronger chlorophyll accumulation as well as increased <italic>POR</italic> transcript levels in <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, C and D</xref>). In this regard, the <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> overexpressor when introduced into <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> behaved in a similar manner as it did in the <italic>PIF3</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> or <italic>spy</italic> background, and this finding suggested that <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> is downstream of SOC1 in the control of greening (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, E&#x2013;H</xref>). Furthermore, while GA treatments had not been sufficient to promote flowering in <italic>soc1</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5, A and B</ext-link>), indicating that <italic>SOC1</italic> acts downstream of GA signaling in the control of flowering, we found that GA treatments of <italic>soc1</italic> are sufficient to suppress the <italic>soc1</italic> mutant&#x2019;s greening phenotype, clearly demonstrating that <italic>SOC1</italic> is upstream of GA in the control of greening (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5C</ext-link>). In summary, these findings suggested a role for <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> downstream from the GA pathway and <italic>SOC1</italic> in the control of chlorophyll biosynthesis and greening.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>GNC and GNL promote greening downstream from <italic>SOC1</italic>. A, C, E, and G, Chlorophyll concentration. B, D, F, and H, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR analyses of <italic>POR</italic> gene expression from 10-d-old seedlings as shown in A, C, E, and G. Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> tests were performed in comparison with the wild type unless indicated otherwise: a = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.05, b = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.01, c = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.001; n.s., not significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_219238_f3"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s5"><title><italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> Promote Cold Tolerance Downstream from <italic>SOC1</italic></title><p>Besides its prominent role in the regulation of flowering time, SOC1 was previously also shown to interfere with cold tolerance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Seo et al., 2009</xref>). Interestingly, a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR analysis of mock- and cold-treated 10-d-old seedlings revealed that <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> are regulated by cold temperatures, pointing at a putative role of the two genes in cold response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Indeed, when we tested cold tolerance in nonacclimated and cold-acclimated <italic>gnc gnl</italic> loss-of-function mutants and the <italic>GNC</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> or <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> overexpression lines, we found that seedling survival in the <italic>GNC</italic> or <italic>GNL</italic> overexpressors is approximately twice as high as in the wild type, regardless of prior acclimation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). At the molecular level, the increased survival correlated with an increase in the expression of <italic>CBF2</italic> and the two cold-response marker genes <italic>COR15a</italic> and <italic>COR15b</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, C and D</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Medina et al., 1999</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> promote cold tolerance downstream from <italic>SOC1</italic>. A, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR analyses of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> expression of 10-d-old seedlings in response to a 9-h cold treatment (4&#x00B0;C). B, F, and I, Seedling survival of nonacclimated and cold-acclimated 10-d-old seedlings after cold treatment. C, D, G, H, J, and K, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR analyses of <italic>CBF</italic> (C, G, and J) and <italic>COR15</italic> (D, H, and K) gene expression in 10-d-old seedlings. E, Representative photograph of nonacclimated and cold-acclimated 10-d-old seedlings before (top panels) and after (bottom panels) cold treatment. Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> tests were performed in comparison with the wild type unless indicated otherwise: a = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.05, b = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.01, c = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.001; n.s., not significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_219238_f4"></graphic></fig><p>As we will show later, we also detected strongly increased <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> transcript levels in the <italic>soc1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>). Since increased cold tolerance is also a phenotype of <italic>soc1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Seo et al., 2009</xref>), we reasoned that the elevated <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> transcript levels in <italic>soc1</italic> may be causative for the cold tolerance phenotype of this mutant. In support of this hypothesis, we found that the increased cold tolerance phenotype of <italic>soc1</italic> is strongly suppressed in the <italic>soc1 gnc gnl</italic> triple mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, E and F</xref>). This genetic suppression of the <italic>soc1</italic> cold tolerance phenotype was mirrored by a decrease in the abundance of the three <italic>CBF</italic> genes as well as that of <italic>COR15a</italic> and <italic>COR15b</italic> in <italic>soc1 gnc gnl</italic> when compared with the <italic>soc1</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, G and H</xref>). Along the same lines, and in contrast to the dominant effect of <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> overexpression over <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> overexpression with regard to the control of flowering, we observed that the overexpression of <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> is dominant over the overexpression of <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> with regard to the cold tolerance of nonacclimated and cold-acclimated seedlings, <italic>CBF</italic> expression, as well as <italic>COR</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, I&#x2013;K</xref>). Taken together, these findings suggest that the cold tolerance phenotype of <italic>soc1</italic> is at least partially mediated by the increase in <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> transcript abundance and that <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> function downstream from <italic>SOC1</italic> in the control of cold tolerance.</p><p>It was previously established that cold-induced growth arrest and cold tolerance in Arabidopsis are promoted by DELLA repressors and that the exposure to cold temperatures correlates with an increase in DELLA protein abundance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Achard et al., 2008a</xref>). In line with a cold-induced stabilization of the DELLAs, we also detected increased levels of the DELLA protein RGA in 10-d-old cold-treated wild-type and <italic>gnc gnl</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>). Interestingly, however, we also found that RGA levels are increased already at ambient temperature in <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> overexpressors of the same age (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>). Thus, the <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> overexpressors mimic the DELLA accumulation phenotype of cold-treated wild-type seedlings. Since we had previously established that DELLA protein abundance correlates with <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> transcript abundance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>), we reasoned that the increased transcript abundance of the <italic>GATAs</italic> may be the molecular cause for the cold tolerance phenotype of <italic>ga1</italic>. However, when we compared the cold tolerance phenotype of <italic>ga1 gnc gnl</italic> with that of <italic>ga1</italic>, we detected only a mild, and in our conditions only in cold-acclimated conditions statistically significant, suppression of the cold tolerance phenotype of <italic>ga1</italic> when examining <italic>ga1 gnc gnl</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>). Surprisingly, the molecular analysis performed in parallel revealed a strong reduction in <italic>CBF</italic> and <italic>COR15</italic> gene expression when compared with <italic>ga1</italic> that we would have expected to correlate with a strong decrease in cold tolerance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, C and D</xref>). The absence of a strong suppression of the <italic>ga1</italic> cold tolerance phenotype and the concomitant presence of a molecular suppression of <italic>CBF</italic> and <italic>COR</italic> gene expression suggests that the accumulation of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> transcript alone is not causative for the cold tolerance observed in the GA-deficient <italic>ga1</italic> mutant, that other genes downstream from GA and DELLA promote cold tolerance in the absence of GA, and that the reduction of <italic>CBF</italic> and <italic>COR</italic> transcript abundance is not sufficient to predict cold tolerance in a <italic>ga1</italic> mutant background.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Analysis of GNC- and GNL-mediated cold tolerance in GA pathway mutants. A, Immunoblot of RGA protein abundance in 10-d-old Arabidopsis seedlings grown before and after a 9-h cold treatment (4&#x00B0;C). CBB, Coomassie Brilliant Blue as a loading control. B and E, Seedling survival of nonacclimated and cold-acclimated 10-d-old seedlings after cold treatment. C and D, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR analyses of <italic>CBF</italic> (C) and <italic>COR15</italic> (D) gene expression in 10-d-old seedlings. Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> tests were performed in comparison with the wild type unless indicated otherwise: a = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.05, b = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.01, c = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.001; n.s., not significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_219238_f5"></graphic></fig><p>When we subsequently explored the relationship between <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> and the <italic>rga gai</italic> loss-of-function mutant with regard to cold tolerance, we found that <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> expression can induce cold tolerance also in this background, indicating that cold tolerance is promoted by <italic>GNL</italic> downstream from GA and DELLAs and, thus, that accumulation of the DELLAs as observed in <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> is not causative for promoting cold tolerance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5E</xref>). In summary, these findings suggest that GNC and GNL as well as other factors are required to confer cold tolerance in the absence of GA. In this respect, the partial suppression of the cold tolerance phenotype of <italic>ga1</italic> in <italic>ga1 gnc gnl</italic> is reminiscent of the partial suppression of the flowering time defect of <italic>ga1</italic> in <italic>ga1 gnc gnl</italic>. As proposed above for the control of flowering time in the <italic>ga1 gnc gnl</italic> mutant, the cold response phenotype of <italic>ga1</italic> also may be regulated by other GATA transcription factors or by unrelated regulators in addition to GNC and GNL.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>SOC1 Represses <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> Transcription</title><p>The suppression of the <italic>soc1</italic> greening and cold tolerance phenotypes in <italic>soc1 gnc gnl</italic> suggested a regulation of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> gene expression by SOC1. Indeed, and as already mentioned before, we detected strongly increased <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> transcript levels in the <italic>soc1</italic> mutant when compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>). Since this may be the consequence of a direct repressive activity of SOC1 on the promoters of the two <italic>GATA</italic> genes, we tested the binding of SOC1:MYC to CArG boxes in the <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> promoters using <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ChIP</xref> analysis. Indeed, we found binding of SOC1 to two promoter regions that span four CArG boxes in each gene promoter (boxes I and II in <italic>GNC</italic> and boxes I and III in <italic>GNL</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, B&#x2013;D</xref>). In both promoters, we further found increased binding of the open chromatin marker <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">H3K9Ac</xref> in the <italic>soc1</italic> mutant at a nucleosome-binding site proximal to their ATG start codons (Hb), while binding to a distal site (Ha) was unaffected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, E and F</xref>). Although the effect of <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> overexpression on the transcript abundance of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> was not strong when we examined whole seedlings using <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR, the repressive action of SOC1 on <italic>GNL</italic> became apparent when we examined <italic>GNL<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> expression in the wild type and the <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> background. Here, a strong reduction of <italic>GNL<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> expression was detectable (e.g. in the upper region of the hypocotyl and the shoot meristem of long-day-grown seedlings; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6G</xref>). Taken together, these observations suggest that SOC1 is a direct transcriptional repressor of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> transcription. There is thus a cross-repressive interaction between <italic>SOC1</italic> and the two GATA factor genes. Their respective gene products can reciprocally repress their transcription and thereby promote or repress SOC1-dependent flowering or GNC- and GNL-dependent greening and cold tolerance, respectively.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>SOC1 is a direct repressor of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> transcription. A, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR analysis of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> transcript abundance in <italic>soc1</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic>. B, Schematic representation of the <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> genomic loci. Black boxes, exons; gray boxes, untranslated regions; underlined roman numbers, promoter regions containing CArG boxes (vertical lines); gray lines, predicted nucleosome-binding regions Ha and Hb. Note that there is no known 5&#x2032; untranslated region for <italic>GNL</italic>. C and D, Fold enrichment (<italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC/soc1</italic>) after PCR amplifications of <italic>GNC</italic> (C) and <italic>GNL</italic> (D) promoter fragments following <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ChIP</xref> with anti-MYC. E and F, Fold enrichment after <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ChIP</xref> with anti-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">H3K9Ac</xref> and PCR amplification of <italic>GNC</italic> (E) and <italic>GNL</italic> (F) promoter fragments in the wild type, <italic>soc1</italic>, and <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic>. G, Representative GUS staining of 10-d-old seedlings expressing <italic>GNL</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> in the wild type and the <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> background. Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> tests were performed in comparison with the wild type unless indicated otherwise: a = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.05, b = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.01, c = <italic>P</italic> &#x2264; 0.001; n.s., not significant. Scale bars &#x003D; 0.5 mm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_219238_f6"></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="discussion|conclusions"><title>DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION</title><p>In this study, we analyze the role of the functionally paralogous GATA factors GNC and GNL in flowering time control, greening, and cold tolerance. This analysis was stimulated by our observations that GNC and GNL repress flowering in the GA-deficient <italic>ga1</italic> mutant, on the one side, and that overexpression of the GATA factors is sufficient to delay flowering in the wild type, on the other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, D and E</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). Furthermore, we found here that overexpression of <italic>GNL</italic>, as a representative for the two GATAs, can delay flowering in a range of early-flowering GA pathway mutants. These findings are thus in line with a role of the two GATAs as repressors of flowering downstream from the GA signaling pathway. Our further observations that GNC and GNL repress flowering in wild-type plants only to a minor extent, under long-day as well as short-day conditions, and that GNC and GNL only partially repress flowering in <italic>ga1</italic> suggest that other regulators in addition to GNC and GNL repress flowering in the absence of the two GATAs. Several possibilities can be envisioned that can serve to explain this phenotype. First, we know from our previous analyses and the analysis of others that the <italic>gnl</italic> allele (SALK_003995) used in our study has reduced <italic>GNL</italic> expression but is not a null allele (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Mara and Irish, 2008</xref>). Unfortunately, we and others have been unable in repeated attempts to reisolate a presumed <italic>gnl</italic> null allele (SALK_021362; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Mara and Irish, 2008</xref>). Thus, the residual flowering time repression in <italic>ga1 gnc gnl</italic> could potentially be the result of repression by residual GNL. Second, it may be that other related GATA factors repress flowering in addition to GNC and GNL. Arabidopsis has at least four GATA factors that are closely related to GNC and GNL and that may act redundantly in the repression of flowering in the absence of <italic>ga1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). Third, it may be that other unrelated proteins repress flowering in addition to GNC and GNL in the absence of GA. In this regard, it is interesting that the protein SPL9 was recently identified as a DELLA-controlled flowering time regulator in Arabidopsis and that GA was recently described to promote the expression of the <italic>SPL</italic> genes <italic>SPL3</italic>, <italic>SPL4</italic>, and <italic>SPL5</italic> in a <italic>SOC1</italic>-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Wu et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Jung et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Yu et al., 2012</xref>). Thus, DELLA repression of <italic>SPL</italic> gene expression and SPL protein activity could potentially delay flowering in <italic>ga1</italic> in parallel to GNC and GNL.</p><p>That the suppression of the phenotypes caused by the GA deficiency of <italic>ga1</italic> must be genetically complex is already suggested by the results of several <italic>ga1</italic> suppressor screens that had been conducted in the past. In summary, only three genetic loci were identified as genetic suppressors of <italic>ga1</italic>, <italic>RGA</italic>, <italic>SPY</italic>, as well as a gain-of-function allele of the F-box protein subunit SLEEPY1 that promotes DELLA protein degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Wilson and Somerville, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Silverstone et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Fu et al., 2004</xref>). In fact, although it is known to date that all five Arabidopsis DELLA proteins contribute to the strong phenotype of the <italic>ga1</italic> mutant, only the suppression of <italic>ga1</italic> by the <italic>RGA</italic> loss-of-function allele significantly suppressed the <italic>ga1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Silverstone et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Cheng et al., 2004</xref>). In turn, the founding member of the DELLA gene family, <italic>GAI</italic>, had been identified based on the gain-of-function phenotype of the <italic>gai-1</italic> mutant, which, as we understand now, encodes for a GA-insensitive stabilized variant of GAI, and the reversion from this gain-of-function phenotype in the intragenic <italic>gai-t6</italic> suppressor mutation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Peng et al., 1997</xref>). Here, we see some parallels between the suppression of <italic>ga1</italic> by the loss of multiple DELLA genes that ultimately fully suppressed the <italic>ga1</italic> phenotype and the partial suppression of <italic>ga1</italic> in <italic>ga1 gnc gnl</italic> that could potentially be enhanced by the loss of other GATA factors or other regulators. Along the same lines, we see parallels in the genetics of the <italic>DELLA</italic> and the <italic>GNC</italic> or <italic>GNL</italic> loss-of-function mutants. In both cases, the repressive function is not obvious in the wild-type background but only apparent in GA deficiency or when protein content is increased due to a stabilization of the DELLA protein or due to an overexpression of the GATA factor.</p><p>While <italic>GNL</italic> overexpression delays flowering in the wild type, we further found that <italic>GNL</italic> overexpression cannot delay flowering when <italic>SOC1</italic> is overexpressed; its expression is thus uncoupled from its normal transcriptional control in the wild type. Since the strong delay in flowering in our <italic>GNL</italic> overexpression studies correlated with the repression of SOC1, we hypothesized and subsequently tested successfully by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ChIP</xref>-PCR that GNC and GNL directly bind to <italic>SOC1</italic> to mediate its transcriptional repression. Using a complementing <italic>GNL</italic> promoter-driven <italic>GNL</italic> transgene, we could further substantiate our findings of <italic>SOC1</italic> as a direct target of the GATAs and thus eliminate the possible criticism that the binding observed with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ChIP</xref>-PCR using GNC:GFP and YFP:GNL is an artifactual off-target binding and amplification resulting from their overexpression. Taken together, our data strongly support a model whereby GNC and GNL are transcriptional repressors of <italic>SOC1</italic>.</p><p>Interestingly, our genetic interaction studies revealed an inverse relationship between SOC1 and the GATAs in the control of greening and cold tolerance. The regulatory role of SOC1 on the expression of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> became apparent due to the visible suppression of the enhanced greening phenotype of <italic>soc1</italic> in a <italic>soc1 gnc gnl</italic> mutant. Since SOC1 has been implicated in the control of cold tolerance, a finding that was initially based on the observation that cold-regulated genes are expressed in <italic>soc1</italic> mutants even at ambient temperature, we also tested the contribution of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> to the enhanced cold tolerance of the <italic>soc1</italic> mutant as well as the cold tolerance phenotype of the late-flowering <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> overexpression lines. Here, we observed a suppression of the increased cold tolerance of <italic>soc1</italic> in the absence of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> as well as an increase in cold tolerance when the two <italic>GATAs</italic> are overexpressed. It was proposed that the antagonistic regulation of cold tolerance and flowering time by SOC1 may be relevant during short periods of cold temperature as they can be experienced by plants during cold periods in spring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Seo et al., 2009</xref>). Two studies have recently reported the genome-wide identification of direct SOC1 targets using <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ChIP</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Immink et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Tao et al., 2012</xref>). Interestingly, neither analysis has resulted in the identification of <italic>GNC</italic> or <italic>GNL</italic> as a direct SOC1 target. Since the different approaches employed make use of different parameters for data analysis, the differences in the results with regard to <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> promoter binding may simply be due to differences in the data analysis and stringency in data analysis.</p><p>Besides positioning the GATA factors and SOC1 within their respective pathways, our observation of a mutual repression of the GATAs and SOC1 with regard to flowering time control, on the one side, and greening and cold tolerance, on the other, is particularly intriguing. In Arabidopsis, vernalization, temperature, photoperiod, as well as light quality and also GA biosynthesis are integrated at the level of <italic>SOC1</italic> expression to ultimately promote flowering (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). Therefore, it is interesting to speculate that, at least in Arabidopsis, the repression of the pathways for cold tolerance and greening following <italic>SOC1</italic> activation and the transition to reproductive growth may ensure that sufficient resources can be allocated to flowering and thereby guarantee the plant&#x2019;s reproductive success (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). Inversely, activation of <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> expression during unfavorable growth conditions, such as cold stress, that will lead to increased DELLA protein levels in the Arabidopsis wild type, would result in increased <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> expression and shift the balance toward the cold tolerance-promoting GNC and GNL pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>).</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Model of the interactions of the GATAs GNC and GNL and the MADS box transcription factor SOC1 in the control of greening, cold tolerance, and flowering with their respective regulators pathways. CO, CONSTANS; FLC, FLOWERING LOCUS C; PHY, phytochrome; SVP, SHORT VEGETATIVE PHASE.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_219238_f7"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s8" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s9"><title>Biological Material</title><p>The following mutants and transgenic lines were used in this study: <italic>ga1</italic> (Salk_109115; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Willige et al., 2007</xref>); <italic>gai-1D</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Peng et al., 1997</xref>); <italic>gnc</italic> (SALK_001778), <italic>gnl</italic> (SALK_003995), <italic>GNC</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic> (<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GNC</italic>:<italic>GFP</italic>), <italic>GNC<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic>, <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> (<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic>), and <italic>GNL<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>); <italic>PIF3</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Clack et al., 2009</xref>); <italic>rga-24 gai-t6</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">King et al., 2001</xref>); <italic>soc1-2</italic>, <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC(9x)</italic>, and <italic>SOC1<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Liu et al., 2008</xref>); and <italic>spy-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Jacobsen and Olszewski, 1993</xref>). With the exception of <italic>rga-24 gai-t6</italic> and <italic>gai-1D</italic> (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">L<italic>er</italic></xref>), all mutants and transgenic lines are in the Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) ecotype Columbia. <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> was introduced into the different genetic backgrounds by genetic crosses from a stably expressing <italic>YFP</italic>:<italic>GNL</italic> line in the Columbia or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">L<italic>er</italic></xref> background.</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>GNL<sub>Pro</sub>:GNL</title><p><italic>HA</italic> was obtained by insertion of a genomic fragment obtained by PCR amplification into the Gateway system-compatible cloning vector pEarleyGate 301 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Earley et al., 2006</xref>). The resulting T-DNA construct was directly transformed into <italic>gnc gnl</italic> mutants using the floral dip transformation method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Clough and Bent, 1998</xref>). For a list of relevant primers, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Physiological Experiments</title><p>For flowering time analyses, plants were randomly arranged and grown in 150 &#x03BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> white light in MobyLux GroBanks (CLF Plant Climatics) under long-day (16 h of light/8 h of dark, 21&#x00B0;C/18&#x00B0;C) or short-day (8 h of light/16 h of dark, 21&#x00B0;C/18&#x00B0;C) conditions. The time of bolting was scored from at least 18 plants by counting the number of rosette leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). For GA treatments, plants were watered twice per week. Cold tolerance experiments were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Achard et al., 2008a</xref>) with the following modification: 14-d-old seedlings that had or had not been cold acclimated for 2 d at 4&#x00B0;C were transferred to &#x2212;20&#x00B0;C and kept at this temperature until the agar or soil temperature reached &#x2212;6&#x00B0;C. Subsequently, seedlings were transferred to ambient temperature for an additional 4 d before seedling survival was quantified. For chlorophyll quantification, chlorophyll was extracted and quantified from 10-d-old seedlings (three independent replicates) as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Inskeep and Bloom, 1985</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR</title><p>Total RNA for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR was isolated with a NucleoSpin RNA plant kit from 10-d-old whole seedlings (Macherey-Nagel). DNA was removed by an on-column treatment with rDNase (Macherey-Nagel), and 2 &#x00B5;g of total RNA was subsequently reverse transcribed with Moloney murine leukemia virus reverse transcriptase (Fermentas) using an oligo(dT) primer. The complementary DNA equivalent of 60 to 80 ng of total RNA was used in a 10-&#x03BC;L PCR in a CFX96 Real-Time System Cycler (Bio-Rad) with iQ SYBR Green Supermix (Bio-Rad) in a 40-cycle two-step amplification protocol (10 s at 95&#x00B0;C, 25 s at 60&#x00B0;C). Relevant primers are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>GUS Staining</title><p>GUS staining was performed according to previously published methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Dohmann et al., 2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Immunoblots and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ChIP</xref></title><p>Immunoblotting was performed with the SuperSignal Femto West substrate as described previously (Thermo Fisher Scientific) using the anti-RGA antibody (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Willige et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Richter et al., 2010</xref>). Immunoblots were imaged using a LAS-4000 Mini image analyzer (FUJIFILM). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ChIP</xref> and the subsequent quantitative PCRs were performed as described by others using antibodies against <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">H3K9Ac</xref> (ab10812; Abcam) and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">H3K9me2</xref> (ab1220; Abcam), with the GFP Vector Fusion Aid kit (Axorra) for GNC:GFP and YFP:GNL, anti-c-Myc agarose (Sigma) for SOC1:MYC, and an anti-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HA</xref> antibody (3F10; Roche) together with A/Gplus-agarose beads (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) for GNL:<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HA</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Fode and Gatz, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Oh et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>Arabidopsis Genome Initiative locus identifiers for the genes mentioned in this article are as follows: <italic>CBF1</italic> (AT4G25490), <italic>CBF2</italic> (AT4G25470), <italic>CBF3</italic> (AT4G25480), <italic>COR15A</italic> (AT2G42540), <italic>COR15B</italic> (AT2G42530), <italic>FT</italic> (AT1G65480), <italic>GA1</italic> (AT4G02780), <italic>GAI</italic> (AT1G14920), <italic>GID1A</italic> (AT3G05120), <italic>GID1B</italic> (AT3G63010), <italic>GID1C</italic> (AT5G27320), <italic>GNC</italic> (AT5G56860), <italic>GNL/CGA1</italic> (AT4G26150), <italic>PIF3</italic> (AT1G09530), <italic>PORA</italic> (AT5G54190), <italic>PORB</italic> (AT4G27440), <italic>PORC</italic> (AT1G03630), <italic>RGA</italic> (AT2G01570), <italic>SOC1</italic> (AT2G45660), and <italic>SPY</italic> (AT3G11540).</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Figure S1</ext-link>.</bold> Contributions of GNC and GNL to the repression of flowering in short-day conditions.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Figure S2</ext-link>.</bold> GNC and GNL repress flowering downstream from DELLAs and PIF3.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Figure S3</ext-link>.</bold> <italic>GNC</italic> and <italic>GNL</italic> transcript levels are increased in <italic>gai-1D</italic> when compared with the wild type.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Figure S4</ext-link>.</bold> Transgenic GNL expressed from its own promoter binds to the <italic>SOC1</italic> promoter.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Figure S5</ext-link>.</bold> Differential GA sensitivity of <italic>soc1</italic> mutants with regard to flowering time but not with regard to chlorophyll accumulation.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Figure S6</ext-link>.</bold> Suppression of the <italic>soc1</italic> chlorophyll accumulation phenotype in <italic>soc1 gnc gnl</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.219238/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.</bold> List of primers used in this study.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Bj&#x00F6;rn Willige and Ulrich Lutz for critical comments on the manuscript and Hao Yu for providing the <italic>SOC1</italic>:<italic>MYC</italic> and <italic>SOC1<sub>Pro</sub></italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> transgenic lines.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baghour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapple</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Straeten</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Genschik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The plant stress hormone ethylene controls floral transition via DELLA-dependent regulation of floral meristem-identity genes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>6484</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6489</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>De Grauwe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Decat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoutteten</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Straeten</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Integration of plant responses to environmentally activated phytohormonal signals</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>311</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>94</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheminant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alioua</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Genschik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year><comment>a</comment>) <article-title>The cold-inducible CBF1 factor-dependent signaling pathway modulates the accumulation of the growth-repressing DELLA proteins via its effect on gibberellin metabolism</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2117</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2129</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Renou</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Berthom&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Genschik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year><comment>b</comment>) <article-title>Plant DELLAs restrain growth and promote survival of adversity by reducing the levels of reactive oxygen species</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>656</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>660</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vriezen</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Straeten</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Ethylene regulates <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> development via the modulation of DELLA protein growth repressor function</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2816</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2825</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Signorelli</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genetic analysis of Arabidopsis GATA transcription factor gene family reveals a nitrate-inducible member important for chlorophyll synthesis and glucose sensitivity</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>680</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>692</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E1;zquez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Independent regulation of flowering by phytochrome B and gibberellins in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>1025</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1032</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Gibberellin regulates Arabidopsis floral development via suppression of DELLA protein function</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>1055</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1064</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zubo</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapken</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavanway</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieber</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Functional characterization of the GATA transcription factors GNC and CGA1 reveals their key role in chloroplast development, growth, and division in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>160</volume>: <fpage>332</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>348</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clack</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shokry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moffet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Faul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharrock</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Obligate heterodimerization of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> phytochromes C and E and interaction with the PIF3 basic helix-loop-helix transcription factor</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>786</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>799</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Floral dip: a simplified method for Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>743</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbesier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Giakountis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrona</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gissot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>FT protein movement contributes to long-distance signaling in floral induction of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>316</volume>: <fpage>1030</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1033</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Lucas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Davi&#x00E8;re</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x00ED;guez-Falc&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglesias-Pedraz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorrain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bl&#x00E1;zquez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Titarenko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Prat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A molecular framework for light and gibberellin control of cell elongation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>451</volume>: <fpage>480</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>484</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Synergistic derepression of gibberellin signaling by removing RGA and GAI function in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>785</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohmann</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Levesque</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>De Veylder</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichardt</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x00FC;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwechheimer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis COP9 signalosome is essential for G2 phase progression and genomic stability</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>2013</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2022</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Earley</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Opper</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Juehne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pikaard</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Gateway-compatible vectors for plant functional genomics and proteomics</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>616</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>629</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gusmaroli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Iglesias-Pedraz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kircher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Coordinated regulation of Arabidopsis thaliana development by light and gibberellins</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>451</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>479</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fode</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Chromatin immunoprecipitation experiments to investigate in vivo binding of Arabidopsis transcription factors to target sequences</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source> <volume>479</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>272</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Rapid evolution of flowering time by an annual plant in response to a climate fluctuation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>1278</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1282</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutant sleepy1gar2-1 protein promotes plant growth by increasing the affinity of the SCFSLY1 E3 ubiquitin ligase for DELLA protein substrates</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1406</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1418</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallego-Bartolom&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Minguet</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mar&#x00ED;n</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Prat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bl&#x00E1;zquez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alabad&#x00ED;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional diversification and functional conservation between DELLA proteins in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1247</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1256</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galv&#x00E3;o</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name><surname>Horrer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x00FC;ttner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Spatial control of flowering by DELLA proteins in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>4072</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4082</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Zentella</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Genetic characterization and functional analysis of the GID1 gibberellin receptors in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>3399</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3414</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x00F6;hmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nettesheim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wisman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning of SVP: a negative regulator of the floral transition in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>360</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hisamatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The nature of floral signals in Arabidopsis. II. Roles for FLOWERING LOCUS T (FT) and gibberellin</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>3821</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3829</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Guevara</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaish</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannam</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>GNC and CGA1 modulate chlorophyll biosynthesis and glutamate synthase (GLU1/Fd-GOGAT) expression in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e26765</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Immink</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pos&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrario</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentim</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>de Folter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Wal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Characterization of SOC1&#x2019;s central role in flowering by the identification of its upstream and downstream regulators</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>160</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>449</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inskeep</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Extinction coefficients of chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic> in <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylformamide and 80% acetone</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>485</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Molecular biology of gibberellins signaling in higher plants</article-title>. <source>Int Rev Cell Mol Biol</source> <volume>268</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>221</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Adaptation of flowering-time by natural and artificial selection in Arabidopsis and rice</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>3091</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3097</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Olszewski</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Mutations at the <italic>SPINDLY</italic> locus of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> alter gibberellin signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>887</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>896</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The SOC1-SPL module integrates photoperiod and gibberellic acid signals to control flowering time in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>577</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>588</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Gibberellins are not required for normal stem growth in Arabidopsis thaliana in the absence of GAI and RGA</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>767</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>776</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Helliwell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A repressor complex governs the integration of flowering signals in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>110</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>120</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Er</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Soo</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liou</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Direct interaction of AGL24 and SOC1 integrates flowering signals in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>1481</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1491</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mara</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Irish</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Two GATA transcription factors are downstream effectors of floral homeotic gene action in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>707</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>718</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Warthmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x00FC;ttner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Export of FT protein from phloem companion cells is sufficient for floral induction in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1055</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1060</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bargues</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Terol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x00E9;rez-Alonso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis <italic>CBF</italic> gene family is composed of three genes encoding AP2 domain-containing proteins whose expression is regulated by low temperature but not by abscisic acid or dehydration</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>463</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>470</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The SOC1 MADS-box gene integrates vernalization and gibberellin signals for flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>613</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>623</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Koizumi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Characterization of a unique GATA family gene that responds to both light and cytokinin in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1557</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1560</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lis&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>DELLAs control plant immune responses by modulating the balance of jasmonic acid and salicylic acid signaling</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>650</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>655</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bl&#x00E1;zquez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Flowering-time genes modulate the response to LEAFY activity</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>410</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide analysis of genes targeted by PHYTOCHROME INTERACTING FACTOR 3-LIKE5 during seed germination in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>419</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parcy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Flowering: a time for integration</article-title>. <source>Int J Dev Biol</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>593</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carol</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis GAI gene defines a signaling pathway that negatively regulates gibberellin responses</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>3194</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3205</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Torti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Romera-Branchat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Spatially distinct regulatory roles for gibberellins in the promotion of flowering of Arabidopsis under long photoperiods</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>2198</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2209</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of flowering time control in Arabidopsis by comparison of double and triple mutants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>1085</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1091</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Behringer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwechheimer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The GATA-type transcription factors GNC and GNL/CGA1 repress gibberellin signaling downstream from DELLA proteins and PHYTOCHROME-INTERACTING FACTORS</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>2093</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2104</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Onouchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ditta</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz-Sommer</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Distinct roles of CONSTANS target genes in reproductive development of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>288</volume>: <fpage>1613</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1616</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwechheimer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Gibberellin signaling in plants: the extended version</article-title>. <source>Front Plant Sci</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Crosstalk between cold response and flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is mediated through the flowering-time gene <italic>SOC1</italic> and its upstream negative regulator <italic>FLC</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>3185</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3197</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverstone</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The new RGA locus encodes a negative regulator of gibberellin response in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>146</volume>: <fpage>1087</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1099</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverstone</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Olszewski</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Functional analysis of SPINDLY in gibberellin signaling in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1000</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide identification of SOC1 and SVP targets during the floral transition in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>549</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>561</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taoka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanase</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Purwestri</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>14-3-3 proteins act as intracellular receptors for rice Hd3a florigen</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>476</volume>: <fpage>332</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>335</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Chlorophyll: a symptom and a regulator of plastid development</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>181</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Salom&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Olszewski</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>SPINDLY and GIGANTEA interact and act in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> pathways involved in light responses, flowering, and rhythms in cotyledon movements</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1550</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1563</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Regulation and identity of florigen: FLOWERING LOCUS T moves center stage</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>594</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueguchi-Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsing</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>GIBBERELLIN INSENSITIVE DWARF1 encodes a soluble receptor for gibberellin</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>437</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>698</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Czech</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>miR156-regulated SPL transcription factors define an endogenous flowering pathway in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>738</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>749</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willige</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nill</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zourelidou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohmann</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwechheimer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The DELLA domain of GA INSENSITIVE mediates the interaction with the GA INSENSITIVE DWARF1A gibberellin receptor of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1209</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1220</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Heckman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Gibberellin is required for flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> under short days</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>408</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Phenotypic suppression of the gibberellin-insensitive mutant (<italic>gai</italic>) of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>502</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The sequential action of miR156 and miR172 regulates developmental timing in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>750</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>759</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>CONSTANS</italic> activates <italic>SUPPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CONSTANS 1</italic> through <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> to promote flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>770</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>778</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Galv&#x00E3;o</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Horrer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>TQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Gibberellin regulates the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> floral transition through miR156-targeted SQUAMOSA promoter binding-like transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>3320</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3332</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
