<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">207233</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.207233</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>DEVELOPMENT AND HORMONE ACTION</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Arabidopsis <italic>COP1</italic> and <italic>SPA</italic> Genes Are Essential for Plant Elongation But Not for Acceleration of Flowering Time in Response to a Low Red Light to Far-Red Light Ratio<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rolauffs</surname><given-names>Sebastian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fackendahl</surname><given-names>Petra</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sahm</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fiene</surname><given-names>Gabriele</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hoecker</surname><given-names>Ute</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Center of Excellence on Plant Sciences, Botanical Institute, Biocenter, University of Cologne, 50674 Cologne, Germany</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (grant nos. SFB572 and SFB635 to U.H.).</p></fn><fn id="afn1" fn-type="present-address"><label>2</label><p>Present address: Brunel GmbH, Franz-Rennefeld-Weg 4, 40472 Duesseldorf, Germany.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>hoeckeru@uni-koeln.de</email>.</corresp><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Ute Hoecker (<email>hoeckeru@uni-koeln.de</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.207233">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.207233</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>12</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>160</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2015</fpage><lpage>2027</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>09</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2012 American Society of Plant Biologists. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="PP_207233_ic1.gif"/><abstract><p>Plants sense vegetative shade as a reduction in the ratio of red light to far-red light (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>). Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) responds to a reduced <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> with increased elongation of the hypocotyl and the leaf petioles as well as with an acceleration of flowering time. The repressor of light signaling, CONSTITUTIVELY PHOTOMORPHOGENIC1 (COP1), has been shown previously to be essential for the shade-avoidance response in seedlings. Here, we have investigated the roles of COP1 and the COP1-interacting SUPPRESSOR OF PHYA-105 (SPA) proteins in seedling and adult facets of the shade-avoidance response. We show that <italic>COP1</italic> and the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes are essential for hypocotyl and leaf petiole elongation in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>, in a fashion that involves the COP1/SPA ubiquitination target LONG HYPOCOTYL IN FR LIGHT1 but not ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL5. In contrast, the acceleration of flowering in response to a low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> was normal in <italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>spa</italic> mutants, thus demonstrating that the COP1/SPA complex is only required for elongation responses to vegetative shade and not for shade-induced early flowering. We further show that <italic>spa</italic> mutant seedlings fail to exhibit an increase in the transcript levels of the auxin biosynthesis genes <italic>YUCCA2</italic> (<italic>YUC2</italic>), <italic>YUC8</italic>, and <italic>YUC9</italic> in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>, suggesting that an increase in auxin biosynthesis in vegetative shade requires SPA function. Consistent with this finding, expression of the auxin-response marker gene <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> did not increase in <italic>spa</italic> mutant seedlings exposed to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. We propose that COP1/SPA activity, via LONG HYPOCOTYL IN FR LIGHT1, is required for shade-induced modulation of the auxin biosynthesis pathway and thereby enhances cell elongation in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">SAS</term><def id="def1"><p>shade-avoidance syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">R:FR</term><def id="def2"><p>ratio of red light to far-red light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">R</term><def id="def3"><p>red light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">FR</term><def id="def4"><p>far-red light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">FRc</term><def id="def5"><p>continuous far-red light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">bHLH</term><def id="def6"><p>basic helix-loop-helix</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">Wc</term><def id="def7"><p>continuous white light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</term><def id="def8"><p>continuous white light supplemented with continuous far-red light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9">LED</term><def id="def9"><p>light-emitting diode</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term10">Col-0</term><def id="def10"><p>ecotype Columbia</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>Plants have evolved the capacity to perceive the ambient light environment and to adapt their growth and development accordingly. In particular, plants like Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) respond to competing vegetation with an increased elongation growth, resulting in a longer hypocotyl, extended internodes, and elongated petioles. Furthermore, shaded plants exhibit an increased leaf angle and an acceleration of flowering when compared with plants grown in open sunlight. These adaptive responses provide an attempt to outgrow the shading neighbors and are, therefore, collectively referred to as the shade-avoidance syndrome (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Ballar&#x00E9;, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Casal, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Ruberti et al., 2012</xref>). Plants sense the proximity of other plants based on the associated reduction in the ratio of red light to far-red light (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>). In full sunlight, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> is high (greater than 1), while under shading conditions, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> of the incoming light is low (less than 1) because neighboring vegetation absorbs red light (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">R</xref>) but reflects and transmits far-red light (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">FR</xref>). The reflected <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">FR</xref> can thus initiate a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> before actual shading occurs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Ballar&#x00E9; et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Casal, 2012</xref>).</p><p>The change in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> is perceived by the phytochrome family of photoreceptors, which are activated by absorption of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">R</xref> and inactivated by absorption of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">FR</xref>. Thus, the proportion of active phytochrome depends on the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> of the incoming light. In Arabidopsis, there are five phytochromes (phyA&#x2013;phyE), among which, phyB has the predominant role in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref>. Hence, phyB-deficient mutants exhibit a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> even in full sunlight and display only weak responses to a reduction in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Franklin, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Franklin and Quail, 2010</xref>). In contrast to phyB to phyE, which are primarily active at a high <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>, the photoreceptor phyA shows a maximum of activity in continuous far-red light (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">FRc</xref>) and, therefore, counteracts the phyB-mediated induction of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>phyB transduces the perceived light signal via interaction with a family of basic helix-loop-helix (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">bHLH</xref>) transcription factors, the PHYTOCHROME-INTERACTING FACTORS (PIFs). The PIF proteins are primarily active in darkness and in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions and are important for elongation responses that seedlings exhibit under these conditions. In light with a high <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>, phyB is converted into the active conformation and transported into the nucleus, where it interacts with the PIF proteins. As a consequence, the PIF proteins are phosphorylated and ubiquitinated, followed by their degradation in the 26S proteasome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Franklin, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Leivar and Quail, 2011</xref>). Four members of the PIF family, PIF3, PIF4, PIF5, and PIF7, were shown to be involved in the elongation response of hypocotyls in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions. Hence, mutants with defects in these genes show a reduced or absent <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lorrain et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Leivar et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Li et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>The PIF-mediated elongation responses are counteracted by atypical <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">bHLH</xref> transcription factors that lack the basic domain responsible for DNA binding. Hence, mutants with a defect in these transcription factors (<italic>long hypocotyl in fr light1</italic> [<italic>hfr1</italic>], <italic>phytochrome rapidly regulated1</italic> [<italic>par1</italic>], <italic>par2</italic>) show an exaggerated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Sessa et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Roig-Villanova et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hornitschek et al., 2009</xref>). The HFR1 protein was shown to physically interact with PIF4 and PIF5 via the helix-loop-helix domain and thereby inhibit the ability of PIF proteins to bind to DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hornitschek et al., 2009</xref>). The transcript levels of <italic>HFR1</italic>, <italic>PAR1</italic>, and <italic>PAR2</italic> rise shortly after the onset of low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions, thus providing a negative feedback loop (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Sessa et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Roig-Villanova et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p>Genetic analyses have identified additional transcription factors involved in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref>. Overexpression of the homeodomain Leu zipper protein Arabidopsis HOMEOBOX PROTEIN2 (ATHB2) leads to longer hypocotyls, while reduced levels of ATHB2 cause shorter hypocotyls compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Schena et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Steindler et al., 1999</xref>). Consistent with this finding, <italic>ATHB2</italic> transcript levels are strongly and rapidly up-regulated in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sorin et al., 2009</xref>). Two other shade-induced members of this family are also positive regulators of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sorin et al., 2009</xref>). The B-box-containing protein B-BOX21 was identified as a negative regulator of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Crocco et al., 2010</xref>). The positive regulator of light signaling, ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL5 (HY5), is involved in the repression of shade avoidance by brief exposure to full sunlight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sellaro et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>Microarray analyses have identified many genes that are regulated by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> in seedlings. This includes a number of auxin-related genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Devlin et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Sessa et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Tao et al., 2008</xref>). Indeed, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> requires functional auxin biosynthesis, auxin transport, and auxin signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Casal, 2012</xref>). Expression of the auxin-responsive <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> reporter increases in hypocotyl and cotyledons of seedlings exposed to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Salisbury et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Tao et al., 2008</xref>). This reflects at least in part a low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-induced increase in auxin biosynthesis via the TRYPTOPHAN AMINOTRANSFERASE OF ARABIDOPSIS1 (TAA1) pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Tao et al., 2008</xref>). While <italic>TAA1</italic> transcript levels are not regulated by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Tao et al., 2008</xref>), the mRNA levels of several YUCCA (YUC) enzymes that act downstream of TAA1 in the auxin biosynthesis pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Stepanova et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Won et al., 2011</xref>) were shown to increase in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. Consistent with this finding, mutants with defects in multiple <italic>yuc</italic> genes show a reduced <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> in seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Won et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Li et al., 2012</xref>). The shade-induced increase in <italic>YUC</italic> expression and in auxin levels requires the transcription factors PIF4, PIF5, and PIF7. Since these PIF proteins directly bind the promoters of these <italic>YUC</italic> genes, they are directly involved in up-regulating auxin biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Hornitschek et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Li et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>Besides auxin biosynthesis, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> also requires polar auxin transport. Treatment of seedlings with NPA, an inhibitor of polar auxin transport, abolishes the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> and the low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-induced increase in <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> expression in the hypocotyl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Steindler et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Tao et al., 2008</xref>). Recently, the auxin efflux carrier PIN3 was shown to be required for the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref>. Low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> exposure increases the expression of <italic>PIN-FORMED3</italic> (<italic>PIN3</italic>) and changes the localization of the PIN3 protein from the basal to the lateral side of endodermal cells in the hypocotyl. This suggests that low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> changes the flux of auxin from inner to outer tissues in the hypocotyl, thus leading to cell and hypocotyl elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Keuskamp et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>The analysis of mutants has also identified CONSTITUTIVELY PHOTOMORPHOGENIC1 (COP1) as a central regulator of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref>, since <italic>cop1</italic> mutants lack the low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-induced elongation response in seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">McNellis et al., 1994</xref>). COP1 acts in concert with SUPPRESSOR OF PHYA-105 (SPA) proteins to suppress photomorphogenesis in darkness. Hence, <italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>spa</italic> mutants undergo constitutive photomorphogenesis, exhibiting features of light-grown seedlings in complete darkness. The COP1/SPA complex is a Cullin4-based E3 ubiquitin ligase that is primarily active in darkness and catalyzes the ubiquitination of positive regulators of the light response, such as the transcription factors HY5, HFR1, and B-BOX21 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lau and Deng, 2012</xref>). At the adult stage, the COP1/SPA complex also regulates photoperiodic flowering by ubiquitinating the activator of flowering CONSTANS (CO) under dark conditions. In the light, the COP1/SPA complex is inactivated by photoreceptors, thus allowing the positive regulators of light signaling to accumulate and photomorphogenesis to be initiated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lau and Deng, 2012</xref>). <italic>COP1</italic> is a single-copy gene, while SPA proteins are encoded by a small family of four genes (<italic>SPA1</italic>&#x2013;<italic>SPA4</italic>). Genetic analysis has shown that the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes have redundant, but also partially distinct, functions in controlling the different facets of light-regulated plant development: seedling skotomorphogenesis in darkness, prevention of exaggerated seedling photomorphogenesis in the light, petiole elongation and leaf expansion, as well as photoperiodic flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Laubinger et al., 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Fittinghoff et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Balcerowicz et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>While the function of the COP1/SPA complex in photomorphogenesis has been intensively studied, its role in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> is not understood. Moreover, little is known about the genetic control of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> beyond the seedling stage. Here, we have analyzed the role of COP1 and the four SPA proteins in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> throughout Arabidopsis development. We show that <italic>COP1</italic> and <italic>SPA</italic> genes are essential for shade-induced elongation responses of seedling and leaf tissues but that neither <italic>COP1</italic> nor the <italic>SPA</italic> genes are required for the acceleration of flowering in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. We provide genetic evidence for an interaction of <italic>HFR1</italic> with the <italic>SPA</italic> genes in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions. Furthermore, transcript level analyses of auxin biosynthesis genes and a histochemical analysis of auxin response indicate that <italic>SPA</italic> genes are involved in the elevation of auxin biosynthesis in response to simulated shade.</p><sec id="s1" sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2"><title><italic>SPA</italic> Genes Are Essential for Enhanced Hypocotyl Elongation in Response to Low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref></title><p>To investigate functions of the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes in shade avoidance, we grew wild-type and <italic>spa</italic> mutant seedlings in continuous white light (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref>; high <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>) and in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> supplemented with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">FRc</xref> (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref>; low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>). Wild-type seedlings responded to simulated shade with increased hypocotyl elongation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, A and B</xref>). As reported previously, this phenotype was dependent on phyB, since <italic>phyB</italic> mutants lacked the shade-avoidance response and displayed even shorter hypocotyls in simulated shade than in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> due to the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">FR</xref> high-irradiance response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 1997</xref>). All four <italic>spa</italic> single mutants exhibited a similar phenotype to the wild type, showing increased hypocotyl elongation in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref>. Since functional redundancy might mask <italic>SPA</italic> function, we tested multiple <italic>spa</italic> mutants. Two double mutants, <italic>spa1 spa2</italic> and <italic>spa3 spa4</italic>, exhibited longer hypocotyls in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> than in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref>, but the elongation response to simulated shade was diminished compared with the wild type and the <italic>spa</italic> single mutants. Multiple <italic>spa</italic> mutants, such as the <italic>spa</italic> quadruple mutant (<italic>spa-Q</italic>) and the <italic>spa1 spa3 spa4</italic> and <italic>spa1 spa2 spa4</italic> triple mutants, lacked any increase in hypocotyl elongation in response to simulated shade (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, A and B</xref>). Similarly, cotyledon petioles of these <italic>spa</italic> mutants failed to elongate in response to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>). These results demonstrate that <italic>SPA</italic> genes have an essential, redundant function in the shade-avoidance response of seedlings.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><italic>SPA</italic> genes are essential for enhanced elongation of seedling hypocotyls and petioles in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. A, Visual seedling phenotypes of the indicated genotypes. Seedlings were grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for 6 d or shifted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> after 3 d in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref>. Within each pair of seedlings of one genotype, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref>-grown seedlings are shown on the left and seedlings grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> are shown on the right. Bar &#x003D; 5 mm. B, Hypocotyl length of seedlings grown as in A. Error bars represent <sc>se</sc>. C, Cotyledon petiole length of seedlings grown as in A. Error bars represent <sc>se</sc>. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Col-0</xref>, Wild-type accession Columbia.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_207233_wc_f1" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>We subsequently compared the phenotypes of the four possible <italic>spa</italic> triple mutants, each retaining the function of only one <italic>SPA</italic> gene. We found that these triple mutants exhibited distinct phenotypes, with <italic>spa2 spa3 spa4</italic> and in particular <italic>spa1 spa2 spa3</italic> mutants retaining significant elongation responses to shade (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). Hence, <italic>SPA1</italic> and <italic>SPA4</italic> are sufficient to sustain a shade-avoidance response in seedlings, while <italic>SPA2</italic> and <italic>SPA3</italic> are not.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title><italic>SPA</italic> Genes and <italic>COP1</italic> Are Essential for the Enhanced Petiole Elongation of Adult Leaves in Response to Low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref></title><p>Adult plants also respond to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions with increased elongation growth. In particular, the petioles of rosette leaves strongly increase in length when plants are grown in simulated shade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Casal, 2012</xref>). Since the role of <italic>COP1</italic> or <italic>SPA</italic> genes in this aspect of the shade-avoidance response has not been investigated so far, we grew <italic>cop1-4</italic> and <italic>spa</italic> mutant plants in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> and under simulated shade conditions. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> shows that petioles of wild-type plants elongated in response to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref>. In contrast, petioles of the <italic>spa</italic> quadruple and <italic>cop1-4</italic> mutants failed to show increased elongation in response to simulated shade treatment. Hence, <italic>SPA</italic> genes and <italic>COP1</italic> are essential for shade-induced petiole elongation in adult plants. All four <italic>spa</italic> triple mutants retained a significant elongation response, which, however, was considerably smaller when compared with the wild type, in particular in those triple mutants retaining only <italic>SPA2</italic>, <italic>SPA3</italic>, or <italic>SPA4</italic> function. The <italic>spa2 spa3 spa4</italic> triple mutant retaining only <italic>SPA1</italic> function showed an almost normal elongation response to shade. Hence, the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes act redundantly in controlling this aspect of the shade-avoidance response, with <italic>SPA1</italic> being the predominant player among the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><italic>SPA</italic> genes and <italic>COP1</italic> are required for leaf petiole elongation in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. A, Photographs show representative plants of the wild type (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Col-0</xref>), <italic>spa</italic> triple mutants, <italic>spa-Q</italic>, and <italic>cop1-4</italic> grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref>. Bars &#x003D; 10 mm. B, Petiole length of the longest leaf of the indicated genotypes, represented as means &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc>. Plants were grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for 4 d and then shifted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> or kept in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for an additional 7 d.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_207233_wc_f2" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4"><title><italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>spa</italic> Mutants Show Normal Acceleration of Flowering Time in Response to Low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref></title><p>Shade conditions cause earlier flowering, thus allowing plants to proceed to reproductive development at an earlier time, which likely provides a competitive advantage under these suboptimal light conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Casal, 2012</xref>). Since COP1 and SPA proteins are required for the photoperiodic regulation of flowering time via controlling CO protein stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Laubinger et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Jang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Liu et al., 2008</xref>), we investigated whether shade-dependent control of flowering time also depends on <italic>COP1</italic> and <italic>SPA</italic> genes. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3, A and B</xref>, shows that wild-type plants flowered at an earlier time and with fewer leaves in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> when compared with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref>. All <italic>spa</italic> triple and quadruple mutants as well as the <italic>cop1-4</italic> mutant exhibited a similar acceleration of flowering time caused by low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>, as it was observed in the wild type. This demonstrates that low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> controls flowering time independently of <italic>COP1</italic> and <italic>SPA</italic> genes.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Shade avoidance-driven acceleration of flowering time does not require <italic>SPA</italic> and <italic>COP1</italic> gene functions. A and B, Number of days (A) and number of rosette leaves (B) at the time of bolting in plants grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref>. Error bars represent <sc>se</sc>. C, Relative transcript levels of the floral integrator <italic>FT</italic> in plants grown for 4 d in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> and then shifted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> or kept in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for an additional 7 d. <italic>UBQ10</italic> was used as an endogenous control. All data were calibrated to the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Col-0</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> samples and represent means of three biological replicates &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_207233_lw_f3" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> increases the transcript levels of <italic>FT</italic>, which encodes a key positive regulator of flowering time in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kim et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wollenberg et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Adams et al., 2009</xref>). Therefore, we tested whether <italic>FT</italic> expression is altered in <italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>spa</italic> mutants. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref> shows that simulated shade caused a similar, approximately 50-fold, increase in <italic>FT</italic> transcript levels in the wild type and in <italic>spa1 spa3 spa4</italic> and <italic>cop1-4</italic> mutants. Hence, low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-induced <italic>FT</italic> regulation was normal in <italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>spa</italic> mutants, which is consistent with the normal low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-induced acceleration of flowering time observed in these mutants. Taken together, these results show that <italic>COP1</italic> and <italic>SPA</italic> genes are essential for low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-induced elongation responses in seedlings and adult plants, while they are dispensable for early flowering caused by simulated shade.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Expression of Early Shade Marker Genes in <italic>spa</italic> Mutant Seedlings</title><p>We further analyzed SPA function in the shade-avoidance response of seedlings. Since <italic>SPA</italic> genes are essential for the morphological response of seedlings to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>, we subsequently asked whether this phenotype reflects defects in the expression of early shade marker genes. Therefore, we analyzed transcript levels of <italic>PHYTOCHROME-INTERACTING FACTOR3-LIKE1</italic> (<italic>PIL1</italic>), <italic>HFR1</italic>, and <italic>ATHB2</italic> in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref>-grown seedlings exposed to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> for 3 h. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref> shows that the levels of these three transcripts increased 10- to 30-fold in shade-exposed wild-type seedlings. <italic>spa</italic> triple mutants and the <italic>spa</italic> quadruple mutant showed a similar increase in transcript levels in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. Hence, expression of these early shade marker genes appeared normal in the absence of <italic>SPA</italic> gene function. Also, over longer periods of low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> treatment, up to 48 h, the <italic>spa1 spa3 spa4</italic> mutant and also the <italic>cop1-4</italic> mutant retained a robust shade-induced increase in <italic>PIL1</italic> mRNA levels that was not different from the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). This suggests that the induction of these early shade marker genes is not sufficient to elicit a morphological elongation response to shade.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Expression of early shade marker genes in the wild type and in <italic>spa</italic> multiple mutants. A, Transcript levels of <italic>PIL1</italic>, <italic>ATHB2</italic>, <italic>HFR1</italic>, and <italic>XTR7</italic> were determined by quantitative reverse transcription-PCR. Seedlings were grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for 4 d (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref>) and subsequently shifted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> for 3 h (3 h <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref>) or kept in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for 3 h (3 h <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref>). <italic>UBQ10</italic> was used as an endogenous control. Data were calibrated to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Col-0</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> and represent means of three biological replicates &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc>. B, Transcript levels of <italic>PIL1</italic> were analyzed by quantitative reverse transcription-PCR. Seedlings were grown for 4 d in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> and subsequently shifted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> or kept in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for the indicated times. <italic>UBQ10</italic> was used as an endogenous control. All data were calibrated to the 0-h <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Col-0</xref>) sample and represent means of three biological replicates &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_207233_wc_f4" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>We subsequently tested transcript levels of <italic>XYLOGLUCAN ENDOTRANSGLYCOSYLASE7</italic> (<italic>XTR7</italic>), a low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-responsive gene coding for a cell wall-modifying enzyme that is thought to be directly involved in cell elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hornitschek et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Sasidharan et al., 2010</xref>). We found that <italic>XTR7</italic> transcript levels increased more than 50-fold in wild-type seedlings exposed to simulated shade (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). In <italic>spa</italic> triple and <italic>spa</italic> quadruple mutants, in contrast, low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> led only to a 3- to 10-fold increase in <italic>XTR7</italic> mRNA levels. These results suggest that an up-regulation of <italic>XTR7</italic> by low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> contributes to the increased hypocotyl elongation observed in simulated shade.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title><italic>SPA</italic> Genes Are Required for Low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-Induced Increase in <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>YUC</italic> Expression</title><p>The shade-avoidance response correlates with an increase in the expression of <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic>, an indirect artificial reporter of auxin-regulated gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Salisbury et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Tao et al., 2008</xref>). To investigate whether <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> expression is altered in the <italic>spa</italic> mutants lacking a shade-avoidance response, we crossed the <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> transgene into the <italic>spa1 spa3 spa4</italic> and <italic>spa1 spa2 spa4</italic> triple mutant backgrounds. Wild-type seedlings grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> exhibited very low levels of DR5::GUS that were visible only at the tips of the cotyledons and at the root tip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>). After exposure to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>, wild-type seedlings responded with a strong increase in DR5::GUS levels, in particular in the cotyledons and in the vasculature of the hypocotyl. The two <italic>spa</italic> triple mutants, in contrast, did not exhibit any increase in DR5::GUS levels in response to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> irradiation. These seedlings exhibited similarly low DR5::GUS levels in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> as the wild type did in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref>. Hence, the lack of a shade-avoidance response in these <italic>spa</italic> triple mutants correlates with a failure to increase <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> expression.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><italic>spa</italic> triple mutants lack the low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-induced increase in the transcript levels of <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>YUC</italic> auxin biosynthesis genes. A, Seedlings carrying the <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> transgene were grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for 4 d and then shifted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> or kept in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for 7 h. Seedlings were then stained for GUS activity. B and C, Transcript levels of <italic>TAA1</italic> (B) and five <italic>YUC</italic> genes (C) in seedlings grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for 4 d and subsequently shifted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> for 3 h or kept in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for 3 h.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_207233_wc_f5" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>The shade-induced increase in DR5::GUS levels may be due to an increase in auxin levels and/or auxin signaling. It was shown previously that an increase in auxin biosynthesis is required for hypocotyl elongation in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Tao et al., 2008</xref>). Therefore, we investigated whether the transcript levels of genes in the auxin biosynthesis pathway are misregulated in <italic>spa</italic> mutants. The levels of the <italic>TAA1</italic> transcript were not responsive to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>), which is in agreement with previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Tao et al., 2008</xref>). <italic>TAA1</italic> levels were also not altered in <italic>spa</italic> triple or quadruple mutants under any of the conditions tested. Among the five <italic>YUC</italic> transcripts that we tested, <italic>YUC2</italic>, <italic>YUC8</italic>, and <italic>YUC9</italic> transcript levels increased 4- to 20-fold in wild-type seedlings exposed to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> for 3 h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>). This is in agreement with the findings reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Li et al. (2012)</xref>. The four <italic>spa</italic> triple mutants showed a reduced shade induction of these three <italic>YUC</italic> transcripts, while the <italic>spa</italic> quadruple mutant fully lacked any significant increase in the levels of these <italic>YUC</italic> transcripts in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>). Hence, <italic>SPA</italic> genes are required for the regulation of <italic>YUC2</italic>, <italic>YUC8</italic>, and <italic>YUC9</italic> transcripts by simulated shade. <italic>YUC1</italic> and <italic>YUC4</italic> transcript levels, in contrast, were not regulated by low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> in the wild type, and <italic>spa</italic> mutants did not show a change in expression of these <italic>YUC</italic> genes when compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title><italic>SPA</italic> Genes Genetically Interact with <italic>HFR1</italic> in Low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> Conditions</title><p>The COP1/SPA complex acts as a negative regulator of transcription factors that trigger light responses. These include HFR1 and HY5, whose levels are strongly increased in <italic>spa</italic> and <italic>cop1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Osterlund et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Yang et al., 2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">2005b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Zhu et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Nixdorf and Hoecker, 2010</xref>). HFR1 also serves a prominent function as a negative regulator of shade-avoidance responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Sessa et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hornitschek et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Galstyan et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, we addressed the question of whether <italic>SPA</italic> genes might function in shade avoidance via controlling HFR1 protein levels. To this end, we analyzed the genetic interaction between <italic>spa</italic> and <italic>hfr1</italic> mutations in the shade-avoidance response. As reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Sessa et al., 2005</xref>), <italic>hfr1-101</italic> mutant seedlings exhibited a longer hypocotyl only in simulated shade when compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>). When the <italic>hfr1-101</italic> allele was introduced into the <italic>spa1 spa3 spa4</italic> triple mutant, which lacks a shade-avoidance response, the elongation response to simulated shade was partially restored in this triple mutant: <italic>spa1 spa3 spa4 hfr1</italic> mutant seedlings exhibited a longer hypocotyl in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> than in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>). This suggests that <italic>SPA</italic> genes genetically interact with <italic>HFR1</italic> in the response of the hypocotyl to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> and suggests that SPA proteins act positively on shade avoidance by repressing HFR1 function.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>The <italic>hfr1</italic> mutation, but not the <italic>hy5</italic> mutation, partially rescues hypocotyl elongation in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> in the <italic>spa1 spa3 spa4</italic> mutant. Hypocotyl lengths are shown for 8-d-old seedlings grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for 4 d and then shifted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> or kept in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for 4 d. Error bars represent <sc>se</sc>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_207233_lw_f6" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Another target of the COP1/SPA complex, HY5, controls the light-induced reduction in cell elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Oyama et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Osterlund et al., 2000</xref>). Therefore, we investigated whether HY5 is also involved in the COP1/SPA-mediated control of shade avoidance. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6B</xref> shows that <italic>spa1 spa3 spa4 hy5</italic> mutant seedlings lacked a shade-avoidance response just like the <italic>spa1 spa3 spa4</italic> triple mutant did. Thus, introducing the <italic>hy5</italic> mutation into a <italic>spa1 spa3 spa4</italic> background did not restore a shade-avoidance response. This indicates that the COP1/SPA-mediated control of HY5 protein levels does not play a major role in shade avoidance.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> Does Not Alter <italic>SPA</italic> Transcript Levels</title><p>We had observed that the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes provide differential contributions to the seedling response to simulated shade, with <italic>SPA1</italic> and <italic>SPA4</italic> being the major players and <italic>SPA2</italic> and <italic>SPA3</italic> being of minor importance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). Since the expression of <italic>SPA</italic> genes is differentially controlled by light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Fittinghoff et al., 2006</xref>), we asked whether the partially distinct functions of the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes may be caused by differential expression in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref> shows that exposure to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> did not significantly change the transcript levels of any of the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes. This indicates that <italic>SPA</italic> genes are not regulated by low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. Thus, the partially distinct functions of the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes are not caused by differential regulation of <italic>SPA</italic> transcript levels in response to shade.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>The transcript levels of the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes do not change in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions. Transcript levels were determined by quantitative reverse transcription-PCR. Seedlings were grown for 4 d in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> and then shifted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> or kept in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for the indicated times. <italic>UBQ10</italic> was used as an endogenous control. Data were calibrated to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Col-0</xref> 0-h <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for each gene and shown as means of three biological replicates &#x00B1; <sc>se</sc>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_207233_lw_f7" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec id="s9"><title>The Distinct Functions of <italic>SPA1</italic> and <italic>SPA2</italic> in the Seedling Shade-Avoidance Response Is Due to Differences in the Regulatory and Protein-Coding Sequences</title><p>We had previously generated transgenic lines expressing chimeric <italic>SPA1/SPA2</italic> constructs that carry swaps between the regulatory sequences (promoter; 3&#x2032; untranslated region) and the protein-coding sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Balcerowicz et al., 2011</xref>). We used these transgenic lines to ask whether the difference between <italic>SPA1</italic> and <italic>SPA2</italic> function in the shade-avoidance response maps to the respective regulatory and/or coding sequences. These chimeric <italic>SPA1/SPA2</italic> constructs were expressed in the <italic>spa-Q</italic> background, which lacks a shade-avoidance response in seedlings. We found that expression of the nonchimeric <italic>SPA2</italic>::<italic>SPA2</italic> construct did not restore a shade-avoidance response in the <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutant, as expected, indicating that this construct correctly phenocopied the <italic>spa1 spa3 spa4</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>). When the SPA1 protein was expressed from the <italic>SPA2</italic> promoter (<italic>SPA2</italic>::<italic>SPA1</italic>), shade avoidance was observed. Hence, the sequence of the SPA1 protein carries intrinsic information for its function in shade avoidance. However, the SPA2 protein can restore shade avoidance when it is expressed from the stronger <italic>SPA1</italic> promoter (<italic>SPA1</italic>::<italic>SPA2</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>). Hence, both the regulatory sequences and the protein-coding sequences contribute to the distinct functions of <italic>SPA1</italic> and <italic>SPA2</italic> in shade avoidance.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Divergent functions of <italic>SPA1</italic> and <italic>SPA2</italic> in simulated shade derives from their regulatory and protein-coding sequences. A, Schematic representation of chimeric <italic>SPA1/SPA2</italic> constructs containing the <italic>SPA1</italic> or <italic>SPA2</italic> promoter (<italic>pSPA1</italic> and <italic>pSPA2</italic>), the <italic>SPA1</italic> or <italic>SPA2</italic> open reading frame (ORF), the hemagglutinin (HA) tag, and the 3&#x2032; untranslated region of <italic>SPA1</italic> or <italic>SPA2</italic> (<italic>3&#x2032; SPA1</italic> and <italic>3&#x2032; SPA2</italic>). B, Hypocotyl length of seedlings expressing the constructs shown in A in the <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutant background. Seedlings were grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for 3 d and then shifted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Wc&#x0394;FRc</xref> or kept in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for an additional 3 d. Error bars indicate <sc>se</sc>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_207233_gs_f8" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s10" sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions lead to a vast change in growth and development throughout the life cycle of a plant. Here, we have analyzed the role of key repressors of photomorphogenesis, COP1 and the four SPA proteins, during three developmental stages of low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-exposed plants: seedlings, adult plants during vegetative growth, and adult plants during the transition to the reproductive flowering stage.</p><p>We found that <italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutant seedlings failed to elongate their hypocotyl and cotyledon petioles in response to simulated shade. This finding agrees with previous studies showing that <italic>cop1</italic> mutants do not show a seedling shade-avoidance response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">McNellis et al., 1994</xref>). We showed that also at the rosette leaf stage, <italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutant plants did not show any elongation of the leaf petioles in response to simulated shade. In contrast, <italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutants exhibited an acceleration of flowering time in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> that was very similar to the wild type. Taken together, these results demonstrate that the COP1/SPA ubiquitin ligase is a key player in the etiolation of seedlings and leaves but not in the acceleration of flowering time in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. Thus, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> involves COP1/SPA-dependent and COP1/SPA-independent signaling activities.</p><p>The increased elongation of hypocotyls in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> is primarily caused by cell elongation and not by cell division (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Gendreau et al., 1997</xref>). When analyzing the transcript levels of shade-regulated genes, we found that <italic>SPA</italic> genes are necessary for normal up-regulation of the <italic>XTR7</italic> transcript, which encodes a cell wall-modifying enzyme thought to function in cell elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Sasidharan et al., 2010</xref>). Hence, the observation that <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutants do not elongate in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> correlates well with the reduced up-regulation of <italic>XTR7</italic> expression in shade-grown <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutants. An important hormone in low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-induced cell elongation is auxin, which is synthesized from Trp via the enzymatic activities of TAA1 and a family of YUC proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Tao et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Stepanova et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Won et al., 2011</xref>). It was shown previously that this pathway is essential for hypocotyl elongation in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>, since <italic>taa1</italic> mutants and <italic>yuc</italic> multiple mutants show no or a reduced shade-avoidance response, respectively, at the seedling stage. While <italic>TAA1</italic> transcript levels are not regulated by shade, several <italic>YUC</italic> transcripts are up-regulated by low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Tao et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Won et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Li et al., 2012</xref>). We found that low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> regulation of exactly these <italic>YUC</italic> transcripts requires SPA proteins, since the <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutant failed to show any increase in the transcript levels of <italic>YUC2</italic>, <italic>YUC8</italic>, and <italic>YUC9</italic> in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. Other, not shade-regulated transcripts tested (<italic>YUC1</italic>, <italic>YUC4</italic>, <italic>TAA1</italic>), in contrast, were expressed at similar levels in wild-type and <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutant seedlings. Hence, the <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutant showed a misregulation specifically of the low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-regulated <italic>YUC</italic> genes. In wild-type seedlings exposed to simulated shade, the increased expression of <italic>YUC</italic> genes leads to higher auxin levels and to higher expression of the auxin-responsive reporter <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Hornitschek et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Li et al., 2012</xref>). In <italic>spa</italic> mutants, in contrast, exposure to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> did not cause any detectable increase in <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> expression. This is consistent with the observed lack of <italic>YUC</italic> gene regulation by low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> in <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutant seedlings. Taken together, these results suggest that the failure of <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutant seedlings to elongate in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> is, at least in part, caused by their failure to up-regulate the expression of <italic>YUC</italic> genes in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>.</p><p>Our epistasis analysis showed that <italic>SPA</italic> genes act upstream of the COP1/SPA ubiquitination substrate HFR1, but not of HY5, in controlling the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref>. HFR1 is an atypical <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">bHLH</xref> protein that lacks a functional DNA-binding domain. It inhibits the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> by forming nonproductive heterodimers with the typical <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">bHLH</xref> proteins of the PIF family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hornitschek et al., 2009</xref>). It was shown that PIF proteins promote cell elongation in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> by binding to the promoters of <italic>YUC8</italic> and <italic>YUC9</italic>, thereby activating gene expression in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Hornitschek et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Li et al., 2012</xref>). Hence, we propose that the COP1/SPA ubiquitin ligase is necessary for the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> because it ubiquitinates HFR1, thereby releasing PIF proteins from the inhibitory activity of HFR1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>). Subsequently, PIF proteins can activate <italic>YUC</italic> expression, which leads to an increase in auxin biosynthesis and in the expression of the artificial reporter <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic>. Since low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> strongly induces <italic>HFR1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Sessa et al., 2005</xref>; this work), COP1/SPA activity may be particularly important in limiting HFR1 function in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions. According to this model, HFR1 would not be degraded in <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutants. As a consequence, HFR1 protein levels would be especially high in low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-grown <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutants and therefore counteract the low-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-induced stabilization of PIF proteins, thereby maintaining the high <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> phenotype even under low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions. Besides controlling PIF protein stability and <italic>HFR1</italic> expression, we speculate that the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> may also affect COP1/SPA ubiquitin ligase activity, since photoreceptors, including phytochromes, are thought to inactivate the COP1/SPA complex in the light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Lau and Deng, 2012</xref>). Hence, COP1/SPA may be more active in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> than in high <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>), which would lead to increased HFR1 degradation in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> and, therefore, increased PIF protein activity.</p><fig id="fig9" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Model of the function of COP1/SPA in controlling hypocotyl elongation in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. For discussion, see text.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_207233_gs_f9" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Apart from regulating HFR1 protein stability, the COP1/SPA complex likely has additional roles in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref>. The levels of the PIF protein PIF3 were shown to be much lower in dark-grown <italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>spa</italic> mutants when compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bauer et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Leivar et al., 2008</xref>). If PIF4, PIF5, and/or PIF7 protein levels are also up-regulated by the COP1/SPA complex, this regulation will also contribute to cell elongation in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. In addition, BBX transcription factors have been shown to act downstream of COP1 in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Crocco et al., 2010</xref>), and ELF3, another target of the COP1/SPA ubiquitin ligase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Yu et al., 2008</xref>), was identified as a quantitative trait locus for the shade-avoidance response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Jimenez-Gomez et al., 2010</xref>). It remains to be determined whether these transcription factors also act on the expression of <italic>YUC</italic> genes or have a different function in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref>.</p><p>In contrast to the misregulated transcripts <italic>XTR7</italic> and <italic>YUC</italic>, the transcript levels of two negative regulators of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">SAS</xref>, <italic>PIL1</italic> and <italic>HFR1</italic>, as well as of <italic>ATHB2</italic> increased normally in <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutants in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> when compared with the wild type. This is in contrast to previous results showing that <italic>cop1</italic> mutants exhibit an approximately 2- to 3-fold reduced response of these early shade marker genes when compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Roig-Villanova et al., 2006</xref>). While these contrasting results may be due to the experimental setups, our results nevertheless show that SPA proteins have a much stronger effect on the expression of <italic>XTR7</italic>, <italic>YUC2</italic>, <italic>YUC7</italic>, and <italic>YUC8</italic> than on <italic>PIL1</italic>, <italic>ATHB2</italic>, and <italic>HFR1</italic>. Since all these genes are regulated by PIF proteins, it is tempting to speculate that these two sets of genes respond to different PIF proteins or exhibit different binding affinities for PIF proteins.</p><p>Our results show that <italic>COP1</italic> and <italic>SPA</italic> genes are also required for elongation of the petiole in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. This aspect of the shade-avoidance response is much less understood than the hypocotyl response. Spotlight irradiation of small areas in the leaf blade or petiole demonstrated that the leaf blade is the photoperceptive site for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">FR</xref>-induced elongation of the petiole. In the leaf blade, <italic>YUC2</italic>, <italic>YUC8</italic>, and <italic>YUC9</italic> were up-regulated in response to end-of-day <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">FR</xref>, although auxin levels did not increase either in the blade or in the petiole of the leaf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kozuka et al., 2010</xref>). The conserved regulation of these <italic>YUC</italic> genes in leaf blades and seedlings nevertheless suggests that COP1/SPA may act in the leaf in a similar way to that in the seedling. In petiole elongation, the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes show fully redundant activities, because only <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutants exhibit a lack of this facet of the shade-avoidance response. With respect to seedling shade avoidance in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>, the four <italic>SPA</italic> genes show distinct actions: <italic>SPA1</italic> and <italic>SPA4</italic> are the primary players, while the contributions of <italic>SPA2</italic> and <italic>SPA3</italic> are of negligible importance. Our functional analysis of <italic>SPA1/SPA2</italic> chimeric genes demonstrates that at least part of the distinct functions of <italic>SPA1</italic> and <italic>SPA2</italic> is encoded in the respective protein sequence. This agrees with our earlier results showing that the SPA2 protein loses repressor activity as soon as dark-grown seedlings are transferred to the light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Balcerowicz et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>One aspect of the shade-avoidance response is earlier flowering in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. We found that <italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutants flowered earlier in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> than in high <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> and thus responded to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> similarly to the wild type. Consistent with this finding, <italic>FT</italic> transcript levels increased very strongly in <italic>spa-Q</italic> mutants in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. This result indicates that the COP1/SPA ubiquitin ligase is not essential for the control of flowering time by simulated shade. The expression of <italic>FT</italic> is primarily regulated by the balancing activities of two transcription factors: the repressor of flowering FLC and the activator of flowering CO. While CO is a target of the COP1/SPA ubiquitin ligase in darkness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Laubinger et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Jang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Liu et al., 2008</xref>), CO degradation in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">R</xref> was found to be independent of COP1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Jang et al., 2008</xref>). This latter finding is in agreement with our results showing that flowering time regulation by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> does not require COP1/SPA. Moreover, SPA proteins and phyB act in distinct tissues in the control of flowering time: while phyB acts in the mesophyll, SPA1 acts in the phloem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Endo et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Ranjan et al., 2011</xref>). Previous results have shown that white light &#x0394; <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">FR</xref> increases <italic>CO</italic> transcript levels and also enhances CO protein stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kim et al., 2008</xref>). Since CO and the activator of <italic>CO</italic> transcription GI are important for the acceleration of flowering in far-red-enriched light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kim et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wollenberg et al., 2008</xref>), low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> clearly acts on <italic>CO</italic> expression and CO stability. However, how low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> regulates <italic>CO</italic> remains to be investigated.</p><p>In summary, we have shown that facets of the shade-avoidance response are genetically separable, with the COP1/SPA complex being required for the elongation of hypocotyl and petiole tissues in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>, while it is dispensable for the acceleration of flowering in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>. This was similarly reported for the transcription factor ATHB2, which is also not required for the control of flowering time by low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Kim et al., 2008</xref>). Moreover, we have demonstrated that SPA proteins are required for the increase in <italic>YUC2</italic>, <italic>YUC8</italic>, and <italic>YUC9</italic> transcript levels in response to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>, suggesting that the COP1/SPA complex regulates cell elongation in low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> by controlling auxin biosynthesis. Taken together, our genetic and molecular characterization has elucidated the role of COP1/SPA within the signaling cascades leading to different features of the shade-avoidance response.</p></sec><sec id="s11" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s12"><title>Plant Material</title><p>All Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) <italic>spa</italic> single, double, triple, and quadruple mutants have been described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Laubinger and Hoecker, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Laubinger et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Fittinghoff et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Balcerowicz et al., 2011</xref>), except for <italic>spa1-7 spa2-1 spa4-1</italic>, which was established by crossing <italic>spa4-1</italic> with the <italic>spa1-7 spa2-1</italic> double mutant. <italic>cop1-4</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">McNellis et al., 1994</xref>), <italic>hy5-215</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Oyama et al., 1997</xref>), <italic>hy5-51</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Ruckle et al., 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">2012</xref>), and <italic>hfr1-101</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Fankhauser and Chory, 2000</xref>) have been described earlier. The <italic>spa1-7 spa3-1 spa4-1 hfr1-101</italic> and <italic>spa1-7 spa3-1 spa4-1 hy5-51</italic> mutants were selected from the respective F2 populations based on phenotype and subsequently confirmed using polymorphic markers (Laubinger and Hoecker, 2003; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Fittinghoff et al., 2006</xref>). The <italic>cop1-4 hy5-215</italic> double mutant was generated by Roman Ulm (University of Geneva). The <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> transgene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Ulmasov et al., 1997</xref>) was crossed into the <italic>spa1-7 spa2-1 spa3-1</italic> and <italic>spa1-7 spa2-1 spa4-1</italic> triple mutants.</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Growth Conditions and Light Treatment</title><p>For seedling experiments and all transcript analyses, seeds were surface sterilized and subsequently sown on Murashige and Skoog (Duchefa) plates without Suc containing 1% activated charcoal. We found that the addition of activated charcoal to the medium enhances the shade-avoidance response in seedlings. Seeds were stratified at 4&#x00B0;C for 2 to 3 d in the dark and subsequently incubated in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> (50 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>), provided by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> light-emitting diodes (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">LEDs</xref>), at 21&#x00B0;C (FloraLED; CLF Plant Climatics) for 3 d. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> was 10.3. For simulated shade treatment, 3-d-old seedlings were then exposed to the same <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> treatment but supplemented with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">FRc</xref> emitted from built-in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">FR</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">LEDs</xref> (FloraLED) for 3 d (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> &#x003D; 0.22). The high-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref>-treated control seedlings were kept in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> for the same period of time.</p><p>For adult plant growth analyses and determination of flowering time, seeds were first incubated in water for 3 d at 4&#x00B0;C and then germinated on soil in single wells of 77-well trays in a randomized fashion. For high <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> treatment, seedlings were grown in a growth chamber (AR-36L; Percival-Scientific) in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Wc</xref> provided by cool-white fluorescent light sources (50 &#x00B5;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>; <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> &#x003D; 9.8) at 21&#x00B0;C and 60% humidity. For simulated shade treatment, seedlings were grown under the same conditions for 4 d and were subsequently transferred to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> conditions. These were produced in the same AR-36L growth chamber that was additionally equipped with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">FR</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">LED</xref> light sources (Quantum Devices). The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> was 0.15.</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Determination of Hypocotyl Length, Petiole Length, and Flowering Time</title><p>Seedlings were flattened on the surface of the agar plates and photographed with a Nikon D5000 digital camera. The measurements of hypocotyl and cotyledon petiole length were carried out using ImageJ 1.43u software (Wayne Rasband, National Institutes of Health). A minimum of 15 seedlings per genotype and condition were analyzed, and each experiment was repeated at least twice. Petiole length of leaves was determined in 11-d-old plants by measuring the petiole of the longest leaf. At least eight leaves were measured per genotype and condition, and the experiment was repeated twice. Flowering time was scored on the first day the inflorescence was visible to the unaided eye. It was determined as the number of rosette leaves formed and the number of days since transfer of sown seeds to 21&#x00B0;C. At least eight plants were analyzed for each genotype and condition, and all experiments were repeated twice.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Analysis of Transcript Levels by Quantitative Reverse Transcription-PCR</title><p>RNA extraction, DNase digestion, complementary DNA synthesis, and quantitative PCR were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Balcerowicz et al., 2011</xref>). The 2<sup>-&#x0394;&#x0394;Ct</sup> method was used to determine relative transcript levels normalized to the <italic>UBQ10</italic> transcript levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Livak and Schmittgen, 2001</xref>). Three biological replicates were used, and each was analyzed in duplicate. The primer pairs used in this study for the amplification of the transcripts of <italic>UBQ10</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Balcerowicz et al., 2011</xref>), <italic>ATHB2</italic>, <italic>HFR1</italic>, and <italic>PIL1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lorrain et al., 2008</xref>), <italic>XTR7</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hornitschek et al., 2009</xref>), <italic>TAA1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Franklin et al., 2011</xref>), <italic>YUC1</italic> and <italic>YUC4</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Rizzardi et al., 2011</xref>), <italic>YUC2</italic>, <italic>YUC8</italic>, and <italic>YUC9</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Stavang et al., 2009</xref>), and <italic>FT</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wollenberg et al., 2008</xref>) were described earlier. Primers for the analysis of <italic>SPA1</italic>, <italic>SPA2</italic>, <italic>SPA3</italic>, and <italic>SPA4</italic> transcript levels by quantitative PCR are provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.207233/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Histochemical Analysis of GUS Activity</title><p>Seedlings were grown on plates in high <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> as described above for 4 d, except that the temperature was raised to 27&#x00B0;C to boost auxin production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Gray et al., 1998</xref>). This was necessary to allow DR5::GUS detection. Seedlings were then either kept in high <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> or shifted to low <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">R:FR</xref> for 7 h. They were incubated in GUS staining buffer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Ranjan et al., 2011</xref>), but without vacuum infiltration, at 37&#x00B0;C for 16 h in darkness and subsequently destained in 70% ethanol.</p><p>The Arabidopsis Genome Initiative numbers for genes mentioned in this article are as follows: <italic>SPA1</italic> (At2g46340), <italic>SPA2</italic> (At4g11110), <italic>SPA3</italic> (At3g15354), <italic>SPA4</italic> (At1g53090), <italic>COP1</italic> (At2g32950), <italic>HY5</italic> (At5g11260), <italic>HFR1</italic> (At1g02340), <italic>YUC1</italic> (At4g32540), <italic>YUC2</italic> (At4g13260), <italic>YUC4</italic> (At5g11320), <italic>YUC8</italic> (At4g28720), <italic>YUC9</italic> (At1g04180), and <italic>TAA1</italic> (At1g70560).</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.<list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.207233/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S1</bold></ext-link>. Primers used for quantitative PCR.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Johannes Stauber, Stephen Dickopf, Vicky Tilmes, and Laura Rupprecht for excellent technical assistance and Klaus Menrath and the greenhouse staff for expert care of our plants. We are grateful to Siegfried Werth for photography. Transgenic seed expressing the <italic>DR5</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> reporter was kindly provided by Tom Guilfoyle. We thank Roman Ulm for providing seed of the <italic>cop1-4 hy5-215</italic> double mutant.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitelam</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Interaction between the light quality and flowering time pathways in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>267</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balcerowicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fittinghoff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirthmueller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fackendahl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiene</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Koncz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoecker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Light exposure of Arabidopsis seedlings causes rapid de-stabilization as well as selective post-translational inactivation of the repressor of photomorphogenesis SPA2</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>712</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>723</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballar&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Keeping up with the neighbours: phytochrome sensing and other signalling mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>102</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballar&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Scopel</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x00E1;nchez</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Far-red radiation reflected from adjacent leaves: an early signal of competition in plant canopies</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>247</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>332</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Viczi&#x00E1;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kircher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nobis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nitschke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunkel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Panigrahi</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ad&#x00E1;m</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fejes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x00E4;fer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Constitutive photomorphogenesis 1 and multiple photoreceptors control degradation of phytochrome interacting factor 3, a transcription factor required for light signaling in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1433</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1445</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casal</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Shade avoidance</article-title>. <source>The Arabidopsis Book</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e0157</fpage>, <comment>doi/10.1199/tab.0157</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crocco</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Botto</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>AtBBX21 and COP1 genetically interact in the regulation of shade avoidance</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>562</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A genomic analysis of the shade avoidance response in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>1617</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1629</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagatani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome B in the mesophyll delays flowering by suppressing FLOWERING LOCUS T expression in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> vascular bundles</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1941</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1952</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>RSF1, an Arabidopsis locus implicated in phytochrome A signaling</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>45</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fittinghoff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Laubinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nixdorf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fackendahl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgardt</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Batschauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoecker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Functional and expression analysis of Arabidopsis <italic>SPA</italic> genes during seedling photomorphogenesis and adult growth</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>577</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>590</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Shade avoidance</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>179</volume>: <fpage>930</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>944</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Spartz</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Breen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome-interacting factor 4 (PIF4) regulates auxin biosynthesis at high temperature</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>20231</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20235</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome functions in Arabidopsis development</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galstyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cifuentes-Esquivel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bou-Torrent</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Garcia</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The shade avoidance syndrome in Arabidopsis: a fundamental role for atypical basic helix-loop-helix proteins as transcriptional cofactors</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>267</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gendreau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Traas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Desnos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandjean</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Caboche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x00F6;fte</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Cellular basis of hypocotyl growth in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>305</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Estelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>High temperature promotes auxin-mediated hypocotyl elongation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>7197</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7202</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hornitschek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohnen</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorrain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rougemont</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x00F3;pez-Vidriero</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco-Zorrilla</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Trevisan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pradervand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome interacting factors 4 and 5 control seedling growth in changing light conditions by directly controlling auxin signaling</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>699</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>711</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hornitschek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorrain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoete</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Michielin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of the shade avoidance response by formation of non-DNA binding bHLH heterodimers</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>3893</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3902</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Panigrahi</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenkel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soppe</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><name><surname>Valverde</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis COP1 shapes the temporal pattern of CO accumulation conferring a photoperiodic flowering response</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1277</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1288</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jimenez-Gomez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Maloof</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Network analysis identifies <italic>ELF3</italic> as a QTL for the shade avoidance response in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1001100</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keuskamp</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Voesenek</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Auxin transport through PIN-FORMED 3 (PIN3) controls shade avoidance and fitness during competition</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>22740</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>22744</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Regulation of CONSTANS and FLOWERING LOCUS T expression in response to changing light quality</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>269</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>279</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Horiguchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Demura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsukaya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagatani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Involvement of auxin and brassinosteroid in the regulation of petiole elongation under the shade</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>153</volume>: <fpage>1608</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1618</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The photomorphogenic repressors COP1 and DET1: 20 years later</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>584</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>593</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laubinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fittinghoff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoecker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The SPA quartet: a family of WD-repeat proteins with a central role in suppression of photomorphogenesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>2293</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2306</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laubinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoecker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The SPA1-like proteins SPA3 and SPA4 repress photomorphogenesis in the light</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>385</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laubinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Gourrierec</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenkel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Adrian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulajta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoecker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis SPA proteins regulate photoperiodic flowering and interact with the floral inducer CONSTANS to regulate its stability</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>3213</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3222</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leivar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Monte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Castillon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Multiple phytochrome-interacting bHLH transcription factors repress premature seedling photomorphogenesis in darkness</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1815</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1823</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leivar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>PIFs: pivotal components in a cellular signaling hub</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>28</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leivar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tepperman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Monte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Sady</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Dynamic antagonism between phytochromes and PIF family basic helix-loop-helix factors induces selective reciprocal responses to light and shade in a rapidly responsive transcriptional network in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1398</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1419</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruneda-Paz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowing-Zitron</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivans</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedmale</surname><given-names>UV</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Linking photoreceptor excitation to changes in plant architecture</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>785</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>790</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>COP1-mediated ubiquitination of CONSTANS is implicated in cryptochrome regulation of flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>292</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>306</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>408</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorrain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Duek</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitelam</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fankhauser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome-mediated inhibition of shade avoidance involves degradation of growth-promoting bHLH transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>312</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>323</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNellis</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>von Arnim</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Komeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mis&#x00E9;ra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X-W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Genetic and molecular analysis of an allelic series of <italic>cop1</italic> mutants suggests functional roles for the multiple protein domains</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>487</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>500</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nixdorf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoecker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>SPA1 and DET1 act together to control photomorphogenesis throughout plant development</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>231</volume>: <fpage>825</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>833</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osterlund</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Targeted destabilization of HY5 during light-regulated development of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>405</volume>: <fpage>462</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>466</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis HY5</italic> gene encodes a bZIP protein that regulates stimulus-induced development of root and hypocotyl</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>2983</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2995</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranjan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiene</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fackendahl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoecker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis repressor of light signaling SPA1 acts in the phloem to regulate seedling de-etiolation, leaf expansion and flowering time</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>1851</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1862</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rizzardi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Landberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sund&#x00E5;s-Larsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>TFL2/LHP1 is involved in auxin biosynthesis through positive regulation of YUCCA genes</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>897</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>906</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roig-Villanova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez-Garc&#x00ED;a</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Identification of primary target genes of phytochrome signaling: early transcriptional control during shade avoidance responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>141</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>96</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roig-Villanova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bou-Torrent</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Galstyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carretero-Paulet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Portol&#x00E9;s</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x00ED;guez-Concepci&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez-Garc&#x00ED;a</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Interaction of shade avoidance and auxin responses: a role for two novel atypical bHLH proteins</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>4756</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4767</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruberti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciolfi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Possenti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carabelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Plant adaptation to dynamically changing environment: the shade avoidance response</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Adv</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1047</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1058</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruckle</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgoon</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinkler</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Plastids are major regulators of light signaling in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>366</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>390</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruckle</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>DeMarco</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Plastid signals remodel light signaling networks and are essential for efficient chloroplast biogenesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>3944</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3960</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salisbury</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grierson</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Phytochrome coordinates Arabidopsis shoot and root development</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>438</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasidharan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinnappa</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Staal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elzenga</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishitani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Voesenek</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Light quality-mediated petiole elongation in Arabidopsis during shade avoidance involves cell wall modification by xyloglucan endotransglucosylase/hydrolases</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>154</volume>: <fpage>978</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>990</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The HAT4 gene of Arabidopsis encodes a developmental regulator</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>379</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sellaro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Casal</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Repression of shade-avoidance reactions by sunfleck induction of HY5 expression in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>919</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>928</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sessa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Carabelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciolfi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Possenti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittempergher</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Morelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruberti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A dynamic balance between gene activation and repression regulates the shade avoidance response in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2811</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2815</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Antagonistic but complementary actions of phytochromes A and B allow seedling de-etiolation</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>637</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>641</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Salla-Martret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bou-Torrent</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Roig-Villanova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez-Garc&#x00ED;a</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>ATHB4, a regulator of shade avoidance, modulates hormone response in Arabidopsis seedlings</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>266</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>277</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stavang</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallego-Bartolom&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x00F3;mez</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Asami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x00ED;a-Mart&#x00ED;nez</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Alabad&#x00ED;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bl&#x00E1;zquez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Hormonal regulation of temperature-induced growth in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>601</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steindler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Matteucci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Weimar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohgishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Morelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruberti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Shade avoidance responses are mediated by the ATHB-2 HD-zip protein, a negative regulator of gene expression</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>4235</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4245</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> YUCCA1 flavin monooxygenase functions in the indole-3-pyruvic acid branch of auxin biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3961</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3973</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pojer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivans</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Rapid synthesis of auxin via a new tryptophan-dependent pathway is required for shade avoidance in plants</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>164</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>176</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ulmasov</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Murfett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Guilfoyle</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Aux/IAA proteins repress expression of reporter genes containing natural and highly active synthetic auxin response elements</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1963</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1971</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wollenberg</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerd&#x00E1;n</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Acceleration of flowering during shade avoidance in Arabidopsis alters the balance between FLOWERING LOCUS C-mediated repression and photoperiodic induction of flowering</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>1681</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1694</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Won</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Mashiguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasahara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Conversion of tryptophan to indole-3-acetic acid by TRYPTOPHAN AMINOTRANSFERASES OF ARABIDOPSIS and YUCCAs in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>18518</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18523</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoecker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year><comment>a</comment>) <article-title>Repression of light signaling by Arabidopsis SPA1 involves post-translational regulation of HFR1 protein accumulation</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>141</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoecker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year><comment>b</comment>) <article-title>Light regulates COP1-mediated degradation of HFR1, a transcription factor essential for light signaling in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>804</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>821</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Irigoyen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>COP1 and ELF3 control circadian function and photoperiodic flowering by regulating GI stability</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>617</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>630</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Laubinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saijo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoecker</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Biochemical characterization of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> complexes containing CONSTITUTIVELY PHOTOMORPHOGENIC1 and SUPPRESSOR OF PHYA proteins in light control of plant development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2307</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2323</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
