<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">214544</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.214544</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>SIGNALING AND RESPONSE</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Lipoxygenase6-Dependent Oxylipin Synthesis in Roots Is Required for Abiotic and Biotic Stress Resistance of Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[C]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[W]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grebner</surname><given-names>Wiebke</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stingl</surname><given-names>Nadja E.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oenel</surname><given-names>Ayla</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>Martin J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>Susanne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Department of Pharmaceutical Biology, Julius-von-Sachs-Institute for Biosciences, Biocenter, University of Wuerzburg, 97082 Wuerzburg, Germany</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the Graduiertenkolleg 1342 and the Sonderforschungsbereich 567.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>berger@biozentrum.uni-wuerzburg.de</email>.</corresp><fn id="afn1"><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Susanne Berger (<email>berger@biozentrum.uni-wuerzburg.de</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[C]</label><p>Some figures in this article are displayed in color online but in black and white in the print edition.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.113.214544">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.113.214544</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>4</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>02</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>161</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2159</fpage><lpage>2170</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>01</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>02</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2013 American Society of Plant Biologists. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="PP_214544_ic1.gif"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><italic>A defect in lipoxygenase6 abolishes production of jasmonates in roots and renders plants more susceptible to drought and crustacean feeding.</italic></p></abstract><abstract><p>Jasmonates are oxylipin signals that play important roles in the development of fertile flowers and in defense against pathogens and herbivores in leaves. The aim of this work was to understand the synthesis and function of jasmonates in roots. Grafting experiments with a jasmonate-deficient mutant demonstrated that roots produce jasmonates independently of leaves, despite low expression of biosynthetic enzymes. Levels of 12-oxo-phytodienoic acid, jasmonic acid, and its isoleucine derivative increased in roots upon osmotic and drought stress. Wounding resulted in a decrease of preformed 12-oxo-phytodienoic acid concomitant with an increase of jasmonic acid and jasmonoyl-isoleucine. 13-Lipoxygenases catalyze the first step of lipid oxidation leading to jasmonate production. Analysis of 13-lipoxygenase-deficient mutant lines showed that only one of the four 13-lipoxygenases, LOX6, is responsible and essential for stress-induced jasmonate accumulation in roots. In addition, LOX6 was required for production of basal 12-oxo-phytodienoic acid in leaves and roots. Loss-of-function mutants of LOX6 were more attractive to a detritivorous crustacean and more sensitive to drought, indicating that LOX6-derived oxylipins are important for the responses to abiotic and biotic factors.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">OPDA</term><def id="def1"><p>12-oxo-phytodienoic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">JA</term><def id="def2"><p>jasmonic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">LOX</term><def id="def3"><p>lipoxygenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">13-HPOTE</term><def id="def4"><p>13(<italic>S</italic>)-hydroperoxyoctadecatrienoic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">JA-Ile</term><def id="def5"><p>jasmonoyl-Ile</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">HOTE</term><def id="def6"><p>hydroxyoctadecatrienoic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">MS</term><def id="def7"><p>mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8">UPLC</term><def id="def8"><p>ultra-high-performance liquid chromatograph</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9">LC</term><def id="def9"><p>liquid chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term10">ESI</term><def id="def10"><p>electrospray interface</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term11">Col-0</term><def id="def11"><p>Columbia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term12">RT</term><def id="def12"><p>reverse transcription</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>Oxylipins are ubiquitous signaling molecules that are derived from polyunsaturated fatty acids by enzymatic and nonenzymatic processes. In plants, the biosynthesis and function of oxylipins of the jasmonate family in aboveground tissues has been investigated in detail. Jasmonates comprise 12-oxo-phytodienoic acid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>), jasmonic acid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>), and derivatives of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>. In leaves, jasmonates accumulate in response to abiotic factors such as wounding, drought, osmotic stress, darkness, and ozone and during interactions with organisms such as herbivores, pathogens, and mutualistic organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Wasternack, 2007</xref>). The relevance of jasmonates in wound response, ozone tolerance, and the defense against herbivores and necrotrophic pathogens in leaves has been well investigated using mutants in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> biosynthesis and signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Browse, 2009a</xref>). In addition, jasmonates play an important role in flower development, and Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) mutants in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> pathway are male sterile (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Browse, 2009b</xref>). The first step in jasmonate biosynthesis is catalyzed by 13-lipoxygenases (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref>). The resulting 13(<italic>S</italic>)-hydroperoxyoctadecatrienoic acid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">13-HPOTE</xref>) is converted by allene oxide synthase (AOS) and allene oxide cyclase to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Wasternack, 2007</xref>). These enzymatic steps are located in plastids. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> is transported to peroxisomes and converted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> can be further metabolized to different derivatives that take place mainly in the cytosol. The conjugation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> with Ile is an important step because jasmonoyl-Ile (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref>) has been identified as a biologically active jasmonate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Staswick and Tiryaki, 2004</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> is also biologically active without conversion to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> derivatives. In contrast to all other jasmonates, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> structure contains an electrophilic &#x03B1;,&#x03B2;-unsaturated carbonyl group that renders <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> more reactive than <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>. Therefore, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> is classified as a reactive electrophile species with unique signaling properties different from other jasmonates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Farmer and Davoine, 2007</xref>).</p><p>Of the six lipoxygenase genes present in Arabidopsis, four genes encode 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref>. For the respective enzymes LOX2, LOX3, LOX4, and LOX6, it was shown that linolenic acid is the preferred substrate and that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">13-HPOTE</xref> is formed in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bannenberg et al., 2009</xref>). All four enzymes are proposed to be located in plastids. LOX2 is highly expressed in leaves; expression is up-regulated by jasmonates and stress treatments such as wounding and osmotic stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bell and Mullet, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Seltmann et al., 2010a</xref>). LOX2 was shown to contribute the majority of jasmonate synthesis upon wounding and osmotic stress and during senescence in leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bell et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Glauser et al., 2009</xref>). LOX2 is also responsible for the accumulation of arabidopsides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Glauser et al., 2009</xref>), which are galactolipids containing esterified <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> in plastids by direct oxidation of galactolipids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Zoeller et al., 2012</xref>). LOX3 and LOX4 are required for the development of fertile flowers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Caldelari et al., 2011</xref>). LOX6 shows overall low expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bannenberg et al., 2009</xref>). Recently, it was reported that LOX6 contributes to the fast accumulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> in wounded leaves and is required for the fast increase of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> in distal leaves after wounding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chauvin et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p>In contrast to leaves and flowers, little is known on jasmonate biosynthesis and function in roots. Expression of the plastid-localized enzymes of jasmonate synthesis LOX2, AOS, and allene oxide cyclase2 is very low in roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Zimmermann et al., 2004</xref>). By contrast, enzymes such as 9-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> and &#x03B1;-dioxygenase1 are strongly expressed in roots. These enzymes are involved in the biosynthesis of oxylipins different from jasmonates, and 9-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> products have been shown to regulate lateral root development because mutants in LOX1 and LOX5 produce more lateral roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Vellosillo et al., 2007</xref>). However, jasmonate function in roots is still obscure. Here, we analyzed jasmonate accumulation in roots upon different stress treatments and show that mutants defective in LOX6 are impaired in stress-induced jasmonate synthesis and are more susceptible to drought and detritivore feeding.</p><sec id="s1" sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2"><title>Oxylipin Profiles in Roots and Shoots</title><p>The plastid localization and low expression in roots of several enzymes of the first steps of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> biosynthesis prompted us to investigate whether the oxylipin profile mirrors the expression of oxylipin biosynthetic enzymes. To enable gentle recovery of root material, plants were grown in a hydroponic system. In this system, plant parts below the hypocotyl were cultivated in darkness. Levels of hydroxyoctadecatrienoic acids (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HOTEs</xref>) and jasmonates in leaves and roots were analyzed. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels were around 1 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight both in roots and shoots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). 9-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HOTE</xref> and 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HOTE</xref> can be synthesized nonenzymatically as well as enzymatically via 9-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> and 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref>, respectively. In agreement with published data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Grun et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Triantaphylid&#x00E8;s et al., 2008</xref>), 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HOTE</xref> (0.28 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight) constituted the highest amount of free <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HOTEs</xref> in leaves followed by 9-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HOTE</xref> (0.16 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight). The high amount of 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HOTE</xref> is in accordance with the high expression of 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> in leaves. In roots, levels of 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HOTE</xref> and 9-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">HOTE</xref> were similar (0.67 and 0.64 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight, respectively) and higher compared with leaves. Amounts of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> (0.8 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight) were in roots only slightly lower than in the shoot (1 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight), indicating that roots contain 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> products and especially jasmonates, despite the low expression of <italic>LOX2</italic> and <italic>AOS</italic>. Basal levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> were very low and at the detection limit in roots and leaves. In addition to free jasmonates, levels of arabidopsides were also analyzed. The presence of arabidopsides in leaves has been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Stelmach et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Hisamatsu et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Kourtchenko et al., 2007</xref>). In roots, levels of all arabidopsides were below the detection limit (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Oxylipin levels in roots and leaves. Roots and shoots of 6-week-old hydroponically grown plants were harvested, and free <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref>, and hydroxy fatty acids were determined. Data represent the mean of at least three biological replicates &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc>. The experiment has been repeated with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_214544_f1"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Synthesis of Jasmonates Is Induced upon Wounding in Roots</title><p>Leaves respond to wounding with an accumulation of arabidopsides, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Buseman et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Koo et al., 2009</xref>). Therefore, we tested if levels of these oxylipins also increase in roots. To avoid exchange of signals between shoots and roots, both parts of the plant were separated and wounded, and oxylipin levels in leaves and roots were determined after incubation of 30 min, 2 h, and 24 h. As expected from published data, in leaves, all oxylipins accumulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). Levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> increased from 1 to 8 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight and remained high. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> increased from the limit of detection to around 11 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight at 0.5 and 2 h and dropped to 1 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight at 24 h. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> showed the most transient kinetic with a maximum of 2.7 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight at 30 min. In roots, levels of arabidopsides were also below or slightly above the detection limit after wounding (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). The course of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> accumulation in roots was similar to leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> levels increased at 30 min to 5 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight and started to decline, with 4 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight at 2 h. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> accumulated to 1.7 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight at 30 min and declined to 0.6 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight at 2 h. Interestingly, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels decreased from 0.8 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight to 0.3 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight at 30 min and showed a further decrease at later time points. This might be due to conversion of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> present in the root to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref>. This raises the question if the roots are able to produce <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> on their own or if <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> is synthesized in plastids in the shoot and transported into the root, where it is further metabolized to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> upon stress stimuli.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Oxylipin accumulation in roots and leaves in response to wounding. Roots and shoots were separated, wounded, and harvested after 30 min, 2 h, and 24 h after wounding. Zero hours indicate untreated plant material. Data represent the mean of at least three biological replicates &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc>. The experiment has been repeated with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_214544_f2"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Roots Synthesize <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> Independent from the Shoot</title><p>To test the possibility of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> import from the shoot into the root, grafting experiments with the mutant <italic>delayed dehiscence2</italic> (<italic>dde2</italic>) were performed. This mutant is deficient in expression of <italic>AOS</italic> and therefore does not produce <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref>. Both grafting combinations with the wild type and <italic>dde2</italic> were performed, and for control experiments, wild-type shoot was grafted on wild-type root.</p><p>Grafting was done at seedling stage, and plants were grown for an additional 7 weeks before wounding experiments were performed. The 30-min time point was chosen for analysis because strongest changes were seen at this time point (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). Basal and wound-induced oxylipin levels in the control grafts were similar to nongrafted wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). In the first combination, <italic>dde2</italic> shoot was grafted on ecotype Columbia (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref>) rootstock. As expected, in the <italic>dde2</italic> mutant leaves, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> were barely detectable both under basal and wound-induced conditions, while the wild-type roots contained normal basal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels, indicating that this organ produces <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> without the need for a shoot with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>-biosynthetic competence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). After wounding of roots, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> increased similarly as in nongrafted plants. In the second combination, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> shoot was grafted on <italic>dde2</italic> rootstock. As expected, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> levels strongly increased in leaves upon wound treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). All three oxylipins were at the detection limit in <italic>dde2</italic> roots before and after wounding. This indicates that there is no significant transport of oxylipins from the shoot to the root.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Oxylipin accumulation in partially jasmonate-deficient plants. Levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> in shoots and roots of <italic>dde2</italic> shoot grafted on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> rootstock (left) and of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> shoot grafted on <italic>dde2</italic> rootstock (middle) basal and 30 min after wounding. Control grafts were performed with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> shoots on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> roots (right). Black bars indicate nonwounded; gray bars indicate wounded. Data represent the mean of at least three biological replicates &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc>. The experiment has been repeated with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_214544_f3"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s5"><title>LOX6 Is Required for Maintaining Basal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> Levels in Shoots and Roots</title><p>To investigate the contribution of the different 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> on oxylipin production in roots, expression of the four 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> and oxylipin levels in the single mutants <italic>lox2</italic> and <italic>lox6</italic> as well as in the <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic> double mutant defective in the expression of the redundant <italic>LOX3</italic> and <italic>LOX4</italic> were determined in roots and leaves of nontreated plants and 30 min after wounding.</p><p>In wild-type leaves and roots, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> is the major jasmonate under basal conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). The <italic>lox2</italic> and <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic> mutant lines displayed similar or even elevated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels (<italic>lox2</italic>, 1.3 and 1 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight; <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic>, 4 and 5.2 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight in roots and leaves, respectively), while <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels in the <italic>lox6</italic> mutant were at the detection limit under basal conditions both in leaves and roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). A second independent <italic>lox6</italic> mutant showed similar effects (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). Hence, LOX6 appears to be essential for maintaining basal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels in both organs. In roots, this is consistent with the expression profile because <italic>LOX6</italic> exhibited the highest basal transcript level among the four <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). In leaves, this result was rather unexpected because <italic>LOX6</italic> showed only low expression, while <italic>LOX2</italic> is strongly expressed. In all <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> mutants, levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> were as low as in the wild type.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Involvement of 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> in the wound response in roots and leaves. Roots and shoots were separated, wounded, and harvested after 30 min (gray bars). As control, untreated plant samples were analyzed (black bars). A, Transcript levels of <italic>LOX2</italic>, <italic>LOX3</italic>, <italic>LOX4</italic>, and <italic>LOX6</italic> were determined by quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">RT</xref>-PCR. B, Levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> were determined in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> and different <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> mutants. Data represent the mean of at least three biological replicates &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc>. Stars indicate significant differences of the level in the mutant compared with the corresponding wild-type sample (&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). The experiment has been repeated with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_214544_f4"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s6"><title>LOX6 Is Essential for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> Signal Production in Response to Wounding in Roots</title><p>Because <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> is a precursor of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref>, deficiency in basal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> accumulation in the <italic>lox6</italic> mutant might affect stress-induced accumulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref>. In wild-type roots, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels drop after wounding, while <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> transiently accumulate. This suggests that preformed and de novo-formed <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> is rapidly converted to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref>. In wounded roots of the <italic>lox6</italic> mutant, levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> were dramatically lower than in the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). This indicates that LOX6 is not only essential for basal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> but also for wound-induced accumulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> in roots. Although LOX3 and LOX4 are more highly expressed in wounded roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>), these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> appear not to be involved in root jasmonate production because wound-induced levels of all three jasmonates are not lower in <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic> roots compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Also, jasmonate amounts in <italic>lox2</italic> roots were similar or slightly higher than in wild-type roots.</p><p>Unlike roots, leaves of the <italic>lox6</italic> mutant exhibited a strong increase of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> after wounding. However, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> level was significantly lower in wounded <italic>lox6</italic> leaves, suggesting that LOX6 is involved in, but not essential for, wound-induced accumulation of jasmonates in leaves. In the <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic> mutant, wound-induced levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> in leaves were similar to the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>) despite a strong up-regulation of both genes by wounding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> accumulated to lower levels in leaves of the <italic>lox2</italic> mutant upon wounding. The effect on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels was even more dramatic because <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> did not increase in <italic>lox2</italic> leaves upon wounding but showed a clear decrease (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). This is in agreement with LOX2 being a major contributor to wound-induced oxylipin production in leaves.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>LOX6 Is Involved in Oxylipin Formation in Roots in Response to Osmotic and Drought Stress</title><p>Jasmonates also accumulate in leaves in response to stresses such as osmotic stress and drought (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Creelman and Mullet, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Seltmann et al., 2010b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">de Ollas et al., 2013</xref>). Therefore, we investigated if LOX6 also contributes to oxylipin synthesis in response to these stress factors. Roots of intact plants grown in the hydroponic system were incubated in 500 m<sc>m</sc> sorbitol, and oxylipin accumulation was analyzed after 24 h.</p><p>In wild-type roots, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels increased about 3.6-fold after sorbitol treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). Also, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> levels were clearly elevated. The increase in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> in <italic>lox2</italic> roots was similar to the wild type, while the rise in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> was lower. Upon osmotic stress, roots of <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic> showed wild-type levels of all jasmonates. In line with the results on wound stress, <italic>lox6</italic> roots exhibited strong differences in oxylipin production compared with the wild type. <italic>lox6</italic> roots did not accumulate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> after sorbitol treatment. This indicates that LOX6 is also required for oxylipin accumulation in roots in response to osmotic stress.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Osmotic stress-induced oxylipin accumulation in roots and shoots of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> and different <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> mutants. Levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> were determined 24 h after replacing the medium with 500 m<sc>m</sc> sorbitol (gray bars). Medium of control plants was replaced with water. Data represent the mean of at least three biological replicates &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc>. Stars indicate significant differences of the level in the mutant compared with the corresponding wild-type sample (&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). The experiment has been repeated with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_214544_f5"></graphic></fig><p>In leaves of the wild type, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels rose about 3-fold (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> strongly accumulated, with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> especially showing a dramatic increase up to 52 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight. No clear elevation of these oxylipins was detected in <italic>lox2</italic> leaves, consistent with a major role of LOX2 in the response of leaves to osmotic stress. In leaves of <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic>, all oxylipins rose, but to a smaller extend than in the wild type. No differences were obvious in the levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, while <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> levels were even slightly higher in leaves of the <italic>lox6</italic> mutant after osmotic stress treatment compared with the wild type.</p><p>To investigate the contribution of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> to drought stress, the liquid medium was removed from plants grown in the hydroponic system, and roots were exposed to air. In leaves, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> levels were at the detection limit, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> levels remained below 0.1 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight after 48-h drought treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). Similarly, no strong increase in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels was detectable. By contrast, roots responded with an accumulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>. Compared with osmotic stress, increases were moderate, reaching about 7 and 0.3 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, respectively. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> levels were at the detection limit but nevertheless tended to rise (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>). Also, in <italic>lox2</italic> and <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic> mutants, levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> increased. By contrast, in <italic>lox6</italic> plants, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> were basal and, after drought treatment, below the detection limit. This suggests that LOX6 is also responsible for drought-induced accumulation of jasmonates in roots.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Drought-induced oxylipin accumulation in roots and shoots of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> and different <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> mutants. Levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> were determined in untreated plant samples (black bars) and 48 h after removing the liquid medium from the roots (gray bars). Data represent the mean of at least three biological replicates &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc>. Stars indicate significant differences of the level in the mutant compared with the corresponding wild-type sample (&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). The experiment has been repeated with similar results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_214544_f6"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Defect in LOX6 Expression Results in Increased Sensitivity to Drought</title><p>Drought stress eventually results in wilting and death of the plant. To assess whether the lack of LOX6 leads to altered tolerance to water limitation, plants were grown in soil, and at the age of 4 weeks, watering was stopped. Wilting symptoms were documented, plants were rewatered, and the survival rate was determined. The <italic>lox6</italic> mutant showed earlier wilting symptoms compared with the wild type. Enhanced sensitivity of <italic>lox6</italic> to water limitation was supported by a lower survival rate of plants after rewatering (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, A and B</xref>). Only 14% of <italic>lox6</italic> plants, compared with 78% of wild-type plants, survived the treatment. The altered drought tolerance might be due to lower levels of jasmonates or other 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> products. To distinguish between these possibilities, <italic>dde2</italic> plants were tested in addition to the <italic>lox6</italic> mutant. Interestingly, <italic>dde2</italic> plants did not show the wilting and survival phenotype of <italic>lox6</italic> but were similar to wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, A and B</xref>). This indicates that mechanisms other than lack of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> and derivatives of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> are responsible for enhanced drought sensitivity of <italic>lox6</italic>.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Wilting phenotype of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref>, <italic>lox6</italic>, and <italic>dde2</italic>. Drought-stressed plants were rewatered, pictures were taken 2 d after rewatering (A), and the surviving plants were scored (B). Data represent the percentage of surviving plants relative to total plants and are the mean of at least three biological replicates &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc>. The experiment has been repeated with similar results. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_214544_f7"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Defect in LOX6 Expression Renders Roots More Attractive to Detritivores</title><p>Jasmonates are important signals in defense responses against herbivores and detritivores. In particular, it was shown that freshly detached leaves of <italic>dde2</italic> plants are consumed by woodlice (<italic>Porcellio scaber</italic>), which usually prefer dead tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Farmer and Dubugnon, 2009</xref>). Woodlice are soil-living organisms that are in frequent contact with plant roots. Therefore, this organism provides a suitable bioassay to test whether the lower levels of jasmonates in roots of <italic>lox6</italic> result in fewer defenses against detritivores and render them more attractive as potential food. Leaves and roots of hydroponically grown plants were provided to rough woodlice that were starved for 2 d prior to the experiment. Pictures were taken at different time points. No clear differences were detectable in the consumption of leaves of <italic>lox6</italic> and wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>). However, in agreement with published data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Farmer and Dubugnon, 2009</xref>), <italic>dde2</italic> leaves were consumed faster than wild-type leaves (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4B</ext-link>), confirming that jasmonate deficiency of leaves results in enhanced attractiveness. Compared with leaves, roots were eaten considerably slower. Roots of <italic>lox6</italic> plants were consumed more rapidly than roots of wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>). After 8 d, 5% of the original root material was left in <italic>lox6</italic> compared with 36% in the wild type, respectively. This indicates that, consistent with the result of wound and osmotic stress, LOX6 is important to restrain crustacean feeding in roots but not in leaves. Roots of <italic>dde2</italic> plants were also preferred over wild-type roots (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4A</ext-link>), suggesting that jasmonates are responsible for the root defense against woodlice.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Feeding of woodlice on roots of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> and <italic>lox6</italic>. Roots (A) and leaves (B) of wild-type and <italic>lox6</italic> plants were provided to woodlice, and pictures were taken at 0 h and after 4 d (leaves) and 8 d (roots). The area of roots (C) and leaves (D) was quantified at the beginning of the experiment and at the time points indicated. Data represent the area relative to the original area. The experiment has been repeated with similar results. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_214544_f8"></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s10" sec-type="discussion|conclusions"><title>DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION</title><sec id="s11"><title>Differential Impact of 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> on Oxylipins Biosynthesis in Roots and Leaves</title><p>In this work, the accumulation of jasmonates in leaves and roots after different stress treatments was compared, and the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> isoform involved in root jasmonate synthesis was identified. Roots accumulated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> in response to wounding, osmotic stress, and, to a lesser extent, drought. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels increased upon osmotic stress and drought but decreased upon wounding. Roots synthesize jasmonates independently of the shoot despite the low expression of several <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>-biosynthetic enzymes in Arabidopsis roots. This was concluded from wounding experiments with grafted <italic>dde2</italic> mutant and wild-type plants. LOX6 was identified as the main enzyme involved in the production of jasmonates in roots constitutively and upon wound, osmotic, and drought stress. The effects were very clear, and none of the mutations in the other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> genes showed a strong effect on jasmonate production in roots, although LOX3 and LOX4 are expressed in roots and show induction by wounding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). This indicates that LOX2, LOX3, and LOX4 cannot substitute a loss of function of LOX6 in roots, even though all four <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> have been shown to catalyze the formation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">13-HPOTE</xref> from linolenate in vitro.</p><p>Wounding of leaves or osmotic stress applied to roots resulted in accumulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> in leaves, which is in agreement with published data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Koo et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Zoeller et al., 2012</xref>). In leaves, the strongest effects on jasmonate levels were observed in <italic>lox2</italic> mutants in which wound- and sorbitol-induced jasmonate accumulation was significantly lower compared with the wild type. This correlates with the very high expression of <italic>LOX2</italic> in leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Zimmermann et al., 2004</xref>) and indicates that LOX2 is the main enzyme responsible for jasmonate accumulation in leaves after both stresses. LOX2 is involved in the accumulation of the bulk of free jasmonates after wounding and osmotic stress and during senescence, but not after pathogen attack (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bell et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Glauser et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Seltmann et al., 2010b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Zoeller et al., 2012</xref>). Lower <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> accumulation, compared with wild-type leaves, was also detectable in <italic>lox6</italic> mutant leaves after wounding and in <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic> mutant leaves after osmotic stress. This suggests that LOX3, LOX4, and LOX6 contribute to stress-induced <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> biosynthesis in leaves and that the contribution depends on the specific stress condition. This is in agreement with a recent report that all 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> contribute to the increase of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> in wounded leaves at a very early time point (190 s; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chauvin et al., 2013</xref>). Unexpectedly, we found that synthesis of basal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> was completely prevented in the <italic>lox6</italic> mutant. This indicates that LOX6 is important for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> formation in leaves, although basal expression of <italic>LOX6</italic> is very low (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Zimmermann et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Vellosillo et al., 2007</xref>). Because LOX2 is highly expressed constitutively in leaves but cannot ensure basal production of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, oxylipin biosynthesis is regulated on other levels than transcription of biosynthetic genes.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>How Is the Stress-Induced Synthesis of Jasmonates Regulated?</title><p>As discussed above, expression of 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> did not always correlate with accumulation of jasmonates. In addition, changes of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> were not necessarily concomitant with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>. For instance, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> levels increased in <italic>lox6</italic> leaves despite very low basal levels of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, and vice versa, increase of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> was reduced in the <italic>lox2</italic> mutant even though basal levels of the precursor <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> were available. Different mechanisms might account for these phenomena. Firstly, enzymatic activity might be regulated posttranslationally. The requirement for regulation of the activity of enzymes that are already present is also obvious from the very fast accumulation of jasmonates upon wounding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Glauser et al., 2009</xref>). Regarding the regulation mechanism of LOX2, it was reported that the ion channel FATTY ACID OXYGENATION UPREGULATED2 (FOU2) regulates activity of LOX2 in response to wounding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bonaventure et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Beyhl et al., 2009</xref>). Secondly, different <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOXs</xref> may generate separate pools of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">13-HPOTE</xref> with different metabolic fates. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">13-HPOTE</xref> might be used for partially competing metabolic routes eventually leading to the accumulation of arabidopsides, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, and its metabolites, or channeled into other oxylipin pathways such as the hydroperoxy lyase or peroxygenase pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Feussner and Wasternack, 2002</xref>). For example in roots, only LOX6 products are channeled into the jasmonate pathway, while LOX3 and LOX4 products might be metabolized to oxylipins other than jasmonates and serve other functions. Thirdly, the conversion of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> might be regulated. In roots, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels decrease in response to wounding concomitant with an increase in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>. This suggests that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> constitutively present in roots is used for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> synthesis. This is in accordance with a lack of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> accumulation in roots of <italic>lox6</italic> mutants, where the basal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> level is at the detection limit. However, the decrease in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> (less than 0.7 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight at 30 min) is not sufficient to account for the increase in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> (more than 3 nmol g<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> dry weight; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref>), suggesting that de novo synthesis of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> is necessary. Changes in oxylipin levels similar to the changes in wounded roots have been demonstrated in unwounded, distal leaves of wounded plants. Also in this system, accumulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref> in distal leaves correlated with a decrease in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Koo et al., 2009</xref>). This indicates that the regulated step of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> production in both scenarios is the conversion from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>. In Arabidopsis, OPDA reductase3 (OPR3) is the first enzyme of this pathway catalyzing the reduction of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref>. OPR3 activity has been discussed to be regulated posttranslationally by homodimerization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Breithaupt et al., 2006</xref>). In wounded roots as well as distal leaves of wounded plants, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> is present and OPR3 is expressed, which is consistent with a regulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref> production by affecting OPR3 activity on a posttranslational level. In the case of osmotic and drought stress, the process of jasmonate production seems to be regulated by different mechanisms, because here <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> levels increase to similar (osmotic) or even higher (drought) levels than <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>. It has to be taken into account that in contrast to the early time point measured after wounding, oxylipin levels were detected after 24 h of sorbitol or 48 h after drought treatment, respectively. Therefore, timing, oxylipin profiles, and regulation of oxylipin synthesis of the responses to these different stresses are obviously different.</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Function of Oxylipins in Roots</title><p>There are several indications for a role of oxylipins in root responses to biotic and abiotic factors. Accumulation of jasmonates has been observed in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> in the mutualistic interactions with soil-borne microorganisms. Using allene oxide cyclase-RNA interference approaches, it was demonstrated that jasmonate synthesis is important for the development of arbuscular mycorrhizal symbiosis but not for nodule formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Isayenkov et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Zdyb et al., 2011</xref>). In addition, it was shown that jasmonate synthesis is important for defense in Arabidopsis and maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) against <italic>Pythium</italic> species, which are soil-borne oomycetes. The fatty acid desaturase mutant <italic>fad3</italic>/<italic>fad7</italic>/<italic>fad8</italic> and <italic>jasmonate resistant1</italic> mutant (<italic>jar1</italic>) in Arabidopsis and an <italic>opr7</italic>/<italic>opr8</italic> double mutant in maize are more susceptible to <italic>Pythium</italic> spp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Staswick et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Vijayan et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Yan et al., 2012</xref>). The <italic>jar1</italic> mutant also develops more disease symptoms after challenge with <italic>Phytophthora parasitica</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Attard et al., 2010</xref>). Furthermore, altering the expression of <italic>LOX3</italic> in maize renders plants more susceptible to root knot nematodes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Gao et al., 2008</xref>). Even though it was not explicitly shown that jasmonate production in the root is relevant, the fact that these organisms originated from soil and that in the experiments the microorganisms/nematodes were applied to roots suggests that root-derived jasmonates are important in these interactions.</p><p>The identification of LOX6 as the one <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> responsible for stress-induced oxylipin accumulation in roots enabled the investigation of the function of oxylipins specifically in roots using the <italic>lox6</italic> mutant. The experiments show that oxylipins in roots are involved in detritivore defense and drought tolerance. Detritivorous crustaceans feed faster on roots of <italic>lox6</italic> and <italic>dde2</italic> mutant plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>) and on leaves of <italic>dde2</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Farmer and Dubugnon, 2009</xref>). The fact that <italic>lox6</italic> and <italic>dde2</italic> mutations have similar effects indicates that jasmonates are responsible for deterring crustacean feeding in the wild type. Restraining detritivore attack might be even more important in roots than in leaves because roots are more accessible to this soil organism. The molecular basis of lower attractiveness of wild-type roots compared with <italic>dde2</italic> and <italic>lox6</italic> roots is not clear. For leaves of different plant species, it was demonstrated that jasmonates are important for induction of secondary metabolism and expression of defense proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Howe et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Reymond et al., 2000</xref>; for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Browse and Howe, 2008</xref>). Comparison of the metabolite profile of wild-type and <italic>lox6</italic> roots will contribute to an understanding of the mechanisms involved.</p><p>In contrast to animal feeding, drought tolerance was impaired in <italic>lox6</italic> but not in <italic>dde2</italic>. This suggests that oxylipins different from jasmonates are important for drought tolerance. The product of 13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">13-HPOTE</xref> can be converted to a variety of oxylipins, such as ketones, aldehydes, epoxides, hydroxides, and divinyl ethers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Feussner and Wasternack, 2002</xref>). Several of these compounds have been shown to be biologically active, for instance, in regulating root growth and gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Vellosillo et al., 2007</xref>). It will be interesting to elucidate which, and how, products of LOX6 regulate drought tolerance. Possibilities are the formation of a long-distance signal in the root that signals water limitation to the leaves. The involvement of oxylipins in root-to-shoot communication has also been suggested in response to wounding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hasegawa et al., 2011</xref>). Alternatively, LOX6-derived products might directly play a role in regulating stomatal opening. Oxylipins such as coronatine, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, and its methyl ester are discussed to regulate stomatal closure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Suhita et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Melotto et al., 2006</xref>). Interestingly, LOX6 has been described to be expressed in guard cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Leonhardt et al., 2004</xref>), which points to a role in stoma function. It is a challenge for the future to identify the oxylipins and mechanisms responsible for the impact of LOX6 on drought tolerance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s14" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s15"><title>Plant Material</title><p>Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) wild-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref>, <italic>dde2</italic>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> mutant lines <italic>lox2</italic>, <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic>, and <italic>lox6</italic> were used. The <italic>lox2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Glauser et al., 2009</xref>), <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic>, and both <italic>lox6</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Caldelari et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Chauvin et al., 2013</xref>) were kindly provided by E.E. Farmer. The <italic>lox6</italic> mutant analyzed throughout the manuscript corresponds to the line SALK_138907. Absence of <italic>LOX6</italic> expression is shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Figure S5</ext-link>. The <italic>lox6</italic> line used in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Figure S2</ext-link> corresponds to SALK_083650. The identity of both <italic>lox6</italic> mutants was confirmed by PCR analysis using primers suggested by the iSect tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://signal.salk.edu/tdnaprimers.2.html">http://signal.salk.edu/tdnaprimers.2.html</ext-link>). The <italic>dde2-2</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">von Malek et al., 2002</xref>) was kindly provided by B. Keller. For the <italic>dde2</italic> and <italic>lox3</italic>/<italic>lox4</italic> mutant, the male-sterile phenotype was monitored.</p><p>For investigations, plants were grown in soil at 22&#x00B0;C under a 9-h photoperiod (100 &#x00B5;mol photons m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>) in a climate chamber or hydroponically in a plant cabinet.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Hydroponic Cultivation</title><p>The hydroponic system was set up according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Tocquin et al. (2003)</xref>. Seeds were surface sterilized and sown on 0.5-mL microtubes filled with the standard nutrient solution described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Tocquin et al. (2003)</xref> with 1% (w/v) Phyto Agar (Duchefa) and cultivated in a sterile box that was placed in a plant cabinet for 14 d at 20&#x00B0;C under a 9-h photoperiod (80 &#x00B5;mol photons m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>). For further cultivation, 2 mm of the microtube bottom was removed, and the tube was placed in a sterile 50-mL Falcon tube containing sterile liquid standard nutrient solution. To avoid the exposure of roots to light, the Falcons were placed in a light-tight box (internal dimensions, 152 &#x00D7; 104 &#x00D7; 102 mm) with the microtube placed through a hole in the lid of the box. The boxes, each containing 11 plants, were cultivated for another 4 weeks at 20&#x00B0;C under a 9-h photoperiod (80 &#x00B5;mol photons m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>) in a plant cabinet. One week before harvest, the standard nutrient solution was refilled.</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Grafting of Arabidopsis Plants</title><p>Arabidopsis <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> wild-type and <italic>dde2</italic> plants were grafted using 7-d-old seedlings based on a micrografting technique described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Turnbull et al. (2002)</xref>. Briefly, surface-sterilized seeds were sown in petri dishes on Murashige and Skoog medium containing 1.5% (w/v) Suc. Seeds were stratified for 2 d at 4&#x00B0;C in the dark, and then petri dishes with seeds were transferred to a growth cabinet with 24&#x00B0;C and constant light (40 &#x00B5;mol photons m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>) and placed in a vertical orientation. After 5 d, light intensity was reduced to 25 &#x00B5;mol photons m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>. For grafting, seedlings were placed under a binocular and cut at the hypocotyl with a razor blade. Shoots and roots were placed in intimate contact on new petri dishes with Murashige and Skoog medium containing 0.5% (w/v) Suc. After 7 d of growing on vertically oriented plates in a growth cabinet at 24&#x00B0;C under constant light (25 &#x00B5;mol photons m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>), all successful grafted plants were transferred to petri dishes with Murashige and Skoog medium containing no Suc and grown for another 14 d at 20&#x00B0;C under a 9-h photoperiod (80 &#x00B5;mol photons m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>) in a plant cabinet. All surviving plants were then transferred to the hydroponic system and cultivated until they were 8 weeks old.</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Wounding and Sorbitol Treatment of Plants</title><p>For wounding experiments 6 to 8 weeks old, hydroponically cultivated plants were used. First, the plants were cut above and below the microtubes, in which they had been sown for germination, to obtain the separated shoot and root. The part of the hypocotyl was removed. The shoots were squeezed with a forceps once across every leaf blade, and the roots were squeezed five times along its full length. Wounded shoots were incubated in the light and roots in the dark until shock freezing in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x2013;80&#x00B0;C for further analysis. Each replicate consisted of shoots/roots of at least three to four plants.</p><p>For sorbitol treatment, the standard liquid media of 6-week-old hydroponically cultivated plants were replaced by 0.5 <sc>m</sc> sorbitol solution or water (control). After 24-h incubation, the roots were washed with water, and shoots and roots were harvested as described above, shock frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at &#x2013;80&#x00B0;C for further analysis. Each replicate consisted of shoots/roots of at least three to four plants.</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>RNA Isolation and Quantitative Reverse Transcription (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">RT</xref>)-PCR</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from ground plant material using TriFast reagent (PEQLAB) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s protocol. RNA concentration was determined spectrophotometrically. Remaining DNA was removed using RNase-Free DNase I (Fermentas) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s protocol. First-strand complementary DNA and real-time PCR were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Szyroki et al., 2001</xref>) using SYBR-Green Capillary Mix (ThermoFisher Scientific) and a CFX 96 Real-Time System C1000 Thermal Cycler (Bio-Rad). Primers used (TIB MOLBIOL) were as follows: LOX2 (At3G45140): forward, 5&#x2032;-GCCATTGAGTTGACTTGTCC-3&#x2032;, reverse, 5&#x2032;-CACTTAGTTGTCTATTTGCCGC-3&#x2032;; LOX3 (At1g17420): forward, 5&#x2032;-TCCCTGCCGATCTAA-3&#x2032;, reverse, 5&#x2032;-GTTTGGGACGTAGCCA-3&#x2032;; LOX4 (At1g72520): forward, 5&#x2032;-GCTTGCTTAGATACGACACT-3&#x2032;, reverse, 5&#x2032;-ATG TGGTCTTCCGTGAGAGC-3&#x2032;; and LOX6 (At1g67560): forward, 5&#x2032;-AAGACTGTTACTGCGGTTG-3&#x2032;, reverse, 5&#x2032;-GGCTGTGAATACGAGGTATC-3&#x2032;.</p><p>The number of transcripts was normalized to AtSAND (At2g28390) complementary DNA fragments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Czechowski et al., 2005</xref>) amplified by AtSANDfwd (5&#x2032;-AACTCTATGCAGCATT-3&#x2032;) and AtSANDrev (5&#x2032;-GGTGGTACTAGCACAA-3&#x2032;) primers.</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Analysis of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">JA-Ile</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> in Arabidopsis</title><p>For analysis of oxylipins, fresh (shock-frozen) plant material was ground by mortar and pestle and afterward freeze dried. For shoots and roots, 25 and 18 mg of freeze-dried material, respectively, were extracted with 950 &#x00B5;L of ethyl acetate/formic acid (99:1, v/v). Dihydrojasmonic acid (50 ng), <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">JA</xref>-nor-Val (50 ng), and [<sup>18</sup>O<sub>2</sub>]<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">OPDA</xref> (50 ng) were added as internal standards. Extraction samples were homogenized with a ball mill for 3 min at 20 Hz. After centrifugation, the supernatant was dried in a vacuum concentrator, and the extraction step was repeated with 1 mL ethyl acetate/formic acid (99:1, v/v). After evaporation of the ethyl acetate, samples were dissolved in 40 &#x00B5;L acetonitrile/water (50:50, v/v) for liquid chromatography (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">LC</xref>)-tandem mass spectrometry (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref>/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref>) analysis.</p><p>Ultra-high-performance <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">LC</xref>/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref>/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> analyses were performed on a Waters Quattro Premier XE triple-quadrupole mass spectrometer with an electrospray interface (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ESI</xref>) coupled to a Waters Acquity ultra-high-performance liquid chromatograph (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">UPLC</xref>). Chromatographic separations were carried out using an Acquity <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">UPLC</xref> BEH C18 column (2.1 &#x00D7; 50 mm, 1.7-&#x00B5;m particle size with a BEH C18 guard column equipped with a prefilter) with the following solvent system: solvent A = 0.1% (v/v) formic acid in water, solvent B = acetonitrile. A gradient elution was performed at a flow rate of 0.25 mL min<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> at 40&#x00B0;C: 97% solvent A, followed by 0% solvent A in 7 min.</p><p>The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ESI</xref> source was operated in negative ionization mode with a capillary voltage of 3.0 kV at 120&#x00B0;C. Quantification was performed using multiple reaction monitoring with a scan time of 0.025 s per transition (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). Cone voltage and collision energy was set at 20 eV, and the desolvation temperature was 400&#x00B0;C. Nitrogen was used as the desolvation and cone gas, with a flow rate of 800 and 50 L h<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>, respectively. Argon was used as the collision gas at a pressure of approximately 3.10 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2013;3</sup> bar.</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Analysis of Free Hydroxy Fatty Acids</title><p>Analysis of free hydroxy fatty acids was performed similarly as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Zoeller et al. (2012)</xref>. Briefly, fresh (shock-frozen) plant material was ground by mortar and pestle and afterward freeze dried. For shoots and roots, 25 and 18 mg of freeze-dried material, respectively, were extracted with 800 &#x00B5;L isopropanol containing 0.5 mg triphenylphosphane and 0.75 mg butylated hydroxytoluene. After 20-min reduction, 15-hydroxy-eicosadienoic acid (150 ng) was added as internal standard. Samples were sonicated for 5 min and centrifuged. The supernatant was recovered, and the residue was further extracted with 1.5 mL chloroform/isopropanol (1:2, v/v) and 1.5 mL chloroform/methanol (2:1, v/v). After each extraction, samples were centrifuged, and the supernatants were combined. The combined lipid extract was dried under a stream of nitrogen at 60&#x00B0;C and reconstituted in 40 &#x00B5;L 1 m<sc>m</sc> ammonium acetate in water/acetonitrile (1:2, v/v) for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">LC</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref>/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> analysis.</p><p>Ultra-high-performance <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">LC</xref>/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref>/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> analyses were performed on a Waters Quattro Premier XE triple-quadrupole mass spectrometer with an <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ESI</xref> coupled to an Acquity <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">UPLC</xref>. Chromatographic separations were carried out using an Acquity <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">UPLC</xref> BEH C18 column (2.1 &#x00D7; 50 mm, 1.7-&#x00B5;m particle size with a BEH C18 guard column equipped with a prefilter) with the following solvent system: solvent A = 1 m<sc>m</sc> aqueous ammonium acetate, solvent B = acetonitrile. A gradient elution was performed at a flow rate of 0.25 mL min<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> at 40&#x00B0;C: 65% solvent A, followed by 30% solvent A in 6 min.</p><p>The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">ESI</xref> source was operated in negative ionization mode at a capillary voltage of 3.0 kV at 120&#x00B0;C. Quantification was performed using multiple reaction monitoring with a scan time of 0.025 s per transition (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). Cone voltage and collision energy was set at 20 eV, and desolvation temperature was 350&#x00B0;C. Nitrogen was used as the desolvation and cone gas, with a flow rate of 800 and 50 L h<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>, respectively. Argon was used as the collision gas at a pressure of approximately 3.10 &#x00D7; 10<sup>&#x2013;3</sup> bar.</p></sec><sec id="s22"><title>Detritivore Feeding</title><p>The detritivore rough woodlouse (<italic>Porcellio scaber</italic>) was collected and cultivated as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Farmer and Dubugnon (2009)</xref>. For the feeding assay, detached leaves and roots of 6-week-old hydroponically cultivated plants were used. Approximately 15 isopods were fed with the detached plant organs. For quantification, digital pictures were taken, including a 5-cm<sup>2</sup>-size marker. The area of leaves and roots was calculated with Photoshop 7 (Adobe).</p></sec><sec id="s23"><title>Drought Resistance Experiments</title><p>To investigate drought tolerance, 4-week-old plants grown in 30 mL soil (Einheitserde P, Klasmann-Deilmann, Geeste; pot dimensions: 5-cm height, 7-cm diameter at the top, 4.5-cm diameter at the bottom) at 22&#x00B0;C under a 9-h photoperiod (100 &#x00B5;mol photons m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>) in a climate chamber were watered for 16 h. The remaining water was removed, and the plants were grown for 25 d without watering. When all plants showed wilting symptoms, plants were rewatered, and the survival rate was calculated after 2 d.</p><p>For oxylipin analysis, the liquid medium of 6-week-old hydroponically grown plants was removed, and the plants were further cultivated at 20&#x00B0;C under a 9-h photoperiod (80 &#x00B5;mol photons m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup>) in a plant cabinet. After 48-h incubation, the shoots and roots were harvested, shock frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at &#x2013;80&#x00B0;C.</p></sec><sec id="s24"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>For statistical analysis of differences between the wild type and several mutants, one-way ANOVAs (Fisher&#x2019;s least significant difference test) were performed with SPSS statistics software (IBM).</p><p>In addition to the analyses performed by quantitative PCR, information on gene regulation was obtained using the Web site <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genevestigator.ethz.ch">www.genevestigator.ethz.ch</ext-link> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Zimmermann et al., 2004</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s25"><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> Basal and wound-induced arabidopside levels in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> roots and shoots.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> Involvement of LOX6 in the wound response in roots and leaves.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S3.</bold></ext-link> Drought-induced oxylipin accumulation in roots of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> and different <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S4.</bold></ext-link> Feeding of woodlice on <italic>dde2</italic> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S5.</bold></ext-link> Transcript levels of <italic>LOX6</italic> in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">Col-0</xref> and the <italic>lox6</italic> mutant plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.214544/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S1.</bold></ext-link> Mass-to-charge proportions of parent and daughter ions from analyzed molecules.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank E.E. Farmer for his help in setting up the woodlice system and providing <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LOX</xref> mutants.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gourgues</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Callemeyn-Torre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The immediate activation of defense responses in Arabidopsis roots is not sufficient to prevent <italic>Phytophthora parasitica</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>187</volume>: <fpage>449</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>460</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bannenberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Diversity of the enzymatic activity in the lipoxygenase gene family of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Lipids</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>95</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Creelman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullet</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>A chloroplast lipoxygenase is required for wound-induced jasmonic acid accumulation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>8675</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8679</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullet</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Characterization of an Arabidopsis lipoxygenase gene responsive to methyl jasmonate and wounding</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>1133</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1137</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beyhl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x00F6;rtensteiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinoia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fromm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marten</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedrich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The fou2 mutation in the major vacuolar cation channel TPC1 confers tolerance to inhibitory luminal calcium</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>715</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>723</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonaventure</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gfeller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Proebsting</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x00F6;rtensteiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ch&#x00E9;telat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinoia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A gain-of-function allele of TPC1 activates oxylipin biogenesis after leaf wounding in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>889</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>898</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breithaupt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurzbauer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Strassner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Macheroux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Clausen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Crystal structure of 12-oxophytodienoate reductase 3 from tomato: self-inhibition by dimerization</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>14337</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14342</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year><comment>a</comment>) <article-title>The power of mutants for investigating jasmonate biosynthesis and signaling</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>1539</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1546</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year><comment>b</comment>) <article-title>Jasmonate passes muster: a receptor and targets for the defense hormone</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>205</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>New weapons and a rapid response against insect attack</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>146</volume>: <fpage>832</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>838</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buseman</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baughman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maatta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Esch</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Wounding stimulates the accumulation of glycerolipids containing oxophytodienoic acid and dinor-oxophytodienoic acid in Arabidopsis leaves</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>39</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caldelari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis lox3 lox4 double mutants are male sterile and defective in global proliferative arrest</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>33</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chauvin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldelari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfender</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Four 13-lipoxygenases contribute to rapid jasmonate synthesis in wounded Arabidopsis thaliana leaves: a role for lipoxygenase 6 in responses to long-distance wound signals</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>197</volume>: <fpage>566</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>575</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Creelman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullet</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Jasmonic acid distribution and action in plants: regulation during development and response to biotic and abiotic stress</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>4114</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4119</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Czechowski</surname><given-names>TSM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide identification and testing of superior reference genes for transcript normalization in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Ollas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernando</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbona</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x00F3;mez-Cadenas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Jasmonic acid transient accumulation is needed for abscisic acid increase in citrus roots under drought stress conditions</article-title>. <source>Physiol Plant</source> <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>296</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>306</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Davoine</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Reactive electrophile species</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>380</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>386</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubugnon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Detritivorous crustaceans become herbivores on jasmonate-deficient plants</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>940</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feussner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasternack</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The lipoxygenase pathway</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>297</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x00F6;bel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelberth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Feussner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumlinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolomiets</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Maize 9-lipoxygenase ZmLOX3 controls development, root-specific expression of defense genes, and resistance to root-knot nematodes</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>98</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>109</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glauser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubugnon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mousavi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfender</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Velocity estimates for signal propagation leading to systemic jasmonic acid accumulation in wounded Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>284</volume>: <fpage>34506</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>34513</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Early accumulation of non-enzymatically synthesized oxylipins in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> after infection with <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic></article-title>. <source>Funct Plant Biol</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>71</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sogabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Asano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Gene expression analysis of wounding-induced root-to-shoot communication in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>705</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>716</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hisamatsu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekiguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigemori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Oxylipins arabidopsides C and D from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>J Nat Prod</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>600</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>603</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lightner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>An octadecanoid pathway mutant (JL5) of tomato is compromised in signaling for defense against insect attack</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>2067</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2077</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isayenkov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mrosk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenzel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hause</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Suppression of allene oxide cyclase in hairy roots of <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic> reduces jasmonate levels and the degree of mycorrhization with <italic>Glomus intraradices</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1401</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1410</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A rapid wound signal activates the systemic synthesis of bioactive jasmonates in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>974</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>986</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kourtchenko</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunnstr&#x00F6;m</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x00F6;bel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McPhail</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerwick</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Feussner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellerstr&#x00F6;m</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Oxo-phytodienoic acid-containing galactolipids in Arabidopsis: jasmonate signaling dependence</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>1658</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1669</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leonhardt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Waner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonhardt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Microarray expression analyses of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> guard cells and isolation of a recessive abscisic acid hypersensitive protein phosphatase 2C mutant</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>596</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>615</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melotto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Underwood</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Koczan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Plant stomata function in innate immunity against bacterial invasion</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>969</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>980</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reymond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Damond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Differential gene expression in response to mechanical wounding and insect feeding in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>707</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>720</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seltmann</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussels</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year><comment>a</comment>) <article-title>Jasmonates during senescence: signals or products of metabolism?</article-title> <source>Plant Signal Behav</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1493</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1496</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seltmann</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stingl</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lautenschlaeger</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Krischke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year><comment>b</comment>) <article-title>Differential impact of lipoxygenase 2 and jasmonates on natural and stress-induced senescence in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>152</volume>: <fpage>1940</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1950</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staswick</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiryaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The oxylipin signal jasmonic acid is activated by an enzyme that conjugates it to isoleucine in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>2117</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2127</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staswick</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Jasmonate signaling mutants of Arabidopsis are susceptible to the soil fungus <italic>Pythium irregulare</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>747</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>754</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stelmach</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennig</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert-Zsilavecz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiler</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A novel class of oxylipins, sn1-O-(12-oxophytodienoyl)-sn2-O-(hexadecatrienoyl)-monogalactosyl Diglyceride, from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>276</volume>: <fpage>12832</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12838</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suhita</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghavendra</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vavasseur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Cytoplasmic alkalization precedes reactive oxygen species production during methyl jasmonate- and abscisic acid-induced stomatal closure</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>1536</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1545</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szyroki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivashikina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelfsema</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ache</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Reintanz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Deeken</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Godde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Felle</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinmeyer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>KAT1 is not essential for stomatal opening</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>2917</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2921</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tocquin</surname><given-names>PCL</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbesier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Havelange</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieltain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurtem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x00E9;rilleux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A novel high efficiency, low maintenance, hydroponic system for synchronous growth and flowering of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>2</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Triantaphylid&#x00E8;s</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Krischke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoeberichts</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ksas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gresser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Havaux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Breusegem</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Singlet oxygen is the major reactive oxygen species involved in photooxidative damage to plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>960</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>968</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Booker</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Micrografting techniques for testing long-distance signalling in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>262</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vellosillo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x00F3;pez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Casc&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Castresana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Oxylipins produced by the 9-lipoxygenase pathway in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> regulate lateral root development and defense responses through a specific signaling cascade</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>831</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>846</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijayan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shockey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x00E9;vesque</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A role for jasmonate in pathogen defense of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>7209</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7214</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Malek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Graaff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneitz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis male-sterile mutant <italic>dde2-2</italic> is defective in the ALLENE OXIDE SYNTHASE gene encoding one of the key enzymes of the jasmonic acid biosynthesis pathway</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>216</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>192</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wasternack</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Jasmonates: an update on biosynthesis, signal transduction and action in plant stress response, growth and development</article-title>. <source>Ann Bot (Lond)</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>681</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>697</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Isakeit</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelberth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meeley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolomiets</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Disruption of OPR7 and OPR8 reveals the versatile functions of jasmonic acid in maize development and defense</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1420</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1436</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zdyb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Demchenko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heumann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mrosk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grzeganek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x00F6;bel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Feussner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pawlowski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hause</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Jasmonate biosynthesis in legume and actinorhizal nodules</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>189</volume>: <fpage>568</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>579</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch-Hoffmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruissem</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>GENEVESTIGATOR. Arabidopsis microarray database and analysis toolbox</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>2621</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2632</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zoeller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stingl</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Krischke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fekete</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Lipid profiling of the Arabidopsis hypersensitive response reveals specific lipid peroxidation and fragmentation processes: biogenesis of pimelic and azelaic acid</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>160</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>378</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
