<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">225144</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.225144</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject><subj-group><subject>GENES, DEVELOPMENT, AND EVOLUTION</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular Mechanism of microRNA396 Mediating Pistil Development in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Gang</given-names></name><ext-link ext-link-type="orcid" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0622-4043"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Hua</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yang</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Fang</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Diqiu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Key Laboratory of Tropical Forest Ecology, Xishuangbanna Tropical Botanical Garden, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, Yunnan 650223, China (G.L., H.H., Y.L., F.W., D.Y.); and</aff><aff id="aff2">University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, China (H.H., Y.L.)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the Natural Science Foundation of China (31100186), the West Light Foundation of the Chinese Academy of Sciences, and the Chinese Academy of Sciences 135 program (XTBG&#x2013;F04).</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Address correspondence to <email>ydq@xtbg.ac.cn</email>.</corresp><fn id="afn1"><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Diqiu Yu (<email>ydq@xtbg.ac.cn</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.113.225144">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.113.225144</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>01</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>164</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>07</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x00A9; 2014 American Society of Plant Biologists. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri content-type="alt-lang-pdf zh" xlink:href="249.chinese.pdf"/><self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="PP_225144_ic1.gif"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><italic>miR396 affects pistil development by suppressing its target genes and cotranscription complex</italic>.</p></abstract><abstract><p>The precise control of gene regulation, and hence, correct spatiotemporal tissue patterning, is crucial for plant development. Plant microRNAs can constrain the expression of their target genes at posttranscriptional levels. Recently, microRNA396 (miR396) has been characterized to regulate leaf development by mediating cleavage of its <italic>GROWTH-REGULATING FACTOR</italic> (<italic>GRF</italic>) targets. miR396 is also preferentially expressed in flowers. However, its function in flower development is unclear. In addition to narrow leaves, pistils with a single carpel were also observed in miR396 overexpression plants. The dramatically reduced expression levels of miR396 targets (<italic>GRF1</italic>, <italic>GRF2</italic>, <italic>GRF3</italic>, <italic>GRF4</italic>, <italic>GRF7</italic>, <italic>GRF8</italic>, and <italic>GRF9</italic>) caused pistil abnormalities, because the miR396-resistant version of <italic>GRF</italic> was able to rescue miR396-overexpressing plants. Both <italic>GRF</italic> and <italic>GRF-INTERACTING FACTOR</italic> (<italic>GIF</italic>) genes are highly expressed in developing pistils, and their expression patterns are negatively correlated with that of miR396. GRF interacted with GIF to form the GRF/GIF complex in plant cell nucleus. miR396 suppressed the expression of <italic>GRF</italic> genes, resulting in reduction of GRF/GIF complex. <italic>gif</italic> single mutant displayed normal pistils, whereas <italic>gif</italic> triple mutant <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> produced abnormal pistils, which was a phenocopy of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>/<italic>grf5</italic> plants. GRF and GIF function as cotranscription factors, and both are required for pistil development. Our analyses reveal an important role for miR396 in controlling carpel number and pistil development via regulation of the GRF/GIF complex.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">miRNA</term><def id="def1"><p>microRNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">qRT</term><def id="def2"><p>quantitative reverse transcription</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">BiFC</term><def id="def3"><p>bimolecular fluorescence complementation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">cDNA</term><def id="def4"><p>complementary DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">OD600</term><def id="def5"><p>optical density at 600 nm</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>The precise spatial and temporal expression of regulatory genes that control tissue patterning and cell fate is important for plant development. Misexpression of certain key regulatory genes causes developmental abnormalities in plants. There is increasing evidence that small RNA molecules are important participants in the control of gene expression, providing sequence specificity for targeted regulation of key developmental factors at the posttranscriptional level. MicroRNAs (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>s) are 21- to 24-nucleotide noncoding RNAs that negatively regulate gene expression by pairing with their target mRNAs. They are produced from primary <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>s that are transcribed from MIRNA genes. After the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref> duplexes are released from the nucleus, mature <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>s are recruited into an RNA-induced silencing complex associated with ARGONAUTE (AGO) proteins, where they suppress target mRNAs by complementary matching for cleavage and/or translational repression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Reinhart et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Carrington and Ambros, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bartel, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brodersen et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Lanet et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>Several plant <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>s have been shown to function in plant development. The lack of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref> processing protein(s) can cause severe developmental phenotypes. For example, the weaker <italic>dicer-like1</italic> (<italic>dcl1</italic>) alleles produce various aberrant morphological phenotypes, including extra whorls of stamens, an indefinite number of carpels, female sterility, altered ovule development, and reduced plant height, indicating that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref> metabolism is essential for normal plant development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Schauer et al., 2002</xref>). <italic>ago1</italic> null mutants exhibit morphological defects similar to those of <italic>dcl1</italic>, <italic>hua enhancer1</italic>, and <italic>hyponastic leaves1</italic> (<italic>hyl1</italic>) mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Vaucheret et al., 2004</xref>). The specific functions of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>s in floral development have been characterized. For example, Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) microRNA160a (miR160a) mutant produced floral organs in carpels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Liu et al., 2010</xref>). Overexpression of miR164 led to flowers with fused sepals, which resembled the flowers of its target mutants, <italic>cuc1cuc2</italic> (for <italic>cup-shaped cotyledon1cup-shapedcotyledon2</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Mallory et al., 2004</xref>). Enhanced expression of the miR164-resistant version of <italic>mCUC1</italic> resulted in flowers with more petals than those of the wild type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Baker et al., 2005</xref>). Plants ectopically expressing miR166 showed extreme fasciation of the inflorescence meristem and a reduced or filamentous gynoecium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Kim et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Williams et al., 2005</xref>). Constitutive expression of miR159 or miR167, which led to reduced expressions of their target genes (<italic>MYB33</italic> and <italic>MYB65</italic>; <italic>Auxin Responsive Factor6</italic> [<italic>ARF6</italic>] and <italic>ARF8</italic>), caused male sterility in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Achard et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Millar and Gubler, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Ru et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Wu et al., 2006</xref>). Elevated miR172 accumulation resulted in floral organ identity defects similar to those in its target gene mutant (<italic>apetala2</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Aukerman and Sakai, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Chen, 2004</xref>).</p><p><italic>GROWTH-REGULATING FACTOR</italic> (<italic>GRF</italic>) genes are a class of plant-specific transcription regulators. In Arabidopsis, there are nine <italic>GRF</italic> genes that can be divided into five subfamilies: group I (<italic>GRF1</italic> and <italic>GRF2</italic>), group II (<italic>GRF3</italic> and <italic>GRF4</italic>), group III (<italic>GRF5</italic> and <italic>GRF6</italic>), group IV (<italic>GRF7</italic> and <italic>GRF8</italic>), and group V (<italic>GRF9</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Kim et al., 2003</xref>). Among them, <italic>GRF1</italic>, <italic>GRF2</italic>, <italic>GRF3</italic>, <italic>GRF4</italic>, <italic>GRF7</italic>, <italic>GRF8</italic>, and <italic>GRF9</italic> are the direct targets of miR396 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Jones-Rhoades and Bartel, 2004</xref>). It has been revealed that miR396 is involved in leaf development by controlling the levels of its <italic>GRF</italic> targets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Liu et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Yang et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Rodriguez et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Wang et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Debernardi et al., 2012</xref>). A GRF protein consists of two regions, the QLQ and WRC domains. The QLQ domain is responsible for protein interaction, while the WRC domain comprises a functional nuclear localization signal and a zinc-finger motif that functions in DNA binding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Kim et al., 2003</xref>). <italic>GRF</italic> genes are involved in regulating leaf growth and morphology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Kim et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Horiguchi et al., 2005</xref>). The GRF-INTERACTING FACTOR1 (GIF1) protein was identified to interact with GRF1 as a transcription coactivator to regulate leaf development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kim and Kende, 2004</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Horiguchi et al. (2005)</xref> revealed that both GRF5 and GRF9 interact with GIF1 to regulate leaf development. GIF1 contains two domains: the SNH and QG domains. The SNH domain is responsible for the interaction with the QLQ domain of GRF. The <italic>GIF</italic> gene family has three members, <italic>GIF1</italic>, <italic>GIF2</italic>, and <italic>GIF3</italic>, which have overlapping functions in determining organ (leaf and petal) size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kim and Kende, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Lee et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>Another group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Hewezi et al., 2012</xref>) revealed the functions of miR396 in reprogramming root cells during infection by a parasitic cyst nematode. Here, we demonstrate that the products of all seven <italic>GRF</italic> targets can interact with GIFs that may function as cotranscription factors. Overexpression of miR396 caused reduced expressions of <italic>GRF</italic> genes, which disrupted the formation of the GRF/GIF complex, leading to pistil anomalies. These results indicate that miR396-directed regulation is critical for pistil development.</p><sec id="s1" sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2"><title>Overexpression of miR396 Resulted in Aberrant Pistils</title><p>Two <italic>MIR396</italic> gene-encoding loci (<italic>MIR396a</italic> and <italic>MIR396b</italic>) have been identified in Arabidopsis. They are processed into two types of mature miR396s with only one nucleotide difference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Jones-Rhoades and Bartel, 2004</xref>). In our previous research, we found that miR396 was ubiquitously expressed in seedlings, roots, leaves, siliques, and inflorescences and that constitutive expression of miR396 caused narrow leaves by targeting <italic>GRF</italic> genes in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Liu et al., 2009</xref>). Further investigation found that miR396-overexpressing plants produced flowers with various deformations. Wild-type flowers often contain four sepals, four petals, six stamens, and two fused carpels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). In miR396-overexpressing plants, approximately 70% of flowers contained aberrant pistils, such as extremely bent pistils, unfused carpels, and single carpels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, B&#x2013;D</xref>). The aberrant pistils formed into short siliques (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1E</xref>). The single-carpel siliques contained only one column of seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1F</xref>), which accounted for approximately 65% of all siliques (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1G</xref>). The abnormal siliques resulted in lower fertility compared with that of the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1H</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Phenotypes of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants. A, Wild-type flower. B to D, Bent pistil (B), unfused carpels (C), and single-carpel pistil (D) in the flowers of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants. E, First 20 siliques in wild-type and <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants. The white asterisk indicates the single-carpel siliques. F, Siliques at stage 15 (left) and mature siliques (right). G, Percentage of siliques containing single carpel or two carpel. H, Percentage of siliques with the indicated number of seeds. Three individuals for each genotype were used for silique analysis. Thirty siliques for each individual were analyzed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_225144_f1"></graphic></fig><p>Given the fact that increased levels of miR396 led to aberrant pistils, we asked what would happen when miR396 expression was repressed. To suppress the functions of both miR396a and miR396b, we used the Short Tandem Target Mimic (STTM) strategy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Yan et al., 2012</xref>) to construct <italic>STTM396</italic>-transgenic plants. Northern-blotting analysis indicated that miR396 was moderately decreased in the flowers of <italic>STTM396</italic> plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1A</ext-link>). However, the pistils and siliques of <italic>STTM396</italic> plants were normal (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1B</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>miR396 Suppressed Expression of <italic>GRF</italic> Genes in Floral Organs</title><p>In Arabidopsis, there are nine <italic>GRF</italic> genes, seven of which are predicted to be targeted by miR396. The cleavage of six <italic>GRF</italic> genes (<italic>GRF1</italic>, <italic>GRF2</italic>, <italic>GRF3</italic>, <italic>GRF7</italic>, <italic>GRF8</italic>, and <italic>GRF9</italic>) has been validated experimentally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Jones-Rhoades and Bartel, 2004</xref>). We confirmed the cleavage of <italic>GRF4</italic> in the predicted miR396 recognition site by 5&#x2032; RACE experiments (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2A</ext-link>).</p><p>We compared the transcript levels of <italic>GRF</italic> genes in flowers among the wild type, <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>, and <italic>STTM396</italic> plants; the level of miR396 was negatively correlated with those of its <italic>GRF</italic> targets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Unexpectedly, two nontargeted <italic>GRF</italic> genes were affected differently by miR396. Like the other targeted <italic>GRF</italic> genes, the level of <italic>GRF6</italic> transcripts was negatively correlated with that of miR396. By contrast, the transcript level of <italic>GRF5</italic> was not influenced by miR396. The levels of <italic>GRF</italic> transcripts and miR396 were further examined in different floral organs of the wild type. The lowest level of miR396 and the highest levels of <italic>GRF</italic> transcripts were in the pistil (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Considering the high frequency of altered pistils in miR396-overexpressing plants, we investigated the levels of <italic>GRF</italic> transcripts and miR396 in the pistils of flowers at three different developmental stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>). There were relatively high transcript levels of <italic>GRF</italic> genes at stages 10 and 13, but low levels at stage 15. By contrast, the transcript levels of both <italic>MIR396</italic>a and <italic>MIR396b</italic> were relatively low at stages 10 and 13, but high at stage 15. Taken together, these results indicated that miR396 may constrain the expression of <italic>GRF</italic> genes.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Regulation of <italic>GRF</italic> genes by miR396. A, Transcript levels of <italic>GRF</italic> genes in flowers. B, Transcript levels of <italic>MIR396</italic> and <italic>GRF</italic> genes in sepal, petal, stamen, and pistil at floral stage 13. C, Transcript levels of <italic>MIR396</italic> and <italic>GRF</italic> genes in pistil at the indicated floral stages. D, Coexpression of various combinations of <italic>MIRNA</italic> and <italic>GRF</italic> expression constructs in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic>. A to D, Error bars represent <sc>se</sc> for three independent experiments. The values marked by an asterisk are significantly different from the control values (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <italic>n</italic> = 3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_225144_f2"></graphic></fig><p>To confirm the direct regulation of <italic>GRF</italic> genes by miR396 in planta, we performed transient coexpression assays in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>. We generated two types of constructs for both <italic>GRF7</italic> and <italic>GRF9</italic>, the miR396-sensitive constructs <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF7</italic> and <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF9</italic> and the miR396-resistant constructs <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mGRF7</italic> and <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mGRF9</italic>. The miR396-resistant version of <italic>mGRF</italic> contained three silent mutations within the miR396-complementary domain of the <italic>GRF</italic> genomic clone, thereby increasing the number of mismatches between miR396 and <italic>mGRF</italic> without altering the amino acid sequence of the encoded GRF protein (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2B</ext-link>). After 3 d of coexpression in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic>, RNA was extracted and the transcript abundances of <italic>GRF7</italic> and <italic>GRF9</italic> were analyzed by real-time quantitative reverse transcription (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>)-PCR. The mRNA levels of miR396-resistant <italic>mGRF7</italic> or <italic>mGRF9</italic> were not affected by coexpression with MIR396a. However, mRNA levels of the miR396-sensitive <italic>GRF7</italic> and <italic>GRF9</italic> were significantly decreased when coexpressed with MIR396a (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2D</xref>). These findings suggested that miR396 directly mediates the cleavage of <italic>GRF</italic> genes in planta.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>miR396-Resistant <italic>mGRF7</italic> or <italic>mGRF9</italic> Rescued miR396 Transgenic Plants</title><p>Analyses of the expression patterns of <italic>GRF</italic> genes showed that all nine <italic>GRF</italic> genes are expressed in roots, upper stems, and shoot tips containing the shoot apical meristem and flower buds, as well as in mature flowers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Kim et al., 2003</xref>). Because <italic>GRF</italic> genes are suppressed by miR396, we expected that <italic>GRF</italic> mutants could phenocopy miR396-overexpressing plants. We obtained six <italic>GRF</italic> single mutants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3A</ext-link>), <italic>grf1</italic>, <italic>grf3</italic>, <italic>grf4</italic>, <italic>grf7</italic>, <italic>grf8</italic>, and <italic>grf9</italic>, all of which produced normal siliques (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3B</ext-link>). The <italic>grf1grf2grf3</italic> triple mutants (ecotype Wassilewskija background; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Kim et al., 2003</xref>) have small leaves, but normal floral organs and fertility. The leaves of the <italic>grf7</italic> single mutant were reported to be smaller than those of the wild type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Kim et al., 2012</xref>), implying that group IV <italic>GRF</italic> genes may play a dominant role. Therefore, we constructed a <italic>grf7grf8</italic> double mutant and a <italic>grf7grf8grf9</italic> triple mutant. These mutants produced normal siliques (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3B</ext-link>). In flowers of miR396-overexpressing plants, all <italic>GRF</italic> genes except for <italic>GRF5</italic> were down-regulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). We could not investigate the individual functions of the <italic>GRF</italic> genes because of the 8-fold redundancy and their overlapping expression patterns. It was also very difficult to obtain an octuple mutant for the eight down-regulated <italic>GRF</italic> genes because of their close linkages on chromosomes.</p><p>To investigate whether reduced expressions of <italic>GRF</italic> genes caused the aberrant pistils of miR396-overexpressing plants, we conducted functional complementation tests. Each of four <italic>GRF</italic> constructs (<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF7</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mGRF7</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF9</italic>, and <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mGRF9</italic>) was transformed into Arabidopsis wild-type plants. All transgenic plants produced normal siliques (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3C</ext-link>). When <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF7</italic> or <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF9</italic> plants were crossed with <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396</italic>a plants, their progenies (<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF7</italic>/<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>miR396a</italic> or <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF9</italic>/<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>miR396a</italic>) still formed abnormal pistils and single-carpel siliques, although there were smaller proportions of abnormal siliques. By contrast, when <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mGRF7</italic> or <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mGRF9</italic> plants were crossed with <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants, their progenies (<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mGRF7</italic>/<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>miR396a</italic> or <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mGRF9</italic>/<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>miR396a</italic>) developed normal siliques (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). We further quantified the transcript levels of <italic>GRF7</italic> and <italic>GRF9</italic> in F1 progenies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>). As expected, the level of <italic>GRF7</italic> transcripts was dramatically decreased in <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF7</italic>/<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>miR396a</italic> plants compared with that in <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF7</italic>/wild-type plants. By contrast, the levels of <italic>GRF7</italic> transcripts in <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mGRF7</italic>/<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>miR396a</italic> plants were similar to that in <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mGRF7</italic>/wild-type plants. A similar case was also observed for <italic>GRF9</italic>. Therefore, miR396-resistant <italic>mGRF7</italic> and <italic>mGRF9</italic>, but not miR396-sensitive <italic>GRF7</italic> and <italic>GRF9</italic>, were sufficient to recover <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>. Our results suggested that the reduced expressions of <italic>GRF</italic> genes were responsible for the pistil abnormalities of miR396-overexpressing plants.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Rescue of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> by <italic>mGRF</italic>. A, Six representative siliques were presented for each plant. The white asterisk indicates the single-carpel siliques. B, Expression of GRF7 and GRF9. Flowers of F1 progenies for indicated two parental plants were used for expression analysis. Error bars represent <sc>se</sc> for three independent experiments. The values marked by an asterisk are significantly different from the control values (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; <italic>n</italic> = 3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_225144_f3"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s5"><title>GRF Interacted with GIF as Cotranscription Factors</title><p>Previous studies demonstrated that GRF1 and GIF1 function as cotranscription factors in regulating leaf growth and morphology in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kim and Kende, 2004</xref>). In Arabidopsis, there are two homologs (GIF2 and GIF3) of GIF1. To determine whether each GRF protein can interact with each GIF protein, we used yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>)-two hybridization assays to investigate their interactions. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref>, GIF1 strongly interacted with seven GRFs, but only weakly interacted with GRF4 and GRF7. By contrast, both GIF2 and GIF3 strongly interacted with all GRFs except for GRF9.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Interaction of GRFs and GIFs. A, Yeast two-hybrid assays. Interaction was indicated by the ability of cells to grow on synthetic dropout medium lacking Leu/Trp/His/Ade. N-terminal truncated GRFs and full-length GIFs were cloned into pGBKT7 and pGADT7, respectively. B, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">BiFC</xref> assays. Fluorescence was observed in nuclear compartments of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaf epidermal cells; the fluorescence resulted from complementation of the N-terminal portion of YFP fused to GRF (GRF-nYFP) with the C-terminal portion of YFP fused to GIF (GIF-cYFP). C, CoIP assays. Flag-fused GRF-nYFP was immunoprecipitated using Flag antibody, and coimmunoprecipitated Myc-GIF-cYFP was then detected using Myc antibody.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_225144_f4"></graphic></fig><p>Next, we used bimolecular fluorescence complementation (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">BiFC</xref>) assays to verify these protein interactions in planta. The N-terminal fragment of yellow fluorescent protein (nYFP) was individually ligated with GRF4, GRF7, and GRF9 to produce GRF4-nYFP, GRF7-nYFP, and GRF9-nYFP, respectively. The GIF1, GIF2, and GIF3 proteins were individually fused with the C-terminal fragment of YFP (cYFP). When GIF1-cYFP was transiently coexpressed with GRF9-nYFP, strong YFP fluorescence was visible in the nucleus of epidermal cells in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>), whereas no YFP fluorescence was detected in negative controls (GIF1-cYFP coexpressed with nYFP or cYFP coexpressed with GRF9-nYFP; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>). Similar results were observed for coexpression of GIF2-cYFP with GRF7-nYFP and GIF3-cYFP with GRF4-nYFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>).</p><p>To further confirm whether GRF and GIF form protein complex in plant cells, we performed coimmunoprecipitation assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>). GRF and GIF were transiently coexpressed in tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>) leaves. The total proteins were incubated with Flag antibody and A/G-agarose beads and then separated on SDS-PAGE for immunoblotting with Myc antibody. In agreement with the results in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">BiFC</xref>, GRF and GIF exist in the same protein complex. Taken together, our results suggested that GRFs and GIFs function as cotranscription factors.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Spatiotemporal Expression of <italic>GRF</italic> and <italic>GIF</italic> Genes in Flowers</title><p>Our results demonstrated that GRF proteins can physically interact with GIF proteins. To serve as cotranscription factors in flowers, GRFs and GIFs must have the same spatiotemporal expression patterns. To determine their expression patterns, Arabidopsis was transformed with <italic>GUS</italic> fusion constructs for each of these 12 genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>). In flowers, the <italic>GRF3</italic> promoter drove GUS expression in the receptacle and the <italic>GRF8</italic> promoter drove GUS expression in the anther. The remaining seven <italic>GRF</italic> gene promoters and three <italic>GIF</italic> gene promoters were mainly activated in the pistil, although they showed somewhat different spatial expression patterns.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Tissue-specific expression of <italic>GRF</italic> and <italic>GIF</italic> genes. A, Inflorescence staining of indicated genes. B, Expression of <italic>GIF</italic> genes in sepal, petal, stamen, and pistil at floral stage 13. C, Expression of <italic>GIF</italic> genes in pistils at the indicated floral stage.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_225144_f5"></graphic></fig><p>We further analyzed the transcript levels of <italic>GIF</italic> genes in sepals, petals, stamens, and pistils. Like <italic>GRF</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, B and C</xref>), the highest levels of <italic>GIF</italic> transcripts were in the pistil (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>) and their expressions in the pistil decreased at later stages of flower development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Suppression of <italic>GRF</italic> Genes by miR396 Caused the Reduction of GRF/GIF Complex</title><p>Because <italic>GRF</italic> genes are posttranscriptionally regulated by miR396, we expected that increased accumulation of miR396 would reduce the abundance of GRF/GIF complexes. To confirm our hypothesis, transient expression assays were conducted in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). When GIF2-cYFP and GRF7-nYFP were coexpressed with miR396a, only a few epidermal cells displayed visible YFP fluorescence. As a negative control, when they were coexpressed with miR395a, which cannot recognize the <italic>GRF7</italic> gene, many cells showed YFP fluorescence. When GIF2-cYFP and mGRF7-nYFP were coexpressed with miR396a, most cells showed strong YFP fluorescence. These results indicated that the suppressed GRF expression reduces the formation of GRF/GIF complex.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>miR396 suppresses formation of the GRF/GIF complex. <italic>MIRNA</italic>, <italic>(m)GRF7-nYFP</italic>, and <italic>GIF2-cYFP</italic> constructs were coinfiltrated into tobacco epidermal cells as described in &#x201C;Materials and Methods.&#x201D; <italic>MIR395a</italic> was used as a negative control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_225144_f6"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Phenotypes of <italic>GIF</italic> Triple Mutant <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> Were Similar to Those of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>/<italic>grf5</italic> Plants</title><p>Because GRF and GIF function as cotranscription factors, we expected that the <italic>GIF</italic> mutants would phenocopy miR396-overexpressing plants. Previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Kim and Kende, 2004</xref>) revealed that the <italic>gif1</italic> mutant produces narrow leaves similar to those of 35S:<italic>MIR396a</italic>. We examined the siliques of <italic>gif1</italic> mutants and found that all of them contained two carpels, but they were significantly shorter than wild-type siliques. We speculated that <italic>GIF1</italic> would be functionally redundant with the other two <italic>GIF</italic> genes. To confirm our hypothesis, we constructed <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>, <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic>, <italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic>, and <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> mutants by crossing <italic>gif</italic> single mutants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5A</ext-link>). Compared with the siliques of the gif1 mutant, those of the <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic> and <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> mutants were shorter, but those of the <italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> mutant were of a similar length. By contrast, the siliques of triple mutants were shorter than those of double mutants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5B</ext-link>). The <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> triple mutant formed bent siliques, single-carpel siliques, and unfused-carpel siliques (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, A&#x2013;D</xref>). However, there were markedly fewer single-carpel siliques in <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> mutants than in <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7E</xref>). In addition, <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> mutants showed very low fertility with no more than 20 seeds per plant, because most siliques did not contain seeds. This differed from <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants, in which only about 10% of siliques did not contain seeds.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p><italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> triple mutants mimic <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>/<italic>grf5</italic>. A, Pistil with unfused carpels in <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> mutants. B, Single-carpel pistil in the <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> flower. C, Normal siliques (left, wild type) and single-carpel silique (right, <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic>). D, Representative siliques for the indicated plants. The white asterisk indicates the single-carpel siliques. E, Percentage of siliques containing single carpel or two carpel. Three individuals for each genotype were used for silique analysis. Thirty siliques for each individual were analyzed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_225144_f7"></graphic></fig><p>Although eight <italic>GRF</italic> genes showed reduced transcript levels in <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants, <italic>GRF5</italic> transcripts were not affected by miR396, which may have contributed to the higher fertility of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants compared with <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> mutants. To explore this idea, the <italic>grf5</italic> mutant was crossed with <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants and <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>/<italic>grf5</italic> plants were obtained by screening F2 plants. As expected, <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>/<italic>grf5</italic> plants displayed lower fertility and had fewer single-carpel siliques than did <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants, indicating that <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>/<italic>grf5</italic> plants phenocopied <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> mutant plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, D and E</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s9" sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>s play a key role in regulating plant development, which can be inferred from the developmental defects in <italic>dcl1</italic>, <italic>hyl1</italic>, <italic>serrate</italic>, and <italic>ago1</italic> mutants and from analyses of plants overexpressing various <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>s (e.g. miR160, miR164, miR166, and miR319, etc.). Here, we demonstrated that overexpression of miR396 results in morphological defects in floral organs. Our results reveal the function of miR396 in reducing the formation of the GRF/GIF complex, which regulates pistil development.</p><sec id="s10"><title>Functional Redundancies of <italic>GRF</italic> Family Members</title><p>Previously, we showed that overexpression of miR396 results in narrow rosette leaves and reduced expressions of its <italic>GRF</italic> target genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Liu et al., 2009</xref>). Here, our results indicate that elevated miR396 also causes floral abnormalities by suppressing the expressions of its <italic>GRF</italic> target genes. The Arabidopsis genome contains nine <italic>GRF</italic> genes, all of which are expressed in leaves and flowers. However, only <italic>grf5</italic> and <italic>grf7</italic> single mutants produced leaves slightly smaller than those of wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Horiguchi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Kim et al., 2012</xref>), whereas the other <italic>grf</italic> single mutants displayed no developmental abnormalities. The <italic>grf1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> triple mutants produced small leaves and cotyledons, indicating that <italic>GRF1</italic>, <italic>GRF2</italic>, and <italic>GRF3</italic> participate redundantly in controlling leaf cell number (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Kim et al., 2003</xref>). Previous investigations confirmed that overexpression of <italic>GRF1</italic>, <italic>GRF2</italic>, or <italic>GRF5</italic> can increase the leaf surface area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Kim et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Horiguchi et al., 2005</xref>). We found that plants overexpressing <italic>GRF7</italic> or <italic>GRF9</italic> showed slightly enlarged leaves (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>), but <italic>grf7</italic>/<italic>grf8</italic>/<italic>grf9</italic> mutants produced leaves similar to those of <italic>grf7</italic> single mutants, suggesting their overlapping functions in regulating leaf development. Our results revealed that the down-regulation of <italic>GRF</italic> genes is responsible for the aberrant siliques of miR396-overexpressing plants, because the miR396-resistant version of <italic>GRF</italic> could recover their silique phenotypes. Both <italic>grf1</italic>/<italic>grf2</italic>/<italic>grf3</italic> and <italic>grf7</italic>/<italic>grf8</italic>/<italic>grf9</italic> mutants produced normal siliques, indicating redundant functions of these <italic>GRF</italic> genes in regulating floral development. Although <italic>GRF5</italic> is not the target of miR396, a <italic>grf5</italic> mutation aggravated the abnormalities in leaves and siliques of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7D</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S7</ext-link>), indicating its redundant functions with other <italic>GRF</italic> genes. Interestingly, the introduction of <italic>grf5</italic> into <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants reduced the number of single-carpel siliques. Meanwhile, we also observed that it also led to nearly sterility. It seems that the single carpel ensures the production of necessary seeds. Further investigation is required to reveal the underlined mechanism. In addition, all of the <italic>GRF</italic> genes showed overlapping expression patterns in the flower, with their highest expression levels in the pistil. Taken together, these results showed that <italic>GRF</italic> genes function redundantly in regulating plant development.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>GRF and GIF Coregulate Pistil Development</title><p>GRF proteins contain two conserved domains, QLQ and WRC, in their N-terminal region. The QLQ domain is very similar to the N-terminal part of the SWI2/SNF2 protein that interacts with another component of the SWI2/SNF2 chromatin-remodeling complex in yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Treich et al., 1995</xref>). The WRC domain consists of a functional nuclear localization signal and a DNA-binding motif. The C-terminal regions of GRFs have common features of transcription factors and are required for their transcription activation activities because N-terminal-truncated GRFs lose their transactivation functions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). GIF proteins contain a SNH domain and a QG domain, which are similar to domains in the SYT protein, a transcriptional coactivator in human (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Brett et al., 1997</xref>). The SYT protein can interact with SWI2/SNF2-chromatin remodeling proteins, which may regulate transcription via chromatin modification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Thaete et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Kato et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aizawa et al., 2004</xref>). Similarly, our results indicated that GIF proteins can interact with GRF proteins in both yeast and plant cells. Thus, similar to the interaction between SYT and SWI2/SNF2 proteins, GIF interacts with GRF to influence the transcriptions of downstream target genes.</p><p>miR396-overexpressing plants, in which all of the <italic>GRF</italic> genes except for <italic>GRF5</italic> were dramatically down-regulated, produced abnormal pistils. The spatiotemporal expression patterns of <italic>GRF</italic> genes in the flower were very similar to those of <italic>GIF</italic> genes, and both were expressed at relatively high levels in the pistil. The combination of their expression patterns and their interactions in the plant cell nucleus implied that <italic>GRF</italic> and <italic>GIF</italic> may coregulate pistil development. Our results revealed that each GIF protein can interact with almost all of the GRF proteins, implying that one GIF modulates the functions of multiple GRFs. That explains why <italic>gif1</italic> single mutants, but not <italic>grf</italic> single mutants, displayed short siliques. We also observed that siliques of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>/<italic>grf5</italic> were shorter than those of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7E</xref>). The siliques of <italic>gif</italic> double mutants (<italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic> and <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic>) were shorter than those of <italic>gif1</italic> mutants, and the siliques of <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> triple mutants were shorter than those of double mutants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S7B</ext-link>). Both <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>/<italic>grf5</italic> and <italic>gif1</italic>/<italic>gif2</italic>/<italic>gif3</italic> caused short and almost completely sterile siliques as well as single-carpel siliques, suggesting that silique development is <italic>GRF</italic> and <italic>GIF</italic> dose dependent.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Proper Regulation of <italic>GRF</italic> Genes by miR396 Is Crucial for Plant Development</title><p>Several <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>s have been shown to function in regulating floral development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Achard et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Chen, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Mallory et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Williams et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Wu et al., 2006</xref>), and all of these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>s are conserved across plant species. The misexpression of these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>s followed by misexpression of their targets can cause abnormal development of floral organs, suggesting that a balance between these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>s and their targets is required for floral development. Similarly, we demonstrated that overexpression of miR396 mediated the down-regulation of their <italic>GRF</italic> targets, resulting in abnormal floral organs. In wild-type flowers, all nine <italic>GRF</italic> genes were highly expressed at an early stage of pistil development, and their abundance decreased as the siliques mature. By contrast, both <italic>MIR396a</italic> and <italic>MIR396b</italic> genes were expressed at low levels in young siliques and their abundance increased as the siliques matured. The inverse correlation between miR396 and its targets implied that miR396 constrains the expression of its target genes. However, the balance between miR396 and its targets was disrupted in flowers of miR396-overexpressing plants, and its target genes were dramatically down-regulated in the flowers, compared with those in wild-type flowers. The altered expressions of <italic>GRF</italic> genes were responsible for the deformed pistils in <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants. When <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants were crossed with <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF7</italic>/<italic>GRF9</italic> plants, their progenies, <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GRF7</italic>/<italic>GRF9</italic>/<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>, displayed phenotypes identical to those of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants. By contrast, <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mGRF7</italic>/<italic>GRF9</italic> restored <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants to the wild type. Therefore, the right amount of <italic>GRF</italic> levels is required for pistil development. A similar case was also observed in tobacco, where overexpression of miR396 caused aberrant pistils via down-regulation of <italic>GRF</italic> targets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Yang et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Baucher et al., 2013</xref>). We also observed that the narrow leaf phenotypes were always linked with aberrant pistils and elevated <italic>GRF</italic> expression could rescue both defects, implying that the miR396/<italic>GRF</italic> cascade regulates the development of both leaf and flower. These results revealed that appropriate regulation of <italic>GRF</italic> genes by miR396 is necessary for plant development.</p><p>Although we reveal that miR396 affects the development of pistils by regulation of <italic>GRF</italic> genes, it is still unclear which developmental processes were linked to the pistil abnormalities. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5A</xref>, both <italic>GRF</italic> and <italic>GIF</italic> genes were expressed in the early pistil developmental stages. It is likely that the GRF/GIF complexes control the expression of genes involved in early pistil development. Further investigation into the detailed expression patterns of <italic>GRF</italic> and <italic>GIF</italic> genes and to establish the direct targets regulated by the GRF/GIF complexes are required to better understand the mechanism of pistil formation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s13" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s14"><title>Plant Materials</title><p>Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) ecotype Columbia was used for all experiments. The generation of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> plants were described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Liu et al., 2009</xref>). Plants were grown in long photoperiods (16-h light/8-h dark) or in short photoperiods (8-h light/16-h dark) at 23&#x00B0;C.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Real-Time <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR Experiments</title><p>One microgram total RNA extracted using the Trizol reagent (Invitrogen) was used for oligo(dT)18 primed complementary DNA (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">cDNA</xref>) synthesis according to the reverse transcription protocol (Fermentas). The resulting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">cDNA</xref> was subjected to relative quantitative PCR using a SYBR Premix Ex Taq kit (TaKaRa) on a Roche LightCycler 480 real-time PCR machine, according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. For each reported result, at least three independent biological samples were subjected to minimum of three technical replicates. The results were normalized to <italic>ACTIN2</italic>. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR primers for nine GRFs were described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Rodriguez et al., 2010</xref>). The other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">qRT</xref>-PCR primers used are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Plasmid Construction</title><p>The pOCA30 binary plasmid was used for an expression vector. For overexpression, the genome sequence for each gene was cloned into the pOCA30 vector. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref> target motif in <italic>GRF7</italic> or <italic>GRF9</italic> was altered, introducing synonymous mutations in a cloned <italic>GRF7</italic> or <italic>GRF9</italic> wild-type genomic fragment.</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) Assays</title><p>For yeast-two hybridization assay, all the N-terminal truncated GRFs containing the QLQ and WRC domains were cloned into pGBKT7, and the full-length <italic>GIF</italic> genes were cloned into pGADT7. The N-terminal sequences of the GRFs for yeast two-hybrid assay can be found according to the primers provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>. For transactivation assays, the full-length <italic>GRF</italic> and <italic>GIF</italic> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">cDNA</xref>s were cloned into pGBKT7 and introduced into yeast cells. Growth was determined as described in the Yeast Two-Hybrid System User Manual (Clontech). Primers used for the vector construction were listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>. Experiments were repeated three times.</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title><italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> Infiltration in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic></title><p>Plasmids were transformed into <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strain EHA105. Agrobacterial cells were infiltrated into leaves of <italic>N. benthamiana</italic>. For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>/GRF coinfiltration experiments, equal volumes of an <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> culture containing <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic> (optical density at 600 nm [<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">OD600</xref>] = 1.75) and <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>(m)GRF7</italic>/<italic>GRF9</italic> (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">OD600</xref> = 0.25) were mixed before infiltration into <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves. After infiltration, plants were placed at 24&#x00B0;C for 72 h before RNA extraction.</p><p>For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">BiFC</xref> assays, full-length coding sequences of Arabidopsis <italic>GRF4</italic>, <italic>GRF7</italic>, <italic>GRF9</italic>, <italic>GIF1</italic>, <italic>GIF2</italic>, and <italic>GIF3</italic> were cloned into the binary nYFP or cYFP vector. <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strains transformed with indicated nYFP or cYFP vector were incubated, harvested, and resuspended in infiltration buffer (0.2 m<sc>m</sc> acetosyringone, 10 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 10 m<sc>m</sc> MES, pH 5.6) to identical concentrations (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">OD600</xref> = 0.5). For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>/GRF/GIF interaction test, equal volumes of an <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> culture containing <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR395a</italic> or <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396</italic>a (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">OD600</xref> = 2.5), <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>(m)GRF7</italic>-<italic>nYFP</italic> (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">OD600</xref> = 0.5), and <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GIF2-cYFP</italic> (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">OD600</xref> = 0.5) were mixed before infiltration into <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves. After infiltration, plants were placed at 24&#x00B0;C for 48 h before observation.</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Coimmunoprecipitation Assay</title><p>Flag-GRF-nYFP and Myc-GIF-cYFP (or Myc-cYFP) were transiently coexpressed in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves. Infected leaves were harvested 48 h after infiltration and used for protein extraction. Flag-fused GRF was immunoprecipitated using Flag antibody, and the coimmunoprecipitated proteins were then detected using Myc antibody.</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Scanning Electron Microscopy and GUS Assays</title><p>For scanning electron microscopy analysis, siliques from flowers at stage 15 were separated, fixed, dehydrated, dried, coated with gold-palladium, and then photographed.</p><p>For promoter-GUS constructs of <italic>GRF</italic> and <italic>GIF</italic> genes, about 2-kb upstream promoter regions were amplified and fused with the GUS gene. The primers were listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>. Transgenic plants were subjected to GUS staining as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Liang et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>Sequence data from this article can be found in the GenBank/EMBL data libraries under accession numbers <italic>MIR396a</italic> (AT2G10606), <italic>MIR396b</italic> (AT5G35407), <italic>GRF1</italic> (AT2G22840), <italic>GRF2</italic> (AT4G37740), <italic>GRF3</italic> (AT2G36400), <italic>GRF4</italic> (AT3G52910), <italic>GRF5</italic> (AT3G13960), <italic>GRF6</italic> (AT2G06200), <italic>GRF7</italic> (AT5G53660), <italic>GRF8</italic> (AT4G24150), GRF9 (AT2G45480), <italic>GIF1</italic> (AT5G28640), <italic>GIF2</italic> (AT1G01160), <italic>GIF3</italic> (AT4G00850), and <italic>ACT2</italic> (AT3G18780). The transfer DNA insertion mutants used in this article include <italic>grf1</italic> (SALK_069339C), <italic>grf3</italic> (SALK_026786), <italic>grf4</italic> (SALK_077829C), <italic>grf5</italic> (SALK_086597C), <italic>grf7</italic> (CS878963), <italic>grf8</italic> (CS804312), <italic>grf9</italic> (SALK_140746C), <italic>gif1</italic> (SALK_150407), <italic>gif2</italic> (CS851972), and <italic>gif3</italic> (SALK_052744).</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> <italic>STTM396</italic> plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> Cleavage of <italic>GRF4</italic> and modification of <italic>GRF7</italic> and <italic>GRF9</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S3.</bold></ext-link> Siliques of <italic>grf</italic> mutants and <italic>GRF</italic> transgenic plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S4.</bold></ext-link> Negative controls for BiFC assays.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S5.</bold></ext-link> <italic>grf</italic> mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S6.</bold></ext-link> Leaf area of third leaves of wild-type, <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>, and various <italic>GRF</italic> transgenic plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S7.</bold></ext-link> Rosette leaves of wild-type, <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>MIR396a/grf5</italic>, and <italic>gif1/gif2/gif3</italic> plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.225144/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S1.</bold></ext-link> Primers used in this article.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the editor and two anonymous reviewers for their constructive comments, which helped us to improve the manuscript, the Arabidopsis Resource Center at the Ohio State University for the transfer DNA insertion mutants, and Yanhui Zhao (Kunming Institute of Botany, Chinese Academy of Sciences) for scanning electron microscope assistance.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Herr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baulcombe</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Modulation of floral development by a gibberellin-regulated microRNA</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>3357</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3365</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bobb</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Balakrishnan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ince</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurevich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Dendrite development regulated by CREST, a calcium-regulated transcriptional activator</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>303</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>202</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aukerman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Regulation of flowering time and floral organ identity by a microRNA and its <italic>APETALA2</italic>-like target genes</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2730</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2741</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieber</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellmer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The early extra petals1 mutant uncovers a role for microRNA miR164c in regulating petal number in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>315</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and function</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>297</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baucher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moussawi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandeputte</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteyne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x00E9;rez-Morga</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>El Jaziri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A role for the miR396/GRF network in specification of organ type during flower development, as supported by ectopic expression of <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> miR396c in transgenic tobacco</article-title>. <source>Plant Biol (Stuttg)</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>892</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>898</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shipley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The SYT protein involved in the t(X;18) synovial sarcoma translocation is a transcriptional activator localised in nuclear bodies</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1559</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1564</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brodersen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakvarelidze-Achard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruun-Rasmussen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunoyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieburth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Voinnet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Widespread translational inhibition by plant miRNAs and siRNAs</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>320</volume>: <fpage>1185</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1190</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambros</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Role of microRNAs in plant and animal development</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>301</volume>: <fpage>336</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>338</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A microRNA as a translational repressor of APETALA2 in Arabidopsis flower development</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>303</volume>: <fpage>2022</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2025</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Debernardi</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mecchia</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Palatnik</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Functional specialization of the plant miR396 regulatory network through distinct microRNA-target interactions</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002419</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hewezi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nettleton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis microRNA396-GRF1/GRF3 regulatory module acts as a developmental regulator in the reprogramming of root cells during cyst nematode infection</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>335</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horiguchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsukaya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The transcription factor AtGRF5 and the transcription coactivator AN3 regulate cell proliferation in leaf primordia of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>78</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones-Rhoades</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Computational identification of plant microRNAs and their targets, including a stress-induced miRNA</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>787</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>799</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjernberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Krutchinsky</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohtsuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>de Bruijn</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chait</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>SYT associates with human SNF/SWI complexes and the C-terminal region of its fusion partner SSX1 targets histones</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>277</volume>: <fpage>5498</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5505</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Narry Kim</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA-directed cleavage of ATHB15 mRNA regulates vascular development in Arabidopsis inflorescence stems</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>94</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kende</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The AtGRF family of putative transcription factors is involved in leaf and cotyledon growth in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>94</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>104</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kende</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A transcriptional coactivator, AtGIF1, is involved in regulating leaf growth and morphology in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>13374</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>13379</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizoi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidokoro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Takiguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohme-Takagi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> growth-regulating factor7 functions as a transcriptional repressor of abscisic acid- and osmotic stress-responsive genes, including <italic>DREB2A</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>3393</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3405</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Delannoy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sormani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Floris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodersen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cr&#x00E9;t&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Voinnet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Robaglia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Biochemical evidence for translational repression by <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> microRNAs</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1762</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1768</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pak</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis <italic>GRF-INTERACTING FACTOR</italic> gene family performs an overlapping function in determining organ size as well as multiple developmental properties</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>151</volume>: <fpage>655</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>668</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA395 mediates regulation of sulfate accumulation and allocation in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>1046</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1057</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Ectopic expression of miR396 suppresses GRF target gene expression and alters leaf growth in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Physiol Plant</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>236</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The role of floral organs in carpels, an Arabidopsis loss-of-function mutation in microRNA160a, in organogenesis and the mechanism regulating its expression</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>416</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>428</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallory</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA regulation of NAC-domain targets is required for proper formation and separation of adjacent embryonic, vegetative, and floral organs</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1035</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1046</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis GAMYB-like</italic> genes, <italic>MYB33</italic> and <italic>MYB65</italic>, are microRNA-regulated genes that redundantly facilitate anther development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>705</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>721</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhoades</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>MicroRNAs in plants</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1616</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1626</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mecchia</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Debernardi</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schommer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Palatnik</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Control of cell proliferation in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> by microRNA miR396</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>112</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ru</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Plant fertility defects induced by the enhanced expression of microRNA167</article-title>. <source>Cell Res</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>457</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>465</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinke</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>DICER-LIKE1: blind men and elephants in Arabidopsis development</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>487</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>491</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thaete</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rennie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Functional domains of the SYT and SYT-SSX synovial sarcoma translocation proteins and co-localization with the SNF protein BRM in the nucleus</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>591</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>de los Santos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewster</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>SNF11, a new component of the yeast SNF-SWI complex that interacts with a conserved region of SNF2</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>4240</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4248</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaucheret</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cr&#x00E9;t&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The action of ARGONAUTE1 in the miRNA pathway and its regulation by the miRNA pathway are crucial for plant development</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1187</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1197</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>miR396-targeted AtGRF transcription factors are required for coordination of cell division and differentiation during leaf development in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>761</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>773</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigg</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Regulation of Arabidopsis shoot apical meristem and lateral organ formation by microRNA miR166g and its AtHD-ZIP target genes</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>3657</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3668</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis microRNA167 controls patterns of ARF6 and ARF8 expression, and regulates both female and male reproduction</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>4211</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4218</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Effective small RNA destruction by the expression of a short tandem target mimic in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>415</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>427</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis miR396 mediates the development of leaves and flowers in transgenic tobacco</article-title>. <source>J Plant Biol</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>481</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
