<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">192369</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.192369</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>DEVELOPMENT AND HORMONE ACTION</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The <italic>microRNA156</italic>-<italic>SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN</italic>-<italic>LIKE3</italic> Module Regulates Ambient Temperature-Responsive Flowering via <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>[C]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[OA]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Jae Joon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Jeong Hwan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Wanhui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Hye Seung</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>Ji Hoon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x002A;</sup></xref></contrib><aff>Creative Research Initiatives, Division of Life Sciences, Korea University, Seoul 136&#x2013;701, Korea (J.J.K., J.H.L., W.K., H.S.J., J.H.A.); and Max Planck Institute for Plant Breeding Research, 50829 Cologne, Germany (P.H.)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="afn1"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the Creative Research Initiatives of the National Research Foundation for the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology (grant no. R16&#x2013;2008&#x2013;106&#x2013;01000&#x2013;0 to J.H.A.), by a Korea University Grant (to J.H.A. and J.H.L.), by the Brain Korea 21 program (to J.H.L., W.K., and H.S.J.), and by a National Research Foundation of Korea grant funded by the Korean Government (Ministry of Education, Science and Technology; grant no. NRF&#x2013;2011&#x2013;355&#x2013;C00040 to W.K.).</p></fn><fn id="afn2" fn-type="equal"><label>2</label><p>These authors contributed equally to the article.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>jahn@korea.ac.kr</email>.</corresp><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Ji Hoon Ahn (<email>jahn@korea.ac.kr</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn1"><label>[C]</label><p>Some figures in this article are displayed in color online but in black and white in the print edition.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[OA]</label><p>Open Access articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.111.192369">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.111.192369</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>5</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>159</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2012 American Society of Plant Biologists. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p></p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The flowering time of plants is affected by modest changes in ambient temperature. However, little is known about the regulation of ambient temperature-responsive flowering by small RNAs. In this study, we show that the <italic>microRNA156</italic> (<italic>miR156</italic>)-<italic>SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN</italic>-<italic>LIKE3</italic> (<italic>SPL3</italic>) module directly regulates <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>) expression in the leaf to control ambient temperature-responsive flowering. Overexpression of miR156 led to more delayed flowering at a lower ambient temperature (16&#x00B0;C), which was associated with down-regulation of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FRUITFULL</italic> expression. Among miR156 target genes, <italic>SPL3</italic> mRNA levels were mainly reduced, probably because miR156-mediated cleavage of <italic>SPL3</italic> mRNA was higher at 16&#x00B0;C. Overexpression of miR156-resistant <italic>SPL3</italic> [<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;)] caused early flowering, regardless of the ambient temperature, which was associated with up-regulation of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FRUITFULL</italic> expression. Reduction of miR156 activity by target mimicry led to a phenotype similar to that of <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants. <italic>FT</italic> up-regulation was observed after dexamethasone treatment in <italic>GVG</italic>-<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants. Misexpression and artificial microRNA-mediated suppression of <italic>FT</italic> in the leaf dramatically altered the ambient temperature-responsive flowering of plants overexpressing miR156 and <italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;). Chromatin immunoprecipitation assay showed that the SPL3 protein directly binds to GTAC motifs within the <italic>FT</italic> promoter. Lesions in <italic>TERMINAL FLOWER1</italic>, <italic>SHORT VEGETATIVE PHASE</italic>, and <italic>EARLY FLOWERING3</italic> did not alter the expression of miR156 and <italic>SPL3.</italic> Taken together, our data suggest that the interaction between the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module and <italic>FT</italic> is part of the regulatory mechanism controlling flowering time in response to ambient temperature.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">miRNAs</term><def id="def1"><p>microRNAs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">LD</term><def id="def2"><p>long-day</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">qRT</term><def id="def3"><p>quantitative reverse transcription</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">Ws</term><def id="def4"><p>Wassilewskija</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">ChIP</term><def id="def5"><p>chromatin immunoprecipitation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">Ct</term><def id="def6"><p>threshold cycle</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">Cv</term><def id="def7"><p>coefficient of variation</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>Flowering, which is a major developmental transition to the reproductive phase, is affected by various environmental stimuli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Simpson and Dean, 2000</xref>). Temperature is one of the most common environmental stimuli affecting plant development. To survive and complete their life cycle, plants continuously adjust their growth and development in response to changing temperature conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Penfield, 2008</xref>). Although plants generally experience only modest variations in temperature during most of their life cycle, genetic analyses have focused on the processes that modulate flowering under severe temperature conditions, such as vernalization and cold/heat stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Sheldon et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Panchuk et al., 2002</xref>).</p><p>Changes in ambient growth temperature significantly affect plant flowering time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Fitter and Fitter, 2002</xref>) and ultimately the ecological distribution of plant species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lenoir et al., 2008</xref>). To elucidate the molecular mechanisms underlying ambient temperature signaling in plants, genetic screens were performed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bl&#x00E1;zquez et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Balasubramanian et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2007</xref>), which revealed the thermosensory pathway mediating ambient temperature responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Lee et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Fornara et al., 2010</xref>). <italic>FCA</italic>, <italic>FVE</italic>, <italic>SHORT VEGETATIVE PHASE</italic> (<italic>SVP</italic>), <italic>EARLY FLOWERING3</italic> (<italic>ELF3</italic>), and <italic>TERMINAL FLOWER1</italic> (<italic>TFL1</italic>) genes are involved in this pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bl&#x00E1;zquez et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Strasser et al., 2009</xref>). H2A.Z-containing nucleosomes have recently been shown to provide thermosensory information by regulating the ambient temperature transcriptome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Kumar and Wigge, 2010</xref>). In addition, <italic>SVP</italic> has been shown to act as a link in small RNA-mediated flowering in response to different ambient temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lee et al., 2010</xref>). It has also been reported that the <italic>microRNA399</italic>-<italic>PHOSPHATE2</italic> module plays a role in the regulation of ambient temperature-responsive flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Kim et al., 2011</xref>). Taken together, these findings suggest a potential role for microRNAs (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNAs</xref>) in ambient temperature-responsive flowering.</p><p>Plant <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNAs</xref> are an important class of regulatory molecules affecting diverse aspects of plant growth and development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Carrington and Ambros, 2003</xref>). They commonly target mRNAs of specific transcription factors, thereby forming so-called <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref> transcription factor regulatory modules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Dugas and Bartel, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Mallory and Vaucheret, 2006</xref>). Examples of such modules in the Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) and other plant species include microRNA156 (miR156) and its targets, namely <italic>SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN</italic>-<italic>LIKE</italic> (<italic>SPL</italic>) genes. These <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL</italic> regulatory modules are known to play a central role in the regulation of diverse developmental processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Schwarz et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Wang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Nodine and Bartel, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Xing et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Yu et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Gou et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Yang et al., 2011</xref>). The <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module has been identified as part of a regulatory mechanism that can induce flowering in the absence of photoperiodic cues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al., 2009</xref>). The expression of <italic>FRUITFULL</italic> (<italic>FUL</italic>), <italic>AGAMOUS</italic>-<italic>LIKE42</italic>, and <italic>SUPPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CONSTANS1</italic> (<italic>SOC1</italic>) is regulated by this module. <italic>SPL3</italic> directly activates the expression of <italic>LEAFY</italic> (<italic>LFY</italic>), <italic>FUL</italic>, and <italic>APETALA1</italic> (<italic>AP1</italic>) to promote floral meristem identity during floral transition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Yamaguchi et al., 2009</xref>). Although miR156 was recently identified as an ambient temperature-responsive <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lee et al., 2010</xref>), little is known about its involvement in the molecular mechanism underlying ambient temperature-responsive flowering.</p><p>In this study, the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module is shown to play an important role in regulating flowering time in response to different ambient temperatures. Expression of miR156, miR156-resistant <italic>SPL3</italic>, or a target mimic of miR156 affected ambient temperature-responsive flowering and induced changes in <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>) and <italic>FUL</italic> expression. Genetic analyses indicated that <italic>FT</italic>, but not <italic>FUL</italic>, is a major output of the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module. The SPL3 protein directly binds to a sequence carrying GTAC motifs within the <italic>FT</italic> locus in vivo. Our results suggest a model in which the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module directly regulates <italic>FT</italic> expression in the leaf to modulate ambient temperature-responsive flowering in Arabidopsis.</p><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>MiR156 Overexpression Prolongs the Delay in Flowering at a Low Ambient Temperature</title><p>To determine whether miR156 regulates flowering time in response to ambient temperature, the phenotype of transgenic plants overexpressing miR156 (<italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic>) was analyzed at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C. Transgenic plants showing strong expression of miR156 at both temperatures were selected (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). Because overexpression of <italic>miR156</italic> is known to increase the leaf initiation rate at the normal temperature (23&#x00B0;C) with a modest delay in flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Schwab et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Wu and Poethig, 2006</xref>), both the plastochron length and the total leaf number were scored in long-day (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref>) conditions to measure flowering time. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions were used because, under short-day conditions, total leaf numbers of wild-type plants grown at 23&#x00B0;C were almost indistinguishable from those grown at 16&#x00B0;C, which indicates that low ambient temperature affects the photoperiodic response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Strasser et al., 2009</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants showed moderate late flowering at 23&#x00B0;C in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions (25.6 leaves; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link> to find detailed information on flowering time of plants used in this study; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Interestingly, flowering at 16&#x00B0;C was even more delayed (61.4 leaves). Thus, the leaf number ratio of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants (16&#x00B0;C/23&#x00B0;C, see &#x201C;Materials and Methods&#x201D;) was 2.4 (compare wild-type plants &#x003D; 1.9; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Also, the bolting time of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants was slightly later than that of wild-type plants at both 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>). As observed at 23&#x00B0;C, the rate of leaf production (the total number of leaves/bolting day) of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants was also faster than that of wild-type plants at 16&#x00B0;C (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>), which indicates that the decreased plastochron length (or increased leaf initiation rates) of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants occurs regardless of ambient temperature. The juvenile leaf number of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156</italic> plants was approximately 14.5 leaves (23&#x00B0;C) and 37 leaves (16&#x00B0;C), indicating that the phase transition in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156</italic> plants was more delayed at 16&#x00B0;C than at 23&#x00B0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>). These results suggest that miR156 overexpression led to ambient temperature-sensitive flowering.</p><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Overexpression of miR156 caused ambient temperature-sensitive flowering in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions. A, Delayed flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants at 16&#x00B0;C. Photographs were taken when <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants flowered at each temperature. B, The leaf morphologies of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants. An inverted triangle indicates the juvenile-to-adult transition point based on the appearance of abaxial trichomes. C and D, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR analysis of <italic>FT</italic>, <italic>FUL</italic>, and <italic>SPL3</italic> expression in the leaves and the shoot apical regions (SA) of 8-d-old seedlings (C) and at DS1.02 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Boyes et al., 2001</xref>; D) of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants grown at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C. Expression levels were measured at Zeitgeber time 16, at which point <italic>FT</italic> transcript levels are high (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Corbesier et al., 2007</xref>). The expression levels of each gene in wild-type (WT) plants at 23&#x00B0;C were set to one. Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc>. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_192369_wc_f1" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Down-Regulation of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> Plants</title><p>We analyzed the expression of flowering time genes in both the leaf and shoot apical region of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants because (1) miR156 is expressed in the leaf and shoot apical region at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>), and (2) a recent report showed that miR156 is probably functional in both samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al., 2009</xref>). To validate all leaf/shoot apex sample preparations used in this study, we first confirmed the preferential enrichment of <italic>RbcS</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Yamakawa et al., 2004</xref>) and <italic>SHOOT MERISTEMLESS</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Endrizzi et al., 1996</xref>) in these samples (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5</ext-link>). In the leaf of 8-d-old <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants, <italic>FUL</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Ferr&#x00E1;ndiz et al., 2000</xref>) expression was down-regulated at both temperatures, whereas <italic>FT</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Kardailsky et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Kobayashi et al., 1999</xref>) expression was not obviously altered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>), consistent with results reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jung et al., 2011</xref>). In the shoot apical region, <italic>FUL</italic> expression was also low at both temperatures and <italic>FT</italic> expression was absent. However, the expression levels of <italic>TWIN SISTER OF FT</italic> (<italic>TSF</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Yamaguchi et al., 2005</xref>) and <italic>SOC1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lee et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Samach et al., 2000</xref>), which are putative outputs within the thermosensory pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2007</xref>), were not dramatically altered (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>A). Notably, the down-regulation of <italic>SPL3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Wu and Poethig, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gandikota et al., 2007</xref>) was more apparent in the leaf than in the shoot apical region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>), which suggests that the leaf may be the primary site of action of miR156 for the regulation of flowering time.</p><p>Due to the shortened plastochron length of miR156-overexpressing plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>), the degree of shoot maturation of these plants may differ from that of wild-type plants of the same age, thereby preventing a direct comparison of the expression levels of flowering time genes. As a consequence, we also analyzed the expression levels of the flowering time genes at a morphologically defined growth stage 1.02 (DS1.02; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Boyes et al., 2001</xref>). At growth stage DS1.02, the down-regulation of <italic>FT</italic> was more apparent in the leaf than in the shoot apical region at both temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1D</xref>). There was a similar down-regulation of <italic>FUL</italic>. At DS1.02, there was once again a more significant decrease in the expression of <italic>SPL3</italic> in the leaf than in the shoot apical region. These results indicate that although the overexpression of miR156 altered plastochron length at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C, it consistently down-regulated <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic>, which are potent floral activators, at both temperatures.</p></sec><sec><title>Down-Regulation of <italic>SPL3</italic> via Enhanced Cleavage by miR156 at 16&#x00B0;C</title><p>The effect of ambient temperature on the expression levels of <italic>SPL</italic> genes was examined. The expression of <italic>SPL</italic> genes was generally lower at 16&#x00B0;C, in contrast to miR156 expression, which was higher at 16&#x00B0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). In particular, <italic>SPL3</italic> mRNA levels were dramatically lower at 16&#x00B0;C than at 23&#x00B0;C. However, the expression of <italic>CUP</italic>-<italic>SHAPED COTYLEDON2</italic> (<italic>CUC2</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Larue et al., 2009</xref>) and <italic>TCP FAMILY TRANSCRIPTION FACTOR4</italic> (<italic>TCP4</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Palatnik et al., 2003</xref>), which are target genes of nonambient temperature-responsive <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNAs</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lee et al., 2010</xref>), was not altered. These results suggest that the elevated miR156 expression at 16&#x00B0;C can enhance <italic>SPL3</italic> cleavage, although we cannot exclude the possibility of the translational inhibition of other <italic>SPL</italic> genes by miR156 at 16&#x00B0;C.</p><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Expression levels and cleavage sites of <italic>SPL</italic> genes at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C. A, Relative expression levels of miR156 and <italic>SPL</italic> genes in 10-d-old wild-type (WT) plants grown at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C. <italic>CUC2</italic> and <italic>TCP4</italic> were used as controls. Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc>. B, Semiquantitative measurement of the level of RLM 5&#x2032;-RACE products of <italic>SPL</italic> genes in 10-d-old wild-type plants. RACE products were hybridized with a 5&#x2032;-RACE adaptor sequence and their relative band intensity is shown. <italic>CUC2</italic> and <italic>TCP4</italic> were used as controls. C, Map of cleavage sites identified in <italic>SPL3</italic> by RLM 5&#x2032;-RACE. A partial sequence of <italic>SPL3</italic> is shown to highlight the miR156a-<italic>SPL3</italic> duplex. A period indicates a G-U pair.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_192369_gs_f2" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>We then examined whether the down-regulation of <italic>SPL3</italic> at 16&#x00B0;C was associated with enhanced cleavage of their mRNAs by miR156. No difference in the DNA methylation pattern at the <italic>SPL3</italic> locus was observed at 16&#x00B0;C, excluding a change in DNA methylation as an explanation of the down-regulation of <italic>SPL3</italic> at 16&#x00B0;C (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S7</ext-link>). A gene-specific RNA ligase-mediated 5&#x2032; rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RLM 5&#x2032;-RACE) assay identified cleavage products of <italic>SPL</italic> genes at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Considerably more cleavage products were produced from <italic>SPL3</italic> at 16&#x00B0;C (2.7-fold increase). In contrast, the levels of RACE products of <italic>CUC2</italic> and <italic>TCP4</italic> were similar at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C. These results suggest that the elevated miR156 expression at 16&#x00B0;C can enhance <italic>SPL3</italic> cleavage, although the possibility cannot be excluded that miR156 also inhibits the translation of other <italic>SPL</italic> genes at 16&#x00B0;C. RLM 5&#x2032;-RACE products obtained were sequenced to map the cleavage sites. In <italic>SPL3</italic>-derived transcripts, a major cleavage site was identified between &#x002B;10 and &#x002B;11 (relative to the 5&#x2032; end of miR156; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>) with a few minor, alternative cleavage sites. Collectively, the results obtained by quantitative reverse transcription (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>)-PCR and RLM 5&#x2032;-RACE revealed that <italic>SPL3</italic> levels were anticorrelated with the level of miR156 at 16&#x00B0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Overexpression of miR156-Resistant <italic>SPL3</italic> Causes Accelerated Flowering at a Low Ambient Temperature</title><p>The available <italic>spl3</italic> mutants (FLAG_173C12, Wassilewskija [<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Ws</xref>] background) exhibited unexpected early flowering with an increased leaf number ratio (1.8; compare wild-type plants &#x003D; 1.6) and were found to be a leaky allele (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S8</ext-link>), suggesting that these mutants are not suitable for inferring the function of <italic>SPL3</italic> in ambient temperature-responsive flowering. Thus, to investigate whether <italic>SPL3</italic> is involved in ambient temperature-responsive flowering, the phenotype of transgenic plants overexpressing <italic>SPL3</italic> either as a miR156-sensitive version, which has an intact miR156 response element in its 3&#x2032;-untranslated regions [hereafter, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x002B;)], or as a miR156-resistant version with the miR156 response element mutated [<italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;)] was analyzed. <italic>SPL3</italic> mRNA levels were greatly increased in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants, but showed a less-pronounced increase in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x002B;) plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S9</ext-link>A). Based on reports of the translational inhibition of the target mRNA by plant <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNAs</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Chen, 2004</xref>), the accumulation of the SPL3 protein in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants was confirmed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S9</ext-link>B).</p><p><italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants exhibited early flowering with similar leaf numbers (with fewer cauline leaves) at both temperatures (5.8 and 7.7 leaves) in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions (leaf number ratio &#x003D; 1.3; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S9</ext-link>C). This indicated that the flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants was almost insensitive to differences in ambient temperature. Unlike <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x002B;) plants produced more leaves at 16&#x00B0;C (23.7 leaves) than at 23&#x00B0;C (14.1 leaves; leaf number ratio &#x003D; 1.7). Thus, the flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x002B;) plants was more ambient temperature sensitive, which was consistent with the diminished <italic>SPL3</italic> expression in these plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S9</ext-link>A). Less juvenile leaves were produced in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants (3.0 and 5.0 leaves at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C, respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>). Adult leaf numbers were also greatly reduced in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants. However, the juvenile leaf number of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x002B;) plants (7.0 and 11.5 leaves at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C, respectively) was similar to that of wild-type plants (6.0 and 11.5 leaves at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C, respectively). These results suggest that <italic>SPL3</italic> modulates ambient temperature-responsive flowering.</p><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Overexpression of miR156-resistant <italic>SPL3</italic> caused ambient temperature-insensitive flowering in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions. A, Accelerated flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants at 16&#x00B0;C. Photographs were taken when the <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants flowered at each temperature. B, The leaf morphologies of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x002B;) and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants. An inverted triangle indicates the juvenile-to-adult transition point based on the appearance of abaxial trichomes. C and D, Expression of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> in the leaves and the shoot apical regions (SA) of 8-d-old seedlings (C) and at DS1.02 (D) of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants grown at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C. The expression levels of each gene in wild-type (WT) plants at 23&#x00B0;C were set to one. E, Phenotype and total leaf numbers of <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> and <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants grown at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C. Photographs were taken when the <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants flowered at each temperature. F, Expression of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> in the leaves of 8-d-old seedlings and at DS1.02 of <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants. G, Expression of <italic>FUL</italic> in the shoot apical regions of 8-d-old seedlings and at DS1.02 of <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants. Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc>. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_192369_wc_f3" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Up-Regulation of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) Plants</title><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR analysis revealed strong <italic>FUL</italic> expression in both the leaf and the shoot apical region of 8-d-old <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants at both ambient temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>), as well as increased <italic>FT</italic> expression in the leaf. However, there was no clear change in the expression of <italic>TSF</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic> in these plants at both temperatures (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>B). The expression of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> was also analyzed at DS1.02, and again <italic>FUL</italic> expression was found to have increased in both the leaf and the shoot apical region at both ambient temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3D</xref>). <italic>FT</italic> expression was also increased in the leaf at DS1.02 at both temperatures (by 4- and 3-fold at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C, respectively). A slightly reduced expression level of <italic>FT</italic> at 16&#x00B0;C in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants suggest that a weak temperature response of <italic>FT</italic> still remained. The weak temperature response seen in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) can be explained by the differential expression of <italic>FT</italic> at different temperature. These data indicated that increased <italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) mRNA expression led to the up-regulation of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> in the leaf and the shoot apex, which is consistent with their down-regulation in miR156-overexpressing plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, C and D</xref>). It was thus concluded that <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> are likely to be the major downstream genes of the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module.</p><p>The requirement of <italic>SPL3</italic> activity in different tissues was investigated through the misexpression of miR156-resistant <italic>SPL3</italic> in the shoot apex (using the <italic>FD</italic> promoter) and the phloem (using the <italic>SUC2</italic> promoter; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al., 2009</xref>). The possibility that <italic>FD</italic> and <italic>SUC2</italic> expression may be regulated by ambient temperature was excluded (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S10</ext-link>). <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants, a miR156-resistant version without the miR156 response element, exhibited moderate early flowering, which was intermediate to that of wild-type plants and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants, at both temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3E</xref>). In contrast, flowering of <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants was largely indistinguishable from that of wild-type plants at both temperatures. The leaf number ratio of <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants was 1.6, whereas that of <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants was 2.0, which indicates that <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants had reduced temperature sensitivity. These results suggest that modulations in <italic>SPL3</italic> activity in the leaf affect ambient temperature-sensitive flowering.</p><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR analysis of the expression levels of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> in <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> and <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants revealed that <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> expression increased (by at least 2-fold) in the leaf of 8-d-old <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants at both temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3F</xref>). This up-regulation of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> expression in the leaf of <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants was more apparent at DS1.02, i.e. at least 3-fold, at both temperatures. In the shoot apical region of 8-d-old seedlings of <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants and at DS1.02, <italic>FUL</italic> expression was increased at both temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3G</xref>); however, <italic>FUL</italic> up-regulation was less apparent than in <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants. Although the expression of <italic>FUL</italic> was increased in the shoot apical region, this increase seemed to be insufficient to accelerate flowering in <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3E</xref>). The results of these expression analyses demonstrate that the flowering of <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants, which showed stronger up-regulation of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> in the leaf, was less sensitive to changes in ambient temperature. Thus, together with the down-regulation of <italic>SPL3</italic> in the leaf of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), these results suggest that the regulation of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> by <italic>SPL3</italic> in the leaf is important for ambient temperature-responsive flowering.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> Plants Show Ambient Temperature-Insensitive Flowering Similar to <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> Plants</title><p>Analyzing a loss-of-function allele of miR156 is a prerequisite to study miR156&#x2019;s function, but obtaining a complete knockout allele of miR156 is very difficult because miR156 is generated from eight loci in the Arabidopsis genome. Thus, we analyzed the flowering phenotype of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Franco-Zorrilla et al., 2007</xref>) in which miR156 activity is reduced via target mimicry. <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants were early flowering at both 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C (8.0 and 12.8 leaves, respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). The leaf number ratio of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants was 1.6 (compare wild-type plants &#x003D; 2.0), indicating that the flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants was less sensitive to changes in ambient temperatures, as seen with <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3E</xref>). The bolting time of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants at 23&#x00B0;C (24.7 d) and 16&#x00B0;C (48.5 d) was similar to that of wild-type plants (24 and 49.7 d at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C, respectively; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>), indicating that leaf initiation rates were reduced in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants regardless of the ambient temperature. Fewer juvenile leaves were produced in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants (4.8 and 6.3 leaves at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C, respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>), implying that the reduction in miR156 activity accelerated phase transition, which was also seen in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants was less ambient temperature sensitive in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions. A, Accelerated flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants at 16&#x00B0;C in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions. Photographs were taken when <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants flowered at each temperature. B, The leaf morphologies of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants. An inverted triangle indicates the juvenile-to-adult transition point based on the appearance of abaxial trichomes. C and D, Relative expression levels of <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants grown for 8 d (C) and at DS1.02 (D) determined via <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR. Expression levels of each <italic>SPL</italic> gene at 23&#x00B0;C were set to one. E and F, Expression of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> in whole seedlings of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants grown for 8 d (E) and at DS1.02 (F). G, Expression of the <italic>SPL3</italic> gene in 8-d-old wild-type (WT), <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic>, <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>, and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants. Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc>. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_192369_wc_f4" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>In <italic>35S::MIM156</italic> plants grown for 8 d and at DS1.02, a general up-regulation of <italic>SPL</italic> genes was observed at both 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, C and D</xref>). In particular, the increase in <italic>SPL3</italic> expression was more obvious than that of the other <italic>SPL</italic> genes at both temperatures, which is consistent with the notion that <italic>SPL3</italic> is a major target of miR156 in plant responses to ambient temperature changes. The expression levels of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> were also analyzed in 8-d-old-seedlings of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants. <italic>FUL</italic> expression was up-regulated at both temperatures, whereas <italic>FT</italic> expression was not obviously altered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4E</xref>), consistent with the reduction in leaf initiation rate observed in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants. However, expression analysis of seedlings at DS1.02 revealed that <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> expression levels were apparently up-regulated (by at least 1.7-fold; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4F</xref>). These results together with the up-regulation of <italic>SPL3</italic> in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants support the concept that alterations in <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> expression by the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module affect ambient temperature-responsive flowering.</p><p>Because <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants were less insensitive to changes in ambient temperature than <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figs. 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4A</xref>), we analyzed the differences in <italic>SPL3</italic> up-regulation in the transgenic plants used in this study. <italic>SPL3</italic> expression was lower in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants than in <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4G</xref>), indicating that the expression level of <italic>SPL3</italic> in each transgenic line was largely consistent with the respective ambient temperature-insensitive flowering phenotype. Although <italic>SPL3</italic> up-regulation in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants was lower than that in <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants, flowering times were similar in both, suggesting the possibility that other <italic>SPL</italic> genes that have different functions were also derepressed and contributed to the phenotype of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants. Taken together, these results suggest that a reduction in miR156 activity via target mimicry affects flowering time in response to the ambient temperature.</p></sec><sec><title>The Limited Role of <italic>FUL</italic> in Ambient Temperature-Responsive Flowering</title><p>Because loss-of-function mutants of <italic>AP1</italic> and <italic>LFY</italic>, the direct targets of SPL3 protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Yamaguchi et al., 2009</xref>), showed ambient temperature-responsive flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2007</xref>) and <italic>FUL</italic> expression was significantly altered in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;), and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref>), the hypothesis that <italic>FUL</italic> functions in ambient temperature-responsive flowering was tested by analyzing the phenotypes of the gain- and loss-of-<italic>FUL</italic> function alleles. Flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FUL</italic> plants was delayed at 16&#x00B0;C (leaf number ratio &#x003D; 1.7; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>), which was in sharp contrast to the almost identical leaf numbers produced at both temperatures in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants (leaf number ratio &#x003D; 1.1). Flowering of <italic>ful</italic>-<italic>8</italic>, an RNA-null allele newly identified in this study (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S11</ext-link>), and <italic>ful</italic>-<italic>2</italic> mutants was normally delayed at 16&#x00B0;C (leaf number ratio &#x003D; 1.9 and 2.0, respectively), indicating that <italic>ful</italic> mutants normally responded to ambient temperature changes.</p><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><italic>FUL</italic> plays a limited role in ambient temperature-responsive flowering in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions. A, Total leaf numbers of gain- and loss-of-function alleles of <italic>FUL</italic> grown at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C. <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic>, <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>FT</italic>, and <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants were used as controls. Numbers listed above the genotypes denote the leaf number ratio. B, Total leaf numbers of <italic>ful</italic>-<italic>8</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;), and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) <italic>ful</italic>-<italic>8</italic> plants grown at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C. C and D, The effect of the <italic>FUL</italic> mutation on <italic>FT</italic> expression in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants grown for 8 d (C) and at DS1.02 (D). The <italic>FT</italic> expression levels in wild-type (WT) plants at 23&#x00B0;C were set to one. Error bars indicate <sc>sd</sc>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_192369_gs_f5" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Leaf numbers of plants that misexpressed <italic>FUL</italic> in the phloem or in the shoot apex were also measured. <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>FUL</italic> plants showed slightly earlier flowering than wild-type plants at both temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>). The leaf number ratio of <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>FUL</italic> plants (1.8) was similar to that of wild-type plants (1.9). In contrast, <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants produced almost identical numbers of leaves at both temperatures (leaf number ratio &#x003D; 1.2), which suggests that the misexpression of <italic>FT</italic> in the phloem is sufficient to cause ambient temperature-insensitive flowering. Flowering of <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>FUL</italic> plants was normally delayed at 16&#x00B0;C (leaf number ratio &#x003D; 2.2). The leaf number ratio of <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants was slightly decreased (1.5), which suggests that <italic>FT</italic> misexpression in the shoot apex is insufficient to cause ambient temperature-insensitive flowering. These results indicated that gain- or loss-of <italic>FUL</italic> function mutations or those of its mistargeting alleles did not result in an ambient temperature-insensitive flowering phenotype, which suggests that <italic>FUL</italic> does not play a major role in ambient temperature-responsive flowering.</p><p>A <italic>ful</italic> mutation was introduced into <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants to test whether the loss of <italic>FUL</italic> activity alters the ambient temperature-insensitive flowering phenotype seen in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants. The leaf number ratio of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) <italic>ful</italic>-<italic>8</italic> plants was slightly higher than that of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants (1.5 versus 1.3; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>), which indicates that the <italic>ful</italic> mutation did not mask the ambient temperature-insensitive flowering phenotype of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants. Expression analysis to test the effect of the <italic>ful</italic> mutation on <italic>FT</italic> up-regulation in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) <italic>ful</italic>-<italic>8</italic> plants revealed that the up-regulation of <italic>FT</italic> was not altered in the leaves of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) <italic>ful</italic>-<italic>8</italic> plants at both temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, C and D</xref>). The observation that a lesion in <italic>FUL</italic> did not greatly affect the temperature-responsive flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants suggests that <italic>FUL</italic> has only a limited role in ambient temperature-insensitive flowering.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>FT</italic> Acts Downstream of miR156 and <italic>SPL3</italic></title><p>We then tested the hypothesis that <italic>FT</italic> functions downstream of the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module. miR156 levels were found to be unaffected in both <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> and <italic>ft</italic>-<italic>10</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>) and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x002B;) and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>) at both temperatures. <italic>SPL3</italic> expression levels were similar in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> and <italic>ft</italic>-<italic>10</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6C</xref>). However, the vasculature-specific expression of <italic>FT</italic> was notably increased in the cotyledons and distal regions of true leaves of 10- and 12-d-old <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6D</xref>). In contrast, <italic>FT</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> expression was greatly reduced in the cotyledons and leaves of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants. The altered expression levels of <italic>FT</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> were confirmed by using the 4-methyl umbelliferyl glucuronide assay (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S12</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><italic>FT</italic> acts downstream of miR156 and <italic>SPL3</italic>. A and B, Expression of miR156 in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> and <italic>ft</italic>-<italic>10</italic> plants (A) and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x002B;) and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants (B) at DS1.02 grown at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C. U6 RNA served as a loading control in these small RNA blots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Yoo et al., 2011</xref>) and the miR156 expression level in wild-type (WT) plants at 23&#x00B0;C were set to one. C, Relative expression levels of <italic>SPL3</italic> in the leaves and the shoot apical regions (SA) of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> and <italic>ft</italic>-<italic>10</italic> plants grown at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C. D, <italic>FT</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity in the cotyledon of 10- and 12-d-old <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants grown on soil at 23&#x00B0;C. Inset shows <italic>FT</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> staining of the leaf. E, Phenotype of <italic>GVG</italic>-<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants and expression of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> of 8-d-old <italic>GVG</italic>-<italic>rSPL3</italic> seedlings after DEX induction. Mock-treated (left) and 30 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> DEX-treated (right) <italic>GVG</italic>-<italic>rSPL3</italic> seedlings grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions were photographed. The <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> expression level was measured 1 d after DEX treatment. Error bars indicate the <sc>sd</sc>. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_192369_wc_f6" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>To determine the induction pattern of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic>, we analyzed <italic>GVG</italic>-<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants in which <italic>rSPL3</italic> transcription was under the control of a dexamethasone (DEX)-inducible promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aoyama and Chua, 1997</xref>). Treatment with DEX induced an early flowering phenotype at 23&#x00B0;C (6.4 leaves; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6E</xref>), similar to that seen in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants, suggesting that the DEX-induced <italic>rSPL3</italic> gene is functional. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR analysis using two independent <italic>GVG</italic>-<italic>rSPL3</italic> lines (numbers 8 and 11) showed that the induction of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> expression began 5 h after the DEX treatment (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S13</ext-link>) and that their levels had increased by 2- to 3-fold 1 d after DEX treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6E</xref>), indicating that induction pattern of <italic>FT</italic> was similar to that of <italic>FUL</italic>. These induction patterns of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> suggest that <italic>SPL3</italic> regulates both <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Genetic Relationship of miR156, <italic>SPL3</italic>, and <italic>FT</italic></title><p>To analyze genetic epistasis between miR156 and <italic>FT</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants were crossed with <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants. <italic>FT</italic> overexpression almost completely suppressed the late flowering phenotype of miR156-overexpressing plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7A</xref>). Moreover, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b 35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants flowered with similar leaf numbers at both 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C (leaf number ratio &#x003D; 1.0). This indicated that <italic>FT</italic> overexpression fully suppressed ambient temperature-sensitive flowering in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants. A significant decrease in miR156 or <italic>FT</italic> expression was not found in these plants, excluding the possibility that gene silencing had occurred (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S14</ext-link>A). We next explored whether the mistargeting of <italic>FT</italic> expression in both the leaf and the shoot apex suppresses the effect of miR156 on flowering. The <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b SUC2</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants flowered with similar leaf numbers as <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants (leaf number ratio &#x003D; 1.3 versus 1.2; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7A</xref>). However, although <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b FD</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants showed early flowering similar to <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants, their leaf number ratio was 1.9, which indicated that their flowering at 16&#x00B0;C was normally delayed. These analyses indicated that <italic>FT</italic> misexpression in the phloem in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants more efficiently led to ambient temperature-insensitive flowering than did <italic>FT</italic> misexpression in the shoot apex. These data suggest that the action of <italic>FT</italic> in ambient temperature-responsive flowering lies downstream of miR156 in the leaf.</p><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Flowering phenotypes of various alleles generated by using <italic>FT</italic> misexpressing lines and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>amiR</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> lines. Total leaf numbers (A and B) of mutants generated by crossing various <italic>FT</italic> alleles with <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) or <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants. Total leaf numbers of F1 progeny grown at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions are presented. Numbers listed above the genotypes denote the leaf number ratio. A plus sign (&#x002B;) indicates a wild-type (WT) background. Error bars indicate <sc>sd</sc>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_192369_lw_f7" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>The effect of the inhibition of <italic>FT</italic> mRNA expression on the ambient temperature-insensitive flowering phenotype caused by <italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) was then assessed by using an artificial <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref> (<italic>amiR</italic>-<italic>FT</italic>) expressed in the leaf or the shoot apex. The <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>amiR</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> plants flowered later than <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants at both 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>), which indicates that <italic>amiR</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> expression driven by the <italic>SUC2</italic> promoter partially suppressed the early flowering of the <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants. Importantly, the leaf number ratio of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>amiR</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> plants was similar to that of <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>amiR</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> plants, which indicates that <italic>amiR</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> misexpression to the phloem suppressed the effect of <italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;). This suppressive effect was also observed in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) <italic>ft</italic>-<italic>10</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). Collectively, the results of the genetic analysis suggest that <italic>FT</italic> is a major output of the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module in the leaf associated with ambient temperature-responsive flowering.</p></sec><sec><title>Direct Binding of SPL3 Protein to the <italic>FT</italic> Locus in Vivo</title><p>SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN box transcription factors are DNA-binding proteins that recognize the GTAC core motif in their target genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Birkenbihl et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Liang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Yamasaki et al., 2009</xref>). To test the possibility that SPL3 protein directly regulates <italic>FT</italic> expression, chromatin immunoprecipitation (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ChIP</xref>) experiments were performed using <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> plants and anticMyc antibody, because our SPL3 antibodies were not suitable for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ChIP</xref> (data not shown). The <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> plants flowered with similar leaf numbers at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C (leaf number ratio &#x003D; 1.3; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>), a phenotype similar to that of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants, suggesting that the cMyc-tagged rSPL3 protein is functional. Western-blot analysis confirmed the overproduction of the cMyc-tagged rSPL3 protein in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig8"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>The SPL3 protein binds to the regulatory region of <italic>FT</italic> in vivo. A, Phenotype and total leaf numbers of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> plants grown at 23&#x00B0;C in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions. Photographs were taken when <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> plants flowered. B, SPL3-cMyc protein expression in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> plants. AnticMyc antibody was used to detect SPL3-cMyc protein. C, Schematic diagram of the <italic>FT</italic> genomic region. Black boxes and thin lines represent exons and introns, respectively. Asterisks indicate the presence of a predicted GTAC core recognition sequence. Gray horizontal bars denote the amplified fragments in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ChIP</xref>-qPCR: region I (&#x2212;2,876 to &#x2212;2494, relative to the translational start codon of <italic>FT</italic>); region II (&#x2212;1,874 to &#x2212;1,649); region III (&#x2212;291 to &#x2212;2); region IV (&#x002B;158 to &#x002B;416); region V (&#x002B;1,196 to &#x002B;1,560); and region VI (&#x002B;2,449 to &#x002B;2,873). D, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ChIP</xref>-qPCR analysis of <italic>FT</italic> genomic fragments in 10-d-old wild-type (WT) and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> seedlings. Relative enrichment of fragments was calculated by comparing samples immunoprecipitated with HA and cMyc antibodies. E, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ChIP</xref>-qPCR analysis of <italic>FT</italic> genomic fragments in 10-d-old WT and two independent <italic>SPL3</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> seedlings. Error bars indicate <sc>sd</sc>. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_192369_wc_f8" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Five regions (the upstream promoter region [I, II, and III], the second intron [V], and the 3&#x2032; region [VI]) containing GTAC motifs, the putative binding sites for SPL3 proteins, of the <italic>FT</italic> locus were explored (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8C</xref>). A region (IV) within the first intron and lacking a GTAC motif was used as a negative control. The SPL3 protein was strongly enriched in region III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8D</xref>). Weak SPL3 enrichment was observed in regions II and V. However, significant SPL3 protein enrichment was not observed in region I, which is distally located, or in regions IV and VI. These results suggest that <italic>FT</italic> is a direct target of the SPL3 protein.</p><p>Because the ectopic expression of <italic>SPL3</italic> driven by the <italic>35S</italic> promoter may cause potential artifacts, we generated and analyzed <italic>SPL3</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> plants. Most of the <italic>SPL3</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> plants flowered much earlier than wild-type plants in the T1 generation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S15</ext-link>), indicating that the <italic>SPL3</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> construct was indeed functional. Strong enrichment of SPL3 protein was found in region III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8E</xref>), which contains two consensus SPL3-binding motifs. Because SPL3 prefers cGTAC or GTACg core sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Birkenbihl et al., 2005</xref>), the first of these motifs likely fits the preferential SPL3-binding site. Weak SPL3 enrichment was observed in region II. The relative binding strength was weaker in <italic>SPL3</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> plants than in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> plants, suggesting that these differences may be due to the different SPL3 protein levels. The results of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ChIP</xref>-qPCR analyses using <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> and <italic>SPL3</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8, D and E</xref>) indicate that the SPL3 protein preferentially bound to region III in the <italic>FT</italic> genomic loci. Collectively, they suggest that SPL3 regulates <italic>FT</italic> expression via directly binding to the GTAC motifs in the <italic>FT</italic> genomic loci for the regulation of ambient temperature-responsive flowering.</p></sec><sec><title>Genetic Interactions between the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> Module and Other Components Involved in Ambient Temperature-Responsive Flowering</title><p>Because miR172 is another ambient temperature-responsive <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref> and its overexpression leads to ambient temperature-insensitive flowering through the up-regulation of <italic>FT</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lee et al., 2010</xref>), the genetic interaction between miR172 and the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module was investigated. Late flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants was strongly, but not completely, suppressed by miR172 overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9A</xref>). <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b 35S</italic>::<italic>MIR172a</italic> plants flowered with 8.4 and 13.4 leaves at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C, respectively. The leaf number ratio of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b 35S</italic>::<italic>MIR172a</italic> plants was greater than that of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR172a</italic> plants (1.6 versus 1.1). Gene silencing was not observed in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b 35S</italic>::<italic>MIR172a</italic> plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S14</ext-link>B). The number of leaves produced in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR172a</italic> plants (3.8 and 5.3 leaves at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C, respectively) was lower than the number of leaves produced by their parental lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9A</xref>) but the leaf number ratio was similar to that of their parental lines (1.4 versus 1.3). These genetic data suggest that the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module acts, at least partially, in parallel with the miR172 pathway in the regulation of ambient temperature-responsive flowering.</p><fig id="fig9"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Genetic interactions among miR156, <italic>SPL3</italic>, and other components involved in ambient temperature-responsive flowering. A, Total leaf numbers of F1 progeny grown at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions are shown. Numbers listed above the genotypes denote the leaf number ratio. B and C, Expression of miR156 (B) and <italic>SPL3</italic> (C) in 8-d-old seedlings of <italic>svp</italic>-<italic>32</italic>, <italic>elf3</italic>-<italic>1</italic>, and <italic>tfl1</italic>-<italic>20</italic> mutants grown at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions. The miR156 expression level in wild-type (WT) plants at 23&#x00B0;C were set to one. Error bars indicate <sc>sd</sc>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_192369_gs_f9" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>It was reported that <italic>SVP</italic>, <italic>TFL1</italic>, and <italic>ELF3</italic> play roles in the flowering response to changes in ambient temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lee et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Strasser et al., 2009</xref>). To test whether the expression of miR156 and <italic>SPL3</italic> is regulated by these genes, we analyzed miR156 and <italic>SPL3</italic> expression levels in <italic>svp</italic>-<italic>32</italic>, <italic>tfl1</italic>-<italic>20</italic>, and <italic>elf3</italic>-<italic>1</italic> mutants. No dramatic alteration in miR156 and <italic>SPL3</italic> expression was observed in these mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figs. 9, B and C</xref>). These results suggest that the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module may act independently of other components in ambient temperature-responsive flowering.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Although periodic temperature changes, both diurnal and seasonal, provide important information for the optimal timing of flowering, little is known about the regulation of flowering time by small RNAs in response to changes in ambient temperature. In this study, we show that ambient temperature-responsive flowering in Arabidopsis is also mediated by the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> genetic circuitry.</p><sec><title><italic>FT</italic> Is a Main Output of the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> Module in the Leaf</title><p><italic>SPL3</italic> regulates the expression of <italic>FUL</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic> in the leaf and the shoot apex independently of the FT/FD complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al., 2009</xref>). However, the activity of <italic>SPL3</italic> appears to be predominant in the leaf, as <italic>SPL3</italic> mRNA is barely detected in vegetative shoot apices but is strongly induced in leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al., 2009</xref>). This study provides evidence that <italic>SPL3</italic> functions as a direct upstream activator of <italic>FT</italic> to modulate ambient temperature-responsive flowering. This conclusion is based on results showing the up-regulation of <italic>FT</italic> in the leaves of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>), the early up-regulation of <italic>FT</italic> in <italic>GVG</italic>-<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>), the epistatic interaction between <italic>SPL3</italic> and <italic>FT</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>), and the direct binding of the SPL3 protein to the <italic>FT</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). Our conclusion is consistent with the finding that the loss of <italic>FT</italic> function completely masks the early flowering phenotype of plants misexpressing <italic>SPL3</italic> in the phloem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>FD protein has been recently reported to bind to the G-box motifs in the <italic>SPL</italic> genomic loci (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Jung et al., 2012</xref>), suggesting that the <italic>FT</italic>-<italic>FD</italic> module regulates <italic>SPL</italic> genes in the shoot apex in the control of flowering time. This hypothesis is supported by our observation that <italic>SPL3</italic> expression was increased in the shoot apex regions of <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants, but remained unchanged in the leaves of <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S16</ext-link>). However, <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> and <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants still showed ambient temperature-responsive flowering (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figs. 3E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7A</xref>) compared with <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> and <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants. Also, <italic>SPL3</italic> expression was increased in the shoot apex regions of <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants only at 23&#x00B0;C (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S16</ext-link>). Thus, it is likely that the regulation of <italic>SPL3</italic> via <italic>FT</italic>-<italic>FD</italic> modules at the shoot apex region does not affect ambient temperature-responsive flowering.</p><p>Because <italic>FUL</italic> expression was more dramatically affected by the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module than <italic>FT</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref>) and <italic>FUL</italic> represents another known direct target of the SPL3 protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Yamaguchi et al., 2009</xref>), an important question is whether <italic>FUL</italic> is a major factor in ambient temperature-responsive flowering. Several lines of evidence in this study suggest that, in contrast to <italic>FT</italic>, <italic>FUL</italic> is not important. First, mutants with altered <italic>FUL</italic> activity or misexpression of <italic>FUL</italic> retained ambient temperature-sensitive flowering, whereas plants constitutively expressing <italic>FT</italic> or misexpressing <italic>FT</italic> in the phloem exhibited ambient temperature-insensitive flowering (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). Second, early flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants was inhibited by <italic>amiR</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> misexpression to the phloem (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>), consistent with the observation that the early flowering of <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic> plants was suppressed by the <italic>ft</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al., 2009</xref>). Third, the <italic>ful</italic> mutation failed to suppress the ambient temperature-insensitive flowering of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). These findings suggested that the effects of ambient temperature on flowering via the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module are mediated primarily by <italic>FT</italic> action.</p><p>Because both <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> act downstream of <italic>SPL3</italic>, two possible interaction mechanisms can be considered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10</xref>). The first possibility is that <italic>SPL3</italic> controls two separate signaling pathways, namely the control of ambient temperature-responsive flowering by <italic>FT</italic> in the leaf, and the control of age-dependent flowering by <italic>FUL</italic> at the shoot apex. In this case, targets of <italic>FT</italic> other than <italic>FUL</italic> are likely to be relevant in ambient temperature-responsive flowering. A second possibility is that <italic>FUL</italic> acts downstream of <italic>FT</italic>, and the regulation of ambient temperature-responsive flowering by <italic>SPL3</italic> is at least partially mediated by <italic>FUL</italic>. The role of <italic>FT</italic> upstream of <italic>FUL</italic> is consistent with the previous observation that the accumulation of <italic>FUL</italic> transcripts in the leaf is dependent on FT and FD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Teper-Bamnolker and Samach, 2005</xref>). Nevertheless, we cannot exclude the possibility that <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> cross-regulate one another in the leaf based both on our findings that <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) <italic>ful</italic>-<italic>8</italic> plants were only weakly temperature responsive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>) and the report of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al. (2009)</xref> that the early flowering phenotype of <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>FUL</italic> plants is completely suppressed by the <italic>ft</italic>-<italic>10</italic> mutation.</p><fig id="fig10"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>A model of flowering time regulation in response to different ambient temperatures. Changes in ambient temperature cause alterations in the expression of miR156, which negatively regulates <italic>SPL3.</italic> The SPL3 protein directly binds to <italic>FT</italic> to regulate ambient temperature-responsive flowering. Although <italic>FUL</italic> is another direct target of <italic>SPL3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Yamaguchi et al., 2009</xref>), it is unlikely to play an important role in ambient temperature-responsive flowering but is possibly important in age-dependent flowering. <italic>SPL9</italic> may act redundantly with <italic>SPL3</italic> in the regulation of ambient temperature-responsive flowering (see &#x201C;Discussion&#x201D;). The <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module and the miR172 pathway may act in parallel, although the genetic relationship between the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module and the target genes of miR172 is not clear. Arrows represent promotion effects, whereas T-bars indicate repression effects. Dotted lines indicate unclear interactions.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_192369_gs_f10" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The Effect of Low Temperature on Flowering Caused by miR156 Overexpression at 23&#x00B0;C May Be Attenuated by the Relatively Low Cleavage of <italic>SPL3</italic> via miR156 at 23&#x00B0;C</title><p>Because the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> module also serves as a regulatory mechanism involved in the control of ambient temperature-responsive flowering, an important question that needs to be answered is why <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> and <italic>35</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants showed contrasting temperature responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs. 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4A</xref>). Similar to the temperature response of gain and loss of function of <italic>FT</italic>, a major output gene within the thermosensory pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2007</xref>), the ambient temperature response was expected to either disappear or be reduced in its gain- and loss-of-function mutants of miR156. However, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants showed an increased temperature response due to more delayed flowering at a low temperature, with the delay in flowering being more profound at 16&#x00B0;C than at 23&#x00B0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). This result suggests that the effect of low temperature on flowering caused by the overexpression of miR156 at 23&#x00B0;C may be attenuated by the relatively low cleavage of <italic>SPL3</italic> via miR156 at 23&#x00B0;C. Our observation that the cleavage of <italic>SPL3</italic> by miR156 was strongly enhanced at 16&#x00B0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>) provides support for this notion. The differential <italic>FT</italic> expression seen in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic> plants at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C provides further support for this concept (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1D</xref>). However, we cannot exclude the possibility that increased or decreased miR156 activity at different ambient temperatures may induce differential responses.</p></sec><sec><title>Other <italic>SPL</italic> Genes May Act Redundantly with <italic>SPL3</italic> in the Regulation of Ambient Temperature-Responsive Flowering</title><p>If <italic>SPL3</italic> were to be the sole regulator of ambient temperature-responsive flowering, it would be expected that the ambient temperature response would either disappear or be reduced in <italic>spl3</italic> mutants. However, the <italic>spl3</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Ws</xref> background) that we tested still retained ambient temperature-responsive flowering. This is an apparent contradiction; however, we suggest that the phenotype of the <italic>spl3</italic> mutants should be interpreted with caution because they are not RNA and protein null and did show unexpected early flowering (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S8</ext-link>), which is contrary to its proposed function as a floral activator. This uncorrelated flowering phenotype may be due to its different genetic background. It is therefore difficult to infer <italic>SPL3</italic>&#x2019;s function from the allele. However, if the phenotype of the <italic>spl3</italic> mutants were indeed to be a reflection of its function, one possible explanation is that there may be a redundant player in ambient temperature-responsive flowering. One potential candidate is <italic>SPL5</italic>. Like <italic>SPL3</italic>, the <italic>SPL5</italic> gene is much smaller than other <italic>SPL</italic> genes and it encodes primarily the DNA-binding domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Wu and Poethig, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Guo et al., 2008</xref>). Although we have demonstrated that <italic>SPL5</italic> expression was greatly reduced at a low temperature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>) and that the cleavage products of <italic>SPL5</italic> at this low temperature were also increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>), we do not suggest that <italic>SPL5</italic> actually plays a role in ambient temperature-responsive flowering because the leaf number ratios of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL5</italic>(&#x002B;/&#x2212;) plants (1.7&#x2013;1.8) were similar to that of wild-type plants (2.0; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S17</ext-link>).</p><p>Another potential candidate redundant player in ambient temperature-responsive flowering is <italic>SPL9</italic>. <italic>SPL9</italic> controls flowering by directly regulating the expression of <italic>SOC1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Wang et al., 2009</xref>), a putative target within the thermosensory pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2007</xref>). <italic>SPL9</italic> expression was down-regulated and cleavage products of <italic>SPL9</italic> were enriched at 16&#x00B0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). The relationship between <italic>SPL3</italic> and <italic>SPL9</italic> is reminiscent of that between <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic>, the potential outputs within the thermosensory pathway. Although <italic>ft</italic> and <italic>soc1</italic> single mutants showed ambient temperature-responsive flowering, <italic>ft soc1</italic> double mutants showed an additive reduction in temperature sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2007</xref>). Considering that <italic>SPL3</italic> and <italic>SPL9</italic> regulate <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic>, respectively, it is possible that <italic>SPL3</italic> and <italic>SPL9</italic> act redundantly in ambient temperature-responsive flowering. Further investigation on whether the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL9</italic>-<italic>SOC1</italic> regulatory module also acts in ambient temperature-responsive flowering would provide a better understanding of flowering behavior of Arabidopsis at different ambient temperatures.</p></sec><sec><title>Possible Connections between the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> Module and the Thermosensory Pathway</title><p><italic>FCA</italic>, <italic>FVE</italic>, and <italic>SVP</italic> are known to play important roles within the thermosensory pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bl&#x00E1;zquez et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Fornara et al., 2010</xref>). <italic>ELF3</italic> and <italic>TFL1</italic> also function in ambient temperature signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Strasser et al., 2009</xref>). We recently showed that the loss of <italic>SVP</italic> activity modulates the expression level of miR172 and its target genes and that the overexpression of miR172 causes ambient temperature-insensitive flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lee et al., 2010</xref>). This suggests that <italic>SVP</italic> acts as a link between small RNA-mediated flowering control and the thermosensory pathway. However, the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module is unlikely to be regulated by <italic>SVP</italic> because the loss of <italic>SVP</italic> function does not alter the expression of miR156 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lee et al., 2010</xref>) and <italic>SPL</italic> genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S18</ext-link>). This reasoning is further supported by the observation that <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) plants showed a greater leaf number ratio value than <italic>svp</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2007</xref>). Furthermore, miR156 and <italic>SPL3</italic> expression was not significantly altered in <italic>elf3</italic> and <italic>tfl1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>). To further examine the genetic relationship between the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module and <italic>SVP</italic>/<italic>ELF3</italic>/<italic>TFL1</italic>, we are currently performing genetic interaction studies. Based on these results, we propose that the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> genetic circuitry plays a role in fine tuning ambient temperature-responsive flowering independently of <italic>SVP</italic>, <italic>ELF3</italic>, and <italic>TFL1</italic> function.</p><p>Whether the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module is integrated into the <italic>SVP</italic>-<italic>miR172</italic> regulatory circuit has yet to be determined. The possibility of this integration is supported by data showing the regulation of miR172 expression by miR156 in the control of developmental timing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Wu and Poethig, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Wang et al., 2011</xref>) and the strong anticorrelation in expression patterns of miR156 and miR172 at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lee et al., 2010</xref>). In this study, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b 35S</italic>::<italic>MIR172a</italic> plants showed ambient temperature-responsive flowering (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9</xref>), although the early flowering phenotype of <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;) <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR172a</italic> plants was additive. These results suggest that the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module and the miR172 pathway act in parallel in the regulation of ambient temperature-responsive flowering, although it was recently shown that the distinct role of miR156 and miR172 on the developmental transition is mediated by <italic>SPL3</italic>/<italic>4</italic>/<italic>5</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Jung et al., 2011</xref>). However, we cannot dismiss the possibility that the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module may be affected by a subset of miR172 target genes because <italic>SPL3</italic> expression was increased in <italic>toe1 toe2</italic> double mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Wu et al., 2009</xref>). Thus, further investigation is required to elucidate the mechanisms of interaction between the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module, miR172 targets, and the <italic>SVP</italic>-<italic>miR172</italic> regulatory pathway before they converge on <italic>FT</italic>.</p><p>In summary, we have shown that the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic> module controls <italic>FT</italic> expression to regulate ambient temperature-responsive flowering. Vernalization is distinct from other temperature-dependent flowering responses in that it is controlled by a pathway that requires <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS C</italic>, which appears to be crucifer specific (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Amasino and Michaels, 2010</xref>). However, in evolutionary terms, miR156 is a highly conserved <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref>, and its interaction with SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN box genes has an ancient origin in land plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Arazi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Riese et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Willmann and Poethig, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Guo et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Wu et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Gou et al., 2011</xref>). Thus, it is possible that the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> genetic circuitry functions in a diverse array of flowering plants. It will be informative and challenging to determine whether the function of the <italic>miR156</italic>-<italic>SPL3</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> genetic circuitry in ambient temperature-responsive flowering is widely conserved.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Plant Materials and Growth Conditions</title><p>All of the mutants used in this study were in the Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>; Columbia) background, except for <italic>spl3</italic> (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Ws</xref>). <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;), <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x002B;), <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic>, <italic>FT</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic>, <italic>ful</italic>-<italic>2</italic>, <italic>ft</italic>-<italic>10</italic>, <italic>tsf</italic>-<italic>1</italic>, <italic>soc1</italic>-<italic>2</italic>, and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR172a</italic> have been described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Ferr&#x00E1;ndiz et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Takada and Goto, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Yoo et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Gandikota et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lee et al., 2010</xref>). The <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>, <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FUL</italic>, <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>FUL</italic>, <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>FUL</italic>, and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Schwab et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Franco-Zorrilla et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Wang et al., 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">2009</xref>) were kindly provided by Dr. Weigel (Max Planck Institute). <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>FT</italic>, <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>FT</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>amiR</italic>-<italic>FT</italic>, <italic>SUC2</italic>::<italic>amiR</italic>-<italic>FT</italic>, and <italic>FD</italic>::<italic>amiR</italic>-<italic>FT</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Mathieu et al., 2007</xref>) were kind gifts from Dr. Schmid (Max Planck Institute). SAIL_726_E08 (<italic>ful</italic>-<italic>8</italic>) was obtained from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">McElver et al., 2001</xref>). Plants were grown in soil or Murashige and Skoog medium at 23&#x00B0;C or 16&#x00B0;C in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">LD</xref> conditions (16-h light/8-h dark) at a light intensity of 120 &#x03BC;mol m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>.</p><p>Flowering time was measured by scoring either total leaf number (at least 10 plants) or bolting days, which was recorded when the primary inflorescence had reached a height of 0.5 cm. The leaf number ratio (16&#x00B0;C/23&#x00B0;C) was used as an indicator of ambient temperature-sensitive flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bl&#x00E1;zquez et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; i.e. a completely ambient temperature-insensitive plant produces an identical total number of leaves at both 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C; thus, its leaf number ratio is 1.0). Because <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIR156b</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SPL3</italic>(&#x2212;), and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>MIM156</italic> plants exhibited high or low leaf initiation rates, with altered flowering time at 16&#x00B0;C, we used the leaf number ratio to describe their temperature responses.</p></sec><sec><title>Transgenic Plants</title><p>To generate <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> and <italic>GVG</italic>-<italic>rSPL3</italic>, the coding region of <italic>SPL3</italic> was amplified by PCR and cloned into a vector that contained the <italic>35S</italic> promoter and a cMyc tag and into a pTA7002 vector, respectively. The pTA7002 vector used in this study is a transcriptional activation system of the target gene, in which an artificial transcription factor (GAL4-VP16-GR) induced by DEX transcriptionally activates the target gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aoyama and Chua, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Xie et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Desvoyes et al., 2006</xref>). To construct <italic>SPL3</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic>, we replaced the <italic>35S</italic> promoter in <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> construct with the endogenous 2.4-kb <italic>SPL3</italic> promoter. Oligonucleotide primers used for cloning are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>. Plants were transformed using the floral-dip method with minor modifications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Weigel and Glazebrook, 2002</xref>) and transformants were selected for kanamycin, hygromycin, or BASTA resistance. At least 30 T1 seedlings were analyzed for each construct.</p></sec><sec><title>Expression Analysis</title><p>To determine gene expression levels via <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR, total RNA was isolated from transgenic lines at DS1.02 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Boyes et al., 2001</xref>), unless otherwise noted, at which wild-type plants remained in the vegetative phase. Seedlings at this morphologically defined growth stage were used to compare gene expression levels due to the possibility that the degree of maturation of these plants may differ at different ambient temperatures based on their altered plastochron length (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). RNA quality was determined by using a Nanodrop ND-2000 spectrophotometer (Nanodrop Technologies) and only qualified RNA samples (A260/A230 &gt; 2.0 and A260/A280 &gt; 1.8) were used for subsequent <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR experiments. To remove possible DNA contamination, RNA samples were treated with DNaseI (NEB) for 60 min at 37&#x00B0;C. A sample of 1 &#x03BC;g of RNA was used for cDNA synthesis using the transcriptor first-strand cDNA synthesis kit (Roche Diagnostics). The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR primers were designed using SciTools at Integrated DNA Technologies (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.idtdna.com">http://www.idtdna.com</ext-link>) with the criteria of a Tm of 62&#x00B0;C &#x00B1; 0.5&#x00B0;C. Specific amplification was confirmed by running PCR products in a 12% polyacrylamide gel. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR analysis was carried out in 384-well plates with a LightCycler 480 (Roche Applied Science) using SYBR green. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR experiments were carried out using KAPA SYBR green master mixture (KAPA Biosystems Inc.). The following program was used for amplification: predenaturation for 3 min at 94&#x00B0;C, followed by 40 cycles of denaturation for 10 s at 94&#x00B0;C, annealing for 10 s at 60&#x00B0;C, and elongation for 10 s at 72&#x00B0;C. Melting curve analysis was performed from 65&#x00B0;C to 97&#x00B0;C to assess the specificity of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR products. For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR analysis, the 11 golden rules for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR were followed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Udvardi et al., 2008</xref>) to ensure reproducible and accurate measurement of transcript levels. Samples for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR were harvested at Zeitgeber time 8, unless otherwise noted. Two reference genes (either AT1G13320/AT2G28390 or AT1G13320/AT4G27960) that are stably expressed at 23&#x00B0;C and 16&#x00B0;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Hong et al., 2010</xref>) were used for quantification. All <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR experiments were carried out in two or three biological replicates (independently harvested samples on different days) with three technical triplicates each with similar results. The results from a biological replicate are shown and the results from other biological replicates are shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Figure S19</ext-link>. Oligonucleotide primers used in this study are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>.</p><p>For western-blot analysis, anti-SPL3 antibodies were raised against a synthetic peptide corresponding to residues 39 to 52 of SPL3 (LEKKQKGKATSSSG), which showed low (14%) similarity to the corresponding regions of SPL4 and SPL5 proteins. Anti-SPL3 antisera were purified using an affinity column immobilized with SPL3 peptides. Total protein extracts were prepared from 10-d-old seedlings and western-blot analysis was performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sambrook et al., 1989</xref>). The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">miRNA</xref> northern blots were processed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lee et al., 2010</xref>). GUS staining was carried out according to standard procedures using 10-d-old seedlings grown on soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Lee et al., 2007</xref>). The 4-methyl umbelliferyl glucuronide assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bl&#x00E1;zquez et al., 1997</xref>) was used to quantify GUS activity. This assay was carried out in triplicate.</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of the Relative Abundance of Transcripts</title><p>Our detailed procedure has been published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Hong et al., 2010</xref>). Threshold cycle (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Ct</xref>) and PCR efficiency of the primers used were calculated using LinRegPCR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Ramakers et al., 2003</xref>). The relative abundance of the transcripts was calculated by the statistical formula from the geNorm. From three technical replicates, the coefficient of variation (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Cv</xref>) was calculated according to the following formula: <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Cv</xref> &#x003D; 100 &#x00D7; (<sc>sd</sc> of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Ct</xref>/average of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Ct</xref>). The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Ct</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Cv</xref> values of each sample were then examined. If a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">Cv</xref> value in a sample was &gt;2.0%, which indicated that there was a reaction that deviated most significantly from the mean in three technical replicates, it was considered an outlier and was thus excluded from further analyses. The gene expression level of wild-type plants at each temperature was set to one to show the effect of a mutation at different ambient temperatures. A &gt;2-fold down-regulation was considered significant.</p></sec><sec><title>RLM 5&#x2032;-RACE</title><p>A modified procedure for RLM 5&#x2032;-RACE was performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Llave et al., 2002</xref>). Total RNA was prepared from 10-d-old seedlings using a Nucleospin RNA extraction kit (Marchery Nargel). RNA was ligated to the RNA oligo-adaptor with T4 RNA ligase. The oligo(dT) primer was used to prime cDNA synthesis with SuperScript III reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen). PCR amplification was performed with a GeneRacer 5&#x2032; primer and a gene-specific 3&#x2032; primer. Two rounds of nested PCR were done using two sets of RACE adaptors and gene-specific primers. For semiquantitative measurement, the RLM 5&#x2032;-RACE products were separated and hybridized with the probes specific to the 5&#x2032;-RACE adapter sequence for <italic>SPL</italic> genes and <italic>UBQ10</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ChIP</xref></title><p>One gram of 10-d-old <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> or <italic>SPL3</italic>::<italic>rSPL3</italic>-<italic>cMyc</italic> seedlings grown on soil was cross-linked in 1% formaldehyde solution on ice using vacuum infiltration. Nuclear extracts were isolated and an immunoprecipitation assay was conducted as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Saleh et al., 2008</xref>). After shearing chromatin via sonication, mouse anti-cMyc or anti-HA polyclonal antibodies (about 5 &#x03BC;g; Santa Cruz Biotechnology) were used to immunoprecipitate genomic DNA fragments. DNA (1 &#x03BC;L) recovered from immunoprecipitation or 10% input DNA was used for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">qRT</xref>-PCR. The relative enrichment of each fragment was calculated by the &#x0394;&#x0394;C<sub>t</sub> method as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Livak and Schmittgen, 2001</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">ChIP</xref> experiments were performed in biological triplicates and results from one biological replicate were presented. The results from other biological replicates are shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1">Supplemental Figure S19</ext-link>.</p><p>Arabidopsis Genome Initiative gene identifiers were as follows: <italic>AP1</italic> (AT1G69120); <italic>CUC2</italic> (AT5G53950); <italic>FD</italic> (AT4G35900); <italic>FT</italic> (AT1G65480); <italic>FUL</italic> (AT5G60910); <italic>LFY</italic> (AT5G61850); <italic>PP2AA3</italic> (AT1G13320); SAND family protein (AT2G28390); <italic>SOC1</italic> (AT2G45660); <italic>SPL2</italic> (AT5G43270); <italic>SPL3</italic> (AT2G33810); <italic>SPL4</italic> (AT1G53160); <italic>SPL5</italic> (AT3G15270); <italic>SPL6</italic> (AT1G69170); <italic>SPL9</italic> (AT2G42200); <italic>SPL10</italic> (AT1G27370); <italic>SPL11</italic> (AT1G27360); <italic>SPL13</italic> (AT5G50670); <italic>SPL15</italic> (AT3G57920); <italic>SUC2</italic> (AT1G22710); small nuclear RNA U6-1 (AT3G14735); <italic>TCP4</italic> (AT3G15030); <italic>TSF</italic> (AT4G20370); miR156b (AT4G30972); miR172a (AT2G28056); and <italic>UBC9</italic> (AT4G27960).</p></sec><sec><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> Confirmation of the overexpression of miR156 in transgenic plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> Total leaf numbers of wild-type plants grown in short days.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S3.</bold></ext-link> Plastochron length of <italic>35S::MIR156b</italic>, <italic>35S::SPL3</italic>(&#x002B;/&#x2212;), and <italic>35S::MIM156</italic> plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S4.</bold></ext-link> Expression of mature miR156 in the leaves and the shoot apices.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S5.</bold></ext-link> Validation of sample preparation.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S6.</bold></ext-link> Expression of <italic>TSF</italic> and <italic>SOC1</italic> in 8-d-old seedlings.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S7.</bold></ext-link> Unaltered cytosine methylation patterns at the <italic>SPL3</italic> locus.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S8.</bold></ext-link> Characterization of <italic>spl3</italic> mutant plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S9.</bold></ext-link> Characterization of <italic>35S::SPL3</italic>(&#x002B;/&#x2212;) plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S10.</bold></ext-link> <italic>FD</italic> and <italic>SUC2</italic> expression in wild-type plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S11.</bold></ext-link> Characterization of <italic>ful-8</italic> allele.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S12.</bold></ext-link> Measurement of GUS activity.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S13.</bold></ext-link> Expression analysis of <italic>FT</italic> and <italic>FUL</italic> in <italic>GVG-rSPL3</italic> plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S14.</bold></ext-link> Expression analysis in double mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S15.</bold></ext-link> Distribution of total leaf numbers of wild-type and <italic>SPL3::SPL3-cMyc</italic> plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S16.</bold></ext-link> Expression of <italic>SPL3</italic> gene in <italic>SUC2::FT</italic> and <italic>FD::FT</italic> plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S17.</bold></ext-link> Ambient temperature-sensitive flowering of <italic>35S::SPL5</italic>(&#x002B;/&#x2212;) plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S18.</bold></ext-link> Expression of <italic>SPL</italic> genes in 8-d-old <italic>svp-32</italic> plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S19.</bold></ext-link> Results of biological replicates in the text.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S1.</bold></ext-link> Flowering time of plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.111.192369/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S2.</bold></ext-link> List of oligonucleotide primers.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Drs. Nam-Hai Chua, Markus Schmid, Jia-Wei Wang, and Detlef Weigel for kindly providing important research materials. We thank Dr. Seong Jeon Yoo, Hyun Jung Cho, Kyung Eun Kim, Soo Hyun Kim, Hanna Lee, and Haeji Ahn for technical assistance.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The timing of flowering</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>154</volume>: <fpage>516</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>520</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aoyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A glucocorticoid-mediated transcriptional induction system in transgenic plants</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>612</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arazi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Talmor-Neiman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stav</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Riese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baulcombe</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Cloning and characterization of micro-RNAs from moss</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>837</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>848</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sureshkumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lempe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Potent induction of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> flowering by elevated growth temperature</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e106</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birkenbihl</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jach</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Functional dissection of the plant-specific SBP-domain: overlap of the DNA-binding and nuclear localization domains</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>352</volume>: <fpage>585</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>596</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E1;zquez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A thermosensory pathway controlling flowering time in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>171</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E1;zquez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Soowal</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>LEAFY expression and flower initiation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>3835</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3844</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyes</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zayed</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ascenzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McCaskill</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x00F6;rlach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Growth stage-based phenotypic analysis of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>: a model for high throughput functional genomics in plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1499</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1510</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambros</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Role of microRNAs in plant and animal development</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>301</volume>: <fpage>336</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>338</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A microRNA as a translational repressor of <italic>APETALA2</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower development</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>303</volume>: <fpage>2022</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2025</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbesier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Giakountis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrona</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gissot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>FT protein movement contributes to long-distance signaling in floral induction of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>316</volume>: <fpage>1030</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1033</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desvoyes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez-Parra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Cell type-specific role of the retinoblastoma/E2F pathway during Arabidopsis leaf development</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>80</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>MicroRNA regulation of gene expression in plants</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>512</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>520</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endrizzi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moussian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Haecker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The SHOOT MERISTEMLESS gene is required for maintenance of undifferentiated cells in Arabidopsis shoot and floral meristems and acts at a different regulatory level than the meristem genes WUSCHEL and ZWILLE</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>967</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>979</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferr&#x00E1;ndiz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Martienssen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Redundant regulation of meristem identity and plant architecture by <italic>FRUITFULL</italic>, <italic>APETALA1</italic> and <italic>CAULIFLOWER</italic></article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>725</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>734</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitter</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitter</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Rapid changes in flowering time in British plants</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>296</volume>: <fpage>1689</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1691</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>de Montaigu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>SnapShot: control of flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>141</volume>: <comment>550, 550.e1&#x2013;2</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franco-Zorrilla</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Valli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Todesco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mateos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Puga</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio-Somoza</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x00ED;a</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Paz-Ares</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Target mimicry provides a new mechanism for regulation of microRNA activity</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1033</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1037</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gandikota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Birkenbihl</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x00F6;hmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardon</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The miRNA156/157 recognition element in the 3&#x2032; UTR of the Arabidopsis SBP box gene <italic>SPL3</italic> prevents early flowering by translational inhibition in seedlings</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>683</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>693</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gou</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Felippes</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Negative regulation of anthocyanin biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> by a miR156-targeted SPL transcription factor</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1512</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1522</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide identification and evolutionary analysis of the plant specific SBP-box transcription factor family</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>418</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>8</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahn</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Identification and testing of superior reference genes for a starting pool of transcript normalization in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1694</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1706</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The SOC1-SPL module integrates photoperiod and gibberellic acid signals to control flowering time in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>577</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>588</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>miR172 signals are incorporated into the miR156 signaling pathway at the SPL3/4/5 genes in Arabidopsis developmental transitions</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>45</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kardailsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagenais</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Activation tagging of the floral inducer <italic>FT</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>1962</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1965</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiou</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The role of the miR399-PHO2 module in the regulation of flowering time in response to different ambient temperatures in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Mol Cells</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>88</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwabuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>A pair of related genes with antagonistic roles in mediating flowering signals</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>286</volume>: <fpage>1960</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1962</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigge</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>H2A.Z-containing nucleosomes mediate the thermosensory response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>136</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>147</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larue</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A microRNA-transcription factor module regulates lateral organ size and patterning in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>450</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>463</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The AGAMOUS-LIKE 20 MADS domain protein integrates floral inductive pathways in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2366</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2376</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genetic framework for flowering-time regulation by ambient temperature-responsive miRNAs in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>3081</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3093</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Ambient temperature signaling in plants: an emerging field in the regulation of flowering time</article-title>. <source>J Plant Biol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>326</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Role of <italic>SVP</italic> in the control of flowering time by ambient temperature in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>397</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>402</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenoir</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x00E9;gout</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquet</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>de Ruffray</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brisse</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A significant upward shift in plant species optimum elevation during the 20th century</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>320</volume>: <fpage>1768</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1771</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazarenus</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Identification of a consensus DNA-binding site for the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> SBP domain transcription factor, AtSPL14, and binding kinetics by surface plasmon resonance</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>3645</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3653</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>408</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Llave</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasschau</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Cleavage of <italic>Scarecrow</italic>-<italic>like</italic> mRNA targets directed by a class of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> miRNA</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>297</volume>: <fpage>2053</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2056</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallory</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaucheret</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Functions of microRNAs and related small RNAs in plants</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <comment>(Suppl)</comment> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>S31</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>S36</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Warthmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x00FC;ttner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Export of FT protein from phloem companion cells is sufficient for floral induction in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1055</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1060</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McElver</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzafrir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Aux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashby</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schetter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Cushman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Insertional mutagenesis of genes required for seed development in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>1751</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1763</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nodine</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>MicroRNAs prevent precocious gene expression and enable pattern formation during plant embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>2678</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2692</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palatnik</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Schommer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Control of leaf morphogenesis by microRNAs</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>425</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>263</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panchuk</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name><surname>Volkov</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x00F6;ffl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Heat stress- and heat shock transcription factor-dependent expression and activity of ascorbate peroxidase in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>838</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>853</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Temperature perception and signal transduction in plants</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>179</volume>: <fpage>615</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>628</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramakers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruijter</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Deprez</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Moorman</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Assumption-free analysis of quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) data</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source> <volume>339</volume>: <fpage>62</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>66</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x00F6;hmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;nster</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Comparative analysis of the SBP-box gene families in <italic>P. patens</italic> and seed plants</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>401</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>37</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez-Venegas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Avramova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>An efficient chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) protocol for studying histone modifications in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1018</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1025</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Onouchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ditta</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz-Sommer</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Distinct roles of CONSTANS target genes in reproductive development of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>288</volume>: <fpage>1613</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1616</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Sambrook J, Fritch EF, Maniatis T (1989) Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold Spring Harbor, NY</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Palatnik</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Riester</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schommer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Specific effects of microRNAs on the plant transcriptome</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>517</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>527</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grande</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bujdoso</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The microRNA regulated SBP-box genes <italic>SPL9</italic> and <italic>SPL15</italic> control shoot maturation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>195</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouse</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Finnegan</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The molecular basis of vernalization: the central role of <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS C</italic> (<italic>FLC</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>3753</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3758</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Environmental-dependent acceleration of a developmental switch: the floral transition</article-title>. <source>Sci STKE</source> <volume>2000</volume>: <fpage>pe1</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Califano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerd&#x00E1;n</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A complementary role for ELF3 and TFL1 in the regulation of flowering time by ambient temperature</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>640</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Terminal flower2, an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homolog of heterochromatin protein1, counteracts the activation of <italic>flowering locus T</italic> by constans in the vascular tissues of leaves to regulate flowering time</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2856</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2865</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teper-Bamnolker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Samach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The flowering integrator FT regulates <italic>SEPALLATA3</italic> and <italic>FRUITFULL</italic> accumulation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> leaves</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>2661</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2675</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Czechowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Eleven golden rules of quantitative RT-PCR</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1736</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1737</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Czech</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>miR156-regulated SPL transcription factors define an endogenous flowering pathway in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>738</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>749</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>miRNA control of vegetative phase change in trees</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002012</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Czech</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mica</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dual effects of miR156-targeted <italic>SPL</italic> genes and <italic>CYP78A5</italic>/<italic>KLUH</italic> on plastochron length and organ size in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1231</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1243</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Weigel D, Glazebrook J (2002) Arabidopsis: A Laboratory Manual. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold Spring Harbor, NY</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willmann</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Conservation and evolution of miRNA regulatory programs in plant development</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>503</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>511</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The sequential action of miR156 and miR172 regulates developmental timing in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>750</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>759</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Temporal regulation of shoot development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> by <italic>miR156</italic> and its target <italic>SPL3</italic></article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>3539</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3547</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Frugis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Colgan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis NAC1 transduces auxin signal downstream of TIR1 to promote lateral root development</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>3024</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3036</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x00F6;hmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berndtgen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>miR156-targeted and nontargeted SBP-box transcription factors act in concert to secure male fertility in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>3935</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3950</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>TWIN SISTER OF FT (TSF) acts as a floral pathway integrator redundantly with FT</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1175</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1189</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The microRNA-regulated SBP-box transcription factor SPL3 is a direct upstream activator of <italic>LEAFY</italic>, <italic>FRUITFULL</italic>, and <italic>APETALA1</italic></article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>278</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamakawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chisaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinmyo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Systematic transient assays of promoter activities for leaf-specific genes identified by gene-expression profiling with cDNA microarrays in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>J Biosci Bioeng</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>140</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>143</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukazawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shikanai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title><italic>SQUAMOSA</italic> promoter binding protein-like7 is a central regulator for copper homeostasis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>361</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Vegetative phase change is mediated by a leaf-derived signal that represses the transcription of miR156</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>249</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>CONSTANS</italic> activates <italic>SUPPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CONSTANS 1</italic> through <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> to promote flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>770</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>778</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>AGAMOUS-LIKE 6 is a floral promoter that negatively regulates the FLC/MAF clade genes and positively regulates FT in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>62</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>76</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Temporal control of trichome distribution by microRNA156-targeted <italic>SPL</italic> genes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2322</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2335</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
