<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">202697</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.202697</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>SYSTEMS BIOLOGY, MOLECULAR BIOLOGY, AND GENE REGULATION</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MEDIATOR25 Acts as an Integrative Hub for the Regulation of Jasmonate-Responsive Gene Expression in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[C]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[W]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>&#x00C7;evik</surname><given-names>Volkan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn2"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>Brendan N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Peijun</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Claire</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kiddle</surname><given-names>Steve</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Denby</surname><given-names>Katherine J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Holub</surname><given-names>Eric B.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>David M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>John M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>Peer M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beynon</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>Kemal</given-names></name></contrib><aff>School of Life Sciences, University of Warwick, Wellesbourne, Warwick CV35 9EF, United Kingdom (V.C., P.Z., C.H., S.K., K.J.D., E.B.H., J.B.); School of Agriculture and Food Sciences, University of Queensland, St Lucia, Queensland 4072, Australia (B.N.K., P.M.S.); Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organization, Plant Industry, Queensland Bioscience Precinct, St Lucia, Queensland 4067, Australia (B.N.K., J.M.M., K.K.); School of Life and Environmental Sciences, Deakin University, Geelong, Victoria 3217, Australia (D.M.C.); and Warwick Systems Biology Centre, Warwick University, Coventry CV4 7AL, United Kingdom (J.B., K.J.D.)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the Australian Research Council (grant no. DP110104354 to P.M.S., D.M.C., J.M.M., and K.K.) and the Biological and Biotechnology Sciences Research Council (grant no. F001347 to J.B.).</p></fn><fn id="afn1" fn-type="equal"><label>2</label><p>These authors contributed equally to the article.</p></fn><fn id="afn2" fn-type="present-address"><label>3</label><p>Present address: The Sainsbury Laboratory, Norwich Research Park, Norwich NR4 7UH, UK.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>volkan.cevik@sainsbury-laboratory.ac.uk</email>.</corresp><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Volkan &#x00C7;evik (<email>volkan.cevik@sainsbury-laboratory.ac.uk</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[C]</label><p>Some figures in this article are displayed in color online but in black and white in the print edition.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.202697">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.202697</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>9</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>07</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>160</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>07</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2012 American Society of Plant Biologists. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year></permissions><abstract><p>The <italic>PHYTOCHROME AND FLOWERING TIME1</italic> gene encoding the MEDIATOR25 (MED25) subunit of the eukaryotic Mediator complex is a positive regulator of jasmonate (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>)-responsive gene expression in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>). Based on the function of the Mediator complex as a bridge between DNA-bound transcriptional activators and the RNA polymerase II complex, MED25 has been hypothesized to function in association with transcriptional regulators of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> pathway. However, it is currently not known mechanistically how MED25 functions to regulate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-responsive gene expression. In this study, we show that MED25 physically interacts with several key transcriptional regulators of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> signaling pathway, including the APETALA2 (AP2)/ETHYLENE RESPONSE FACTOR (ERF) transcription factors OCTADECANOID-RESPONSIVE ARABIDOPSIS AP2/ERF59 and ERF1 as well as the master regulator MYC2. Physical interaction detected between MED25 and four group IX AP2/ERF transcription factors was shown to require the activator interaction domain of MED25 as well as the recently discovered Conserved Motif IX-1/EDLL transcription activation motif of MED25-interacting AP2/ERFs. Using transcriptional activation experiments, we also show that OCTADECANOID-RESPONSIVE ARABIDOPSIS AP2/ERF59- and ERF1-dependent activation of <italic>PLANT DEFENSIN1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> as well as MYC2-dependent activation of <italic>VEGETATIVE STORAGE PROTEIN1</italic> requires a functional MED25. In addition, MED25 is required for MYC2-dependent repression of pathogen defense genes. These results suggest an important role for MED25 as an integrative hub within the Mediator complex during the regulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated gene expression.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">JA</term><def id="def1"><p>jasmonate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">TFs</term><def id="def2"><p>transcription factors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">ET</term><def id="def3"><p>ethylene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">Y2H</term><def id="def4"><p>yeast two-hybrid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">BiFC</term><def id="def5"><p>bimolecular fluorescent complementation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">TAD</term><def id="def6"><p>transcriptional activation domain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">RT-qPCR</term><def id="def7"><p>real-time quantitative PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8">Y1H</term><def id="def8"><p>yeast-one-hybrid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9">3-AT</term><def id="def9"><p>3-amino-1,2,4-triazole</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term10">Ni-NTA</term><def id="def10"><p>nickel-nitrilotriacetic acid agarose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term11">bHLH</term><def id="def11"><p>basic helix-loop-helix</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>The plant hormone jasmonic acid and its conjugate derivatives, collectively known as jasmonates (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JAs</xref>), are known to play an important role in the response to plant pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Penninckx et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Thomma et al., 1998</xref>), wounding, and herbivores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">McConn et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Zhang and Turner, 2008</xref>), as well as regulating plant developmental processes such as stamen development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Feys et al., 1994</xref>) and senescence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">He et al., 2002</xref>). The involvement of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JAs</xref> in this diverse range of processes suggests a mechanism for fine-tuning the activation of specific response pathways while controlling other nonessential response pathways. The activation of herbivory-associated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> genes and the suppression of pathogen defense genes by the basic helix-loop-helix (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">bHLH</xref>) transcription factor (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref>) MYC2 is one example of this fine control of gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lorenzo et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>). In addition, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> signaling can act either synergistically or antagonistically with the signaling pathways of other plant hormones and understanding the cross talk between plant hormone pathways has been the focus of numerous research efforts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Penninckx et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Schenk et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Spoel et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Anderson et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Navarro et al., 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">2008</xref>).</p><p>The F-box protein CORONATINE INSENSITIVE1 (COI1) is important in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> signaling as it is required for almost all <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-responsive phenotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Feys et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Devoto et al., 2005</xref>). Together with S-PHASE KINASE-ASSOCIATED PROTEIN1 (SKP1) and CULLIN proteins, COI1 forms an SKP/CULLIN/F-box complex, which attaches ubiquitin to target proteins to signal their degradation by the 26S proteasome (for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Howe, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Pauwels and Goossens, 2011</xref>). The importance of COI1 in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> perception was revealed with the discovery of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> ZIM domain (JAZ) proteins, which act as repressors of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Chini et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Thines et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Yan et al., 2007</xref>). Genetic, biochemical, and structural studies have confirmed the COI1-JAZ complex as the coreceptor for the biologically active <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-Ile ligand and these findings provide insights into the regulation of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> signaling pathway through release of transcriptional repression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Howe, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Sheard et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>Recently, a number of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> have been identified as binding partners of the JAZ proteins with a variety of different roles in regulating <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated gene expression (for review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kazan and Manners, 2012</xref>). MYC2 was the first <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> to be identified as a JAZ-binding partner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Chini et al., 2007</xref>), and recently, two MYC2-related <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">bHLH</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> (MYC3 and MYC4) also have been shown to interact with JAZ proteins to regulate both pathogen and herbivore defense pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Cheng et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Fern&#x00E1;ndez-Calvo et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Niu et al., 2011</xref>). In addition, three other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">bHLH</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> (TRANSPARENT TESTA8, GLABRA3 [GL3], and ENHANCER of GL3) and two MYB domain <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> (MYB75 and GL1) interact with the JAZ proteins, and are known to have roles in both anthocyanin and trichome production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Qi et al., 2011</xref>). Additionally, JAZ proteins have been found to interact with two MYB domain <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> (MYB21 and MYB24) that control stamen development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Song et al., 2011</xref>), and also two ethylene (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ET</xref>)-associated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> (EIN3 and EIL1) that regulate pathogen defense and root growth through <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ET</xref> signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Zhu et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>The removal of JAZ-mediated repression would allow <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> proteins to recruit the general <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> and RNA polymerase II machinery to initiate transcription. In eukaryotes, the multiprotein complex that connects <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> with the core transcriptional machinery is called the Mediator complex and was recently purified in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">B&#x00E4;ckstr&#x00F6;m et al., 2007</xref>). Approximately 30 Mediator subunits were isolated from Arabidopsis and functional roles in important plant processes such as development, flowering, and abiotic and biotic stress responses have been identified for some Mediator subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Autran et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Boyce et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Dhawan et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Gillmor et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Wathugala et al., 2012</xref>). One subunit that exemplifies the diverse roles that a Mediator subunit can possess in different plant processes is the MEDIATOR25 (MED25) subunit. MED25 (previously known as PHYTOCHROME AND FLOWERING TIME1 [PFT1]) has been shown to play a role in the control of flowering time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cerd&#x00E1;n and Chory, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Wollenberg et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">I&#x00F1;igo et al., 2011</xref>), cell proliferation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Xu and Li, 2011</xref>), as well as abiotic and biotic stress responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Elfving et al., 2011</xref>). The role of MED25 in biotic stress responses was discovered with <italic>med25</italic>/<italic>pft1</italic> mutants (hereafter referred to as <italic>med25</italic>) displaying increased susceptibility to leaf-infecting necrotrophic pathogens <italic>Alternaria brassicicola</italic> and <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>, yet increased resistance to the root-infecting hemibiotroph <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>). The <italic>med25</italic> mutant also showed attenuated expression of both herbivore- and pathogen-associated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> genes as well as decreased production of anthocyanin and a reduced sensitivity to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-mediated root inhibition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>). These findings suggested an important role for MED25 in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> signaling, and thus potentially implicate MED25 as an interacting partner for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> in the Mediator complex.</p><p>In this study we aimed to identify MED25-interacting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> that have roles in the MED25-mediated control of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated gene expression. Through the use of yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) two-hybrid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref>) screening, we identified several MED25-interacting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> known to function in the control of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated gene expression. These included the defense-associated APETALA2 (AP2)/ETHYLENE RESPONSE FACTORs (ERFs); ERF1, OCTADECANOID-RESPONSIVE ARABIDOPSIS AP2/ERF59 (ORA59), and TDR1/ERF98 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Berrocal-Lobo et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lorenzo et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gutterson and Reuber, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>), as well as the defense- and herbivore-associated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">bHLH</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>; MYC2, MYC3, and MYC4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Cheng et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Fern&#x00E1;ndez-Calvo et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Niu et al., 2011</xref>). We demonstrated the functional requirement for MED25 in ERF1- and ORA59-dependent activation of the <italic>PLANT DEFENSIN1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> (<italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>) gene and MYC2-dependent activation of the <italic>VEGETATIVE STORAGE PROTEIN1</italic> (<italic>VSP1</italic>) insect defense gene. Importantly, we provide evidence for the role of the EDLL motif, the recently discovered transcription activation domain from MED25-interacting AP2/ERFs, as an important domain for MED25 interaction. Together, our results suggest that MED25 acts an integrative hub for the regulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-dependent gene expression.</p><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Identification of MED25-Interacting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref></title><p>To identify interacting partners of MED25, we carried out <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> screening using two different bait constructs that corresponded to the N-terminal von Willebrand Factor A (vWF-A) domain responsible for Mediator binding and the C-terminal activator interaction domain (ACID) of the MED25 protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). We found that the first construct (MED25&#x0394;ACID/Q-rich) that consisted of amino acids 1 to 558 but lacked the ACID domain, as well as the Q-rich region at the C terminus of the MED25 protein, did not yield any interactions. However, when the second MED25 construct was expressed, which contained the ACID domain but lacked the N-terminal vWF-A domain and the C-terminal Q-rich domain (MED25&#x0394;vWF-A/Q-rich, 228&#x2013;681 amino acids), 12 interacting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> were identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>). Retesting these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> with the MED25&#x0394;ACID/Q-rich construct did not show any interaction, suggesting that the interaction with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> requires the ACID domain of the MED25 protein. Among the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> identified were a number of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>- and plant-defense-associated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>. For instance, four members of group IX of the AP2/ERF <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> family, ERF1, ORA59, TDR1/ERF98, and ERF15 were identified, as well as MYC2 and the related <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">bHLH</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>, MYC3 and MYC4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>). All of these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>, with the exception of ERF15, have been previously implicated in the regulation of plant defense signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Berrocal-Lobo et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lorenzo et al., 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Gutterson and Reuber, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">McGrath et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Cheng et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Fern&#x00E1;ndez-Calvo et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Niu et al., 2011</xref>). While not currently having a published role in regulating defense signaling, ERF15 is the closest homolog of ORA59 based on its nucleotide sequence and forms a separate clade with ORA59 and ERF1 based on their similarity at the conserved AP2 domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">McGrath et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Nakano et al., 2006</xref>). The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> screen also identified additional interacting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> such as the drought and cold response regulator DREB2A, which belongs to group IV of the AP2/ERF <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> family, as well as WRKY10, MYB104, and two uncharacterized <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> encoding a B-box zinc-finger (At4g39070) and a bZIP (At2g31370) <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref>. Four of the 12 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> that we identified, DREB2A, ERF1, TDR1/ERF98, and the B-box zinc finger (At4g39070), have recently been reported as interacting partners of MED25 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Elfving et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Ou et al., 2011</xref>). The independent discovery of these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> in our interaction screen indicates the reliability of our <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> system in detecting MED25-interacting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>The ACID domain of MED25 interacts with a number of Arabidopsis <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> analyses. Representative schematics of the MED25 fragments used to screen the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> library along with the full-length MED25 protein (A). Only the fragment containing the ACID domain, MED25&#x0394;vWF-A/Q-rich resulted in positive interactions in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> screen and 12 positive interactions were identified (B). No interactions were seen for the binding domain (BD) only or when an empty activation domain (AD) was used. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2Hs</xref> were performed with SD-Leu-Trp as well as SD-Leu-Trp-His supplemented with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">3-AT</xref>. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_202697_wc_f1"></graphic></fig><p>To verify the interactions between MED25 and the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> proteins identified through <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> analysis, we carried out a single in vitro pull-down experiment using the MED25&#x0394;vWF-A/Q-rich protein fused to a poly-His tag together with individual glutathione-<italic>S</italic>-transferase (GST)-tagged <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> proteins. No interaction was observed with the control GST-GFP fusion protein, and with the exception of ORA59, 11 of the identified <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> interacted with the MED25&#x0394;vWF-A/Q-rich protein, confirming the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A&#x2013;C</xref>). We repeated the pull-down experiment with MYC2, ERF1, and ORA59 three times; however, only MYC2 and ERF1 proteins could be successfully pulled down. We also carried out a pull-down experiment with the His-GFP protein as an additional control; however, none of the GST-tagged <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> proteins showed interaction with this protein (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). Overall, we conclude that MED25 can potentially interact with a number of Arabidopsis <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>, including those with known roles in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> and stress signaling.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>MED25 is able to bind to the interacting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> proteins in pull-down experiments. An in vitro His-pull-down experiment confirmed the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> interactions for 11 of the 12 interacting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>. The GST-tagged <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> that were used as the input to the pull-down experiment are shown in an SDS polyacrylamide gel (A). After extensive washing, bound proteins were eluted and analyzed by IB assays with the indicated antibodies (B and C). Expected sizes of corresponding fusion proteins are marked by asterisks.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_202697_gs_f2"></graphic></fig><p>As the ORA59 protein was unable to be pulled down with the MED25 protein, we decided to investigate the interaction of ORA59 and MED25 further. We determined the MED25-interaction domain of ORA59 by performing <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> experiments with three overlapping derivatives of the ORA59 protein (amino acids 1&#x2013;139, 80&#x2013;214, and 139&#x2013;244). We observed an interaction only with the fragment containing the amino acids 139 to 244, suggesting that the interaction with MED25 requires the last 30 amino acids at the C terminus of ORA59 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). Furthermore, the full length as well as overlapping fragments of ORA59 were fused to the N-terminal fragment of the yellow fluorescent protein (YFP<sup>N</sup>) and coexpressed with MED25 fragments fused to the C-terminal fragment of the yellow fluorescent protein (YFP<sup>C</sup>) for bimolecular fluorescent complementation (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">BiFC</xref>) experiments. These experiments confirmed the results of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> analysis with the YFP<sup>C</sup>-fused MED25&#x0394;vWF-A/Q-rich protein producing fluorescence only when expressed with the full-length ORA59 or the 139 to 244 amino acid fragment fused to YFP<sup>N</sup> and not with the other ORA59 fragments (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>). We also expressed the full-length ORA59 and 139 to 244 amino acid fragment with the MED25&#x0394;ACID/Q-rich protein; however these combinations did not result in detectable fluorescence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>). These results suggest that the MED25 ACID domain is required for interaction with ORA59 and that a specific domain in the C terminus of ORA59 is required for MED25 interaction.</p></sec><sec><title>The Conserved Motif IX-1/EDLL Transcription Activation Motif of ERF1, ERF15, and TDR1/ERF98 Is Required for MED25 Binding</title><p>The ACID domain of the human MED25 protein has previously been shown to interact with the transcriptional activation domain (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">TAD</xref>) of VP16, the potent activator from the herpes simplex virus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Mittler et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Yang et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Milbradt et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Vojnic et al., 2011</xref>). It is therefore likely that the interaction we observed between AP2/ERFs and MED25 also requires the ACID domain of MED25 and the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">TAD</xref> domain of the AP2/ERFs. The Conserved Motif IX-1 (CMIX-1) motif has been identified in the carboxy termini of eight AP2/ERF proteins belonging to group IXc (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Nakano et al., 2006</xref>) although until recently the functional importance of this motif has been unknown. Interestingly, six of the eight proteins belonging to group IXc (ERF1, ERF15, ORA59, ESE1, TDR1/ERF98, and ERF91) have been found to interact with MED25 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Ou et al., 2011</xref>; this study). Recently, the CMIX-1 motif from TDR1/ERF98 has been shown to act as a strong <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">TAD</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tiwari et al., 2012</xref>). The CMIX-1 motif was renamed as the EDLL motif based on the conserved amino acids between Arabidopsis TDR1/ERF98 and TDR1-like proteins from other plant species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tiwari et al., 2012</xref>). It was shown that removal of the CMIX-1/EDLL motif or mutation of the conserved Leu residues abolished transcriptional activation ability of TDR1/ERF98 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tiwari et al., 2012</xref>). Interestingly, while the specific Glu and Asp residues of the EDLL motif in TDR1/ERF98 are not conserved among the other CMIX-1 motif-containing proteins, the six MED25-interacting AP2/ERFs share a number of conserved Leu and Glu residues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). As the Leu residues of TDR1/ERF98 were shown to be required for transcriptional activation, we mutated the same Leu residues in three selected <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> namely ERF1, ERF15, and TDR1/ERF98 to Val to determine whether this mutation would affect the interaction of these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> with MED25 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> experiments with full-length ERF1, ERF15, and TDR1/ERF98 proteins containing either mutated or native CMIX-1/EDLL motifs revealed that the conserved Leu in ERF1, ERF15, and TDR1/ERF98 are essential for MED25 interaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>). These results together with the previous <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> results with ORA59 suggest that the C-terminal CMIX-1/EDLL motif previously implicated in transcriptional activation is also important for interaction of ERF1, ERF15, TDR1/ERF98, and ORA59 with MED25.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>The EDLL motif found in the carboxy-terminal region of ERF1, ERF15, and TDR1/ERF98 is important for interaction with MED25. The sequence of the CMIX-1 domain from the MED25-interacting group IX AP2/ERFs (A). The conserved EDLL amino acid residues from TDR1/ERF98-like proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tiwari et al., 2012</xref>) are highlighted in red (A). The mutated Leu residues of ERF1, ERF15, and TDR1/ERF98 are shown in red (B). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> analyses between MED25&#x0394;vWF-A/Q-rich and full-length or mutated ERF1, ERF15, and TDR1/ERF98 show that the Leu residues in the EDLL motif are required for interaction with MED25 (C). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2Hs</xref> were performed with SD-Leu-Trp as well as SD-Leu-Trp-His supplemented with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">3-AT</xref>. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_202697_wc_f3"></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>MED25 Is Required for the Transcription Activation Ability of MYC2, ERF1, and ORA59</title><p>Of the MED25-interacting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>, ERF1, ORA59, and MYC2 are better characterized for their roles as important regulators of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated pathogen and herbivore defense genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lorenzo et al., 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>). The interaction between these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> and MED25 could potentially explain why <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated gene expression is reduced in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>). Therefore we decided to investigate these three <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> further to determine whether MED25 acts downstream to activate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated transcription. To test whether MYC2, ERF1, or ORA59 proteins require MED25 for transcriptional activation, we performed in vivo transactivation experiments with MYC2, ERF1, or ORA59 using wild-type Arabidopsis plants and the previously characterized <italic>med25</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>). In these experiments, we cobombarded a reporter gene construct containing the GAL4 upstream activation sequence (<italic>pGAL4UAS</italic>) linked to the <italic>GUS</italic> gene (<italic>pGAL4UAS</italic>-<italic>GUS</italic>), together with cauliflower mosaic virus <italic>35S</italic> expression constructs of <italic>MYC2</italic>, <italic>ERF1</italic>, and <italic>ORA59</italic> fused to the <italic>GAL4</italic> DNA-binding domain (<italic>GAL4BD</italic>) or <italic>GAL4BD</italic> alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). In addition, an expression construct of the firefly (<italic>Photinus pyralis</italic>) <italic>LUCIFERASE</italic> (<italic>LUC</italic>) gene was cobombarded as a normalization control.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>MED25 is required for proper transcriptional activation by ERF1, ORA59, and MYC2 in transient activation assays in Arabidopsis leaves. Schematic diagrams of the effector, reporter, and normalization control constructs are shown in insets (A&#x2013;C). The activity of the reporter gene <italic>GUS</italic> was normalized to the activity of the firefly <italic>LUC</italic> gene cobombarded as a reference. Relative GUS/luciferase activity ratios after cobombardment of the reporter, effector, and control constructs are shown in A to C. MED25 is required by ERF1, ORA59, and MYC2 for both general transcriptional activation using the GAL4 binding domain (BD) and upstream activation sequence (<italic>GAL4</italic>-<italic>UAS</italic>; A), as well as for specific activation of the <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> promoter by ERF1 and ORA59 (B) and for activation of the <italic>VSP1</italic> promoter by MYC2 (C). Error bars indicate <sc>sd</sc>. Data are from three biological replicates of two bombarded leaves. Asterisks represent significant differences between wild-type and <italic>med25</italic> plants (two-way ANOVA, Tukey&#x2019;s honestly significant difference [HSD] test; &#x002A; &#x003D; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; &#x002A;&#x002A; &#x003D; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; and &#x002A;&#x002A;&#x002A; &#x003D; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_202697_wc_f4"></graphic></fig><p>As expected, the addition of the vector constructs expressing either <italic>MYC2</italic>-, <italic>ERF1</italic>-, or <italic>ORA59-GAL4BD</italic> produced significantly higher transcription activity of the GUS reporter gene compared with the control effector plasmid (<italic>GAL4BD</italic> only) in wild-type Arabidopsis plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). No significant difference was observed in GUS reporter gene activity between the wild type and <italic>med25</italic> with the control effector plasmid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). However, transcription activation abilities of the MYC2-, ERF1-, and ORA59-GAL4BD fusion proteins were significantly reduced in <italic>med25</italic> leaves compared with the wild-type leaves in independent experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). As an additional control experiment, we cotransformed wild-type and <italic>med25</italic> plants with a <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>LUC</italic> construct without the effector plasmid. We did not observe any significant difference between <italic>GUS</italic>/<italic>LUC</italic> ratios, suggesting that the differences observed in transcription activation were not due to different transformation efficiencies (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5</ext-link>). These results suggest that a functional MED25 is required for transcriptional activation by ERF1, ORA59, and MYC2 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>MED25 Is Required for ORA59- and ERF1-Dependent Activation of <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic></title><p>ERF1 and ORA59 have both been shown to activate expression of the <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> gene, with the expression of <italic>ORA59</italic> being essential for <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> activation in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lorenzo et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>). The <italic>med25</italic> mutant has reduced expression of the <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>), raising the hypothesis that both ERF1 and/or ORA59 may require a functional MED25 protein to activate <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> expression. To test this, we repeated the transactivation experiments as above but with the 1,187-bp fragment of the <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> promoter (<italic>pPDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>) linked to the <italic>GUS</italic> reporter gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). This promoter fragment has been used previously to test the activation of <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> in response to pathogens, hormone treatment, or the addition of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Manners et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brown et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Zarei et al., 2011</xref>). In agreement with previous studies, the expression of either <italic>ERF1</italic> or <italic>ORA59</italic> significantly induced the expression of <italic>pPDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>-<italic>GUS</italic> in wild-type leaves, and as previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>), ORA59 activated <italic>pPDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>-<italic>GUS</italic> expression to higher levels than ERF1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Interestingly, when either <italic>ORA59</italic> or <italic>ERF1</italic> was expressed in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant plants, only partial activation of <italic>pPDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>-<italic>GUS</italic> expression was achieved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). These experiments indicate that both ERF1- and ORA59-dependent activation of <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> are dependent on MED25.</p></sec><sec><title>MED25 Is Required for MYC2-Dependent Activation of <italic>VSP1</italic></title><p>In contrast to ERF1 and ORA59, MYC2 acts as a negative regulator of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-inducible defense genes such as <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> and a positive regulator of insect and herbivore response genes such as <italic>VSP1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Boter et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lorenzo et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>). Therefore, we tested the ability of MYC2 to activate <italic>VSP1</italic> gene expression in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant by using the <italic>VSP1</italic> promoter in transactivation experiments. Expression of MYC2 in wild-type plants resulted in induction of <italic>VSP1</italic> expression. However, in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant line, expression of MYC2 resulted in significantly reduced expression of <italic>VSP1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>). These results demonstrate that MED25 is required for MYC2-dependent activation of <italic>VSP1</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>ERF1-, ORA59-, and MYC2-Regulated Genes Are Attenuated in <italic>med25</italic></title><p>To further investigate the requirement of MED25 for ERF1-, ORA59-, or MYC2-regulated gene expression, we compared published microarray data from <italic>ERF1</italic> and <italic>ORA59</italic> overexpression lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lorenzo et al., 2003</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>) and the <italic>myc2</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>) with microarray data obtained from the <italic>med25</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Tables S1&#x2013;S4</ext-link>). The ERF1-regulated gene list (e.g. genes that are either activated or repressed in <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>ERF1</italic> relative to the wild type) used in this comparison (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lorenzo et al., 2003</xref>) consisted of 99 genes and 18 of these genes were found to be in common with the <italic>med25</italic>-regulated genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>). The majority (16 out of 18) of the common genes were ERF1-activated genes, and all 16 of these genes showed reduced expression in the <italic>med25</italic> microarray relative to the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>). The gene list obtained from the <italic>ORA59</italic> microarray experiment contained 86 <italic>ORA59</italic>-activated genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>), and of the 26 genes that were common to the <italic>ORA59-</italic> and <italic>med25-</italic>regulated gene lists, almost all (25 out of 26) had reduced expression in <italic>med25</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S3</ext-link>). Finally, 116 genes were common between the <italic>med25</italic>- and <italic>myc2</italic>-regulated gene lists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). MYC2-activated genes were found to be mostly repressed (41 out of 50) in <italic>med25</italic>, suggesting that MED25 is required for their activation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). In addition, genes that are repressed by MYC2 had also predominantly reduced expression in <italic>med25</italic> (57 out of 66; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). Therefore, both MYC2-activated and MYC2-repressed genes are attenuated in <italic>med25</italic>. Statistical tests using the hypergeometric distribution (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) showed that the number of MED25<italic>-</italic>regulated genes found to be in common with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> arrays was significantly higher than expected, given the total number of common genes present between each microarray experiment. In addition, as the majority of the common genes showed reduced expression in <italic>med25</italic>, this suggests that a functional MED25 may be required for activation of ERF1-, ORA59-, and MYC2-regulated genes.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>ERF1-, ORA59-, and MYC2-responsive genes have reduced expression in <italic>med25</italic>. Genes differentially expressed by ERF1, ORA59, and MYC2 were obtained from published gene lists; <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>ERF1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lorenzo et al., 2003</xref>); <italic>XVE</italic>:<italic>ORA59</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>); and <italic>myc2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>). The total number of genes in each list is shown in brackets under each genotype. Common genes with the <italic>med25</italic> microarray were identified and presented as Venn diagrams (A&#x2013;C). The genes that were common between <italic>med25</italic> and the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> lists (<italic>med25</italic>-<italic>35S</italic>:<italic>ERF1</italic> &#x003D; 18; <italic>med25</italic>-<italic>XVE</italic>:<italic>ORA59</italic> &#x003D; 26; <italic>med25</italic>-<italic>myc2</italic> &#x003D; 116) were then used to construct heat maps and their expression marked depending on whether they were induced or repressed compared with the wild type in the <italic>med25</italic> array and the <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>ERF1</italic>, <italic>XVE</italic>:<italic>ORA59</italic>, or <italic>myc2</italic> arrays (A&#x2013;C). Genes were then ranked according to their expression in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> array from highest to lowest to produce the heat maps. Asterisks represent higher than expected common genes using the hypergeometric distribution. &#x002A; &#x003D; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_202697_wc_f5"></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>MED25 Is Required for Repression of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-Associated Defense Genes by MYC2</title><p>In the microarray comparisons, MED25 appeared to be required for both MYC2-activated genes such as <italic>VSP1</italic>, and MYC2-repressed genes such as <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>, as expression of both genes were reduced in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). To further investigate whether MED25 is required for the repression of defense genes by MYC2, we created a <italic>med25 myc2</italic> double mutant and analyzed gene expression in the double and single mutants with and without <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> treatment, using real-time quantitative PCR (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">RT-qPCR</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, A&#x2013;E</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S5</ext-link>). In support of previous results, the expression of defense genes, <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>, <italic>HEVEIN</italic>-<italic>LIKE</italic> (<italic>HEL</italic>), and <italic>BASIC CHITINASE</italic> (<italic>CHI</italic>-<italic>B</italic>), were significantly reduced in the <italic>med25</italic> single mutant after <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, A&#x2013;C</xref>). In the <italic>myc2</italic> single mutant these genes were expressed at a significantly higher level compared with the wild type after <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> treatment, confirming the negative effect of MYC2 on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-regulated defense gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lorenzo et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>). In the <italic>med25 myc2</italic> double mutant, these genes were significantly attenuated and showed an expression level similar to that of the <italic>med25</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, A&#x2013;C</xref>). These results suggest that MED25 is essential for the activation of <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>, <italic>CHI</italic>-<italic>B</italic>, and <italic>HEL</italic> expression and that MYC-mediated repression of these genes acts on a pathway that is dependent on MED25.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>MED25 is required for the repression of defense-associated genes by MYC2. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">RT-qPCR</xref> analysis shows the <italic>med25</italic> mutant has decreased expression of <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>, <italic>HEL</italic>, <italic>CHI</italic>-<italic>B</italic>, and <italic>ORA59</italic> relative to the wild type after <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> treatment (A&#x2013;C). The expression of <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>, <italic>HEL</italic>, and <italic>CHI</italic>-<italic>B</italic> is increased in <italic>myc2</italic> after <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> treatment, however remained attenuated in the <italic>med25 myc2</italic> double mutant (A&#x2013;C). The expression of <italic>ORA59</italic> and <italic>ERF1</italic> in the <italic>med25 myc2</italic> double mutant was partially attenuated relative to the <italic>myc2</italic> single mutant after <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> treatment and was expressed similar to the wild type (D and E). Data represents the relative transcript abundance to the housekeeping genes (&#x03B2;-<italic>ACTIN2</italic>, &#x03B2;-<italic>ACTIN7</italic>, and &#x03B2;-<italic>ACTIN8</italic>). Error bars are <sc>se</sc> of three biological replicates of 15 plants per replicate. a, b, c, and d represent significance (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) using a 2-way ANOVA with the Bonferroni method applied as a post hoc test. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_202697_wc_f6"></graphic></fig><p>To investigate how MYC2-mediated repression of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-responsive defense genes may be occurring, we analyzed the expression of <italic>ORA59</italic> and <italic>ERF1</italic> in the single and double mutants. After <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> treatment, <italic>ORA59</italic> and <italic>ERF1</italic> expression was induced higher than the wild type in the <italic>myc2</italic> single mutant, confirming previously published results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, D and E</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Zander et al., 2010</xref>). Interestingly both <italic>ORA59</italic> and <italic>ERF1</italic> showed attenuated expression in the <italic>med25 myc2</italic> double mutant, relative to the <italic>myc2</italic> single mutant. However, <italic>ORA59</italic> and <italic>ERF1</italic> expression levels in the double mutant were not as strongly reduced as the defense genes (e.g. <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>) and appeared similar to the wild type. These results suggest that MYC2 suppresses <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated defense genes through repression of the defense-associated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>, <italic>ERF1</italic> and <italic>ORA59</italic>, and that this repression by MYC2 is dependent on a functional MED25.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>ORA59</italic> Expression Is Reduced in the <italic>med25</italic> Mutant</title><p>The reduced expression of ERF1-, ORA59-, and MYC2-dependent genes in the <italic>med25</italic> microarray suggests that the interaction with MED25 is important for ERF1-, ORA59-, and MYC2 gene activation. However, an alternative reason for reduced expression of ERF1-, ORA59-, and MYC2-dependent genes could be reduced expression of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> themselves in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant. We therefore examined the expression of <italic>ERF1</italic>, <italic>ORA59</italic>, and <italic>MYC2</italic> in the <italic>med25</italic> microarray experiment. The <italic>med25</italic> microarray experiment involved treatment with the hemibiotrophic pathogen <italic>F. oxysporum</italic>, which is known to induce <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated defense gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Thatcher et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>Interestingly, <italic>ORA59</italic> expression was found to be induced in the wild type by <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> infection but was attenuated in <italic>med25</italic> under both mock and infected conditions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6A</ext-link>). In contrast, <italic>ERF1</italic> expression was unresponsive to <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> infection and no significant difference in <italic>ERF1</italic> expression could be found between wild-type and <italic>med25</italic> plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6B</ext-link>). Therefore, down-regulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated defense genes in the <italic>med25</italic> microarray could also be due to a reduction in <italic>ORA59</italic> expression but not <italic>ERF1</italic>. The expression of <italic>MYC2</italic> in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant appeared similar to the wild type in the microarray experiment (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6C</ext-link>). This suggests that down-regulation of MYC2 target genes in the microarray is not due to reduced expression of the <italic>MYC2</italic> gene but may be a result of the reduced transcriptional activation ability of MYC2 protein in <italic>med25</italic> mutant plants. We also looked at the expression of <italic>MYC3</italic> and <italic>MYC4</italic> in the microarray. These genes also showed no significant change in expression in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6, D and E</ext-link>). Therefore, alterations in <italic>MYC3</italic> or <italic>MYC4</italic> expression cannot explain the alterations in MYC2 target genes in <italic>med25</italic>. These results suggest MED25 is required for the expression of <italic>ORA59</italic> but not <italic>ERF1</italic> or the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">bHLH</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> <italic>MYC2</italic>, <italic>MYC3</italic>, or <italic>MYC4</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>ORA59 and Other MED25-Interacting AP2/ERFs Bind to the <italic>ORA59</italic> Promoter</title><p>The attenuation of <italic>ORA59</italic> in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant as well as the results from the transcriptional activation experiments suggests that MED25 is required both upstream for the expression of <italic>ORA59</italic> as well as downstream for the activation of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ET</xref> defense pathway by the ORA59 protein. We performed yeast one-hybrid (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Y1H</xref>) experiments with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> library using the promoter region of <italic>ORA59</italic> as bait to determine which <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> were able to interact with the <italic>ORA59</italic> promoter and therefore may be able to regulate <italic>ORA59</italic> expression. Two overlapping fragments of the <italic>ORA59</italic> promoter region were cloned and used to screen the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> library (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7A</xref>). Thirteen AP2/ERF <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> were identified that bind to the <italic>ORA59</italic> promoter including ORA59 itself (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S6</ext-link>). With the exception of At2g47520 and At1g03800, all of the AP2/ERFs identified belonged to group IX of the AP2/ERF family and five of them were found to interact with MED25 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S6</ext-link>). All 13 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> were identified with promoter fragment 2, while only five of these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> showed interaction with promoter fragment 1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S6</ext-link>). The <italic>ORA59</italic> promoter contains a GCC box located between nucleotides &#x2212;369 and &#x2212;363 upstream of the translation start site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7A</xref>) and it is likely that the identified <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> bind to this element. However, the small number of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> identified with promoter fragment 1 in the initial screen could be due to the distance of this element from the translation start site present in the reporter vector that was used for the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Y1H</xref> experiment as it has been shown that transcription activation diminishes with distance in yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Dobi and Winston, 2007</xref>). Supporting this, retesting of these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> with the promoter fragment 1 in the presence of 3-amino-1,2,4-triazole (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">3-AT</xref>) abolished their transcription activation abilities, suggesting that the observed interaction is rather weak (data not shown). We therefore used promoter fragment 2 for further analyses. We retested the four group IX AP2/ERF <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> that interacted with MED25 as well as control <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> proteins ERF4 and GFP using selective media supplemented with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">3-AT</xref> to further assess the strength of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref>-promoter interaction using promoter fragment 2. In nonselective media (SD-Leu-Trp), we observed growth with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> ERF1, ORA59, and ERF15 as well as EFR4 and GFP. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>, ERF1, ORA59, and ERF15 showed strong interaction with promoter fragment 2 on selective media (SD-Leu-Trp-His) in the presence of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">3-AT</xref>, while growth of the yeast cells with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> TDR1/ERF98 was weak. No growth was observed with ERF4 and GFP on selective media with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">3-AT</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). To test if the AP2/ERF <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> that were identified are binding to the GCC box located on the <italic>ORA59</italic> promoter, we mutated the GCC box (GCCGCC to TCCTCA) in fragment 2 and retested the same <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> with ERF4 and GFP as controls. We found that the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> were no longer able to bind to the mutated promoter with the addition of 25 m<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">3-AT</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). These results suggest that the GCC box is an important element for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> binding in the ORA59 promoter. Overall these results show that a number of MED25-interacting AP2/ERFs, including ORA59 itself, are able to bind to the <italic>ORA59</italic> promoter and therefore provides evidence for a positive feedback loop to further enhance <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ET</xref>/<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> defense.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>MED25-interacting AP2/ERFs can bind to the <italic>ORA59</italic> promoter in yeast. Schematics of the <italic>ORA59</italic> promoter, with the GCC box motif (located on &#x2212;369 to &#x2212;363) and the promoter fragments used for the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Y1H</xref> screen (A). mFragment2 contains point mutations in GCC box and the mutated nucleotides are indicated in lowercase. TSS, Translation start site. Binding analysis of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> to the promoter fragments Fragment2 and mFragment2 tested in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Y1H</xref> using SD-Leu-Trp as well as SD-Leu-Trp-His supplemented with 25 m<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">3-AT</xref> (B). [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_202697_wc_f7"></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The Mediator complex, which functions as a universal adaptor for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>, was recently identified in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">B&#x00E4;ckstr&#x00F6;m et al., 2007</xref>) and is expected to have roles in integrating multiple plant signaling pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kidd et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Mathur et al., 2011</xref>). In accordance with this, the MED25 subunit of the Mediator complex has been shown to be a regulator of a number of developmental and physiological processes such as flowering time, cell size, abiotic and biotic stress responses, as well as regulation of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> signaling pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Cerd&#x00E1;n and Chory, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Elfving et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">I&#x00F1;igo et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Xu and Li, 2011</xref>). Here we have identified 12 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> that interact with MED25. Some of the identified <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> (e.g. MYC2, MYC3, MYC4, and the group IX AP2/ERF <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>) have previously been shown to be important for correct regulation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated herbivore and pathogen defense genes. In this report, we explored the ability of three of these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>, ERF1, ORA59, and MYC2, to activate <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-dependent gene expression through MED25. Using transcription activation assays, we found MED25 to be required for ERF1- and ORA59-dependent activation of the <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> gene as well as MYC2-dependent activation of the <italic>VSP1</italic> gene. These results suggest that MED25 acts downstream of ERF1, ORA59, and MYC2 for the activation of <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> and <italic>VSP1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>).</p><fig id="fig8" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>A proposed model of the role of MED25 in coordinating <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated gene expression. ERF1 and ORA59 interact with MED25 and MED25 is required for activation of the <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> gene by these <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>. ERF1 and ORA59 bind to the ORA59 promoter, providing evidence of a positive feedback loop (shown by a looped arrow) to enhance <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> expression and other <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ET</xref>- and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated defense genes. MED25 interacts with MYC2 and is required for the correct activation of the <italic>VSP1</italic> gene by MYC2. MED25 is also required for the suppression of <italic>ORA59</italic>, <italic>ERF1</italic>, and defense genes such as <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> by MYC2. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="PP_202697_wc_f8"></graphic></fig><p>To see whether MED25 may be required for other ERF1-, ORA59-, and MYC2-regulated genes, we compared published microarray data from <italic>ERF1</italic> and <italic>ORA59</italic> overexpressing lines as well as <italic>myc2</italic> and <italic>med25</italic> mutant lines. Despite the limitations of comparing across different microarray experiments, a higher than expected number of common genes were identified between the microarray comparisons. In addition, of the ERF1-, ORA59-, and MYC2-induced genes that were found to be common with the <italic>med25</italic> array, the majority showed reduced expression in <italic>med25</italic>. While further experiments are needed to determine whether MED25 interacts directly with ERF1, ORA59, and MYC2 at the promoter regions of these genes, these results suggest that MED25 may be required for the regulation of ERF1-, ORA59-, and MYC2-activated genes. In addition to the MYC2-activated genes, the genes repressed by MYC2 were also reduced in <italic>med25</italic>. MYC2 is known to repress ERF1- and ORA59-regulated defense genes such as <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lorenzo et al., 2004</xref>). To determine whether the repression of these genes by MYC2 was dependent on MED25, we created a <italic>med25 myc2</italic> double mutant and examined the expression of defense genes (<italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>, <italic>HEL</italic>, and <italic>CHI</italic>-<italic>B</italic>), as well as the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> <italic>ERF1</italic> and <italic>ORA59</italic>. As previously reported, the <italic>myc2</italic> mutant was found to have increased expression of <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>, <italic>HEL</italic>, <italic>CHI</italic>-<italic>B</italic>, <italic>ERF1</italic>, and <italic>ORA59</italic> relative to the wild type after <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> treatment, suggesting that MYC2-mediated repression of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated pathogen defense genes may potentially occur through repression of <italic>ERF1</italic> and <italic>ORA59</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lorenzo et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Zander et al., 2010</xref>). In the <italic>med25 myc2</italic> double mutant, the expression of <italic>PDF1.2</italic>, <italic>HEL</italic>, <italic>CHI</italic>-<italic>B</italic>, <italic>ERF1</italic>, and <italic>ORA59</italic> was significantly attenuated relative to the <italic>myc2</italic> single mutant, suggesting that MYC2-mediated repression of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated pathogen defense genes is at least partially dependent on a functional MED25 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>).</p><p>Lastly, as the <italic>ORA59</italic> gene has reduced expression in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant, we decided to identify the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> that bind to the <italic>ORA59</italic> promoter to see whether they also interact with MED25. Using <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Y1H</xref> experiments we found that ORA59 as well as other MED25-interacting AP2/ERFs can bind to the <italic>ORA59</italic> promoter. This suggests a positive feedback loop for activation of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> responses through <italic>ORA59</italic> expression that may be attenuated in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>).</p><p>Integrating these conclusions, we propose a model for the role of MED25 in regulating the expression of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated defense genes such as <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> through ERF1 and ORA59 as well as <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated herbivore genes such as <italic>VSP1</italic> through MYC2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). MED25 is also required for the suppression of defense genes by MYC2 and is therefore important in the regulatory cross talk between these two pathways. Finally, MED25 is also important in the amplification of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> defense pathway through <italic>ORA59</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). Therefore MED25 plays a critical role in the regulation of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> pathway for both pathogen and wound and herbivore responses.</p><p>The novel finding reported herein that ORA59 interacts with MED25 is particularly noteworthy, given the primary integrative role proposed for this gene in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">ET</xref> signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>). The expression of <italic>ORA59</italic> has been shown to be essential for activation of <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic>, as silencing of <italic>ORA59</italic> leads to attenuated <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>). Our data supports this finding with reduced expression of both <italic>ORA59</italic> and <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> expression in the <italic>med25</italic> line despite wild-type-like activation of <italic>ERF1</italic> expression. As <italic>ORA59</italic> but not <italic>ERF1</italic> expression was reduced in <italic>med25</italic>, this suggests that <italic>ORA59</italic> is regulated by a different transcriptional pathway that is dependent on MED25. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Y1H</xref> experiments aimed to identify the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> that can bind to the ORA59 promoter and revealed a number of MED25-interacting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>. However, further work is required to determine whether the MED25-dependent regulation of <italic>ORA59</italic> has some connection with its essential role in <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> expression. Nevertheless, our experiments suggest that the attenuation of <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> expression in <italic>med25</italic> is compounded by at least two factors. First, <italic>ORA59</italic> expression levels are attenuated in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant, leading to reduced <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> expression and second, we showed that both ORA59 and ERF1 proteins have a reduced ability to activate <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> expression in <italic>med25</italic> that may further contribute to the reduced level of <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> expression. Therefore our results reveal an important role for MED25 downstream of ORA59 and ERF1 for the activation of defense gene expression.</p><p>As well as the defense-associated AP2/ERFs, we identified the related <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">bHLH</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>, MYC2, MYC3, and MYC4 as MED25-interacting proteins and despite having wild-type levels of <italic>MYC2</italic>, <italic>MYC3</italic>, and <italic>MYC4</italic> expression in the microarray experiment, genes such as <italic>VSP1</italic> that are positively regulated by MYC2, were reduced in <italic>med25</italic>. The reductions in <italic>VSP1</italic> and other MYC2-regulated genes could be due to the reduced ability of MYC2 and potentially also MYC3 and MYC4 proteins, to activate transcription in the <italic>med25</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>). However, further experiments need to be performed to ascertain the relative contribution of MYC2, MYC3, and MYC4 in controlling activation as well as repression through MED25.</p><p>Currently, 18 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> have been identified to interact with MED25 and all of the identified <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> have been shown to interact with the MED25 fragment containing the ACID yet lacking the N-terminal vWF-A domain. Based on the results presented here as well as others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Elfving et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Ou et al., 2011</xref>), the Arabidopsis MED25 ACID domain appears to be an effective interaction domain for a number of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> proteins. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> we identified belong to the AP2/ERF, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">bHLH</xref>, MYB, WRKY, bZIP, and zinc-finger <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> families, demonstrating that the ACID domain of Arabidopsis MED25 is able to interact with a diverse range of plant <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> and is therefore an important component in MED25&#x2019;s regulatory function in a range of environmental, biotic, and developmental processes.</p><p>Half of the MED25-interacting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> that have been identified belong to the AP2/ERF family of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> and two-thirds of the identified AP2/ERFs belong to the group IXc with the remaining three AP2/ERFs belonging to groups IV, VII, and X (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Nakano et al., 2006</xref>). The identification of group IXc AP2/ERFs as opposed to other AP2/ERF family members suggests that this subgroup may preferentially bind to MED25. One explanation for the identification of group IXc AP2/ERFs as MED25-interacting proteins came with the recent report of the EDLL motif of TDR1/ERF98 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tiwari et al., 2012</xref>). The EDLL motif, otherwise known as CMIX-1, is a conserved motif in the C terminus of group IXc AP2/ERFs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Nakano et al., 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tiwari et al. (2012)</xref> recently reported that mutation of the conserved Leu or deletion of the CMIX-1 motif in TDR1/ERF98 removed the transcriptional activation ability of this <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref>. We demonstrate that deletion of the CMIX-1 motif in ORA59 as well as mutation of the conserved Leu in ERF1, ERF15, and TDR1/ERF98 abolished the interaction with MED25. This suggests a common domain among the group IXc AP2/ERFs that interact with MED25 to recruit the Mediator complex to activate transcription. Interestingly,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tiwari et al. (2012)</xref> suggested that the CMIX-1 motif of TDR1/ERF98 possessed a similar pattern of acidic amino acids as the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">TAD</xref> from the potent viral activator VP16. VP16 is able to interact with human MED25 and the NMR analysis of MED25 bound to the VP16 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">TAD</xref> has recently been published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bontems et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Eletsky et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Milbradt et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Vojnic et al., 2011</xref>). While detailed structural studies on the Arabidopsis MED25 have not been performed, further investigation may reveal a common acidic amino acid motif that can interact with MED25 to activate transcription.</p><p>Lastly, the interaction of MED25 with DREB2A has recently been characterized (Blomberg et al., 2012). As the CMIX-1 motif is not present in the DREB2A protein, it is likely that a different domain may be utilized for MED25 interaction with DREB2A. Further investigation of the CMIX-1 motif and the identification of activation domains in the other identified <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> may help uncover the ability of MED25 to interact with a diverse range of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> proteins. In addition, further investigation of the other subunits of the Mediator complex and their interaction partners could provide the potential for discovering new links into a range of plant signaling pathways.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>In conclusion, the results presented in this article reveal a new role for MED25 as an integrative hub that coordinates <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> signaling through interaction with multiple <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>. We demonstrate a mechanistic role for MED25 acting downstream of key <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref>-associated <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> and identify a common interaction domain in a subset of AP2/ERF <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref>. Further investigation of the other subunits of the Mediator complex and their interaction partners could provide the potential for discovering new links into a range of plant signaling pathways. In addition future research into the Mediator complex should reveal new insights into the recruitment of the RNA polymerase II transcription apparatus to promoter regions and the transcription of protein-coding genes in eukaryotes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Plant Materials</title><p>Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) ecotype Columbia-0 was used as the wild type and the <italic>med25</italic>-<italic>2</italic>/<italic>pft1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> (SALK_129555) and the <italic>myc2</italic> mutant (SALK_017005) was described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Anderson et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>). The <italic>med25 myc2</italic> mutant was created by pollinating an emasculated <italic>myc2</italic> mutant with <italic>med25</italic> pollen. Double-mutant plants were confirmed by PCR using the primers obtained using the iSct primers tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://signal.salk.edu/cgi-bin/tdnaexpress">http://signal.salk.edu/cgi-bin/tdnaexpress</ext-link>) for the <italic>med25</italic> and <italic>myc2</italic> single transferred DNA lines (SALK_129555 and SALK_017005). Arabidopsis plants were grown at 20&#x00B0;C with a 16-h-light/8-h-dark photoperiod and a light intensity of 140 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> photons m<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> plants were grown at 25&#x00B0;C under a 16-h-light/8-h-dark photoperiod. The methyl jasmonate treatments for the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">RT-qPCR</xref> experiment were performed according to the method published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Schenk et al. (2000)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Y1H</xref> Library Screening</title><p>The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> library (REGIA &#x002B; REGULATORS; RR Library) used in this study has been described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Castrillo et al., 2011</xref>) and is a kind gift from the authors. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> in this library had been fused to the GAL4 activation domain (GAL4AD) into pDEST22 (Invitrogen). Two derivatives of MED25 were fused to DNA-binding domain (GAL4BD) in pDEST32 (Invitrogen). pDEST32-MED25&#x0394;ACID/Q-rich and pDEST32-MED25&#x0394;vWFA/Q-rich constructs were generated by fusing 1 to 558 amino acids and 228 to 681 amino acids of MED25 protein with GAL4BD, respectively. To carry out <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> screening of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> library with two different bait constructs, we first bulked the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> clones in pDEST22 in each 96-well plate. Both bait and prey constructs were then cotransformed into the yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) strain MaV203 (Invitrogen) following manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions, and the selection of the positive clones were carried out on SD-Leu-Trp-His plates with 12.5 m<sc>m</sc> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">3-AT</xref> to prevent autoactivation by MED25. The positive protein-protein interactions were further investigated as described by the ProQuest <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> system (Invitrogen). For the identification of MED25-interacting domain of ORA59, three fragments of ORA59 were amplified with the primers pGWORA-F1 (5&#x2032;-AAAAAGCAGGCTTCATGGAATATCAAACTAACTTC-3&#x2032;) and pGWORA-R1 (5&#x2032;-CAAGAAAGCTGGGTCTAGGGGAAATTGAGTACTGCG-3&#x2032;) for ORA59<sup>1-139</sup>; pGWORA-F2 (5&#x2032;-AAAAAGCAGGCTTCTCATACAGAGGAGTGAGGAAAC-3&#x2032;) and pGWORA-R2 (5&#x2032;-CAAGAAAGCTGGGTCTAACTCTGTTTTCTACTTCTTGACG-3&#x2032;) for ORA59<sup>80-214</sup>; and pGWORA-F3 (5&#x2032;-AAAAAGCAGGCTTCGCGGATGTCGTTGAAGAATCTC-3&#x2032;) and pGWORA-R3 (5&#x2032;-CAAGAAAGCTGGGTTCAAGAACATGATCTCATAAG-3&#x2032;) for ORA59<sup>139-244</sup> followed by second amplification with pAttB1 (5&#x2032;-GGGGACAAGTTTGTACAAAAAAGCAGGCT-3&#x2032;) and pAttB2 (5&#x2032;-GGGGACCACTTTGTACAAGAAAGCTGGGT-3&#x2032;), and cloned into the pDONRZeo plasmid (Invitrogen). The entry clones were then recombined with the pDEST22 plasmid. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> experiments were carried out as above using pDest32-MED25&#x0394;vWFA/Q-rich construct as bait.</p><p>To determine if the conserved Leu residues within ERF1, ERF15, and TDR1/ERF98 proteins are crucial for MED25 interaction, we mutated Leu to Val using QuickChange II site-directed mutagenesis kit (Agilent Technologies) following manufacturer&#x2019;s recommendations. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">Y2H</xref> experiments expressing either the mutated or native proteins were carried out as above.</p><p>For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Y1H</xref> screen, the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> clones in pDEST22 were individually transformed into the yeast strain AH109 (<italic>MATa</italic>) and pooled 12 clones to a well in two 96-well plates, in two alternative arrangements giving a total of four 96-well plates. To generate pHISLEU2, the <italic>LEU</italic> auxotrophy marker was amplified from the pDEST32 vector (Invitrogen) using primers SABR68 (5&#x2032;-ggggggatcctccggaCAACTGTGGGAATACTCAGGTATCG-3&#x2032; contains a 5&#x2032; <italic>Bam</italic>HI site followed by a <italic>Kpn</italic>2I site shown in lowercase) and SABR69 (5&#x2032;-ccccggatcccctgc aggtcgactctaCTACCCTATGAACATATTCC-3&#x2032; includes a 5&#x2032; <italic>Bam</italic>HI site followed by a <italic>Sbf</italic>I site shown in lowercase) and the fragment was then ligated into the pHIS2.1 vector (Clontech) after <italic>Sbf</italic>I and <italic>Kpn</italic>2I digestion replacing the <italic>TRP</italic> marker. Gateway conversion (Invitrogen) of the resulting vector was then carried out. Two promoter fragments of <italic>ORA59</italic> (fragment 1: from &#x2212;42 to &#x2212;478; fragment 2: from &#x2212;348 to &#x2212;836) were amplified from Arabidopsis (Columbia-0) genomic DNA in a two-step PCR approach using the Gateway compatible specific primers pOra59F1-F (5&#x2032;-AAAAAAGCAGGCTTC GTGCAATTGATCACTATATTAGTTGAACTG-3&#x2032;) and pOra59F1-R (5&#x2032;-CAAGAAAGCTGGGTCGTGTCTAAGTGGCACTAAGTTTGGG-3&#x2032;) for fragment 1 or pOra59F2-F (5&#x2032;-AAAAAAGCAGGCTTCCCGCCTTAGTTTCTGACAGAGTTTCGACTC-3&#x2032;) and pOra59F2-R (5&#x2032;-CAAGAAAGCTGGGTCGAGTGTATGACGTACGGCGGCGTATTCCCG-3&#x2032;) for fragment 2, as well as the generic primers pAttB1 and pAttB2, and cloned into the pDONRZeo plasmid (Invitrogen). The mutated fragment2 (mFragment2), which contains mutated nucleotides in the GCC box, was generated using QuickChange II site-directed mutagenesis kit (Agilent Technologies) following manufacturer&#x2019;s recommendations. The entry clones were then recombined with the pHISLEU2 plasmid. pHISLEU2 vectors with the promoter fragments were then transformed into the yeast strain Y187 (<italic>MAT</italic>&#x03B1;). The pooled library and the bait clones were grown in SD-Trp or SD-Leu media. The pooled library clones were mixed with the bait clones and 3 &#x03BC;L of bait and prey were spotted and overlaid onto yeast peptone dextrose adenine plates. After 1 d of growth at 30&#x00B0;C, diploid cells were replica plated on screening plates (SD-Leu-Trp and SD-Leu-Trp-His &#x00B1; <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">3-AT</xref>). Following a further overnight incubation at 30&#x00B0;C, plates were replica cleaned to thin out the yeast and grown for a further 3 d before scoring.</p></sec><sec><title>In Vitro Protein-Protein Interactions</title><p>His-tagged (6&#x00D7; His) MED25&#x0394;VWA/Q-rich (228&#x2013;681 amino acids) and GFP were cloned into pDEST17 (Invitrogen) via the Gateway cloning system. GST-tagged <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> as well as GFP were generated using the destination vector pDEST15. The constructs were then transformed into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> Rosetta II cells (Merc4Biosciences) and proteins expressed at 30&#x00B0;C in the presence of 0.5 m<sc>m</sc> isopropyl b-<sc>d</sc>-thiogalactoside. For His pull-down experiments, nickel-nitrilotriacetic acid agarose (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Ni-NTA</xref>) magnetic beads (Qiagen) were used following the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. <italic>E. coli</italic> lysate containing His-MED25&#x0394;VWA/Q-rich or His-GFP was incubated with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Ni-NTA</xref> magnetic beads for 1 h at 4&#x00B0;C. Following one wash with the extraction/interaction buffer, the poly-His proteins immobilized with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Ni-NTA</xref> magnetic beads were incubated with <italic>E. coli</italic> lysate containing GST-tagged GFP or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TFs</xref> for 3 h at 4&#x00B0;C. Following four washes, proteins retained on the magnetic beads were eluted. The eluted proteins and input fractions separated by SDS-PAGE were analyzed by immunoblotting with anti-His (Invitrogen) or anti-GST (Sigma-Aldrich) antibodies.</p></sec><sec><title>Transcriptional Activation Assays</title><p>Full-length <italic>MYC2</italic>, <italic>ORA59</italic>, and <italic>ERF1</italic> were used to construct effector plasmids by fusing with the yeast <italic>GAL4</italic> DNA-binding domain (<italic>GAL4DB</italic>)-coding region under the control of the cauliflower mosaic virus 35S promoter into the Gateway (GWC_RfB; Invitrogen) converted <italic>pJG</italic> vector (<italic>pGAL4DBGW</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Gonzalez et al., 2007</xref>; a kind gift from S. Conlan). <italic>pGAL4UAS</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> was used as the reporter plasmid. To normalize reporter gene activity, we used <italic>p2X35S</italic>:<italic>fLUC</italic> as control. The effector, reporter, and reference plasmids (3, 3, and 2 &#x03BC;g, respectively) were delivered into rosette leaves of 5- to 6-week-old Arabidopsis plants by particle bombardment using the Bio-Rad PDS-1000/He machine (Bio-Rad). Cobombardment assays were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Rehmany et al., 2005</xref>). Three replicates (two to three leaves for each replicate) were used for each construct/genotype transformation experiment and each experiment was repeated at least twice. After bombardment, the samples were incubated on one-quarter-strength Murashige and Skoog medium at 22&#x00B0;C for 24 h, and then quantified for luciferase and GUS activities. Luciferase assay system (Promega) was used to quantify luciferase activity according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. Fluorometric assays of GUS activity were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Jefferson et al., 1987</xref>). Luminescence and fluorescence were determined with GENios microplate reader (Tecan).</p><p>For transient expression assays involving the <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> and <italic>VSP1</italic> promoter fragments, full-length <italic>MYC2</italic>, <italic>ORA59</italic>, and <italic>ERF1</italic> were cloned into the plant expression vector pEarleyGate100 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Earley et al., 2006</xref>) using Gateway recombination system (Invitrogen). The 1,187-bp promoter fragment of the <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Zarei et al., 2011</xref>) and 1,860-bp <italic>VSP1</italic> promoter fragment were amplified with Gateway compatible primers and cloned into pDONRZeo (Invitrogen) and then recombined with the binary vector pBGWFS7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Karimi et al., 2002</xref>). The transient expression assays by particle bombardment were essentially carried out same as above except that the amount of the reporter plasmid used was 5 &#x03BC;g.</p></sec><sec><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">BiFC</xref> Experiments</title><p>For the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">BiFC</xref> experiments, YFP<sup>C</sup>:Med25&#x0394;Q-rich and YFP<sup>C</sup>:Med25&#x0394;ACID/Q-rich constructs were generated by fusing 1 to 681 amino acids and 1 to 558 amino acids of MED25 protein with the binary vector <italic>pBiFP</italic>-<italic>3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Azimzadeh et al., 2008</xref>), respectively. YFP<sup>N</sup>:Ora59, YFP<sup>N</sup>:ORA59<sup>1-139</sup>, YFP<sup>N</sup>:ORA59<sup>80-214</sup>, and YFP<sup>N</sup>:ORA59<sup>139-244</sup> were generated by fusing the full length or 1 to 139, 80 to 214, and 139 to 244 amino acids of ORA59 with the binary plasmid <italic>pBiFP</italic>-<italic>2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Azimzadeh et al., 2008</xref>). We also coexpressed red fluorescent protein (mRFP), which accumulates in the cytoplasm and nucleus, and provides a positive transformation control. For this, we cloned mRFP into the binary plasmid pEarleyGate 100 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Earley et al., 2006</xref>) to generate <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>mRFP</italic>. The constructs were then transformed into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain GV3101 (pMP90). <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic>-mediated transient expression experiments were performed on 4- to 5-week-old <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> plants. <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strains grown in Luria broth were harvested by centrifugation and resuspended in infiltration medium (10 m<sc>m</sc> MES pH 5.6; 10 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>; 150 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> acetosyringone) to a final OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.5 and incubated at room temperature for 3 h. For all transient coexpression assays, <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strains carrying the constructs were mixed in a 1:1:1 ratio in infiltration medium to a final OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.2 and infiltrated into <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves using a needleless syringe. Two days after infiltration, the images were obtained using an LSM 710 laser scanning microscope (Carl Zeiss). Images were processed with Zen software (Carl Zeiss) and ImageJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abramoff et al., 2004</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Microarray Comparisons</title><p>The <italic>med25</italic> array was analyzed as previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>). The genes differentially regulated by <italic>med25</italic> were determined using a two-way ANOVA for either genotype or treatment using GeneSpring (Agilent Technologies) and the gene list obtained based on the effect of genotype was used for comparisons. To make the array more comparable to the <italic>myc2</italic> gene list the Benjamini and Hochberg false discovery rate was removed and only genes that passed Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) were compiled and compared with those genes found to be significantly different in the <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>ERF1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lorenzo et al., 2003</xref>), <italic>XVE</italic>:<italic>ORA59</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>), and <italic>myc2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>) arrays using their published gene lists. Common genes between <italic>med25</italic> and the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> gene lists were identified using either FiRe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Garcion et al., 2006</xref>) or manually using the VLOOKUP function in Microsoft Excel 2007 (Microsoft Corporation). The common genes were then sorted based on their fold-change expression in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> array and color coded depending on whether they were induced or repressed. The statistical analysis on the common genes was performed using the hypergeometric distribution in R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">R Development Core Team, 2011</xref>). This analysis calculates the likelihood of observing the number of common genes by chance given the size of the two gene lists and the total number of common genes from which the gene lists were derived.</p></sec><sec><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">RT-qPCR</xref> Analyses</title><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">RT-qPCR</xref> experiments were done as described previously using the 7900HT real-time PCR system (Applied Biosystems) in conjunction with SYBR Green fluorescence to detect transcript levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">McGrath et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>). Absolute gene expression levels relative to the previously validated reference genes &#x03B2;-<italic>ACTIN2</italic>, &#x03B2;-<italic>ACTIN7</italic>, and &#x03B2;-<italic>ACTIN8</italic> were used for each complementary DNA sample using the equation: relative abundance &#x003D; [Egene^(&#x2212;Ct gene)]/[EACTIN^(&#x2212;Ct ACTIN)]. The mean expression range of the reference gene was found to be within &#x00B1;1 Ct across all experiments. The sequences of the primer pairs have been previously published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Anderson et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">McGrath et al., 2005</xref>).</p><p>Sequence data from this article can be found in the Arabidopsis Genome Initiative data libraries under the following accession numbers: MED25 (AT1G25540); MYC2 (AT1G32640); ERF1 (AT3G23240); ERF4 (AT3G15210); WRKY10 (AT1G55600); MYB104 (AT2G26950); ERF15 (AT2G31230); bZIP (AT2G31370); TDR1 (AT3G23230); MYC3 (AT5G46760); MYC4 (AT4G17880); B-Box (AT4G39070); DREB2A (AT5G05410); PDF1.2 (AT5G44420); and VSP1 (AT5G24780).</p></sec><sec><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> Pull-down experiment using GST-tagged <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> proteins with His-GFP protein as an additional control.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> Identification of MED25-interacting domain of ORA59 in yeast.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S3.</bold></ext-link> Detection of MED25-ORA59 interactions via transient coexpression of YFPC:MED25&#x0394;Q-rich and YFPN:ORA59, YFPN:ORA591-139, YFPN:ORA5980-214, or YFPN:ORA59139-244 constructs as well as YFPC:MED25&#x0394;ACID/Q-rich with YFPN:ORA59 or YFPN:ORA59139-244 constructs.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S4.</bold></ext-link> Quantitative assays of &#x03B2;-galactosidase activity reveal a reduction in LacZ activity in the interactions of MED25&#x0394;vWF-A/Q-rich fragment with mutant forms of TDR1, ERF1, and ERF15.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S5.</bold></ext-link> Cotransformation of wild-type and <italic>med25</italic> plants with <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> and <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>LUC</italic> constructs using particle bombardment method shows no significant difference between wild-type and <italic>med25</italic> plants for transformation efficiencies.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S6.</bold></ext-link> The expression of <italic>ORA59</italic>, <italic>ERF1</italic>, <italic>MYC2</italic>, <italic>MYC3</italic>, and <italic>MYC4</italic> is unchanged in <italic>med25</italic> relative to the wild type.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S1.</bold></ext-link> The <italic>med25</italic> gene list used for the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> microarray comparisons.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S2.</bold></ext-link> The genes that were common between the <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>ERF1</italic> microarray gene list (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lorenzo et al., 2003</xref>) and the <italic>med25</italic> microarray gene list (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>).</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S3.</bold></ext-link> The genes that were common between the <italic>XVE</italic>:<italic>ORA59</italic> microarray gene list (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pr&#x00E9; et al., 2008</xref>) and the <italic>med25</italic> microarray gene list (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>).</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S4.</bold></ext-link> The genes that were common between the <italic>myc2</italic> microarray gene list (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Dombrecht et al., 2007</xref>) and the <italic>med25</italic> microarray gene list (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kidd et al., 2009</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>).</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S5.</bold></ext-link> The average relative expression of defense-associated genes in the <italic>med25</italic>, <italic>myc2</italic>, and <italic>med25 myc2</italic> mutants with or without <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">JA</xref> treatment using <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">RT-qPCR</xref>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202697/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S6.</bold></ext-link> The list of AP2/ERFs that were identified using two different <italic>ORA59</italic> promoter sequences in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Y1H</xref> analyses along with their groups according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Nakano et al. (2006)</xref>.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We wish to thank Franziska Turck (Max Planck Institute, Cologne) for providing the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">TF</xref> library.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abramoff</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Magelhaes</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ram</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Image processing with ImageJ</article-title>. <source>Biophot Internat</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>36</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>42</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Badruzsaufari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Desmond</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehlert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Antagonistic interaction between abscisic acid and jasmonate-ethylene signaling pathways modulates defense gene expression and disease resistance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>3460</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3479</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Autran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Belcram</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Beemster</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronenberger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandjean</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Inz&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Traas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Cell numbers and leaf development in Arabidopsis: a functional analysis of the STRUWWELPETER gene</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>6036</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>6049</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azimzadeh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nacry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Christodoulidou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Drevensek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Camilleri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Amiour</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Parcy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastuglia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouchez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> TONNEAU1 proteins are essential for preprophase band formation and interact with centrin</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2146</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2159</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x00E4;ckstr&#x00F6;m</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Elfving</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingsle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x00F6;rklund</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Purification of a plant mediator from Arabidopsis thaliana identifies PFT1 as the Med25 subunit</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>717</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>729</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berrocal-Lobo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Constitutive expression of ETHYLENE-RESPONSE-FACTOR1 in Arabidopsis confers resistance to several necrotrophic fungi</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>32</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blomberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x00E4;nnstr&#x00F6;m</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rautio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Olofsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittung-Stafshede</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x00F6;rklund</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Interactions between DNA, transcriptional regulator Dreb2a and the Med25 mediator subunit from Arabidopsis thaliana involve conformational changes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>5938</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5950</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bontems</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Verger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewitte</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lens</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Baert</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>de Launoit</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sizun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Guittet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Villeret</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>NMR structure of the human Mediator MED25 ACID domain</article-title>. <source>J Struct Biol</source> <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>251</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ru&#x00ED;z-Rivero</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdeen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Conserved MYC transcription factors play a key role in jasmonate signaling both in tomato and Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1577</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1591</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Deyholos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Openshaw</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Galbraith</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The sfr6 mutant of Arabidopsis is defective in transcriptional activation via CBF/DREB1 and DREB2 and shows sensitivity to osmotic stress</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>395</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>406</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A role for the GCC-box in jasmonate-mediated activation of the <italic>PDF1</italic>.<italic>2</italic> gene of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>1020</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1032</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castrillo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Turck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Leveugle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecharny</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Paz-Ares</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x00F1;ate-S&#x00E1;nchez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Speeding cis-trans regulation discovery by phylogenomic analyses coupled with screenings of an arrayed library of Arabidopsis transcription factors</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e21524</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cerd&#x00E1;n</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Regulation of flowering time by light quality</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>423</volume>: <fpage>881</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>885</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The bHLH transcription factor MYC3 interacts with the jasmonate ZIM-domain proteins to mediate jasmonate response in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>288</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x00E1;ndez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Adie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chico</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x00ED;a-Casado</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x00F3;pez-Vidriero</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponce</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The JAZ family of repressors is the missing link in jasmonate signalling</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>448</volume>: <fpage>666</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>671</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Magusin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chilcott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Expression profiling reveals COI1 to be a key regulator of genes involved in wound- and methyl jasmonate-induced secondary metabolism, defence, and hormone interactions</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>497</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>513</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhawan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Foerster</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abuqamar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittelsten Scheid</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Mengiste</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>HISTONE MONOUBIQUITINATION1 interacts with a subunit of the mediator complex and regulates defense against necrotrophic fungal pathogens in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1000</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1019</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobi</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Winston</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Analysis of transcriptional activation at a distance in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</italic></article-title> <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>5575</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5586</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dombrecht</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkegaard</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitt</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sewelam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>MYC2 differentially modulates diverse jasmonate-dependent functions in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2225</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2245</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Earley</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Opper</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Juehne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pikaard</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Gateway-compatible vectors for plant functional genomics and proteomics</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>616</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>629</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eletsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruyechan</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Acton</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Montelione</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Szyperski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Solution NMR structure of MED25(391-543) comprising the activator-interacting domain (ACID) of human mediator subunit 25</article-title>. <source>J Struct Funct Genomics</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>166</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elfving</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Davoine</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Benlloch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Blomberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x00E4;nnstr&#x00F6;m</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulfstedt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingsle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis thaliana Med25 mediator subunit integrates environmental cues to control plant development</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>8245</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>8250</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x00E1;ndez-Calvo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x00E1;ndez-Barbero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chico</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimenez-Ibanez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Geerinck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eeckhout</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweizer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Godoy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco-Zorrilla</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> bHLH transcription factors MYC3 and MYC4 are targets of JAZ repressors and act additively with MYC2 in the activation of jasmonate responses</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>701</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>715</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feys</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Penfold</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutants selected for resistance to the phytotoxin coronatine are male sterile, insensitive to methyl jasmonate, and resistant to a bacterial pathogen</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>751</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>759</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcion</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Baltensperger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasquier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnetzer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00E9;traux</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>FiRe and microarrays: a fast answer to burning questions</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>320</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>322</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillmor</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepitone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerstetter</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The MED12-MED13 module of Mediator regulates the timing of embryo patterning in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>122</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Conlan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The transcription corepressor LEUNIG interacts with the histone deacetylase HDA19 and mediator components MED14 (SWP) and CDK8 (HEN3) to repress transcription</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>5306</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5315</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuber</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Regulation of disease resistance pathways by AP2/ERF transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>465</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>471</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukushige</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Evidence supporting a role of jasmonic acid in Arabidopsis leaf senescence</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>876</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>884</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Ubiquitin ligase-coupled receptors extend their reach to jasmonate</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>154</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>474</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>I&#x00F1;igo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Califano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerdan</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>PFT1, the MED25 subunit of the plant Mediator complex, promotes flowering through CONSTANS dependent and independent mechanisms in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>601</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>612</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavanagh</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bevan</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>GUS fusions: beta-glucuronidase as a sensitive and versatile gene fusion marker in higher plants</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>3901</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3907</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Inz&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Depicker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>GATEWAY vectors for Agrobacterium-mediated plant transformation</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>195</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>JAZ repressors and the orchestration of phytohormone crosstalk</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>31</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Diverse roles of the Mediator complex in plants</article-title>. <source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>741</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>748</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The mediator complex subunit PFT1 is a key regulator of jasmonate-dependent defense in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>2237</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2252</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Chico</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x00E1;nchez-Serrano</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>JASMONATE-INSENSITIVE1 encodes a MYC transcription factor essential to discriminate between different jasmonate-regulated defense responses in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1938</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1950</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Piqueras</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x00E1;nchez-Serrano</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>ETHYLENE RESPONSE FACTOR1 integrates signals from ethylene and jasmonate pathways in plant defense</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>178</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Penninckx</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermaere</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cammue</surname><given-names>BPA</given-names></name><name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The promoter of the plant defensin gene PDF1.2 from Arabidopsis is systemically activated by fungal pathogens and responds to methyl jasmonate but not to salicylic acid</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1071</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1080</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Mediator complex in plants: structure, phylogeny, and expression profiling of representative genes in a dicot (Arabidopsis) and a monocot (rice) during reproduction and abiotic stress</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>157</volume>: <fpage>1609</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1627</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McConn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Creelman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullet</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Jasmonate is essential for insect defense in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>5473</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5477</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dombrecht</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Repressor- and activator-type ethylene response factors functioning in jasmonate signaling and disease resistance identified via a genome-wide screen of Arabidopsis transcription factor gene expression</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>949</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>959</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milbradt</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Selenko</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x00E4;&#x00E4;r</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Structure of the VP16 transactivator target in the Mediator</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>410</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>415</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mittler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x00FC;hler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Santolin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhlmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kremmer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lottspeich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Berti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Meisterernst</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A novel docking site on Mediator is critical for activation by VP16 in mammalian cells</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>6494</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>6504</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinshi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide analysis of the ERF gene family in Arabidopsis and rice</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>411</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>432</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Achard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lis&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harberd</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JDG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>DELLAs control plant immune responses by modulating the balance of jasmonic acid and salicylic acid signaling</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>650</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>655</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunoyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dharmasiri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Estelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Voinnet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A plant miRNA contributes to antibacterial resistance by repressing auxin signaling</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>312</volume>: <fpage>436</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>439</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Characterization of JAZ-interacting bHLH transcription factors that regulate jasmonate responses in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>2143</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2154</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>KQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wing Hui</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A high-throughput screening system for Arabidopsis transcription factors and its application to Med25-dependent transcriptional regulation</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>546</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>555</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pauwels</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Goossens</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The JAZ proteins: a crucial interface in the jasmonate signaling cascade</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3089</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3100</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penninckx</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomma</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00E9;traux</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Concomitant activation of jasmonate and ethylene response pathways is required for induction of a plant defensin gene in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>2103</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2113</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pr&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Atallah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Champion</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Memelink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The AP2/ERF domain transcription factor ORA59 integrates jasmonic acid and ethylene signals in plant defense</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>1347</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1357</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The jasmonate-ZIM-domain proteins interact with the WD-repeat/bHLH/MYB complexes to regulate Jasmonate-mediated anthocyanin accumulation and trichome initiation in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1795</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1814</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><citation citation-type="other"><collab>R Development Core Team</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <comment>R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna</comment>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rehmany</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Whisson</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamoun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Beynon</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Differential recognition of highly divergent downy mildew avirulence gene alleles by RPP1 resistance genes from two <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> lines</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1839</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1850</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Coordinated plant defense responses in Arabidopsis revealed by microarray analysis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>11655</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>11660</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheard</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Withers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Nissan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Jasmonate perception by inositol-phosphate-potentiated COI1-JAZ co-receptor</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>468</volume>: <fpage>400</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>405</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The jasmonate-ZIM domain proteins interact with the R2R3-MYB transcription factors MYB21 and MYB24 to affect jasmonate-regulated stamen development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1000</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1013</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spoel</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Claessens</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Korzelius</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Pelt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchala</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00E9;traux</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title><italic>NPR1</italic> modulates cross-talk between salicylate- and jasmonate-dependent defense pathways through a novel function in the cytosol</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>760</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>770</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thatcher</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Manners</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title><italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> hijacks COI1-mediated jasmonate signaling to promote disease development in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>927</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>939</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thines</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsir</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Melotto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandaokar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>JAZ repressor proteins are targets of the SCF(<sup>COI1</sup>) complex during jasmonate signalling</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>448</volume>: <fpage>661</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>665</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomma</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggermont</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Penninckx</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauch-Mani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelsang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cammue</surname><given-names>BPA</given-names></name><name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Separate jasmonate-dependent and salicylate-dependent defense-response pathways in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> are essential for resistance to distinct microbial pathogens</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>15107</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>15111</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Belachew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ade</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Holtan</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The EDLL motif: a potent plant transcriptional activation domain from AP2/ERF transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>855</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>865</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vojnic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mour&#x00E3;o</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seizl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenzeck</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Larivi&#x00E8;re</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Meisterernst</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sattler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Structure and VP16 binding of the Mediator Med25 activator interaction domain</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>404</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>409</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wathugala</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemsley</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moffat</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cremelie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Mediator subunit SFR6/MED16 controls defence gene expression mediated by salicylic acid and jasmonate responsive pathways</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>195</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>230</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wollenberg</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerd&#x00E1;n</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Acceleration of flowering during shade avoidance in Arabidopsis alters the balance between FLOWERING LOCUS C-mediated repression and photoperiodic induction of flowering</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>1681</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1694</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Control of final organ size by Mediator complex subunit 25 in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>4545</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>4554</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ch&#x00E9;telat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reymond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubugnon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A downstream mediator in the growth repression limb of the jasmonate pathway</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2470</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2483</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>DeBeaumont</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x00E4;&#x00E4;r</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The activator-recruited cofactor/Mediator coactivator subunit ARC92 is a functionally important target of the VP16 transcriptional activator</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>2339</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2344</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>La Camera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamotte</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00E9;traux</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis thaliana class-II TGA transcription factors are essential activators of jasmonic acid/ethylene-induced defense responses</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>200</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>210</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zarei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x00F6;rbes</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Younessi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Montiel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Champion</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Memelink</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Two GCC boxes and AP2/ERF-domain transcription factor ORA59 in jasmonate/ethylene-mediated activation of the PDF1.2 promoter in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>331</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Wound-induced endogenous jasmonates stunt plant growth by inhibiting mitosis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e3699</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>A</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>To</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Derepression of ethylene-stabilized transcription factors (EIN3/EIL1) mediates jasmonate and ethylene signaling synergy in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>12539</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>12544</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
