<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">171462</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.171462</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>DEVELOPMENT AND HORMONE ACTION</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Role of PENNYWISE and POUND-FOOLISH in the Maintenance of the Shoot Apical Meristem in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[OA]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ung</surname><given-names>Nolan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lal</surname><given-names>Shruti</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Harley M.S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&ast;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Center for Plant Cell Biology, Institute for Integrative Genome Biology, Department of Botany and Plant Sciences (N.U., H.M.S.S.), and Genetics, Genomics, and Bioinformatics Graduate Program (S.L., H.M.S.S.), University of California, Riverside, California 92521</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&ast;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>harleys@ucr.edu</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation (grant no. IOB&ndash;0615774), by the U.S. Department of Agriculture-Agricultural Experimental Station, and by the National Institutes of Health (grant no. GM062756 to N.U.).</p></fn><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Harley M.S. Smith (<email>harleys@ucr.edu</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[OA]</label><p>Open Access articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.110.171462">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.110.171462</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>6</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>156</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>614</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2011 American Society of Plant Biologists</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p></p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Growth of the aerial part of the plant is dependent upon the maintenance of the shoot apical meristem (SAM). A balance between the self-renewing stem cells in the central zone (CZ) and organogenesis in the peripheral zone (PZ) is essential for the integrity, function, and maintenance of the SAM. Understanding how the SAM maintains a balance between stem cell perpetuation and organogenesis is a central question in plant biology. Two related BELL1-like homeodomain proteins, PENNYWISE (PNY) and POUND-FOOLISH (PNF), act to specify floral meristems during reproductive development. However, genetic studies also show that PNY and PNF regulate the maintenance of the SAM. To understand the role of PNY and PNF in meristem maintenance, the expression patterns for genes that specifically localize to the peripheral and central regions of the SAM were examined in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>). Results from these experiments indicate that the integrity of the CZ is impaired in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants, which alters the balance of stem cell renewal and organogenesis. As a result, pools of CZ cells may be allocated into initiating leaf primordia. Consistent with these results, the integrity of the central region of <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs can be partially restored by increasing the size of the CZ. Interestingly, flower specification is also reestablished by augmenting the size of the SAM in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants. Taken together, we propose that PNY and PNF act to restrict organogenesis to the PZ by maintaining a boundary between the CZ and PZ.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Postembryonic shoot development is dependent upon the shoot apical meristem (SAM), a highly organized group of self-renewing cells, which initiates leaves, axillary meristems, and structures such as internodes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Steeves and Sussex, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lyndon, 1998</xref>). The SAM is subdivided into cytohistological domains including the central zone (CZ), which is located at the apical tip of the SAM and is the site at which stem cells are maintained. Lateral organs are initiated at the peripheral zone (PZ), which surrounds the CZ on its flanks, while the rib meristem (RM) located beneath the CZ produces cells that differentiate into the internal stem tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bernier et al., 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Steeves and Sussex, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lyndon, 1998</xref>). The maintenance of the SAM is achieved by a balance of stem cell renewal in the CZ and the allocation of cells into primordia in the PZ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Vollbrecht et al., 2000</xref>). To date, little is known about how the SAM regulates the balance of these two interdependent processes in the CZ and PZ.</p><p>In Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), recent studies show that the integrity of the CZ and RM is maintained by the CLV-WUS negative feedback system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Sablowski, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Tucker and Laux, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bleckmann and Simon, 2009</xref>). The <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> (<italic>WUS</italic>) homeobox gene, expressed in a small number of cells in the core of the SAM, acts to maintain stem cell identity in the CZ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laux et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mayer et al., 1998</xref>). The <italic>CLAVATA</italic> (<italic>CLV</italic>) genes encode receptors, CLV1 and CLV2, and a secreted ligand, CLV3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Clark, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Fletcher, 2002</xref>). The <italic>CLV3</italic> expression domain marks the CZ, while <italic>CLV1</italic> is expressed in the core of the meristem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Clark et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Fletcher et al., 1999</xref>). The CLV pathway functions to down-regulate and restrict the <italic>WUS</italic> expression domain to the cells in the core of the SAM. At the same time, WUS somehow signals to the apical cells to promote <italic>CLV3</italic> expression in the CZ. The negative feedback interaction displayed by CLV3 and WUS acts to maintain a stable population of stem cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brand et al., 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Schoof et al., 2000</xref>). Mathematical modeling predicts that an additional signaling mechanism(s) is required to maintain stem cells in the CZ and the <italic>WUS</italic> expression domain in the RM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">J&#x00F6;nsson et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Geier et al., 2008</xref>). Recent studies indicate that stem cells produce active cytokinins (CKs; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kurakawa et al., 2007</xref>), which regulate the <italic>WUS</italic> expression domain through CLV-dependent and independent pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Gordon et al., 2009</xref>). At the same time, WUS functions to down-regulate the CK negative RESPONSE REGULATOR5 (ARR5), ARR6, ARR7, and ARR15, creating a region of high CK response in the RM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Leibfried et al., 2005</xref>). Thus, CK and WUS form a positive feedback loop, which functions to specify the RM and the stem cells during shoot growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Gordon et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>The Arabidopsis KNOTTED1-like HOMEOBOX (KNOX) protein SHOOT MERISTEMLESS (STM) regulates the maintenance of the SAM during shoot development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Long et al., 1996</xref>). Phenotypic analysis of weak <italic>stm</italic> alleles indicates that this homeodomain protein maintains the central region of the SAM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Endrizzi et al., 1996</xref>) as well as organ boundaries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Barton and Poethig, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Endrizzi et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kanrar et al., 2006</xref>). Experimental studies indicate that STM regulates lateral organ boundaries via the interplay between cytokinin and gibberellin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Jasinski et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Yanai et al., 2005</xref>). Genetic analyses demonstrate that loss of CLV1 and CLV3 function partially restores shoot development in <italic>stm</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Clark et al., 1996</xref>). At the same time, <italic>stm</italic> suppresses the enlarged meristems produced in <italic>clv1</italic> and <italic>clv3</italic> plants. Therefore, results from this study indicate that STM and CLV proteins act in an opposite manner to regulate meristem maintenance and cell proliferation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Clark et al., 1996</xref>). In maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>), the interplay between <italic>knotted1</italic> and <italic>thick tassel dwarf1</italic>, the orthologs of <italic>STM</italic> and <italic>CLV1</italic>, respectively, appear to also act oppositely in regulating SAM homeostasis, but only during reproductive development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Lunde and Hake, 2009</xref>). Interestingly, the hypomorphic mutant called <italic>gorgon</italic> represents a novel <italic>stm</italic> allele that leads to an increase in the size of the SAM due to the expansion of the central region, which includes the <italic>CLV3</italic> and <italic>WUS</italic> expression domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Takano et al., 2010</xref>). It was postulated that the increase in the size of the central region of the SAM is attributed to a reduction in the allocation of cells into lateral organs and axillary meristems. Taken together, STM acts to control multiple processes that maintain the integrity and function of the SAM.</p><p>Genetic and molecular studies indicate that KNOX proteins are regulated in part by the interaction with specific BELL1-like homeodomain (BLH) proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Hake et al., 2004</xref>). In Arabidopsis, BLH proteins play crucial roles in regulating meristem function and fate during plant development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hamant and Pautot, 2010</xref>). Genetic studies show that the <italic>BLH</italic> gene called <italic>PENNYWISE</italic> (<italic>PNY</italic>; also known as <italic>BELLRINGER</italic>, <italic>REPLUMLESS</italic>, <italic>VAAMANA</italic>, and <italic>BLH9</italic>) is required for internode patterning as well as flower and fruit development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Byrne et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Roeder et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Smith and Hake, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bao et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bhatt et al., 2004</xref>). Mutations in a gene closely related to <italic>PNY</italic> called <italic>POUND-FOOLISH</italic> (<italic>PNF</italic>) have no visible phenotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rutjens et al., 2009</xref>). However, the <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants initiate compact shoots that fail to form flowers even though a subset of inflorescence meristem identity genes are expressed in the SAM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rutjens et al., 2009</xref>). In the SAM, PNY is mainly expressed in the PZ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Smith and Hake, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Cole et al., 2006</xref>), while PNF transcripts localize to the CZ and PZ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>). Genetic analyses show that PNY and PNF also act to regulate meristem maintenance. For example, the SAM of <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants frequently terminates during early stages of vegetative growth, which corresponds to a time at which the meristem is small (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rutjens et al., 2009</xref>). After termination of the main shoot, the outgrowth of axillary shoots from the axils of the rosette leaves restores shoot development. Once the development of the axillary shoots is established, the frequency of SAM termination decreases. Histological analyses demonstrate that <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs are smaller and narrower than wild-type SAMs, indicating that the integrity of the CZ and/or PZ is altered. The fact that internode patterning is impaired in <italic>pny</italic> and <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants suggests that these homeodomain proteins also regulate RM integrity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Byrne et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Roeder et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Smith and Hake, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bao et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bhatt et al., 2004</xref>). Genetic evidence indicates that the association of PNY and PNF with STM regulates meristem maintenance during shoot growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Byrne et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bhatt et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kanrar et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rutjens et al., 2009</xref>). Currently, the role of PNY and PNF in regulating meristem maintenance is not understood.</p><p>In this paper, the role of PNY and PNF in SAM integrity was investigated. Localization of a PZ-expressed gene indicates that the integrity of the meristem&#x2019;s central region is impaired in <italic>pny pnf</italic>. Consistent with this result, the localization pattern for genes expressed in the central region of the SAM, including <italic>CLV3</italic> and <italic>WUS</italic>, is altered in <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs. Interestingly, the expression patterns for WUS and CLV3 are reestablished in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants lacking CLV function. The reproductive potential is also restored in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants, with a reduction in CLV function or an increase in WUS function. We propose a model in which PNY and PNF regulate the integrity of the central region of the SAM by maintaining a boundary between the CZ and PZ, which restricts the allocation of cells into leaf primordial to the PZ.</p><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>A Role for PNY and PNF in Regulating the Integrity of the Central Region of the SAM</title><p>Histological studies indicate that the SAM of <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants is narrower than that of wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>). To determine if PNY and PNF regulate the integrity of the SAM, the localization pattern of genes expressed in specific regions of the SAM was analyzed in 30-d-old wild-type and <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs. In wild-type inflorescence meristems, <italic>STM</italic> was expressed in the PZ and CZ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Long et al., 1996</xref>). On the flanks of wild-type shoot meristems, <italic>STM</italic> is down-regulated in a small group of cells that correspond to initial cells, which give rise to lateral organs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Long et al., 1996</xref>). In <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants, <italic>STM</italic> was also expressed in the SAM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>). In contrast to the mRNA localization pattern in wild-type SAMs, the expression domain for <italic>STM</italic> was narrower in <italic>pny pnf</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>). In addition, the cells in the periphery of <italic>pny pnf</italic> shoot meristems that fail to express <italic>STM</italic> appeared to impinge on the central region of the SAM, indicating that a higher proportion of meristem cells are allocated into leaf primordia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>, arrows). The fact that the size of the SAM and the expression domain for <italic>STM</italic> was narrower in <italic>pny pnf</italic> compared with the wild type indicates that the integrity of the central and/or peripheral regions of the SAM may be impaired. To address this, we first localized the transcripts for <italic>MONOPTEROS</italic> (<italic>MP</italic>), which was expressed in the PZ in wild-type inflorescence meristems (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hardtke and Berleth, 1998</xref>). <italic>MP</italic> encodes an auxin response factor, which regulates the positioning and organization of vascular cells required for patterning of the reproductive shoot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Przemeck et al., 1996</xref>). In <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants, cells expressing <italic>MP</italic> were detected on the flanks of the SAM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1D</xref>). However, in contrast to the wild type, the central region separating the <italic>MP</italic> expression domains was reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1D</xref>). These results indicate that the integrity of the central region of the SAM in <italic>pny pnf</italic> is impaired.</p><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>The integrity of the meristem&#x2019;s central region is impaired in <italic>pny pnf</italic>. Localization is shown for <italic>STM</italic> (A and B) and <italic>MP</italic> (C and D) transcripts in 30-d-old wild-type (WT) inflorescence (A and C) and <italic>pny pnf</italic> shoot (B and D) apices. In B, the arrows point to the leaf initial cells. In C and D, the arrows point to the <italic>MP</italic>-expressing cells. Bar &equals; 50 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_171462_gs_f1" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>PNY and PNF Regulate Gene Expression Patterns in the Core of the SAM</title><p>To gain insight into the role of PNY and PNF in regulating the central region of the SAM, the expression pattern for three genes expressed in the core of the SAM was compared between wild-type and <italic>pny pnf</italic> shoot apices. In wild-type inflorescence meristems, <italic>WUS</italic> localizes to a small number of cells located in the core of the SAM, overlapping with the apical cells of the RM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mayer et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). In contrast to the wild type, the <italic>WUS</italic> expression domain was diffuse and slightly expanded in <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Slight alterations in the <italic>WUS</italic> expression domain are observed during the floral transition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Geier et al., 2008</xref>). However, the perturbation of the <italic>WUS</italic> domain in <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs was not likely due to periodic fluctuations, since the diffuse pattern of expression for <italic>WUS</italic> was displayed in all the <italic>pny pnf</italic> shoot meristems analyzed (data not shown). To further characterize SAM integrity in <italic>pny pnf</italic>, two additional genes, <italic>At3g59270</italic> and <italic>At1g26680</italic>, expressed in the core of wild-type inflorescence meristems were examined (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Yadav et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, C and E</xref>). <italic>At3g59270</italic> and <italic>At1g26680</italic> encode a syntaxin-like protein and a B3 transcription factor, respectively. Unlike the diffuse localization pattern displayed by <italic>WUS</italic>, the <italic>At3g59270</italic> expression pattern was confined to fewer cells in the core of <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2D</xref>). Unlike <italic>WUS</italic> or <italic>At3g59270</italic>, transcripts for <italic>At1g26680</italic> were not detected in <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2F</xref>) even after a long period of exposure (data not shown). Although the functions of <italic>At3g59270</italic> and <italic>At1g26680</italic> have not been determined, this study shows that genes expressed in the core of the SAM respond differentially to the loss of PNY and PNF.</p><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Alteration in the expression patterns for genes transcribed in the core <italic>pny pnf</italic> shoot meristems. In 30-d-old plants, in situ hybridization was utilized to determine the spatial expression patterns for <italic>WUS</italic> (A), <italic>At3g59270</italic> (C), and <italic>At1g26680</italic> (E) in wild-type (WT) inflorescence apices. The mRNA localization patterns for <italic>WUS</italic> (B), <italic>At3g59270</italic> (D), and <italic>At1g26680</italic> (F) were examined in 30-d-old <italic>pny pnf</italic> apices. Bars &equals; 50 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_171462_gs_f2" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>PNY and PNF Regulate the Integrity of the CZ</title><p>To determine if the integrity of the CZ is altered in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants, the localization pattern of <italic>CLV3</italic> was determined. In wild-type inflorescence SAMs, <italic>CLV3</italic> transcripts localized to the CZ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Fletcher et al., 1999</xref>). In contrast to the wild type, <italic>CLV3</italic> transcript accumulation was not detected by in situ hybridization in <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>). The inability to detect <italic>CLV3</italic> transcript in the apical cells of <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs was surprising, since the shoot meristems of <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants are smaller than those of wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rutjens et al., 2009</xref>). A recent study indicates that the stability of GUS activity allows for the spatial detection of low-abundance transcripts that cannot be visualized by mRNA in situ hybridization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Shuai et al., 2002</xref>). Therefore, to examine the <italic>CLV3</italic> expression pattern further, <italic>pCLV3</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> was crossed into <italic>pny pnf</italic>. In wild-type SAMs, the pattern of <italic>pCLV3</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> activity was detected in the CZ of the SAM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brand et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3C</xref>). In contrast to the wild type, <italic>pCLV3</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> activity was detected throughout the SAM in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3D</xref>). The broad expression pattern detected for <italic>pCLV3</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants was not due to a diffusion of the signal, as the conditions used for this experiment were identical to those used to detect the expression of organ boundary genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Shuai et al., 2002</xref>). To determine if the relative levels of <italic>CLV3</italic> were similar in wild-type and <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs, quantitative (q)-PCR was performed. The results showed that transcript levels for <italic>CLV3</italic> were comparable between wild-type and <italic>pny pnf</italic> apices (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3E</xref>). Taken together, we propose that a decrease in the integrity of CZ in <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs alters the expression domain of <italic>CLV3</italic>. Furthermore, the impaired CZ may explain the aberrant expression patterns for genes expressed in the core of <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs, including <italic>WUS</italic>.</p><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>The <italic>CLV3</italic> expression domain is altered in <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs. A and B, <italic>CLV3</italic> transcripts were localized in 30-d-old wild-type inflorescence (A) and <italic>pny pnf</italic> shoot (B) apices. C and D, GUS activity was visualized in the apices of 30-d-old wild-type (C) and <italic>pny pnf</italic> (D) plants containing the <italic>CLV3</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> transgene. Bar &#x003D; <italic>50</italic> &#x03BC;m. E, The relative levels of <italic>CLV3</italic> transcripts were determine by q-PCR in the shoot apices of wild-type (WT) and <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants during vegetative (Veg) and inflorescence (Inf) development. In the q-PCR analysis, <italic>UBIQUITIN10</italic> (<italic>AT4G05320</italic>) was used as a reference.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_171462_gs_f3" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Restoration of Floral Specification in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> Plants</title><p>Mutations in <italic>clv</italic> genes result in a lateral expansion of the CZ and RM during shoot development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brand et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Schoof et al., 2000</xref>). Therefore, to determine if the alteration in the integrity of the CZ is attributed to the <italic>pny pnf</italic> phenotype, <italic>clv3-2</italic> was crossed to <italic>pny pnf</italic> and the <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> plants were examined. In the wild type, <italic>pny</italic>, and <italic>clv3</italic>, the inflorescences initiated flowers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, A&ndash;C</xref>). The inflorescence phenotypes of <italic>pny clv3</italic> plants are additive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Byrne et al., 2003</xref>), and the loss of these genes had no effect on floral specification (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4D</xref>). In addition, the inflorescence shoots produced by <italic>pnf clv3</italic> were morphologically similar to <italic>clv3</italic> (data not shown). In <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants, the compact shoots initiated leaves and displayed a non-flower-producing phenotype when plants were grown in long or short days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rutjens et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4E</xref>). Interestingly, under long-day photoinductive conditions, the SAMs of <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> underwent the floral transition, producing compact inflorescence shoots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, F&ndash;I</xref>) that initiated flower-like structures composed mostly of unfused carpels and some sepals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, J&ndash;L</xref>). The inflorescence shoots of <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> initiated under short-day growth conditions were similar in morphology to those in long-day conditions (data not shown). Floral specification also occurred in <italic>pny pnf clv1</italic>; however, the shoots were less compact and petals as well as stamen-like organs were initiated in addition to carpels and sepals (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.171462/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.171462/DC1">Supplemental Materials and Methods S1</ext-link>). These results demonstrate that loss of CLV function partially restored the floral specification potential of <italic>pny pnf</italic> shoots.</p><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Restoration of floral specification during <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> shoot development. A to D, Inflorescence shoots of wild-type (A), <italic>pny</italic> (B), <italic>clv3</italic> (C), and <italic>pny clv3</italic> (D) plants. E and F, Images of <italic>pny pnf</italic> (E) and <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> (F) plants. In F, the arrow points to the compact inflorescence shoot produced in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> plants. G, Closeup of a <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> inflorescence. H and I, Scanning electron microscopy images of a reproductive <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> apex. In H, bar &equals; 1 mm. In I, the arrow points to the shoot meristem. Bar &equals; 100 &#x03BC;m. J, Scanning electron microscopy image of unfused carpels produced during later stages of reproductive development. The arrow points to one of the unfused carpels. Bar &equals; 200 &#x03BC;m. K, A mature reproductive shoot of <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> was dissected with a razor blade to display the growth patterns. The arrows point to the reproductive shoots that produce the carpel-like organs. L, Closeup view of a carpel-bearing shoot. The arrow points to a carpel-like organ.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_171462_wc_f4" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title><italic>LEAFY</italic> Is Up-Regulated in the Reproductive Shoots of <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic></title><p>In Arabidopsis, environmental and endogenous cues converge and activate the key flower meristem identity gene <italic>LEAFY</italic> (<italic>LFY</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bl&#x00E1;zquez and Weigel, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Yamaguchi et al., 2009</xref>). LFY functions downstream of PNY and PNF, as flower specification is restored in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants overexpressing <italic>LFY</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kanrar et al., 2008</xref>). Therefore, to determine if the floral specification phenotype of <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> is attributed to the up-regulation of <italic>LFY</italic>, the expression pattern of this flower meristem identity gene was examined. In wild-type inflorescence apices, <italic>LFY</italic> was expressed in a small group of cells in the PZ of the SAM as well as in the floral meristem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Weigel et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>). During <italic>clv3</italic> inflorescence development, <italic>LFY</italic> was expressed in the floral meristem and small groups of cells in the peripheral region near the base of the SAM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>). In addition, <italic>LFY</italic> expression was not detected in the central region of the <italic>clv3</italic> inflorescence meristem, which corresponds to the enlarged CZ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>). In contrast to the wild type and <italic>clv3</italic>, <italic>LFY</italic> transcripts failed to accumulate in <italic>pny pnf</italic> shoot meristems under conditions that promote reproductive development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kanrar et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>). In <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic>, <italic>LFY</italic> was expressed in the reproductive shoot meristems, demonstrating that the floral specification potential was restored in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> SAMs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5D</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic>LFY</italic> in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> reproductive shoots. The spatial expression pattern for <italic>LFY</italic> was determined in wild-type (WT; A), <italic>pny pnf</italic> (B), <italic>clv3</italic> (C), and <italic>pny pnf</italic> (D) apices after 30 d of growth. The inflorescence meristem of <italic>clv3</italic> (C) is much larger than the wild-type meristems (A), due to the expanded CZ. In A and C, the arrows point to <italic>LFY</italic>-expressing cells in the PZ of the shoot meristem. The arrowheads point at the floral meristems. Bars &equals; 50 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_171462_gs_f5" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The Integrity of the <italic>WUS</italic> Expression Domain Is Restored in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> Plants</title><p>To determine if PNY and PNF control the expression patterns for <italic>WUS</italic>, <italic>At3g59270</italic>, and <italic>At1g26680</italic> by maintaining the integrity of the CZ, the mRNA localization patterns for these genes were examined in the <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> triple mutant. Mutations in <italic>clv3</italic> led to the formation of enlarged shoot meristems in which the <italic>WUS</italic> domain expanded laterally in the SAM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brand et al., 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Schoof et al., 2000</xref>). In <italic>clv3</italic> SAMs, the expression domains also expanded for <italic>At3g59270</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6C</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Aggarwal et al., 2010</xref>) and <italic>At1g26680</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6E</xref>). Interestingly, in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic>, the <italic>WUS</italic> expression domain appeared to be restored such that <italic>WUS</italic> transcripts were easily detected in a small group of cells in the core of the SAM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>). In addition, the mRNA localization pattern for <italic>At3g59270</italic> expanded in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> SAMs compared with the expression pattern observed in <italic>pny pnf</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6D</xref>). However, unlike <italic>WUS</italic> and <italic>At3g59270</italic>, transcripts for <italic>At1g26680</italic> could not be detected in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> SAMs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6F</xref>) even after a long exposure period (data not shown). Taken together, these results indicate that functional integrity of the central region of the SAM is partially restored in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> plants. The fact that the <italic>WUS</italic> expression domain was reestablished in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> indicates that PNY and PNF regulate the <italic>WUS</italic> expression domain by maintaining the integrity of the CZ. That the expression pattern for <italic>At1g26680</italic> was not restored in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> SAMs suggests that PNY and PNF control a subset of &#x201C;core expressed genes&#x201D; independent of CZ regulation.</p><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Reestablishment of the <italic>WUS</italic> and <italic>At3g59270</italic> expression domains in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> shoot meristems. In 30-d-old plants, in situ hybridization was utilized to determine the spatial expression patterns for <italic>WUS</italic> (A), <italic>At3g59270</italic> (C), and <italic>At1g26680</italic> (E) in <italic>clv3</italic> inflorescence apices. The mRNA localization patterns for <italic>WUS</italic> (B), <italic>At3g59270</italic> (D), and <italic>At1g26680</italic> (F) were examined in 30-d-old <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> apices. Bars &equals; 50 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_171462_gs_f6" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Restoration of the <italic>CLV3</italic> Expression Domain in <italic>pny pnf clv1</italic></title><p>Although the expression domains do not completely coincide, experimental observations indicate that WUS positively regulates <italic>CLV3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brand et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Schoof et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Yadav et al., 2010</xref>). Since <italic>clv1</italic> produces a similar phenotype as <italic>clv3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Clark et al., 1995</xref>), we asked if restoration of the <italic>WUS</italic> expression domain correlated with the accumulation of <italic>CLV3</italic> transcripts in the apical cells of <italic>pny pnf clv1-8</italic> shoot meristems. In the SAMs of <italic>clv1</italic>, both the <italic>WUS</italic> and <italic>CLV3</italic> expression domains were expanded compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, A and C</xref>). Similar to <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic>, transcripts for <italic>WUS</italic> were detected at relatively high levels in the cells of the RM in <italic>pny pnf clv1-8</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). Moreover, the <italic>CLV3</italic> expression domain was also reestablished in the apical cells of the SAM in <italic>pny pnf clv1-8</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7D</xref>). Therefore, results from this experiment show that the loss of CLV signaling in <italic>pny pnf</italic> restores the ability of WUS to positively activate <italic>CLV3</italic> in the apical cells of the SAM.</p><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Restoration of the <italic>CLV3</italic> expression domain in <italic>pny pnf clv1</italic> plants. The spatial expression pattern for <italic>WUS</italic> was determined in 30-d-old <italic>clv1</italic> (A) and <italic>pny pnf clv1</italic> (C) inflorescence shoot apices. An expanded <italic>CLV3</italic> expression domain is detected in <italic>clv1</italic> (B) and <italic>pny pnf clv1</italic> (D) inflorescence apices. Bar &equals; 50 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_171462_gs_f7" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>An Increase in WUS Function Promotes Reproductive Development in <italic>pny pnf</italic> Plants</title><p>The fact that loss of CLV signaling in <italic>pny pnf</italic> restored floral specification and the <italic>WUS</italic> expression domain led us to examine whether the levels of this homeobox gene could trigger reproductive development in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants. Loss-of-function <italic>wus</italic> plants produced terminal shoots during vegetative and reproductive development due to the failure to maintain stem cells in the shoot and floral meristems (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Laux et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mayer et al., 1998</xref>). Genetic studies showed that <italic>clv3</italic> and <italic>clv1</italic> phenotypes are dependent upon WUS function, since <italic>wus clv3</italic> and <italic>wus clv1</italic> mutants display a phenotype similar to <italic>wus</italic> single mutants during vegetative and reproductive development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Schoof et al., 2000</xref>). To determine if WUS function is required for reproductive development in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic>, <italic>pny pnf clv3 wus-1</italic> plants were created and analyzed. During the vegetative mode of development, the plants of <italic>pny pnf clv3 wus-1</italic> produced terminal shoots that were morphologically similar to <italic>wus-1</italic> single mutants (data not shown). However, in contrast to <italic>wus-1</italic>, inflorescence shoots and flowers were never produced in <italic>pny pnf clv3 wus-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8B</xref>). Thus, these results showed that WUS function was required for reproductive development in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> plants.</p><fig id="fig8"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>The levels of WUS control floral specification in plants with reduced PNY and PNF function. A, Image of <italic>wus</italic> inflorescence shoots. B, The shoots of <italic>pny pnf clv3 wus</italic> fail to initiate flowers. C, The shoot apex of a <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>WUS-GR pny pnf</italic> plant treated with a mock solution without DEX. The arrow points to the leaf-bearing shoot apex. D, Repeated applications of DEX to <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>WUS-GR pny pnf</italic> plants promotes inflorescence development. E, Closeup of a carpel-like floral organ in a <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>WUS-GR pny pnf</italic> inflorescence. F, A single application of DEX to <italic>WUS-GR pny pnf</italic> induced the formation of terminal flowers. Bars &equals; 0.5 mm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_171462_wc_f8" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>The fusion of WUS to the glucocorticoid receptor-binding domain (GR) has been successfully used to induce WUS function in order to identify genes regulated by this homeodomain protein in a dexamethasone (DEX)-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brand et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Lenhard et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Leibfried et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Busch et al., 2010</xref>). Applications of 1 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> DEX to wild-type inflorescences have mild effects on flower development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kieffer et al., 2006</xref>; data not shown). To determine if an increase in WUS function can promote the floral specification in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants, <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>WUS-GR</italic> was crossed to <italic>pny pnf</italic> to create <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>WUS-GR pny pnf</italic> plants. In the absence of DEX, the shoots of <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>WUS-GR pny pnf</italic> plants treated with a control solution continued to produce leaves without any visible signs of flower formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8C</xref>). However, repeated applications of 1 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> DEX to <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>WUS-GR pny pnf</italic> produced inflorescences that terminated with sepal- and carpel-like organs approximately 43% of the time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8, D and E</xref>). In addition, a terminal flower often formed after <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>WUS-GR pny pnf</italic> plants were treated with a single application of 1 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> DEX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8F</xref>). These results showed that an increase in WUS function promotes the floral specification in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The function of the SAM is dependent upon the balance between the self-renewing activities of the stem cells and the allocation of PZ cells into lateral organs and axillary meristems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Vollbrecht et al., 2000</xref>). An alteration in the balance between stem-cell perpetuation and organogenesis is predicted to disrupt meristem function. In this paper, we provide evidence that PNY and PNF act to control meristem maintenance by regulating the integrity of the central region of the SAM. First, the expression pattern for <italic>MP</italic> indicates that the central region of the SAM is reduced in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants. Second, the expression patterns for <italic>WUS</italic>, <italic>At3g59270</italic>, <italic>At1g26680</italic>, and <italic>CLV3</italic> are altered. Third, the loss of CLV signaling, which increases the size of the central region of the SAM, restores the expression patterns for <italic>WUS</italic>, <italic>At3g59270</italic>, and <italic>CLV3</italic> in <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants. Experimental evidence indicates that PNY/PNF-STM complexes act to regulate meristem maintenance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Byrne et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bhatt et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kanrar et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rutjens et al., 2009</xref>). Furthermore, genetic analyses indicate that STM also regulates the central region of the SAM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Clark et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Endrizzi et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Long et al., 1996</xref>). Therefore, the association of PNY and PNF with STM may act to regulate the integrity of the CZ during shoot development.</p><p>During early stages of vegetative growth, the SAM of <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants frequently terminates after several leaves are initiated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rutjens et al., 2009</xref>). Shoot development is reestablished by the outgrowth of axillary shoots, which results in a bushy plant phenotype. The frequency of meristem termination decreases as the shoots grow and mature, presumably due to an increase in meristem size, which may render the SAM to be less susceptible to termination. This hypothesis is supported by studies showing that a null allele of the <italic>STM</italic> ortholog in maize called <italic>knotted1</italic> (<italic>kn1</italic>) displays a terminal shoot phenotype in inbred lines that typically produce smaller embryonic meristems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Vollbrecht et al., 2000</xref>). However, in inbred lines that initiate larger meristems, the SAM is readily maintained in <italic>kn1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kerstetter et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Vollbrecht et al., 2000</xref>). How might PNY and PNF regulate the integrity of the central region of the SAM? mRNA in situ hybridization experiments indicate that PNY and PNF expression patterns overlap in the PZ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Smith and Hake, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Cole et al., 2006</xref>). Therefore, these homeodomain proteins may act in the PZ to mediate the allocation of cells into initiating leaf primordia. Based on the expression patterns of <italic>STM</italic>, leaf initial cells appear to impinge on the central region of <italic>pny pnf</italic> shoot meristems. Thus, in the absence of PNY and PNF, the balance of organogenesis and stem cell renewal is altered, leading to the allocation of CZ cells into developing leaf primordia. Based on genetic analyses between <italic>clv</italic> and <italic>stm</italic> mutants, it was hypothesized that STM functions to maintain a boundary between the CZ and PZ in the SAM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Clark et al., 1996</xref>). In support of this hypothesis, we propose that PNY/PNF-STM complexes act to maintain a boundary between the CZ and PZ, which restricts organogenesis to the peripheral region of the SAM. During early stages of vegetative development, the small size of the <italic>pny pnf</italic> vegetative SAM combined with the failure to maintain the CZ/PZ boundary may result in the allocation of all of the CZ or stem cells into leaf primordia, resulting in the termination of the SAM. However, once shoot growth is established, the SAM is able to maintain itself, because the size of the meristem increases to a point at which a small pool of CZ or stem cells can be readily maintained. In <italic>pny pnf clv</italic> mutants, the central region of the meristem expands, leading to an increase in the size of the SAM. Expression analyses of <italic>WUS</italic>, <italic>At3g59270</italic>, and <italic>CLV3</italic> in <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> suggest that the integrity of the SAM&#x2019;s central region is partially restored, indicating that the CZ/PZ boundary is reestablished.</p><p>The CLV3-WUS negative feedback loop plays a pivotal role in maintaining a stable population of stem cells in the CZ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Sablowski, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Tucker and Laux, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bleckmann and Simon, 2009</xref>). To date, the mechanism by which WUS controls the spatial expression pattern of <italic>CLV3</italic> is poorly understood. However, the CZ/PZ boundary may provide positional cues that direct the transcription of <italic>CLV3</italic> to the CZ. In this study, experimental evidence suggests that the transcript levels for <italic>CLV3</italic> are similar between wild-type and <italic>pny pnf</italic> apices. However, we were unable to detect the <italic>CLV3</italic>-expressing cells by in situ hybridization in <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAMs. Furthermore, analysis of the <italic>CLV3</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> expression pattern in <italic>pny pnf</italic> shoot meristems suggests that the <italic>CLV3</italic> expression domain is expanded throughout the SAM. Based on our results, we propose that in the absence of PNY and PNF, the CZ/PZ boundary is not properly maintained. Therefore, the positional cues required for confining the spatial expression pattern of <italic>CLV3</italic> to the CZ are absent. As a result, WUS activates <italic>CLV3</italic> in all the cells of the meristem. However, since the CLV pathway acts to negatively regulate <italic>WUS</italic>, transcript levels for <italic>CLV3</italic> are expected to be significantly lower in the meristem cells of <italic>pny pnf</italic> than in the CZ cells of the wild type. Therefore, the cells of <italic>pny pnf</italic> shoot meristems express <italic>CLV3</italic> at a level that cannot be detected by in situ hybridization.</p><p>Recent studies show that a mutation in the <italic>BLH</italic> gene <italic>ARABIDOPSIS THALIANA HOMEOBOX1</italic> (<italic>ATH1</italic>) enhances the terminal shoot phenotype of <italic>pny pnf</italic> that occurs shortly after germination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rutjens et al., 2009</xref>). <italic>ATH1</italic> appears to be structurally and phylogenetically distinct from PNY and PNF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Quaedvlieg et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Mukherjee et al., 2009</xref>). Genetic studies indicate that ATH1 acts to maintain the basal boundary between the stem and lateral organ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">G&#x00F3;mez-Mena and Sablowski, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rutjens et al., 2009</xref>). Similar to PNY and PNF, ATH1 interacts with STM to regulate meristem maintenance events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hackbusch et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Rutjens et al., 2009</xref>). However, it is unclear if ATH1 acts redundantly with PNY and PNF. As postulated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Cole et al. (2006)</xref>, distinct KNOX-BLH complexes may regulate specific meristem maintenance pathways in discrete regions of the SAM. Therefore, the function of STM may be modulated by interaction with specific BLH proteins in the SAM. Consequently, ATH1-STM complexes may control the basal organ boundaries, while PNY/PNF-STM complexes act to restrict organogenesis to the PZ. Thus, the terminal SAM phenotype of <italic>pny pnf ath1</italic> plants may be due to combinatorial loss of multiple meristem maintenance pathways controlled by STM.</p><p>The fact that <italic>pny pnf clv</italic> mutants specify floral cell fate is quite intriguing. In <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants, leaf organogenesis is not perturbed, while the formation of flowers and the development of internodes are severely impaired. Clonal analysis studies indicate that a small number of meristem initial cells give rise to lateral organs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Stewart and Dermen, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Poethig, 1989</xref>). During the allocation processes, PNY and PNF may function in the PZ to establish positional cues in the initial cells that give rise to floral meristems and internodes. In the absence of PNY and PNF, the initial cells may not be competent for floral specification and internode patterning cues. In addition, fewer initial cells may be produced due to the smaller size of the <italic>pny pnf</italic> SAM. As a result, a reduction in the number of initial cells combined with a loss of positional information may have a dramatic effect on floral specification and internode patterning. However, in <italic>pny pnf clv</italic> shoots, the increase in the size of the SAM may augment the number of cells that are responsive to or competent for the cues that promote floral specification. Future studies are aimed at understanding how PNY and PNF act to establish positional cues in the PZ of the SAM.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Expression Analyses</title><p>Wild-type inflorescence and <italic>pny pnf</italic> apices from Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) were harvested and fixed 30 d after germination under long-day growth conditions. Tissue fixation, processing, and in situ hybridization were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jackson, 1991</xref>). Preparation of <italic>WUS</italic>, <italic>CLV3</italic>, <italic>At3g59270</italic>, and <italic>At1g26680</italic> in situ probes was described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Yadav et al., 2009</xref>). Preparation of <italic>STM</italic> and <italic>MP</italic> in situ probe was published previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Long et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Zhao et al., 2010</xref>). For each genotype examined by in situ hybridization, at least three biological replicas were fixed and sectioned. Two to three sectioned apices from each genotype were adhered to a single microscope slide. In this analysis, we performed at least one hybridization experiment for each replica. Therefore, each genotype was hybridized with a specific in situ probe six or more times.</p><p>For q-PCR, apices from wild-type and <italic>pny pnf</italic> plants were dissected before and after floral induction. Note that transcripts for the flower meristem identity gene, <italic>APETALA1</italic>, were only detected in the inflorescence shoot apices of the wild type (data not shown). RNA was isolated using the RNeasy kit from Qiagen. cDNA synthesis and q-PCR procedures were described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kanrar et al. (2008)</xref>. The <italic>CLV3-F</italic> (5&#x2032;-ATGGATTCGAAGAGTTTTCTG-3&#x2032;) and <italic>CLV3-R</italic> (5&#x2032;-CAAGGGAGCTGAAAGTTGTTTC-3&#x2032;) primers were used to amplify <italic>CLV3</italic>. <italic>UBIQUITIN10</italic> (<italic>AT4G05320</italic>) was used as a reference gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kanrar et al., 2008</xref>). Genotype determination for <italic>pny-40126</italic> and <italic>pnf-33879</italic> was described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Smith and Hake, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>). The procedure used to visualize GUS activity in plant tissues was described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Sundaresan et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Springer, 2000</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Genetic Analyses</title><p>The <italic>pny-40126</italic> and <italic>pnf-33879</italic> alleles used in this study were identified previously in the Columbia ecotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Smith and Hake, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Smith et al., 2004</xref>). <italic>clv1-8</italic>, which is in the Columbia background, was crossed to <italic>pny PNF/pnf</italic> in order to characterize the <italic>pny pnf clv1-8</italic> phenotype. The <italic>clv3-2</italic> and <italic>wus-1</italic> alleles, both in the Landsberg ecotype, were backcrossed to wild-type Columbia plants two times before crossing to <italic>pnf</italic>, <italic>pny</italic>, <italic>pny PNF/pnf</italic>, and <italic>pnf clv PNY/pnf</italic> plants. <italic>PNF</italic> and <italic>CLV3</italic> are located on chromosome 2 approximately 255 kb apart. To generate <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic> plants, we first crossed <italic>pnf</italic> with <italic>clv3</italic> and screened F3 for <italic>clv3</italic> plants that were heterozygous for <italic>pnf</italic>. After allowing these plants to self-pollinate, <italic>pnf clv3</italic> plants were crossed to <italic>pny</italic>. The phenotypes for <italic>pny pnf clv3</italic>, <italic>pny pnf clv1</italic>, and <italic>pny pnf clv3 wus</italic> plants were characterized by maintaining <italic>pnf clv3 PNY/pnf</italic>, <italic>pny clv1 PNF/pnf</italic>, and <italic>pnf clv3 PNY/pny WUS/wus</italic> plants. F3 <italic>pny clv3 WUS/wus</italic> and <italic>pny WUS/wus</italic> plants were used to characterize <italic>pny clv3 wus</italic> and <italic>pny wus</italic> plants. The <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>WUS-GR pny pnf</italic> plants were characterized by maintaining <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>WUS-GR pny PNF/pnf</italic> plants. To examine the spatial patterns of <italic>CLV3</italic>, wild-type plants containing <italic>pCLV3</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> were crossed to <italic>pny PNF/pnf</italic> plants. Seeds derived from <italic>pny PNF/pnf</italic> plants containing <italic>pCLV3</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> were used to analyze the expression pattern for <italic>CLV3</italic> in <italic>pCLV3</italic>:<italic>GUS pny pnf</italic> plants. <italic>CLV3</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> was created by fusing the <italic>CLV3</italic> promoter and 3&#x2032; enhancer region to <italic>GUS</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Brand et al., 2002</xref>).</p><p>All DEX induction experiments were performed 4 weeks after germination, to allow sufficient time for shoot maturation. In these experiments, 1 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> DEX was applied once or every other day for a 10-d period. The TM-1000 Tabletop Microscope from Hitachi (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.hitachi.com">www.hitachi.com</ext-link>) was used for scanning electron microscopy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Kanrar et al., 2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.171462/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1</bold></ext-link>. Flower specification occurs in <italic>pny pnf clv1</italic> plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.110.171462/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Materials and Methods S1</bold></ext-link>. Formation of inflorescence-like structures in <italic>pny pnf clv1</italic>.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Drs. Patricia Springer, Sarah Hake, Venugopala Reddy, and Alon Samach for critical reading of the manuscript. We thank Jennifer Fletcher for the <italic>clv1-8</italic> allele, Rudiger Simon for <italic>CLV3</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic>, and Detlef Weigel for the <italic>pDW124</italic> plasmid used to synthesize the <italic>LFY</italic> in situ probe. We also thank Venugopala Reddy for providing us with the <italic>wus-1</italic> allele, <italic>35S</italic>:<italic>WUS-GR</italic> seed, and plasmids containing <italic>CLV3</italic>, <italic>WUS</italic>, <italic>At3g59270</italic>, and <italic>At1g26680</italic>, which were used to synthesize the antisense UTP-digoxigenin-labeled probes. We thank Dr. David Carter for help with scanning electron microscopy.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Identification of novel markers for stem-cell niche of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> shoot apex</article-title>. <source>Gene Expr Patterns</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>264</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Repression of <italic>AGAMOUS</italic> by BELLRINGER in floral and inflorescence meristems</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1478</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1489</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Formation of the shoot apical meristem in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: an analysis of development in the wild type and in the <italic>shoot meristemless</italic> mutant</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>823</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>831</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>The Physiology of Flowering</article-title>, <volume>Vol 2</volume>. <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Etchells</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Canales</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagodienko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>VAAMANA, a BEL1-like homeodomain protein, interacts with KNOX proteins BP and STM and regulates inflorescence stem growth in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>328</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>111</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E1;zquez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Integration of floral inductive signals in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>404</volume>: <fpage>889</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>892</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bleckmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Interdomain signaling in stem cell maintenance of plant shoot meristems</article-title>. <source>Mol Cells</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>615</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>620</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Dependence of stem cell fate in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> on a feedback loop regulated by <italic>CLV3</italic> activity</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>289</volume>: <fpage>617</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>619</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Gr&#x00FC;newald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Regulation of <italic>CLV3</italic> expression by two homeobox genes in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>565</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>575</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Miotk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ariel</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Forner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Daum</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultheiss</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leibfried</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional control of a plant stem cell niche</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>849</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>861</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Groover</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Martienssen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Phyllotactic pattern and stem cell fate are determined by the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homeobox gene <italic>BELLRINGER</italic></article-title> <source>Development</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>3941</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3950</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Meristems: start your signaling</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>32</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The <italic>CLAVATA</italic> and <italic>SHOOT MERISTEMLESS</italic> loci competitively regulate meristem activity in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>1567</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1575</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Running</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title><italic>CLAVATA3</italic> is a specific regulator of shoot and floral meristem development affecting the same processes as <italic>CLAVATA1</italic></article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>2057</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2067</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The CLAVATA1 gene encodes a putative receptor kinase that controls shoot and floral meristem size in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>575</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>585</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Werr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Nuclear import of the transcription factor SHOOT MERISTEMLESS depends on heterodimerization with BLH proteins expressed in discrete sub-domains of the shoot apical meristem of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>1281</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1292</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Endrizzi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moussian</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Haecker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The <italic>SHOOT MERISTEMLESS</italic> gene is required for maintenance of undifferentiated cells in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> shoot and floral meristems and acts at a different regulatory level than the meristem genes <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> and <italic>ZWILLE</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>967</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>979</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Shoot and floral meristem maintenance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>66</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Running</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Signaling of cell fate decisions by CLAVATA3 in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> shoot meristems</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>1911</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1914</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerstung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A quantitative and dynamic model for plant stem cell regulation</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e3553</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x00F3;mez-Mena</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sablowski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title><italic>ARABIDOPSIS THALIANA HOMEOBOX GENE1</italic> establishes the basal boundaries of shoot organs and controls stem growth</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2059</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2072</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chickarmane</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Multiple feedback loops through cytokinin signaling control stem cell number within the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> shoot meristem</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>16529</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>16534</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hackbusch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhrig</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A central role of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> <italic>thaliana</italic> ovate family proteins in networking and subcellular localization of 3-aa loop extension homeodomain proteins</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>4908</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>4912</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Holtan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mele</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The role of knox genes in plant development</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>151</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamant</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Pautot</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Plant development: a TALE story</article-title>. <source>C R Biol</source> <volume>333</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>381</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Berleth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gene <italic>MONOPTEROS</italic> encodes a transcription factor mediating embryo axis formation and vascular development</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1405</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1411</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>, <comment>editor</comment> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title><italic>In Situ</italic> Hybridisation in Plants</article-title>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jasinski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Piazza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Craft</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsiantis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>KNOX action in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is mediated by coordinate regulation of cytokinin and gibberellin activities</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1560</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1565</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x00F6;nsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Heisler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gor</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mjolsness</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Modeling the organization of the WUSCHEL expression domain in the shoot apical meristem</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics (Suppl 1)</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>i232</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>i240</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanrar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arthur</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Courtier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Regulatory networks that function to specify flower meristems require the function of homeobox genes <italic>PENNYWISE</italic> and <italic>POUND-FOOLISH</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>924</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>937</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanrar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Onguka</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HMS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> inflorescence architecture requires the activities of KNOX-BELL homeodomain heterodimers</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>224</volume>: <fpage>1163</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1173</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerstetter</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laudencia-Chingcuanco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Loss-of-function mutations in the maize homeobox gene, knotted1, are defective in shoot meristem maintenance</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>3045</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3054</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Clerici</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Maulbetsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Analysis of the transcription factor WUSCHEL and its functional homologue in <italic>Antirrhinum</italic> reveals a potential mechanism for their roles in meristem maintenance</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>560</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>573</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Maekawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyozuka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Direct control of shoot meristem activity by a cytokinin-activating enzyme</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>445</volume>: <fpage>652</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>655</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x00FC;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The WUSCHEL gene is required for shoot and floral meristem integrity in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>96</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leibfried</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>To</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Stehling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kehle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Demar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieber</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>WUSCHEL controls meristem function by direct regulation of cytokinin-inducible response regulators</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>438</volume>: <fpage>1172</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1175</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x00FC;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The WUSCHEL and SHOOTMERISTEMLESS genes fulfil complementary roles in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> shoot meristem regulation</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>3195</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3206</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moan</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name><surname>Medford</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>A member of the KNOTTED class of homeodomain proteins encoded by the <italic>STM</italic> gene of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>379</volume>: <fpage>66</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>69</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lunde</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The interaction of knotted1 and thick tassel dwarf1 in vegetative and reproductive meristems of maize</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>181</volume>: <fpage>1693</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1697</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lyndon</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The Shoot Apical Meristem: Its Growth and Development</article-title>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoof</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Haecker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x00FC;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Role of <italic>WUSCHEL</italic> in regulating stem cell fate in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> shoot meristem</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>805</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>815</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brocchieri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x00FC;rglin</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A comprehensive classification and evolutionary analysis of plant homeobox genes</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2775</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2794</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Genetic mosaics and cell lineage analysis in plants</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>277</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Przemeck</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardtke</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Berleth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Studies on the role of the Arabidopsis gene MONOPTEROS in vascular development and plant cell axialization</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>200</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>237</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quaedvlieg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dockx</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rook</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisbeek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Smeekens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The homeobox gene <italic>ATH1</italic> of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is derepressed in the photomorphogenic mutants <italic>cop1</italic> and <italic>det1</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>129</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferr&#x00E1;ndiz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The role of the REPLUMLESS homeodomain protein in patterning the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> fruit</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1630</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1635</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutjens</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>van Eck-Stouten</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smeekens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Proveniers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Shoot apical meristem function in Arabidopsis requires the combined activities of three BEL1-like homeodomain proteins</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>641</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>654</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sablowski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The dynamic plant stem cell niches</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>644</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoof</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenhard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haecker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>KFX</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x00FC;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The stem cell population of Arabidopsis shoot meristems in maintained by a regulatory loop between the CLAVATA and WUSCHEL genes</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>635</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>644</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shuai</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynaga-Pe&#x00F1;a</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The <italic>lateral organ boundaries</italic> gene defines a novel, plant-specific gene family</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>747</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>761</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Competence to respond to floral inductive signals requires the homeobox genes <italic>PENNYWISE</italic> and <italic>POUND-FOOLISH</italic></article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>812</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>817</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The interaction of two homeobox genes, <italic>BREVIPEDICELLUS</italic> and <italic>PENNYWISE</italic>, regulates internode patterning in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> inflorescence</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1717</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1727</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Gene traps: tools for plant development and genomics</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1007</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1020</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steeves</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sussex</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Patterns in Plant Development</article-title>, <edition>Ed 2</edition>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Dermen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Flexibility in ontogeny as shown by the contribution of the shoot apical layers to leaves of periclinal chimeras</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>935</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>947</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundaresan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Volpe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Haward</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JDG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Martienssen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Patterns of gene action in plant development revealed by enhancer trap and gene trap transposable elements</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1797</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1810</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Niihama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>gorgon, a novel missense mutation in the <italic>SHOOT MERISTEMLESS</italic> gene, impairs shoot meristem homeostasis in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>621</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>634</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Connecting the paths in plant stem cell regulation</article-title>. <source>Trends Cell Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>410</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vollbrecht</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Shoot meristem size is dependent on inbred background and presence of the maize homeobox gene, <italic>knotted1</italic></article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>3161</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3172</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title><italic>LEAFY</italic> controls floral meristem identity in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>843</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>859</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Girke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Gene expression map of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> shoot apical meristem stem cell niche</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>4941</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>4946</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavakkoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>WUSCHEL mediates stem cell homeostasis by regulating stem cell number and patterns of cell division and differentiation of stem cell progenitors</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>3581</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3589</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poethig</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The microRNA-regulated SBP-box transcription factor SPL3 is a direct upstream activator of LEAFY, FRUITFULL, and APETALA1</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>268</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>278</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yanai</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Shani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolezal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarkowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sablowski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Samach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ori</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis KNOXI proteins activate cytokinin biosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1566</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1571</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolezal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miotk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultheiss</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Hormonal control of the shoot stem-cell niche</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>465</volume>: <fpage>1089</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1092</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
