<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">213223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.213223</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>GENES, DEVELOPMENT, AND EVOLUTION</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>EMBRYONIC FLOWER1 and ULTRAPETALA1 Act Antagonistically on Arabidopsis Development and Stress Response<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Mao-Sen</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Sang Yeol</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Long-Fang O.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>Jennifer C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>Zinmay Renee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Department of Plant and Microbial Biology, University of California, Berkeley, California 94720 (L.P., S.Y.K., J.C.F., Z.R.S.); and</aff><aff id="aff2">Institute of Plant and Microbial Biology, Academia Sinica, Nankang 115, Taipei, Taiwan (M.-S.L., L.-F.O.C.)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>sungr@berkeley.edu</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation (grant no. IOS 0956409 to Z.R.S.) and the National Science Council, Taiwan (grant no. 98&#x2013;2311&#x2013;B&#x2013;001&#x2013;001&#x2013;MY3 to L.O.C.).</p></fn><fn id="afn1"><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Zinmay Renee Sung (<email>sungr@berkeley.edu</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.213223">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.213223</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>06</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>04</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>162</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>830</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>04</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2013 American Society of Plant Biologists. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="PP_213223_ic1.gif"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><italic>EMF1 and ULT1 counteract each other in the regulation of flowering and stress tolerance.</italic></p></abstract><abstract><p>Epigenetic regulation of gene expression is of fundamental importance for eukaryotic development. <italic>EMBRYONIC FLOWER1</italic> (<italic>EMF1</italic>) is a plant-specific gene that participates in Polycomb group-mediated transcriptional repression of target genes such as the flower MADS box genes <italic>AGAMOUS</italic>, <italic>APETALA3</italic>, and <italic>PISTILLATA</italic>. Here, we investigated the molecular mechanism underlying the curly leaf and early flowering phenotypes caused by reducing EMF1 activity in the leaf primordia of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> transgenic plants and propose a combined effect of multiple flower MADS box gene activities on these phenotypes. ULTRAPETALA1 (ULT1) functions as a trithorax group factor that counteracts Polycomb group action in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>). Removing ULT1 activity rescues both the abnormal developmental phenotypes and most of the misregulated gene expression of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants. Reducing EMF1 activity increases salt tolerance, an effect that is diminished by introducing the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation into the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> background. EMF1 is required for trimethylating lysine-27 on histone 3 (H3K27me3), and ULT1 associates with ARABIDOPSIS TRITHORAX1 (ATX1) for trimethylating lysine-3 on histone 4 (H3K4me3) at flower MADS box gene loci. Reducing EMF1 activity decreases H3K27me3 marks and increases H3K4me3 marks on target gene loci. Removing ULT1 activity has the opposite effect on the two histone marks. Removing both gene activities restores the active and repressive marks to near wild-type levels. Thus, ULT1 acts as an antirepressor that counteracts EMF1 action through modulation of histone marks on target genes. Our analysis indicates that, instead of acting as off and on switches, EMF1 and ULT1 mediate histone mark deposition and modulate transcriptional activities of the target genes.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="19"/></counts></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">PcG</term><def id="def1"><p>Polycomb group</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">trxG</term><def id="def2"><p>trithorax group</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">DAG</term><def id="def3"><p>days after germination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">LD</term><def id="def4"><p>long-day</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">SD</term><def id="def5"><p>short-day</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">RT</term><def id="def6"><p>reverse transcription</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">MS</term><def id="def7"><p>Murashige and Skoog</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8">qPCR</term><def id="def8"><p>quantitative PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9">ChIP</term><def id="def9"><p>chromatin immunoprecipitation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term10">aRNA</term><def id="def10"><p>amino allyl-modified RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term11">cDNA</term><def id="def11"><p>complementary DNA</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>The life cycle of eukaryotes is marked by developmental phases specified by spatial and temporal patterns of gene expression. Polycomb group (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref>) and trithorax group (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">trxG</xref>) proteins function as epigenetic repressors and activators, respectively. They act dynamically in regulating gene expression patterns to specify cell fates and maintain differentiated cell states (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Schuettengruber et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hennig and Derkacheva, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Holec and Berger, 2012</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref> genes were first discovered in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> as repressors of the homeotic <italic>Hox</italic> genes involved in embryo segmentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Lewis, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Jurgens, 1985</xref>). The two <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref> protein complexes, Polycomb Repressive Complex1 (PRC1) and PRC2, the components of which are highly conserved among eukaryotic organisms, cooperate to maintain silencing through trimethylation of histone 3 Lys-27 (H3K27me3) of their target genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Schwartz and Pirrotta, 2007</xref>). <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">trxG</xref> proteins were identified as suppressors of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref> mutations that cause trimethylation of histone 3 Lys-4 (H3K4me3) and activate gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Poux et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Klymenko and M&#x00FC;ller, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Schwartz and Pirrotta, 2007</xref>). Subtle regulation of histone methylation homeostasis by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">trxG</xref> on target genes determines gene expression status; however, the molecular mechanisms that translate histone modification patterns to specific transcriptional states remain unclear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Poux et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Klymenko and M&#x00FC;ller, 2004</xref>).</p><p>In Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), proteins homologous to core components of <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> PRC2 are required for three developmental functions: FERTILIZATION INDEPENDENT SEED2-harboring PRC2 regulates seed development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Chaudhury et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">K&#x00F6;hler et al., 2003</xref>); VERNALIZATION2 (VRN2)-PRC2 is involved in vernalization-mediated flowering via the regulation of <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS C</italic> (<italic>FLC</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gendall et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Wood et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">De Lucia et al., 2008</xref>); and EMBRYONIC FLOWER2 (EMF2)-PRC2 is required to maintain the vegetative phase by repressing the expression of the flower homeotic MADS box genes <italic>AGAMOUS</italic> (<italic>AG</italic>), <italic>APETALA3</italic> (<italic>AP3</italic>), and <italic>PISTILLATA</italic> (<italic>PI</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kinoshita et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Yoshida et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Chanvivattana et al., 2004</xref>). Plants impaired in EMF2-PRC2 complex members display pleiotropic phenotypes, including early flowering, curly leaves, terminal flower, and abnormal flower organs, caused by the widespread misexpression of multiple flower homeotic genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">S&#x00E1;nchez et al., 2009</xref>). In Arabidopsis, the PRC1 RING-finger homologs, AtRING1A/B and AtBMI1A/B, are essential for maintaining cell identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Sanchez-Pulido et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Xu and Shen, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Bratzel et al., 2010</xref>). Several other proteins are involved in AtPRC1 functions, namely LIKE HETEROCHROMATIN PROTEIN1/TERMINAL FLOWER2 (TFL2), VRN1, and EMF1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Mylne et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Turck et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Zhang et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Calonje et al., 2008</xref>). EMF1 binds four RING-finger proteins and is required for H2A Lys-119 monoubiquitination activity on select EMF1 target genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Bratzel et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>EMF1 is a plant-specific protein that encodes a transcriptional regulator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Aubert et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Calonje et al., 2008</xref>). Although EMF1 shares no sequence homology with animal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref> protein genes, it is involved in plant <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref>-mediated gene repression and targets flower homeotic genes directly, as does EMF2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim et al., 2010</xref>). Mutations in <italic>EMF1</italic> and <italic>EMF2</italic> cause plants to skip the vegetative phase, transforming the embryonic meristem from an indeterminate to a determinate state and producing a terminal flower (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Sung et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Yang et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Chen et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Yoshida et al., 2001</xref>). Global gene expression analysis revealed that EMF1 regulates a remarkably high number of genes involved in transcription factor activity, developmental pathways, microRNA gene silencing, and stress responses in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim et al., 2010</xref>). Tissue-specific removal of EMF1 activity from leaf primordia in transgenic plants expressing <italic>antisenseEMF1</italic> under the control of the <italic>LEAFY</italic> (<italic>LFY</italic>) promoter (<italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>) permits vegetative growth but leads to early flowering plants with upward-curled leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">S&#x00E1;nchez et al., 2009</xref>) similar to those of <italic>curly leaf (clf</italic>), a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Goodrich et al., 1997</xref>). Genome-wide investigation of EMF1 targets has revealed that EMF1 mediates gene expression via diverse mechanisms. It acts along with PRC2 to repress the flower MADS box genes as well as with PRC1 to regulate the expression of many other genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>The Arabidopsis genome encodes nine proteins related to the <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> TRITHORAX proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Alvarez-Venegas and Avramova, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Baumbusch et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Ng et al., 2007</xref>). Among these, the Arabidopsis homolog of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">trxG</xref>, <italic>ARABIDOPSIS TRITHORAX1</italic> (<italic>ATX1</italic>), harbors a SET domain with weak methylating activity in vitro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Alvarez-Venegas et al., 2003</xref>). ATX1 and ARABIDOPSIS TRITHORAX-RELATED7 are required for expression of the MADS box genes involved in flower organogenesis and of the floral repressor <italic>FLC</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Tamada et al., 2009</xref>). <italic>atx1</italic> mutants have minor defects in leaf and flower organs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Pien et al., 2008</xref>). The ULTRAPETALA1 (ULT1) gene encodes a protein containing a putative DNA-binding SAND (for Sp100, AIRE-1, NucP41/75, DEAF-1) domain and a B box-like motif that may mediate protein-protein interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Carles et al., 2005</xref>). Although ULT1 has no homology with animal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">trxG</xref> components, <italic>ult1</italic> mutations suppress all of the phenotypes caused by mutations in <italic>CLF</italic>, indicating that <italic>ULT1</italic> meets the genetic definition of a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">trxG</xref> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Carles and Fletcher, 2009</xref>). In addition, ULT1 physically interacts with ATX1 and acts as an antirepressor to CLF-mediated gene repression in Arabidopsis by limiting the deposition of repressive H3K27me3 marks on target gene chromatin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Carles and Fletcher, 2009</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we investigated the impact of EMF1 in every stage of Arabidopsis development through a detailed characterization of the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> defects. Comparing the gene expression pattern of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and plants with similar phenotypes led to the conclusion that it is the combined transcriptional activity from multiple flower MADS box genes, rather than the ectopic expression of a single MADS box gene, that regulates flowering time and leaf differentiation in these plants. Our investigation of the effect of ULT1 on EMF1-mediated gene repression in Arabidopsis showed that ULT1 functions as an antirepressor that counteracts EMF1-mediated repression. Furthermore, our analysis revealed a close link between transcriptional activity and differences in the active and repressive histone marks on the target genes. We propose that, in addition to maintaining off/on states, these histone marks play a role in modulating transcriptional activity.</p><sec id="s1" sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2"><title>The Phenotypes of <italic>ult1-3 emf1-2</italic> Double Mutants Are <italic>emf1</italic> Like</title><p>Plants impaired in <italic>EMF1</italic> activity (e.g. <italic>emf1-2</italic> mutants) flower upon germination (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1A</ext-link>). Plants that lack <italic>ULT1</italic> function, such as <italic>ult1-3</italic> null mutants, flower late and produce extra floral organs, predominantly sepals and petals, hence the name ULTRAPETALA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Fletcher, 2001</xref>). <italic>ult1</italic> mutations rescue the <italic>clf</italic> phenotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Carles and Fletcher, 2009</xref>). Because EMF1 shows a close functional relationship to EMF2, which forms a putative PRC2 with CLF, we investigated whether ULT1 could counteract <italic>EMF1</italic> gene action. <italic>emf1-2 ult1-3</italic> double mutants were generated as described in &#x201C;Materials and Methods&#x201D; to determine whether <italic>ult1</italic> can rescue the <italic>emf1</italic> phenotype (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1, B and C</ext-link>). <italic>ult1-3</italic> seedlings resemble those of the wild type (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1A</ext-link>), whereas <italic>emf1-2 ult1-3</italic> plants look liked the <italic>emf1-2</italic> plants, producing oval-shaped, petioleless cotyledons that later become carpelloid, extremely short hypocotyls, and no leaf primordia (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1A</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Chen et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Moon et al., 2003</xref>). Since the <italic>emf1-2 ult1-3</italic> double mutants are similar to <italic>emf1-2</italic> single mutants, we concluded that the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation cannot rescue the <italic>emf1-2</italic> phenotypes.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>The <italic>ult1</italic> Mutation Rescued <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> Phenotypes</title><p>The <italic>ult1</italic> mutant has no visible phenotype in the seedling and early vegetative phases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Fletcher, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Carles et al., 2004</xref>). Hence, we reasoned that ULT1 probably does not play a major role in development until the adult phase of Arabidopsis. Therefore, <italic>ult1</italic> cannot counteract the loss of <italic>EMF1</italic> function during the seedling growth phase. However, <italic>ult1</italic> mutations delay flowering and can restore the curly leaf and early flowering phenotypes of the <italic>clf</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Chanvivattana et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Carles and Fletcher, 2009</xref>). We have previously generated transgenic <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">S&#x00E1;nchez et al., 2009</xref>). The <italic>LFY</italic> promoter is known to be active in leaf primordia by 4 d after germination (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>) and is gradually up-regulated during vegetative development, peaking in the floral meristem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bl&#x00E1;zquez et al., 1997</xref>). Similar to <italic>clf</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Goodrich et al., 1997</xref>), these plants showed curly leaves and early flowering phenotypes in both long-day (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref>) and short-day (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref>) conditions, implying a functional relationship between EMF1 and CLF.</p><p>To study whether <italic>ult1</italic> mutations can rescue the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> phenotypes, we crossed homozygous <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants with homozygous <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> transgenic plants and selected F2 plants homozygous for <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> (see &#x201C;Materials and Methods&#x201D;). We then genotyped these plants and their progeny to identify those homozygous for the <italic>ult1-3</italic> allele (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1, B and C</ext-link>) and characterized plants homozygous for both <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and <italic>ult1-3</italic>, as described below.</p><p>In early development, the cotyledons of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants had shorter petioles and larger blades than wild-type cotyledons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, A and B</xref>). The blades were round but did not curl downward like wild-type cotyledon blades (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Introduction of the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation into the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants rescued the altered cotyledon growth patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, A and B</xref>). <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants produced rosette leaves at a faster pace or displayed heterochronic changes when grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Wild-type plants produced a new leaf every 4.9 d, <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants every 5.6 d, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants every 3.9 d, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants every 6.7 d. The double mutant leaf production rate is closer to the wild type and <italic>ult1-3</italic> than to <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>. These results showed that EMF1 and ULT1 act in an opposite manner on the rate of leaf production, with EMF1 impeding it and ULT1 promoting it. The <italic>ult1</italic> mutation also seems to be epistatic to <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, indicating that normal ULT1 activity is required to condition the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> phenotype.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><italic>ult1-3</italic> restores seedling and curly leaf phenotypes of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>. A, Three-week-old wild-type (WT), <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants grown on agar plates under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions. The <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> cotyledons are flat and round, while those of the other three genotypes are slightly downward curled. B, Adaxial surface areas of the cotyledons of the four genotypes grown on agar plates under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions. Significant difference from the wild type (Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test) is marked with the asterisk (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). C, Plastochron of the four plants grown on agar plates under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions. The plastochron was calculated based on the slope of the number of days per leaf produced from 13 through 21 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>. Significant differences from the wild type (Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test) are marked with asterisks (&#x002A; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). The number sign indicates that the plants have bolted. D and E, Phenotypes of soil-grown <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants rescued by the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation. Plants shown are 4 weeks old grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> (D) or 8 weeks old grown in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> in a greenhouse (E) after 2 weeks of growth on agar plates under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions. CL, Curly leaf; TF, terminal flower. F, Curly leaf phenotype of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions. Blue areas, normal, not curly; brown areas, weak, mild curliness; purple areas, strong curliness. The top panel at right shows the strategy for counting leaf number from the bottom up, and the bottom panel at right shows variations in the extent of curliness. Bars = 1 mm (A), 1 cm (D), and 2 cm (E).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213223_f1"></graphic></fig><p>Later in development, upward-curling leaves is the most prominent phenotype when EMF1 activity is reduced in the leaf primordia of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants. Soil-grown <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants produced small rosette leaves that were curled upward along the proximal distal axis, whereas wild-type and <italic>ult1-3</italic> leaves had a broad and flat lamina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, D and E</xref>). The increasing curvature as the leaf enlarged was classified as strong, weak, or normal. The oldest 10 leaves had the most pronounced curvature with leaf margins curled upward, and the 11th to 15th leaves were weakly curled (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1F</xref>). Newly emerging <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> leaves were flat and similar to wild-type leaves but curled upward as the leaf expanded and matured. Introduction of the <italic>ult1</italic> mutation rescued the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> curly rosette leaf phenotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, D&#x2013;F</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1F</xref>, only the first three largest leaves in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants displayed mild curliness, demonstrating a nearly full rescue of the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> curly leaf phenotype by the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation. We likewise observed that the upward-curled cauline leaves of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1E</xref>) were rescued by the introduction of the <italic>ult-3</italic> mutation.</p><p>The vegetative-to-reproductive transition takes place prematurely in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">S&#x00E1;nchez et al., 2009</xref>). These plants produced fewer rosette leaves than wild-type plants (<italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, 20.6 &#x00B1; 2.8 at <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> and 5.7 &#x00B1; 0.8 at <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref>; wild type, 59.1 &#x00B1; 4.1 at <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> and 11 &#x00B1; 1 at <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutants flowered late (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Carles et al., 2005</xref>) and produced more rosette leaves than wild-type plants (<italic>ult1-3</italic>, 65.2 &#x00B1; 3.5 at <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> and 14.1 &#x00B1; 0.7 at <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Introduction of <italic>ult1-3</italic> into <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> restored rosette leaf numbers to nearly those of wild-type plants (<italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic>, 59.9 &#x00B1; 6 at <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> and 10.1 &#x00B1; 1.1 at <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). The early flowering phenotype of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants was rescued by <italic>ult1-3</italic> under both <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> conditions. <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants also produced far fewer cauline leaves and inflorescence nodes than wild-type or <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Consequently, they often produced a short inflorescence with a terminal flower phenotype like that of the <italic>emf1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs. 1, D and E</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2D</xref>). The inflorescence defects of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> were rescued by the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation, with the numbers of cauline leaf nodes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>) and flower buds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, C&#x2013;F</xref>) in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants similar to those of wild-type plants.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><italic>ult1-3</italic> represses <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> early flowering and abnormal flower phenotypes. A and B, Flowering times of wild-type (WT), <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants, measured as rosette leaf number (A) during <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> growing conditions in soil and cauline leaf number (B) during <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> growing conditions in soil after 15 d on agar plates grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions. Error bars represent <sc>se</sc>. Asterisks indicate values that are significantly different from the wild type (&#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 using Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test). C, A wild-type inflorescence apex. D, A <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> inflorescence apex bearing abnormal flowers and a terminal flower (TF). E, An <italic>ult1-3</italic> inflorescence apex that generated flowers containing additional floral organs. The inset shows the extra petal in an <italic>ult1-3</italic> flower. F, A <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> inflorescence apex that is normal. G, A wild-type flower with four petals, four sepals, six stamens, and two carpels. H, A <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> flower with four curly petals, four curly sepals, four curly stamens, and two carpels forming a twisted pistil. I, An <italic>ult1-3</italic> flower with six sepals, six petals, six stamens, and two carpels. J, A <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> flower with four normal petals and sepals, six stamens, and two carpels. K to N, Siliques from wild-type (K), <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> (L), <italic>ult1-3</italic> (M), and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> (N) plants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213223_f2"></graphic></fig><p><italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> flowers displayed a variety of phenotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, D and H</xref>). In severely affected flowers, usually terminal flowers, the first and second whorl organs were missing, the number of stamens was reduced, and multiple carpelloid organs were fused together (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2, A&#x2013;C</ext-link>). We also observed the &#x201C;flower-in-flower&#x201D; phenotype, where one flower arose inside another in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2, D&#x2013;F</ext-link>). In flowers with milder phenotypes, the sepals and petals were smaller and narrower, and all flower organs became curled like the rosette and cauline leaves. As a result, the sepals could not completely enclose the inner organs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2H</xref>). The flower buds often opened later than normal (e.g. after silique elongation). Consequently, silique growth was constrained compared with wild-type and <italic>ult1-3</italic> siliques (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, H and K&#x2013;M</xref>). Abnormal flower development was followed by poor seed set in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2L</xref>). Thus, reducing EMF1 activity affected flowering time and floral organ development as well as vegetative growth. <italic>ult1-3</italic> flowers often contained more floral organs that frequently included extra petals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, E and I</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Fletcher, 2001</xref>). The introduction of <italic>ult1-3</italic> restored <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> to an almost normal phenotype that included sepals, petals, stamens, pistils, and siliques (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, J and N</xref>). <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants did not have extra petals. Occasionally, the floral organs of <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants were slightly abnormal, with smaller and narrower sepals and petals. In summary, eliminating <italic>ULT1</italic> function via the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation rescued the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> defects in almost every aspect of seedling and adult development.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Global Gene Expression Pattern in Wild-Type, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> Plants</title><p>To investigate the molecular basis of the rescued phenotype, we compared global gene expression patterns in 7- and 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic>, and wild-type seedlings grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions using a custom-designed Agilent GeneChip containing probe sets representing 29,104 unique Arabidopsis genes (see &#x201C;Materials and Methods&#x201D;). We analyzed the 22,770 Arabidopsis genes that met the criterion of a hybridization signal greater than or equal to 50 in at least one of the four plant samples. Genes showing more than a 2-fold change in the hybridization signals were designated as up-regulated or down-regulated if those signals were higher or lower in the mutants than in the wild type (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). GeneChip results were confirmed by reverse transcription (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">RT</xref>)-PCR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>).</p><p>We first analyzed gene expression in the single mutant parent plants <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and <italic>ult1-3</italic>. In <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants, 2,415 genes (10.6%) were up-regulated and 1,746 genes (7.7%) were down-regulated at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>. Thus, 18.3% of genes analyzed had altered expression in 7-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblI">Table I</xref>). In 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants, 1,438 genes (6.3%) were up-regulated and 1,706 genes (7.5%) were down-regulated: 13.8% of the genes differed in expression (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblI">Table I</xref>). The <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutants showed a lower percentage of misregulated genes than the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblI">Table I</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tblI"><label>Table I.</label><caption><title>Gene expression changes in LFYasEMF1 and ult1-3</title><p>Up and Down denote the number (percentage) of genes up-regulated and down-regulated, respectively, more than 2-fold in mutant or transgenic plants compared with the wild type.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col">Effect</th><th colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup">7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup">15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref><hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup"><italic>LFYasEMF1</italic></th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>ult1-3</italic></th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>LFYasEMF1</italic></th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>ult1-3</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Up</td><td align="center">2,415 (10.6%)</td><td align="center">934 (4.1%)</td><td align="center">1,438 (6.3%)</td><td align="center">964 (4.2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Down</td><td align="center">1,746 (7.7%)</td><td align="center">1,176 (5.2%)</td><td align="center">1,706 (7.5%)</td><td align="center">893 (3.9%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Total</td><td align="center">4,161 (18.3%)</td><td align="center">2,110 (9.3%)</td><td align="center">3,144 (13.8%)</td><td align="center">1,875 (8.1%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s5"><title><italic>ult1-3</italic> Restored the Misregulated Gene Expression Pattern of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic></title><p>We then investigated whether <italic>ult1-3</italic> affected the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> gene expression pattern and found that the majority of the misregulated genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> were restored to wild-type levels by the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>). We found that 1,905 (79%) of 2,415 up-regulated genes in the 7-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings were no longer up-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings. Among these, 1,577 genes (65%) were restored to wild-type expression levels and 328 genes (14%) were down-regulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S3</ext-link>). Similarly, 68% of the up-regulated genes in 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> were no longer up-regulated in 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants, with 832 genes (58%) restored to wild-type levels and 148 genes (10%) being down-regulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S3</ext-link>). Also, of the down-regulated genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, 65% were restored to wild-type levels at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> and 68% were restored to wild-type levels at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S3</ext-link>). The high percentage of genes with restored expression levels corresponds well with the phenotypic rescue of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> by the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Gene expression pattern in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings. A, Pie charts of gene expression pattern affected by <italic>ult1-3</italic> on 2-fold or greater up-regulated (left) and down-regulated (right) genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants at 7 or 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>. The number reflects the percentage of misregulated genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> restored to wild-type expression levels or 2-fold or greater up-regulated (blue) or down-regulated levels in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants. B, Pie charts of gene expression patterns affected by <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> on 2-fold or greater up-regulated (left) and down-regulated (right) genes in <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants at 7 or 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>. The number reflects the percentage of misregulated genes in <italic>ult1-3</italic> restored to wild-type expression levels or 2-fold or greater up-regulated or down-regulated levels in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213223_f3"></graphic></fig><p>EMF1 interacts with several thousand target genes, 3,227 (58%) of which are also marked with H3K27me3 (EMF1_K27) in Arabidopsis seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2012</xref>). These EMF1_K27 genes are most likely regulated via <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref> mechanisms. We investigated the impact of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> on the EMF1_K27 genes and found that 326 (22.7%) of the 1,438 up-regulated genes in 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants were EMF1_K27 genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblII">Table II</xref>). Similarly, 295 (17.3%) down-regulated genes were EMF1_K27 genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblII">Table II</xref>). Both classes are greater than 11.4%, the fraction of EMF1_K27 genes in the Arabidopsis genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2012</xref>). Of the 326 up-regulated EMF1_K27 genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings, 171 (52.5%) were not up-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings. These included 150 (46.1%) restored to wild-type expression levels and 21 (6.4%) that became down-regulated (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblII">Table II</xref>). Of the 295 down-regulated EMF1_K27 genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants, 250 (84.8%) were not down-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants, including 194 (65.8%) restored to wild-type expression levels and 56 (19%) that became up-regulated (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblII">Table II</xref>). The majority of the genes for which their misregulation in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants was restored by the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation are EMF1_K27 genes, suggesting that ULT1 acts on many EMF1 target genes and antagonizes EMF1 action on gene expression.</p><table-wrap id="tblII"><label>Table II.</label><caption><title>Effects of ult1-3 on expression patterns of misregulated EMF1_K27 genes in LFYasEMF1 plants</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col">Gene</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col">Genome</th><th colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup"><italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> (1,438)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblIIfn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup"><italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic><hr/></th><th colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup"><italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> (1,706)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblIIfn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup"><italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic><hr/></th></tr><tr><td align="center" scope="row">Up</td><td align="center">Up</td><td align="center">Down</td><td align="center">Restored</td><td align="center">Down</td><td align="center">Up</td><td align="center">Down</td><td align="center">Restored</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" scope="row">EMF1_K27 (3,227)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center">11.4%</td><td align="center">326 (22.7%)<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center">155 (47.5%)</td><td align="center">21 (6.4%)</td><td align="center">150 (46.1%)</td><td align="center">295 (17.3%)<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center">56 (19%)</td><td align="center">45 (15.3%)</td><td align="center">194 (65.8%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblIIfn1"><label>a</label><p>Up- or down-regulated genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants by at least 2-fold at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>.&#x2003;&#x2003;<sup>b</sup>Genes that are bound by EMF1 and marked by H3K27me3, 3,227 of 29,336, in the Arabidopsis genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2012</xref>).&#x2003;&#x2003;<sup>c</sup>Number (percentage) of EMF1_K27 genes up- or down-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To understand the function of the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> misregulated genes restored by <italic>ult1-3</italic>, we considered the 15 functional categories described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim et al., 2010</xref>), with appropriate modifications of the gene list. These categories include genes involved in flower organ identity, flowering time, seed development, photoreceptor and photosynthesis system, cell expansion, auxin, GA, ethylene, and abscisic acid synthesis and signaling, stress, cold, and heat responses, and histone and transcription factor genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). Analysis of the genes in these 15 categories showed that <italic>ult1-3</italic> can restore the expression of approximately 60% of the up- and down-regulated genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings to wild-type levels (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4A</ext-link>). In every one of the 15 categories, expression of a substantial number of genes was restored (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblIII">Table III</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). Restored genes that affect flower organ identity, flowering time, seed formation, and stress are described further.</p><table-wrap id="tblIII"><label>Table III.</label><caption><title>ult1-3 restoration of misregulated genes in LFYasEMF1 plants at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="center" scope="col">Category</th><th align="center" scope="col">No. of Genes Investigated</th><th align="center" scope="col">Change in Gene Expression</th><th align="center" scope="col">No. of Genes Misregulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblIIIfn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" scope="col">No. of Genes with Expression Restored to Wild-Type Level in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic><sup>b</sup></th><th align="center" scope="col">Example of Genes with Expression Restored to Wild-Type Level in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic><sup>c</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Abscisic acid</td><td align="char" char=".">12</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="char" char=".">1</td><td align="left">RNA-binding protein</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Auxin</td><td align="char" char=".">107</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">8</td><td align="char" char=".">4</td><td align="left">Auxin-responsive family protein</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">13</td><td align="char" char=".">11</td><td align="left"><italic>SAUR24</italic>, <italic>GH3.17</italic>, <italic>IAA14</italic>, <italic>SAUR19</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Cold</td><td align="char" char=".">19</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Ethylene</td><td align="char" char=".">56</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">14</td><td align="char" char=".">8</td><td align="left"><italic>RRTF1</italic>, <italic>ERF5</italic>, <italic>ERF73</italic>, <italic>ERF-1</italic>, <italic>ORA59</italic>, <italic>MBF1C</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Expansin</td><td align="char" char=".">20</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">5</td><td align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="left"><italic>EXPA1</italic>, <italic>EXPA5</italic>, <italic>EXPA10</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Flower organ identity</td><td align="char" char=".">14</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">10</td><td align="center">10<sup>d</sup></td><td align="left"><italic>AG</italic>, <italic>SEP1</italic>, <italic>SEP2</italic>, <italic>SEP3</italic>, <italic>AP1</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, <italic>PI</italic>, <italic>SHP1</italic>, <italic>SHP2</italic>, <italic>STK</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">1</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Flowering time</td><td align="char" char=".">98</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">12</td><td align="char" char=".">9</td><td align="left"><italic>AGL24</italic>, <italic>TFL1</italic>, <italic>TEM1</italic>, <italic>ATC</italic>, <italic>MAF3</italic>, <italic>CO</italic>, <italic>SPL3</italic>, <italic>CPL3</italic>, <italic>FPF1</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">11</td><td align="char" char=".">8</td><td align="left"><italic>SPL1</italic>, <italic>SPL5</italic>, <italic>FLD</italic>, <italic>DNF</italic>, <italic>TOE1</italic>, <italic>FRI</italic>, <italic>GID1B</italic>, <italic>GA1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">GA</td><td align="char" char=".">13</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">1</td><td align="char" char=".">1</td><td align="left"><italic>GASA6</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">1</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Heat</td><td align="char" char=".">50</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">9</td><td align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="left"><italic>HSFB2A</italic>, <italic>HSFA7A</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">4</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="left"><italic>HSFC1</italic>, <italic>HSP23.6-MITO</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Histone</td><td align="char" char=".">36</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">5</td><td align="char" char=".">4</td><td align="left"><italic>HTA12</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Photoreceptor</td><td align="char" char=".">28</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="char" char=".">1</td><td align="left"><italic>ELIP1</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="left"><italic>PAT1</italic>, <italic>IOS1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Photosynthesis</td><td align="char" char=".">54</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">1</td><td align="char" char=".">1</td><td align="left">PSII 5-kD protein</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="char" char=".">1</td><td align="left">Chlorophyll <italic>a</italic>/<italic>b</italic>-binding protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Seed</td><td align="char" char=".">119</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">25</td><td align="char" char=".">12</td><td align="left">Protease inhibitor genes, <italic>XYP1</italic>, <italic>M17</italic>, <italic>LEC1</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">5</td><td align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="left"><italic>SIP1</italic>, <italic>SIP2</italic>, <italic>EM1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Stress</td><td align="char" char=".">46</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="left"><italic>STZ</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Transcription factor</td><td align="char" char=".">588</td><td align="left">Up</td><td align="char" char=".">77</td><td align="char" char=".">48</td><td align="left">No apical meristem (NAM) family genes</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Down</td><td align="char" char=".">46</td><td align="char" char=".">22</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Total</td><td align="char" char=".">1,260</td><td></td><td align="char" char=".">264</td><td align="char" char=".">156</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblIIIfn1"><label>a</label><p>Genes more than 2-fold up- or down-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>. Fold changes are calculated using the signal intensity, which measures the change in expression level for each probe set between wild-type and mutant or transgenic plants.&#x2003;&#x2003;<sup>b</sup>Genes up- or down-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants that were restored to wild-type expression levels (less than 2-fold) by <italic>ult1-3</italic> at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>.&#x2003;&#x2003;<sup>c</sup>For a complete list, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.&#x2003;&#x2003;<sup>d</sup>Eight of the 10 flower organ identity genes remained up-regulated by more than 2-fold in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants but are included here because their up-regulation is greatly reduced (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="s6"><title>Flower Organ Identity Genes</title><p>The 10 flower-specific MADS box genes <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>PI</italic>, <italic>APETALA1</italic> (<italic>AP1</italic>), <italic>AP3</italic>, <italic>SHATTERPROOF1</italic> (<italic>SHP1</italic>), <italic>SHP2</italic>, <italic>SEPALLATA1</italic> (<italic>SEP1</italic>), <italic>SEP2</italic>, <italic>SEP3</italic>, and <italic>SEEDSTICK</italic> (<italic>STK</italic>) are all EMF1_K27 genes. In <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants, they showed significant ectopic expression at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> that increased at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). This suggests that more <italic>antisenseEMF1</italic>, and hence less <italic>EMF1</italic>, is present in the plants at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> than at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>, consistent with the increasing <italic>LFY</italic> promoter activity as plants mature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bl&#x00E1;zquez et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Winter et al., 2011</xref>). In contrast, the mRNA levels of the 10 flower MADS box genes in <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants were unchanged except for <italic>AG</italic> and <italic>SEP3</italic>, which were lower, and <italic>SEP2</italic>, which was higher, than in wild-type plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). Introduction of the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation significantly reduced the expression level of these 10 highly up-regulated genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants, although eight of the 10 genes still showed more than 2-fold up-regulation at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). For example, <italic>AG</italic> had a 110-fold up-regulation in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> but only 6-fold in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic>. The highly up-regulated genes are not completely restored to wild-type levels (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Opposite regulation of gene expression by EMF1 and ULT1. A, Relative expression levels of flower MADS box genes in plants at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> (left panel) and 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> (right panel) using data based on GeneChip analysis. The log<sub>2</sub> values of the fold change were calculated for comparison of the changes in gene expression levels in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants relative to wild-type plants. A log<sub>2</sub> ratio of 1 is the same as a 2-fold change in gene expression. B, Relative expression changes of flowering-time genes. C, Relative expression changes of seed genes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213223_f4"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Flowering-Time Genes</title><p>Among the 98 flowering-time genes investigated (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>), 12 genes are up-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> and 11 genes are up-regulated at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblIII">Table III</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). Eight of these are directly regulated by EMF1: <italic>AGAMOUS-LIKE24</italic> (<italic>AGL24</italic>), <italic>FLC</italic>, <italic>FLOWERING PROMOTING FACTOR1</italic> (<italic>FPF1</italic>), <italic>MADS AFFECTING FLOWERING2 (MAF2</italic>)<italic>/AGL31</italic>, <italic>MAF3</italic>, <italic>SQUAMOSA PROMOTER BINDING PROTEIN-LIKE3</italic> (<italic>SPL9</italic>), <italic>TEMPRANILLO1</italic> (<italic>TEM1</italic>), and <italic>TFL1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2012</xref>). <italic>AGL24</italic>, <italic>FPF1</italic>, and <italic>SPL9</italic> promote flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Kania et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Melzer et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Michaels et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Schwarz et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Wang et al., 2009</xref>), whereas <italic>FLC</italic>, <italic>TEM1</italic>, <italic>TFL1</italic>, <italic>MAF2</italic>, and <italic>MAF3</italic> repress flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Michaels and Amasino, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Ratcliffe et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Castillejo and Pelaz, 2008</xref>).</p><p>Genes misregulated in 7- and/or 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants include 17 that are not EMF1 targets, such as <italic>CENTRORADIALIS</italic> (<italic>ATC</italic>), <italic>CONSTANS</italic> (<italic>CO</italic>), <italic>SPL3</italic>, <italic>SPL4</italic>, <italic>SPL5</italic>, and <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). EMF1 may regulate these genes indirectly through the activities of genes it does interact with and regulate directly. For example, EMF1 interacts directly with <italic>FLC</italic> but does not interact with <italic>FT</italic> chromatin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim et al., 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">2012</xref>). <italic>FT</italic> mRNA levels increase as plants mature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Farrona et al., 2011</xref>), but <italic>FT</italic> is not up-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants until 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>. Ectopic expression of <italic>FLC</italic> is lower at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> than at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>), which would reduce FLC-mediated <italic>FT</italic> repression at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>. Thus, <italic>FT</italic> mRNA levels are much higher at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> than at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> in wild-type plants. The age-dependent increase in <italic>FT</italic> mRNA levels is enhanced by the reduced expression of <italic>FLC</italic> in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>).</p><p>In <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants, nine of 12 flowering-time genes up-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> and six of 11 genes up-regulated at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> were restored to wild-type expression levels by the introduction of the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblIII">Table III</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). Similarly, eight of 11 down-regulated genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> and three of seven down-regulated genes at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> were restored to wild-type expression levels (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblIII">Table III</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). Together, the expression levels of 73% of the genes directly or indirectly regulated by EMF1 were restored in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants at 7 and/or 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>. The restoration of the misregulated flowering-time genes is consistent with the normal flowering time of the <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Seed Genes</title><p>We examined 119 genes involved in seed development. The 25 genes up-regulated at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> and the nine genes up-regulated at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants include the <italic>LATE EMBRYOGENESIS ABUNDANT</italic>, <italic>OLEOSIN2</italic>, <italic>SEED STORAGE PROTEIN/LIPID TRANSFER PROTEIN</italic> (<italic>LTP</italic>), <italic>ARABIDOPSIS THALIANA SEED GENE3</italic>, and <italic>LEAFY COTYLEDON1</italic> (<italic>LEC1</italic>) genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). Sixteen of the 7-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> up-regulated genes and six of the 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> up-regulated genes showed reduced ectopic expression in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants. Among these, 12 of the 7-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> genes and three of the 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> genes were restored to wild-type expression levels in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblIII">Table III</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). Three major seed regulator genes, <italic>ABSCISIC ACID INSENSITIVE3</italic> (<italic>ABI3</italic>), <italic>FUSCA3</italic>, and <italic>LEC2</italic>, to which EMF1 binds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">To et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2012</xref>), did not show increased expression in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants by GeneChip analysis. <italic>ABI3</italic> mRNA levels were confirmed by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">RT</xref>-PCR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>). Seed storage protein and lipid transfer protein genes (e.g. <italic>LTP4</italic>), which are downstream genes controlled by these major seed regulators, did show ectopic expression in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants that was restored by the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). We also found that five seed development genes were down-regulated in the 7-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings and 13 seed development genes were down-regulated in the 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings. More than 50% of these were restored to wild-type expression levels in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblIII">Table III</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). The ectopic expression and restoration of downstream seed storage gene expression suggest that there are subtle changes in the expression of the seed regulatory genes that are not readily detectable in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s9"><title>EMF1 and ULT1 Modulate the Salt Stress Response</title><p>Our previous study showed that EMF1 binds preferentially to genes involved in biotic and abiotic stress responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2012</xref>). To investigate whether the EMF1 interaction with stress genes would affect the stress response, we studied salt tolerance in wild-type, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings and adult plants. To avoid adverse effects of salt treatment on germination, we transferred 3-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> wild-type, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings from Murashige and Skoog (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref>) plates to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> medium containing different concentrations of salt (0, 100, 125, 150, and 200 m<sc>m</sc>) and grew them for an additional 8 d under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions. The <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> roots grew longer than the wild-type and <italic>ult1-3</italic> roots on 100, 125, and 150 m<sc>m</sc> salt plates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, A and B</xref>), suggesting that <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings are more salt tolerant than the wild-type and <italic>ult1-3</italic> seedlings.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><italic>ult1-3</italic> restores <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> enhanced salt tolerance and salt gene expression. A, Salt tolerance test of seedling growth. Wild-type (WT), <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings at 3 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> were transferred from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> medium to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> medium containing 125 m<sc>m</sc> salt and grown for an additional 8 d. Short black lines indicate the junction of hypocotyl and root. B, Root length of seedlings grown on medium with and without salt, showing an enhanced salt tolerance in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> that was restored by the introduction of <italic>ult1</italic> into <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>. Root length was measured after 8 d of growth on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> with different concentrations of salt (<italic>n</italic> = 20). C, Salt tolerance test of plant growth in soil. Wild-type, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants at 36 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> were watered with or without 150 m<sc>m</sc> salt. D, Effect of salt on shoot growth, showing an enhanced salt tolerance in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> that was restored in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants. Rosette size was measured by rosette diameter. While wild-type, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants displayed about 80% inhibition of shoot growth by the 150 m<sc>m</sc> salt treatment, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> growth inhibition was 50% at 36 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> (<italic>n</italic> = 10). E, Quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">RT</xref>-PCR analysis of the transcript levels of two salt-responsive genes, <italic>AT2G38380</italic> and <italic>AT1G52890</italic>, in 6-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> seedlings grown with or without salt.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213223_f5"></graphic></fig><p>The growth advantage of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings on salt was diminished by the introduction of the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation, as shown by a modest change in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> root length compared with wild-type and <italic>ult1-3</italic> root length. At 200 m<sc>m</sc> salt, the seedling root growth of all four genotypes was equally inhibited (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, A and B</xref>). We then transferred these plants to soil and continued the same salt treatment as on the agar plates and the same <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> condition. As mentioned above (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, D and E</xref>), <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants watered with 0 m<sc>m</sc> salt exhibited curly leaves, early flowering, and smaller rosette size. However, they were more tolerant to salt treatment, as shown by their larger rosette size compared with wild-type, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants when watered with 150 m<sc>m</sc> salt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, C and D</xref>). Whereas the wild-type, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants displayed about 80% inhibition of shoot growth by the 150 m<sc>m</sc> salt treatment, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>&#x2019;s growth inhibition was 50% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5D</xref>). Thus, both seedling and adult growth of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants was more salt tolerant, and this tolerance was reduced by the introduction of the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation.</p><p>To elucidate the molecular mechanism of the EMF1-mediated salt response, we studied the expression levels of two salt-responsive genes, a gene belonging to the peroxidase superfamily, <italic>AT2G38380</italic>, and a NAC domain protein gene, <italic>AT1G52890</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Tran et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Jiang et al., 2007</xref>), in wild-type, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings. As expected, salt increased, albeit to varying degrees, the transcript levels of these two genes in all four types of seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5E</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5</ext-link>). Importantly, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants accumulated more salt-inducible transcripts, especially <italic>AT1G52890</italic>, than wild-type plants when grown in the absence of salt. Salt treatment further increased its transcript level in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> more than it did in wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5E</xref>). The <italic>AT1G52890</italic> transcript level in <italic>ult1-3</italic> was higher than in wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5E</xref>). However, a comparison of the transcript levels between <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants showed that the introduction of <italic>ult1-3</italic> greatly reduced the transcript levels of these two genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants. These results indicate that the transcripts of salt-inducible genes are more readily accumulated in plants with reduced EMF1 activity, confirming a role for EMF1 in regulating the stress response. Removing <italic>ULT1</italic> activity restored the misregulation of these genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants, consistent with the reduced salt tolerance in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1</italic> plants to a level closer to that of wild-type and <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, B and C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>The Effect of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> on the <italic>ult1-3</italic> Misregulated Gene Expression Pattern</title><p>Since reducing ULT1 activity restored gene expression patterns in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, we also analyzed the impact of the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> transgene on the misregulation of genes in <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants. Interestingly, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> had a limited impact on misregulated genes in the <italic>ult1-3</italic> background. The majority of genes up-regulated (63% at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>, 55% at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>) or down-regulated (60% at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>, 76% at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>) in <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants remained up- and down-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Tables S2 and S5</ext-link>). Similarly, analysis of the genes in 15 categories showed that the majority of the up- and down-regulated genes in <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants remained up- and down-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4B</ext-link>). Nevertheless, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> had a stronger impact on gene expression pattern in 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> than in 7-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants, suggesting that ULT1 and EMF1 share more target genes at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> than at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>. This is consistent with the observation that the <italic>ult1</italic> mutation does not cause visible phenotypes in early development and cannot rescue <italic>emf1</italic> mutations that obliterated seedling and rosette development.</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Temporal and Spatial <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> Expression Patterns in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic></title><p>To investigate the role of the misexpressed MADS box genes on the aberrant development of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, we studied the temporal and spatial expression patterns of <italic>AP3</italic> in wild-type, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants harboring an <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GLUCURONIDASE</italic> (<italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic>) reporter construct. <italic>AP3</italic> is normally activated in stage 3 flower primordia to specify petal and stamen identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Krizek and Fletcher, 2005</xref>). The <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants at 21 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions looked like wild-type plants but showed ectopic <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity in the shoot apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, A and D</xref>). As expected, wild-type and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> shoot apices did not show <italic>GUS</italic> activity at this developmental stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, A and G</xref>). After flowering, <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity in wild-type flowers was restricted to the stamens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, B and C</xref>). However, the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants exhibited ectopic <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity in buds, petals, receptacles, and even some carpels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, E and F</xref>). Furthermore, the six stamens varied in the extent of <italic>GUS</italic> activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6F</xref>). The <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> flowers had wild-type-like <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, H and I</xref>). Ectopic <italic>AP3</italic> activity in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> shoot apices at 21 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> is consistent with its early flowering phenotype. Disturbed EMF1 activity in the flower corresponds with the misexpression of <italic>AP3</italic> that resulted in abnormal flower organ development in severe cases. This indicates that tight regulation of EMF1 is necessary for normal floral organ differentiation. The absence of <italic>ULT1</italic> activity can counteract the effects of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and restore normal <italic>AP3</italic> expression patterns in the shoot apex and in the flower.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity in wild-type (WT), <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants. A, Wild-type plants at 21 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>, grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions, showing no <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity. B and C, Wild-type plants showing <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity in the stamens but not in the flower buds or petals. D, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants at 21 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> showing strong <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity at the shoot apex. The inset shows a magnified shoot apex. E and F, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants showing ectopic <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity in flower buds and petals but not all the stamens. Some stamens display no GUS activity. G, <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants at 21 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> showing no <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity. H and I, <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants showing <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity in the stamens but not in the flower buds or petals.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213223_f6"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Effects of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and <italic>ult1-3</italic> on the Histone Methylation Patterns of the Flower Homeotic Genes</title><p>Genome-wide analysis of histone methylation patterns revealed that the 5&#x2032; end sequences in the promoter and gene body are highly enriched in H3K4me3 or H3K27me3 marks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Zhang et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2012</xref>). Therefore, we performed chromatin immunoprecipitation (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ChIP</xref>)-quantitative PCR (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">qPCR</xref>) analysis in these regions of the three EMF1_K27 genes, <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, and <italic>PI</italic>, using <italic>AT2G4000</italic>, which is not trimethylated, as a negative control for H3K27me3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Influence of EMF1 and ULT1 on <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, and <italic>PI</italic> histone methylation patterns and transcriptional activities. A, Schematic representation of <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, <italic>PI</italic>, and <italic>AT2G40000</italic> gene structures. The exon/intron structures are depicted as black boxes/black lines. The regions amplified by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">qPCR</xref> are depicted as horizontal lines below the schemes. B, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ChIP</xref> analysis of H3K27me3 levels at the <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, and <italic>PI</italic> loci in wild-type (WT), <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>. Anti-H3K27me3 antibody was used to immunoprecipitate (IP) nuclear proteins from plants. Input is preimmunoprecipitated DNA after sonication. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ChIP</xref> products were analyzed by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">qPCR</xref> using the primers corresponding to the gene region shown in A. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ChIP</xref> results are expressed as a percentage of input DNA, with error bars representing <sc>sd</sc> of three replicates. C, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ChIP</xref> analysis of H3K4me3 levels at the <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, and <italic>PI</italic> loci in wild-type, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ChIP</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">qPCR</xref> were carried out as described in B. Asterisks in B and C indicate values that are significantly different from the wild type (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 using Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test). D, Correlation between the relative mRNA expression levels (log<sub>2</sub>) and the difference between the active H3K4me3 (+) and repressive H3K27me3 (&#x2212;) marks on the <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, and <italic>PI</italic> genes calculated by subtracting the enrichment level of the repressive H3K27me3 signal from that of the active H3K4me3 signal based on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">qPCR</xref> results in B and C. The relative expression levels of <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, and <italic>PI</italic> in plants at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> were based on GeneChip data (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). The log<sub>2</sub> values of the fold changes were calculated for comparisons of the changes in expression level for each gene in the four plant samples. A log<sub>2</sub> ratio of 1 is the same as a fold change of 2.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213223_f7"></graphic></fig><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ChIP</xref> results showed that the H3K27me3-repressive marks are greatly reduced at the <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, and <italic>PI</italic> loci in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> relative to wild-type seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). Conversely, <italic>ult1-3</italic> seedlings were slightly enriched in H3K27me3 at the <italic>AG</italic> and <italic>PI</italic> loci compared with wild-type seedlings, and both loci showed significant gains compared with <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings had more H3K27me3 marks at these loci than <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings but fewer than wild-type and <italic>ult1-3</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). These results are consistent with reduced expression of these genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> compared with <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants and slightly increased expression compared with wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Despite the similar phenotype rescue of <italic>clf</italic> mutants and <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants by the <italic>ult1</italic> mutation, there is a difference between the interaction of ULT1 with EMF1 and that of ULT1 with CLF. In <italic>clf-2</italic> plants, <italic>AG</italic> was depleted of H3K27me3 regardless of the presence or absence of ULT1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Carles and Fletcher, 2009</xref>). In <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants, however, removing ULT1 restored H3K27me3 to a nearly wild-type level. One reason may be that CLF is the methyltransferase while EMF1 participates in its enzyme activity via yet unknown mechanisms.</p><p>H3K4me3 is a histone mark for active chromatin. However, it is also found on inactive genes in mammalian cells and on the <italic>AG</italic> loci in Arabidopsis seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bernstein et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Saleh et al., 2007</xref>). The <italic>AG</italic> locus was more enriched for the H3K4me3 activation marks in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings than in wild-type seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7C</xref>). That the <italic>AG</italic> locus in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants has more active H3K4me3 marks and fewer repressive H3K27me3 marks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, B and C</xref>) indicates that the locus has shifted toward a more active state. This is consistent with ectopic <italic>AG</italic> expression in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants before flowering. A previous study reported minor effects of <italic>ult1</italic> on H3K4me3 deposition in the wild type, although <italic>ult1-3</italic> did reduce its deposition in <italic>clf-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Carles and Fletcher, 2009</xref>). Here, we found that H3K4me3 marks on the <italic>AG</italic> locus were greatly reduced in <italic>ult1-3</italic> seedlings compared with wild-type and <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7C</xref>). In the <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants, the level of H3K4me3 marks on the <italic>AG</italic> locus recovered to a level near that of wild-type plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7C</xref>). These results indicate that, besides restricting H3K27me3 on PRC2 target loci, ULT1 plays an important role in H3K4 trimethylation. The other two MADS box genes, <italic>AP3</italic> and <italic>PI</italic>, also displayed varying levels of H3K4me3 enrichment in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7C</xref>). Importantly, introduction of the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation reduced the H3K4me3 marks on all three genes in the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> background. The finding that removing <italic>ULT1</italic> function from <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants reduced active marks but increased repressive marks on target genes is consistent with ULT1 and EMF1 having antagonistic functions. H3K4 trimethylation in the absence of <italic>ULT1</italic> may result from gene redundancy (i.e. ULT2 may substitute for ULT1 functions in <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutants; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Carles et al., 2005</xref>). While <italic>EMF1</italic> is a single gene, it may not be the core component of the PRC2 necessary for the H3K27 trimethylase activity of CLF.</p><p>The coexistence of the active and repressive histone marks on the target genes led us to examine the data further. We subtracted the signals corresponding to the repressive H3K27me3 histone marks on the target gene chromatin from those of the active H3K4me3 marks and plotted this relative value for each genotype against the relative mRNA transcription levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7D</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S6</ext-link>). This revealed that the more active (+) or less repressive (&#x2212;) the differences between the histone marks, the higher the transcriptional activities of the three genes, as the relative <italic>AG</italic> transcript levels among the four genotypes are <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> &gt; <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1</italic> &gt; the wild type &gt; <italic>ult1-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7D</xref>). A similar pattern was observed with <italic>AP3</italic> and <italic>PI</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7D</xref>). These data indicate a close correlation between the difference of the active and repressive histone marks and transcriptional activity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s13" sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Since vegetative growth is largely eliminated in <italic>emf1</italic> mutants, we employed tissue-specific removal of EMF1 activity to study the effects of EMF1 during the vegetative phase. Analyses of the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> phenotype and expression patterns showed that EMF1 is required for lateral organ differentiation and stable phase transitions in Arabidopsis. We found that ectopic expression of not one but multiple MADS box genes underlies the curly leaf and early flowering phenotypes of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants. These plants were also useful in investigating the epigenetic mechanisms of gene regulation by EMF1 and ULT1. In this study, we discovered that <italic>ult1</italic> can suppress the defects caused by partial removal of EMF1 activity but not the defects at germination caused by the <italic>emf1</italic> mutation. Our results indicate also that the difference in repressive and active histone marks on target genes modulates transcriptional activity in Arabidopsis.</p><sec id="s14"><title>Role of EMF1 in Arabidopsis Seedling Development</title><p>Reducing EMF1 activity at the onset of leaf development did not prevent rosette leaf growth. This indicates that EMF1 is not required for organ initiation, although it is required for subsequent leaf differentiation. <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants produced bigger and rounder cotyledons than wild-type plants and also formed new rosette leaves at a faster pace. <italic>SPL9</italic>, an SBP box transcriptional factor involved in the juvenile-to-adult phase transition, is up-regulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). <italic>spl9</italic> mutants produce leaves at a slower pace and are delayed in flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Schwarz et al., 2008</xref>). Thus, the <italic>SPL9</italic> up-regulation in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants is consistent with their faster pace of leaf production and earlier flowering. The rosette leaves of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants were small and curled upward along the proximal distal axis. In fact, all lateral organs, including cauline leaves and flower organs, are curled in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants. The molecular mechanisms underlying these phenotypes are discussed below.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Role of EMF1 in Flower Meristem Determination and Flower Organ Development</title><p>EMF1 involvement in flower organ development is evidenced by the fact that <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants displayed a variety of phenotypes, ranging from reduced flower organ size and missing flower organs to terminal flower, floral homeotic defects, and floral reversion in severe cases. This is counter to the expectation that epigenetic repressors would play a limited role in flower organ development when the flower MADS box genes they target are active. Flower patterning depends on PRC2 activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Wu et al., 2012</xref>). The abnormal flower morphology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>) and irregular <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> expression patterns in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>) indicate that a fine-tuning of flower MADS box gene expression during successive flower organ transition also depends on EMF1-mediated gene silencing.</p><p>The flower-in-flower phenotype observed in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2, D&#x2013;F</ext-link>) is a form of floral reversion, in which the flower meristem reverts back to the inflorescence meristem. Floral reversion occurs in plants impaired in the floral meristem identity genes <italic>LFY</italic> and <italic>AP1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Weigel et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Wagner et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Parcy et al., 2002</xref>). Ectopic expression of <italic>AGL24</italic>, an EMF1_K27 gene, also led to floral reversion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Yu et al., 2004</xref>). Reduced EMF1 activity in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> flowers would allow ectopic expression of <italic>AP1</italic> and <italic>AGL24</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>), resulting in flower formation within a flower. Before bolting, <italic>AP1</italic> and its downstream flower MADS box genes are ectopically expressed in the shoot apex of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6D</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">S&#x00E1;nchez et al., 2009</xref>). This may be sufficient to initiate terminal flower formation in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Parcy et al., 2002</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Role of EMF1 in the Salt Stress Response</title><p>EMF1 preferentially binds genes involved in biotic and abiotic stress responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2012</xref>), suggesting its involvement in stress regulation. To investigate the function of EMF1 interaction with stress gene chromatin, we investigated the salt stress response and found that <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants were more, albeit mildly, salt tolerant than wild-type plants. The <italic>LFY</italic> promoter is known to be active in leaf primordia by 4 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> and is gradually up-regulated during vegetative development, peaking in the floral meristem but not in the rest of the plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bl&#x00E1;zquez et al., 1997</xref>). Hence, only leaf primordia would experience reduced EMF1 due to the expression of <italic>asEMF1</italic> driven by the <italic>LFY</italic> promoter, whereas EMF1 would be expressed at normal levels in mature organs. Localized reduction of EMF1 activity in the shoot apex region may not lead to high stress tolerance. Inducible expression of <italic>asEMF1</italic> in response to stress in whole plants would potentially increase the extent of salt tolerance.</p><p>Because <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants have more EMF1 activity and display weaker phenotypes than <italic>emf1</italic> mutants, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants would not display as many misregulated genes as <italic>emf1</italic> mutants. Thus, two stress-related genes are up-regulated in 7-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblIII">Table III</xref>), whereas 21 genes are up-regulated in 7-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> <italic>emf1-2</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim et al., 2010</xref>). Nevertheless, we identified two salt-inducible genes that are EMF1 bound and trimethylated on H3K27 (EMF1_K27), <italic>At2G38380</italic> and <italic>At1G52890</italic>. Both of these genes are expressed at a higher level in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> than in wild-type plants when grown in the absence or presence of salt, consistent with the ability of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants to endure higher salt stress conditions. In the <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants, the transcript levels of these two genes and the salt tolerance of the plants were reduced to near the wild-type level. Reduction of salt tolerance in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants by removing ULT1 activity indicates that EMF1 regulation of the two salt-inducible genes is counteracted by ULT1 activity, as is the case for the flower MADS box genes (see below). Should future investigations of the tissue-specific expression pattern of stress genes indicate an advantage of expressing salt-inducible genes in roots (or shoots) only, it will be possible to express <italic>asEMF1</italic> under the control of a root-specific promoter in generating plants with high salt tolerance.</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Mechanisms Underlying the Curly Leaf and Early Flowering Phenotypes</title><p><italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and <italic>clf</italic> plants, as well as transgenic plants constitutively expressing <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>FT</italic>, and <italic>SEP3</italic> under the control of the <italic>35S</italic> promoter (<italic>35S</italic>::<italic>AG</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic>, and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SEP3</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Mizukami and Ma, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Honma and Goto, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lopez-Vernaza et al., 2012</xref>), all have curly leaf and early flowering phenotypes. Besides the similarity in phenotypes, these plants share one other thing in common: ectopic expression of multiple flower MADS box genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblIV">Table IV</xref>). The aberrant phenotypes can be rescued by removing the ectopic activity of just one of the flower MADS box genes without altering the ectopic expression of the others. For example, <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>SEP3</italic>, <italic>FT</italic>, and <italic>FLC</italic> are ectopically expressed in <italic>clf</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Goodrich et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lopez-Vernaza et al., 2012</xref>). Mutations in <italic>SEP3</italic>, <italic>FT</italic>, or <italic>FLC</italic> were able to suppress the <italic>clf</italic> phenotype, while <italic>AG</italic> remained highly expressed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lopez-Vernaza et al., 2012</xref>). Thus, <italic>AG</italic> misexpression is not the only reason for the curly leaf phenotype.</p><table-wrap id="tblIV"><label>Table IV.</label><caption><title>Ectopic expression of MADS box and flowering-time genes in plants displaying early flowering and curly leaf phenotypes</title><p>+ indicates genes up-regulated as reported in the references provided.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col">Genotype</th><th colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup">Phenotypes<hr/></th><th colspan="8" align="center" scope="colgroup">MADS Box and Flowering-Time Genes Up-Regulated<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col">References</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup">Flowering</th><th align="center" scope="col">Leaf</th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>AG</italic></th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>SEP3</italic></th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>AP3</italic></th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>PI</italic></th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>AP1</italic></th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>FUL</italic></th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>FT</italic></th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>FLC</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>35S</italic>::<italic>AG</italic></td><td align="center">Early</td><td align="center">Curly</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Mizukami and Ma (1992)</xref>; G&#x00F3;mez-Mena et al. (2005)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic></td><td align="center">Early</td><td align="center">Curly</td><td align="center">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblIVfn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblIVfn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="center">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblIVfn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td></td><td align="left">Teper-Bamnolker and Samach (2005)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SEP3</italic></td><td align="center">Early</td><td align="center">Curly</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Honma and Goto (2001)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Castillejo et al. (2005)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>35S</italic>::<italic>AP3 35S</italic>::<italic>PI</italic></td><td align="center">Early</td><td align="center">Curly</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Krizek and Meyerowitz (1996)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Honma and Goto (2001)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>clf</italic></td><td align="center">Early</td><td align="center">Curly</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="left"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Goodrich et al. (1997)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lopez-Vernaza et al. (2012)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>LFYasEMF1</italic></td><td align="center">Early</td><td align="center">Curly</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="left"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">S&#x00E1;nchez et al. (2009)</xref>; this study</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblIVfn1"><label>a</label><p>Genes up-regulated as predicted by the up-regulation of <italic>SEP3</italic> in the <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic> plants.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Many MADS box genes are ectopically expressed in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants, including the 10 flower homeotic genes and the flowering-time genes <italic>FLC</italic>, <italic>SUPPRESSOR OF OVEREXPRESSION OF CONSTANS1</italic>, and <italic>AGL24</italic>. In the <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants, ectopic expression of these genes is greatly reduced. Flowering-time genes regulate each other and the downstream flower homeotic genes, which also regulate each other, in a complex network. Some regulatory actions are positive and some are negative. MADS domain proteins form homodimers and heterodimers, ternary, quaternary, and multimers to regulate downstream gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Honma and Goto, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">de Folter et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Liu et al., 2008</xref>). The end result of the ectopic expression of one or more flower homeotic or flowering-time genes would be the excessive accumulation of multiple flower MADS domain proteins. This ectopic expression of one or more MADS domain proteins could create new complexes, displacing or substituting for other MADS domain proteins in stage-specific multiprotein complexes. Nevertheless, protein complexes of diverse components seem to act redundantly by regulating similar downstream genes, presumably those regulated by MADS domain protein complexes at that developmental stage. Although <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>clf</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>AG</italic>, <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>FT</italic>, and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>SEP3</italic> plants are not identical in their gene expression patterns, each shows ectopic expression of multiple flower MADS box genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblIV">Table IV</xref>). This is sufficient to cause the common aberrant phenotypes.</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Epigenetic Regulation of Flower MADS Box Genes, <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, and <italic>PI</italic></title><p>ULT1 harbors the SAND domain with DNA-binding activity; thus, it may function as a transcriptional coactivator to regulate a few specific genes. As a result, the <italic>ult1</italic> mutation may rescue the curly leaf and early flowering phenotypes of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> through the reduced expression of a few genes such as the MADS box genes. However, 2,110 genes in diverse functional groups are misregulated in <italic>ult1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblI">Table I</xref>), so ULT1 is not likely to act on the relatively few floral homeotic genes. Based on the ability of ULT1 to act as an antirepressor of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref>, a fundamental property of a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">trxG</xref> factor, we propose that ULT1 is an epigenetic regulator rather than a transcriptional activator. First, the <italic>ult1</italic> mutation completely suppresses the phenotypes caused by the mutations in <italic>CLF</italic>, a well-characterized <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Carles and Fletcher, 2009</xref>). Second, besides the flower organ and flowering-time genes, the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation restores the expression of many classes of genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants, including seed genes, histone genes, stress genes, expansion genes, and hormone response genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblIII">Table III</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S4</ext-link>). In the case of the stress genes, we established a direct link between the misregulation and restoration of the EMF1-targeted stress genes with the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants, respectively, to show a separation of the EMF1-mediated flower program from that of the stress program. Third, the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation not only affects the transcript levels of its target genes but also their chromatin marks, H3K4me3, functioning to limit the deposition of repressive histone H3K27me3 marks. Fourth, ULT1 can physically interact with the Arabidopsis <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">trxG</xref> factor ATX1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Carles and Fletcher, 2009</xref>).</p><p>The <italic>ult1</italic> mutation counteracted the impact of the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> transgene at nearly every stage of development. <italic>ult1-3</italic> restored the expression of the majority (68%&#x2013;82%) of misregulated genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> seedlings to wild-type levels. This suggests a molecular basis for the phenotype rescue and a mechanism for the restoration of gene expression. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">trxG</xref> factors trimethylate a different Lys on the same histone of the common target genes. The presence of both active H3K4me3 and repressive H3K27me3 at silent loci, termed the &#x201C;bivalent mark,&#x201D; was proposed to mark silent genes poised for activation during differentiation in mouse embryonic stem cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bernstein et al., 2006</xref>). Thus, the existence of both H3K27me3 and H3K4me3 marks on <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, and <italic>PI</italic> silent loci might represent a plastic state of these genes in seedling cells that are subject to activation by changing developmental and environmental cues. However, how <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">trxG</xref> act antagonistically in regulating gene activities remains unclear.</p><p>Recent studies showed that H3K27me3 stimulates PRC2 activity, whereas H3K4me3 inhibits it through allosteric inhibition of H3K27me3 deposition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schmitges et al., 2011</xref>). A genome-wide study showed that EMF1 is required for H3K27me3 on a fraction of its target gene loci in Arabidopsis seedlings, indicating EMF1 acting along with PRC2 for the trimethylation of H3K27 on these loci (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kim et al., 2012</xref>). Consistent with a feedback mechanism of H3K27me3 stimulation of PRC2, reduced EMF1 in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants would reduce H3K27me3-repressive mark deposition, in turn reducing PRC2 activity on the flower MADS box genes. In <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutants, we found reduced H3K4me3 active marks, which would remove the allosteric inhibition of the PRC2 deposition of the repressive marks, resulting in high levels of repressive marks, on the target gene histones. The restoration of the repressive marks in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings shows that PRC2 is able to integrate opposing H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 modifications into an intermediary H3K27 methylation activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schmitges et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>Although H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 are strongly associated with active and inactive chromatin, respectively, the debate continues whether these histone marks, H3K4me3 in particular, are the cause or consequence of transcriptional change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Henikoff and Shilatifard, 2011</xref>). In the case of EMF1 and ULT1, their molecular and biochemical functions have not been fully characterized. The ULT1 protein contains the SAND domain, known to function in chromatin-dependent transcriptional control, and can be associated with other modules, including the PHD finger (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Bottomley et al., 2001</xref>). EMF1 is a plant-specific protein that contains a few known motifs, such as the ATP/GTP-binding motif (P loop) and the LXXLL motif, which is thought to be a transcriptional regulatory motif (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Aubert et al., 2001</xref>) and is implicated in chromatin compaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Calonje et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Beh et al., 2012</xref>). If these two proteins are required for histone methylation, as our data indicate, the simple explanation would be that histone methylation change is causal to the transcriptional change seen in the plants impaired in their expression. On the other hand, should these two proteins affect transcription directly, the change in histone methylation pattern may be a consequence of the transcription change in the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and <italic>ult1</italic> plants. Regardless, our analysis revealed a close relationship between histone methylation levels and transcriptional activity. Mutually exclusive <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PcG</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">trxG</xref> domains are known to maintain stable off and on developmental states, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Papp and M&#x00FC;ller, 2006</xref>); nevertheless, the inhibitory circuitry present in PRC2 does not function as a binary on/off switch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schmitges et al., 2011</xref>). Our study further demonstrates a quantitative correlation rather than an on/off relationship between the histone methylation pattern and the transcript levels of the three flower MADS box genes. There is an additive effect of the repressive (&#x2212;) and active (+) marks on the chromatin, such that the more (+) histone marks are found on a given gene the higher the transcript levels, whereas the presence of fewer (+) or more (&#x2212;) histone marks leads to lower transcript levels. We propose that a balance of the H3K27 and H3K4 methyl marks on the gene locus mediates its transcriptional activity. This indicates that, besides maintaining active versus repressive chromatin states, histone methylation marks may function as modulators of target gene expression levels.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s19" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s20"><title>Plant Materials and Growth Conditions</title><p>Wild-type, mutant, and transgenic plants used in this study are all in the Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) Columbia background. The <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> transgenic plants harbor an <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> construct, kindly provided by Dr. Vivian Irish (Yale University), and a construct that expresses <italic>asEMF1</italic> under the control of the <italic>LFY</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">S&#x00E1;nchez et al., 2009</xref>). For all experiments, Arabidopsis seeds were surface sterilized and plated on agar plates containing two-fifth-strength <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> Basal Salt Mixture (Sigma), 1.5% Suc, and 0.8% agar. The plates were placed at 4&#x00B0;C for 2 d and moved to an <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> growth room (8 h of light/16 h of dark) at 21&#x00B0;C for 15 d. Seedlings were then transferred to soil to be grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> conditions (16 h of light/8 h of dark) at 21&#x00B0;C in the greenhouse.</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Genetic Crosses, Cotyledon Measurements, and GUS Activity Assays</title><p><italic>emf1 ult1</italic> double mutants were generated by crossing homozygous <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants with heterozygous <italic>emf1-2</italic> plants and identifying homozygous <italic>ult1-3</italic> progeny in the F2 population based on <italic>ult1-3</italic>&#x2019;s extra-petal phenotype. The F3 segregating progeny displaying the <italic>emf1-2</italic> phenotype were subjected to PCR-based genotyping to identify <italic>ult1-3</italic> alleles using the primers shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S7</ext-link>.</p><p>To introduce the <italic>ult1-3</italic> mutation into the <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> background, we crossed homozygous <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants harboring <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">S&#x00E1;nchez et al., 2009</xref>) with <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants. F2 progeny were grown on two-fifth-strength <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> medium containing 40 mg L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> hygromycin B to select for homozygous <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> individuals, which would segregate 100% hygromycin-resistant progeny. Progeny that showed <italic>AP3</italic>::<italic>GUS</italic> activity in stamens were subsequently identified. Homozygous <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> plants were screened by allele-specific polymorphism genotyping, using the primers listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S7</ext-link> to genotype <italic>ult1-3</italic> and <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>.</p><p>To measure cotyledon sizes, we took photographs of the cotyledons of 2-week-old seedlings and obtained the surface area of the cotyledon blades using the ImageJ software program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/">http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>).</p><p>GUS activity in transgenic plants was assayed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Pu et al., 2008</xref>) with slight modifications. Briefly, seedlings or tissues were incubated in 2 m<sc>m</sc> 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl-&#x03B2;-<sc>d</sc>-GlcA in 50 m<sc>m</sc> phosphate buffer, pH 7.0, containing 0.5 m<sc>m</sc> K<sub>3</sub>Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub> and 0.5 m<sc>m</sc> K<sub>4</sub>Fe(CN)<sub>6</sub> for 12 h at 37C, rinsed with 70% ethanol (v/v) at room temperature, and observed and photographed with a dissecting microscope. All subsequent image manipulation and figure preparation were performed with Adobe Photoshop.</p></sec><sec id="s22"><title>Salt Treatment, and Root Length and Rosette Diameter Measurements</title><p>Wild-type, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seeds were sown on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> agar medium. The plates were incubated at 4&#x00B0;C for 2 d before being transferred to 21&#x00B0;C under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions. The 3-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> seedlings of the wild type, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> were transferred from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> plates to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MS</xref> medium supplemented with different concentrations of salt (0, 100, 125, 150, and 200 m<sc>m</sc>) and then grown for an additional 8 d under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions. The root length was measured daily for 8 d post transfer (<italic>n</italic> = 20). The 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> seedlings were transferred to soil and continued with the same salt treatment as when they were grown on agar plates. The rosette diameter of plants grown in soil was measured at 36 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> to obtain average rosette size (<italic>n</italic> = 10).</p></sec><sec id="s23"><title>Microarray Experiments and Data Analysis</title><p>Total RNA was extracted by TRIzol Reagent (Invitrogen) following instructions in the user&#x2019;s manual. DNA was eliminated by the use of the TURBO DNA-free kit (Ambion). Microarray experiments were performed in the DNA microarray core laboratory (Institute of Plant and Microbial Biology, Academia Sinica; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ipmb.sinica.edu.tw/affy/">http//ipmb.sinica.edu.tw/affy/</ext-link>). One microgram of total RNA from each sample was used as a template to generate amino allyl-modified RNA (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">aRNA</xref>). The amplified <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">aRNA</xref> was labeled with Alexa Fluor 555 reactive dyes (Invitrogen) and fragmented according to the Amino Allyl MessageAmp <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">aRNA</xref> Amplification Kit (Ambion) instruction manual before hybridization to the Arabidopsis Gene Expression Microarray chip version 4 with 43,803 Arabidopsis probes represented (G2519F; Agilent Technologies; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genomics.agilent.com">http://www.genomics.agilent.com</ext-link>). The chips were hybridized with equal amounts (1.65 &#x03BC;g) of Alexa Fluor 555-labeled <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">aRNA</xref> for 17 h at 65&#x00B0;C and washed according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions in the Agilent Gene Expression Hybridization Kit. Chip images were scanned and analyzed by the use of Feature Extraction software (version 10.7.1.1) following the GE1-107_Sep09 protocol (Agilent Technologies). Microarray hybridization was repeated two times with independent biological samples. The results presented were based on one set of microarray analyses. Genes with hybridization signals of 50 or greater in at least one of four plant samples were analyzed. The fold change of gene expression was based on the ratio of mutant or transgenic plants to the wild type, with the ratio greater than 2-fold used to identify up- or down-regulated genes.</p></sec><sec id="s24"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">RT</xref>-PCR and Real-Time Quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">RT</xref>-PCR</title><p>Total RNA was isolated from 6-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>) or 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>) seedlings using the RNeasy plant kit (Qiagen) as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Pu et al., 2008</xref>). RNA samples were treated with RNase-free DNaseI (Invitrogen) for 15 min at room temperature, and then DNaseI was inactivated by treatment with 25 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA solution. First-strand complementary DNA (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">cDNA</xref>) synthesis was performed on 1 &#x03BC;g of total RNA using SuperScript II reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen) and 12mer to 18mer oligo(dT) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">RT</xref>-PCR, samples of the first-strand <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">cDNA</xref> were then used in PCR with Phusion high-fidelity DNA polymerase according to the recommendations of the supplier. At least two independent experiments employing biological replicates were performed. Three technical replicates of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">RT</xref>-PCR were performed for each biological sample with similar results. Thirty-one to 36 cycles of PCR were used for all genes with the gene-specific primers listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S7</ext-link>. The intensity of DNA bands in each image (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5</ext-link>) was measured using ImageJ software. The relative DNA level of each gene was then normalized to each UBQ control and the wild type and is represented as an Arabic number beneath each gel image. For quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">RT</xref>-PCR, samples of the first-strand <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">cDNA</xref> were then analyzed (Thermocycler ABI 7300) using SYBR Green and standard settings. Quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">RT</xref>-PCR was performed in a final volume of 20 &#x03BC;L. Three technical replicates were done for each sample. Amplification of UBQ was used as an internal control to normalize all data. Quantification was determined by applying the comparative cycle threshold formula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Pu et al., 2008</xref>). All gene-specific primers are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S7</ext-link>. The intensity of DNA bands in each image (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5</ext-link>) was measured using ImageJ software. The relative DNA level of each gene was then normalized to each UBQ control and the wild type and is represented as an Arabic number beneath each gel image.</p></sec><sec id="s25"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ChIP</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ChIP</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">qPCR</xref></title><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ChIP</xref> experiments were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kim et al., 2010</xref>). Briefly, fresh tissues of 15-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref> seedlings were infiltrated in 1% formaldehyde solution under a vacuum for 30 min to cross link the chromatin. The reaction was stopped by adding 0.1 <sc>m</sc> Gly. Fixed tissues were ground in liquid nitrogen, nuclei were isolated, and chromatin was extracted and sheared by sonication (Microson MS-50; 10 s on and 10 s off for 10 times) to generate 0.5- to 2-kb fragments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Bowler et al., 2004</xref>). Anti-H3K27me3 (Millipore) and anti-H3K4me3 (Abcam) antibodies were used to immunoprecipitate the fragmented chromatin. Cross linking of immunoprecipitated chromatin was reversed with 5 <sc>m</sc> salt, and DNA was precipitated with 100% ethanol. For the input control, 5 <sc>m</sc> salt was added to 0.5% total chromatin before immunoprecipitation to reverse the cross linking, and DNA was isolated by 100% ethanol. The relative amount of DNA was determined by spectrophotometry (NanoDrop ND1000). Immunoprecipitated DNA was analyzed by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">qPCR</xref> (Thermocycler ABI 7300) using SYBR Green and standard settings. PCR was performed in a final volume of 20 &#x03BC;L, and dilutions of purified input DNA were measured together with the immunoprecipitated DNA samples. Three technical replicates were done for each sample. Quantification was determined by applying the 2<sup>-&#x2206;Ct</sup> formula (SuperArray <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ChIP</xref>-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">qPCR</xref> user manual; Bioscience Corporation). Average immunoprecipitates from chromatin isolated independently are expressed on graphs as percentages of corresponding input DNA with error bars representing the <sc>sd</sc>. Primers used for the detection of <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, <italic>PI</italic>, and <italic>AT2G40000</italic> are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1">Supplemental Table S7</ext-link>.</p><p>The microarray data from this article are deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus with accession number GSE39947. Sequence data can be found in the Arabidopsis Genome Initiative or GenBank/EMBL databases under the following accession numbers: <italic>At5G11530</italic> (<italic>EMF1</italic>), <italic>At4G28190</italic> (<italic>ULT1</italic>), <italic>At3G54340</italic> (<italic>AP3</italic>), <italic>At4G18960</italic> (<italic>AG</italic>), and <italic>At5G20240</italic> (<italic>PI</italic>).</p></sec><sec id="s26"><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.<list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> Phenotype and genotype of <italic>emf1-2 ult1-3</italic> double mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> Homeotic defects of <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> flowers.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S3.</bold></ext-link> Expression of the flower MADS box and seed genes in plants impaired in <italic>EMF1</italic> and/or <italic>ULT1</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S4.</bold></ext-link> Restoration of misregulated genes of 15 functional categories in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> seedlings.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S5.</bold></ext-link> Effects of <italic>emf1</italic> and <italic>ult1</italic> on salt-responsive gene expression.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S1.</bold></ext-link> Expression pattern of the 15 categories of genes in wild-type, <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic>, <italic>ult1-3</italic>, and <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic> Arabidopsis at 7 and 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S2.</bold></ext-link> Significantly misregulated genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> and <italic>ult1-3</italic> and restored in <italic>LFYasEMF1 ult1-3</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S3.</bold></ext-link> Expression change by <italic>ult1-3</italic> on genes misregulated in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S4.</bold></ext-link> <italic>ult1-3</italic> restoration of misregulated genes in <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> plants at 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">DAG</xref>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S5.</bold></ext-link> Expression change by <italic>LFYasEMF1</italic> on misregulated genes in <italic>ult1-3</italic> plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S6.</bold></ext-link> Differences of active H3K4me3 (+) and repressive H3K27me3 (&#x2212;) marks on the flower MADS box genes <italic>AG</italic>, <italic>AP3</italic>, and <italic>PI</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213223/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S7.</bold></ext-link> Primers.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the following people from the Department of Plant and Microbial Biology, University of California, Berkeley: Yvonne Kim, Nathalie Quintero, Tiffany Wang, and Gilbert Garcia for assistance and Drs. Andy Jackson and Russell Jones for critical reading of the manuscript and their valuable comments.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez-Venegas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Avramova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Two Arabidopsis homologs of the animal trithorax genes: a new structural domain is a signature feature of the trithorax gene family</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>271</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>221</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez-Venegas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pien</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Witmer</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Avramova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>ATX-1, an Arabidopsis homolog of trithorax, activates flower homeotic genes</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>627</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>637</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aubert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>EMF1, a novel protein involved in the control of shoot architecture and flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1865</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1875</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baumbusch</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorstensen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Naumann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Assalkhou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Aalen</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis thaliana genome contains at least 29 active genes encoding SET domain proteins that can be assigned to four evolutionarily conserved classes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>4319</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4333</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beh</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A core subunit of Polycomb repressive complex 1 is broadly conserved in function but not primary sequence</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>E1063</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>E1071</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huebert</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Meissner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wernig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Plath</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A bivalent chromatin structure marks key developmental genes in embryonic stem cells</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>326</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bl&#x00E1;zquez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Soowal</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>LEAFY expression and flower initiation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>3835</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3844</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bottomley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Collard</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Huggenvik</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sattler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The SAND domain structure defines a novel DNA-binding fold in transcriptional regulation</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>626</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>633</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Benvenuto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Laflamme</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Molino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Probst</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Tariq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paszkowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Chromatin techniques for plant cells</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>776</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>789</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bratzel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x00F3;pez-Torrej&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Pozo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Calonje</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Keeping cell identity in Arabidopsis requires PRC1 RING-finger homologs that catalyze H2A monoubiquitination</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1853</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1859</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calonje</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>EMBRYONIC FLOWER1 participates in polycomb group-mediated AG gene silencing in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>291</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carles</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Choffnes-Inada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Reville</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lertpiriyapong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>ULTRAPETALA1 encodes a SAND domain putative transcriptional regulator that controls shoot and floral meristem activity in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>897</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>911</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carles</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The SAND domain protein ULTRAPETALA1 acts as a trithorax group factor to regulate cell fate in plants</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2723</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2728</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carles</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lertpiriyapong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Reville</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The ULTRAPETALA1 gene functions early in Arabidopsis development to restrict shoot apical meristem activity and acts through WUSCHEL to regulate floral meristem determinacy</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>167</volume>: <fpage>1893</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1903</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castillejo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Romera-Branchat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A new role of the Arabidopsis <italic>SEPALLATA3</italic> gene revealed by its constitutive expression</article-title>. <source>Plant Journal</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>586</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>596</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castillejo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The balance between CONSTANS and TEMPRANILLO activities determines FT expression to trigger flowering</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1338</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1343</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chanvivattana</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishopp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Interaction of Polycomb-group proteins controlling flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>5263</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5276</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaudhury</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koltunow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Control of early seed development</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>677</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>699</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>EMF genes regulate <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> inflorescence development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>2011</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2024</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Folter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Immink</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parenicov&#x00E1;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Henz</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Busscher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kooiker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kater</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><bold>, et al</bold> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive interaction map of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> MADS box transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1424</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1433</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Lucia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Crevillen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AME</given-names></name><name><surname>Greb</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A PHD-polycomb repressive complex 2 triggers the epigenetic silencing of FLC during vernalization</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>16831</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>16836</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farrona</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhorn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Adrian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarid-Krebs</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Turck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Tissue-specific expression of FLOWERING LOCUS T in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is maintained independently of polycomb group protein repression</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>3204</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3214</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The ULTRAPETALA gene controls shoot and floral meristem size in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>1323</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1333</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gendall</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The VERNALIZATION 2 gene mediates the epigenetic regulation of vernalization in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>525</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>535</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez-Mena</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>de Folter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Angenent</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sablowski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional program controlled by the floral homeotic gene AGAMOUS during early organogenesis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>438</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Puangsomlee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A Polycomb-group gene regulates homeotic gene expression in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>386</volume>: <fpage>44</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>51</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henikoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shilatifard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Histone modification: cause or cog?</article-title> <source>Trends Genet</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>389</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>396</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hennig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Derkacheva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Diversity of Polycomb group complexes in plants: same rules, different players?</article-title> <source>Trends Genet</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>414</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>423</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holec</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Polycomb group complexes mediate developmental transitions in plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>158</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>43</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Complexes of MADS-box proteins are sufficient to convert leaves into floral organs</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>409</volume>: <fpage>525</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>529</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Deyholos</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Comparative proteomic analysis of NaCl stress-responsive proteins in Arabidopsis roots</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>3591</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3607</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jurgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>A group of genes controlling the spatial expression of the bithorax complex in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>316</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>155</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kania</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Russenberger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Apel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Melzer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>FPF1 promotes flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1327</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1338</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshed-Williams</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilberman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>EMF1 and PRC2 cooperate to repress key regulators of Arabidopsis development</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002512</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Epigenetic regulation of gene programs by EMF1 and EMF2 in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>152</volume>: <fpage>516</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>528</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Polycomb repression of flowering during early plant development</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>14156</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14161</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klymenko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The histone methyltransferases Trithorax and Ash1 prevent transcriptional silencing by Polycomb group proteins</article-title>. <source>EMBO Rep</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>377</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x00F6;hler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouveret</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gheyselinck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruissem</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis MSI1 is a component of the MEA/FIE Polycomb group complex and required for seed development</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>4804</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4814</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krizek</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homeotic genes <italic>APETALA3</italic> and <italic>PISTILLATA</italic> are sufficient to provide the B class organ identity function</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>22</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krizek</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of flower development: an armchair guide</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>688</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>698</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>A gene complex controlling segmentation in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>276</volume>: <fpage>565</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>570</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Er</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Soo</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liou</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Direct interaction of AGL24 and SOC1 integrates flowering signals in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>1481</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1491</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez-Vernaza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>de Leau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Antagonistic roles of SEPALLATA3, FT and FLC genes as targets of the polycomb group gene CURLY LEAF</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e30715</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melzer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kampmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Apel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>FPF1 modulates the competence to flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>395</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>405</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>FLOWERING LOCUS C encodes a novel MADS domain protein that acts as a repressor of flowering</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>949</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>956</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ditta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafson-Brown</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>AGL24 acts as a promoter of flowering in Arabidopsis and is positively regulated by vernalization</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>867</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>874</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizukami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Ectopic expression of the floral homeotic gene AGAMOUS in transgenic Arabidopsis plants alters floral organ identity</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>131</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maffeo</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>EMF genes maintain vegetative development by repressing the flower program in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>681</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>693</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mylne</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessadori</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesnage</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernatavichute</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fransz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>LHP1, the Arabidopsis homologue of HETEROCHROMATIN PROTEIN1, is required for epigenetic silencing of FLC</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>5012</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5017</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrasekharan</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Aramayo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kertbundit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Plant SET domain-containing proteins: structure, function and regulation</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source> <volume>1769</volume>: <fpage>316</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>329</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Histone trimethylation and the maintenance of transcriptional ON and OFF states by trxG and PcG proteins</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2041</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2054</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parcy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bomblies</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Interaction of LEAFY, AGAMOUS and TERMINAL FLOWER1 in maintaining floral meristem identity in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>2519</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2527</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pien</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mylne</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Crevillen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Inz&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Avramova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>ARABIDOPSIS TRITHORAX1 dynamically regulates <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS C</italic> activation via histone 3 lysine 4 trimethylation</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>580</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>588</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Horard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigrist</surname><given-names>CJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirrotta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The Drosophila trithorax protein is a coactivator required to prevent re-establishment of polycomb silencing</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>2483</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2493</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The R2R3 MYB transcription factor GhMYB109 is required for cotton fiber development</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>180</volume>: <fpage>811</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>820</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ratcliffe</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumimoto</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Riechmann</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Analysis of the <italic>Arabidopsis MADS AFFECTING FLOWERING</italic> gene family: <italic>MAF2</italic> prevents vernalization by short periods of cold</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1159</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1169</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Abdallat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndamukong</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez-Venegas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Avramova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis homologs of trithorax (ATX1) and enhancer of zeste (CLF) establish &#x2018;bivalent chromatin marks&#x2019; at the silent AGAMOUS locus</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>6290</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6296</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x00E1;nchez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Calonje</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Temporal and spatial requirement of EMF1 activity for Arabidopsis vegetative and reproductive development</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>643</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>653</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez-Pulido</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Devos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Calonje</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>RAWUL: a new ubiquitin-like domain in PRC1 ring finger proteins that unveils putative plant and worm PRC1 orthologs</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitges</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Prusty</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Faty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>St&#x00FC;tzer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lingaraju</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aiwazian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Histone methylation by PRC2 is inhibited by active chromatin marks</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>330</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>341</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuettengruber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chourrout</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vervoort</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leblanc</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Genome regulation by polycomb and trithorax proteins</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>745</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirrotta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Polycomb silencing mechanisms and the management of genomic programmes</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>22</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grande</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bujdoso</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Saedler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The microRNA regulated SBP-box genes SPL9 and SPL15 control shoot maturation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>195</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Belachew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shunong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertrand-Garcia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>EMF, an Arabidopsis gene required for vegetative shoot development</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>258</volume>: <fpage>1645</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1647</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>ARABIDOPSIS TRITHORAX-RELATED7 is required for methylation of lysine 4 of histone H3 and for transcriptional activation of FLOWERING LOCUS C</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>3257</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3269</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teper-Bamnolker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Samach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The flowering integrator FT regulates <italic>SEPALLATA3</italic> and <italic>FRUITFULL</italic> accumulation in Arabidopsis leaves</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>2661</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2675</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>To</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Valon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Savino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Guilleminot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Devic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraudat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parcy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A network of local and redundant gene regulation governs <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seed maturation</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1642</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1651</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Isolation and functional analysis of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> stress-inducible NAC transcription factors that bind to a drought-responsive cis-element in the early responsive to dehydration stress 1 promoter</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>2481</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2498</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Roudier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrona</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin-Magniette</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillaume</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Buisine</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagnot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martienssen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Colot</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis TFL2/LHP1 specifically associates with genes marked by trimethylation of histone H3 lysine 27</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>855</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>866</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sablowski</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional activation of APETALA1 by LEAFY</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>285</volume>: <fpage>582</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>584</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Czech</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>miR156-regulated SPL transcription factors define an endogenous flowering pathway in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>738</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>749</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>LEAFY controls floral meristem identity in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>843</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>859</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanvillain-Baufum&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reback</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Monniaux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>LEAFY target genes reveal floral regulatory logic, cis motifs, and a link to biotic stimulus response</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>430</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>443</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Helliwell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis thaliana vernalization response requires a polycomb-like protein complex that also includes VERNALIZATION INSENSITIVE 3</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>14631</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>14636</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezhani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Slewinski</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>SWI2/SNF2 chromatin remodeling ATPases overcome polycomb repression and control floral organ identity with the LEAFY and SEPALLATA3 transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>3576</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3581</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Polycomb silencing of KNOX genes confines shoot stem cell niches in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1966</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1971</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Genetic regulation of shoot development in Arabidopsis: role of the EMF genes</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source> <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>435</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiratsuka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>EMBRYONIC FLOWER2, a novel polycomb group protein homolog, mediates shoot development and flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>2471</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2481</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellmer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Repression of AGAMOUS-LIKE 24 is a crucial step in promoting flower development</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>161</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernatavichute</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cokus</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide analysis of mono-, di- and trimethylation of histone H3 lysine 4 in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>R62.1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>62.14</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Germann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Blus</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Khorasanizadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaudin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis LHP1 protein colocalizes with histone H3 Lys27 trimethylation</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>869</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>871</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
