<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">202192</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.202192</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>DEVELOPMENT AND HORMONE ACTION</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>LONO1</italic> Encoding a Nucleoporin Is Required for Embryogenesis and Seed Viability in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[C]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4"><sup>[OA]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Braud</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Wenguang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Wenyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><aff>Department of Biology, Saint Louis University, St. Louis, Missouri 63103</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health (grant nos. 1R15GM086846&#x2013;01 and 3R15GM086846&#x2013;01S1 to W.X.).</p></fn><fn id="fn5" fn-type="equal"><label>2</label><p>These authors contributed equally to the article.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>wxiao@slu.edu</email>.</corresp><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Wenyan Xiao (<email>wxiao@slu.edu</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[C]</label><p>Some figures in this article are displayed in color online but in black and white in the print edition.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn4"><label>[OA]</label><p>Open Access articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.202192">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.202192</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>10</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>160</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>836</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>06</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>08</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2012 American Society of Plant Biologists. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p></p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Early embryogenesis in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) is distinguished by a predictable pattern of cell divisions and is a good system for investigating mechanisms of developmental pattern formation. Here, we identified a gene called <italic>LONO1</italic> (<italic>LNO1</italic>) in Arabidopsis in which mutations can abolish the first asymmetrical cell division of the zygote, alter planes and number of cell divisions in early embryogenesis, and eventually arrest embryo development. <italic>LNO1</italic> is highly expressed in anthers of flower buds, stigma papilla of open flowers, and embryo and endosperm during early embryogenesis, which is correlated with its functions in reproductive development. The homozygous <italic>lno1-1</italic> seed is not viable. <italic>LNO1</italic>, a homolog of the nucleoporin <italic>NUP214</italic> in human (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>) and <italic>Nup159</italic> in yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>), encodes a nucleoporin protein containing phenylalanine-glycine repeats in Arabidopsis. We demonstrate that <italic>LNO1</italic> can functionally complement the defect in the yeast temperature-sensitive nucleoporin mutant <italic>nup159</italic>. We show that LNO1 specifically interacts with the Arabidopsis DEAD-box helicase/ATPase LOS4 in the yeast two-hybrid assay. Furthermore, mutations in <italic>AtGLE1</italic>, an Arabidopsis homolog of the yeast <italic>Gle1</italic> involved in the same poly(A) mRNA export pathway as <italic>Nup159</italic>, also result in seed abortion. Our results suggest that LNO1 is a component of the nuclear pore complex required for mature mRNA export from the nucleus to the cytoplasm, which makes <italic>LNO1</italic> essential for embryogenesis and seed viability in Arabidopsis.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">NPC</term><def id="def1"><p>nuclear pore complex</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">FG</term><def id="def2"><p>Phe-Gly</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">mRNP</term><def id="def3"><p>mRNA protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">RT</term><def id="def4"><p>reverse transcription</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">DAP</term><def id="def5"><p>days after pollination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">SD</term><def id="def6"><p>synthetic dextrose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">YPD</term><def id="def7"><p>yeast peptone dextrose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8">Col-0</term><def id="def8"><p>ecotype Columbia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9">cDNA</term><def id="def9"><p>complementary DNA</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>In Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), early embryogenesis follows a predictable pattern of cell divisions. For example, the zygote first divides asymmetrically to form a small apical cell and a large basal cell after fertilization, establishing two cell lineages with fundamentally different growth patterns and developmental fates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Scheres and Benfey, 1999</xref>). The apical cell then undergoes two rounds of longitudinal cell divisions and one round of transverse division to form eight cells, which divide periclinally to produce a 16-cell proembryo. The spherical proembryo continues to develop and passes through a series of stages that can be defined morphologically as globular, transition, heart, torpedo, and walking stick stages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Goldberg et al., 1994</xref>). The basal cell elongates and divides transversely to form a structure of seven to nine cells called the suspensor, which follows an extraembryonic cell fate. However, mutations in some genes can make the basal lineage cells adopt an embryonic cell fate by undergoing longitudinal cell divisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Vernon and Meinke, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Zhang and Somerville, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Lotan et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lukowitz et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>The normal pattern formation is important in embryogenesis, and many genes have been shown to regulate the process. The <italic>PIN-FORMED</italic> (<italic>PIN</italic>) genes encode transporter-like membrane proteins that function as auxin efflux carriers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Friml, 2003</xref>). PIN proteins control polar auxin transport and establish auxin gradients during embryogenesis, which are required for early embryo pattern formation in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Friml et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Weijers et al., 2005</xref>). Genes encoding transcription factors, such as <italic>AUXIN RESPONSE FACTORS</italic>, <italic>MONOPTEROS</italic>, <italic>BODENLOS</italic>, <italic>TARGET OF MONOPTEROS5</italic> (<italic>TMO5</italic>), <italic>TMO7</italic>, <italic>HANABA TARANU</italic>, <italic>PLETHORA1</italic> (<italic>PLT1</italic>), and <italic>PLT2</italic>, are also involved in pattern formation and/or embryonic root initiation in early embryogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Berleth and Jurgens, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Hamann et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Aida et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Nawy et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Schlereth et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>Determination of the apical and basal cell fates requires the signaling pathways regulated by <italic>YODA</italic> (a MEK kinase; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Lukowitz et al., 2004</xref>), <italic>SHORT SUSPENSOR</italic> (an IL-1 receptor-associated kinase/Pelle-like kinase; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Bayer et al., 2009</xref>), <italic>WUSCHEL-LIKE HOMEOBOX</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Haecker et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Breuninger et al., 2008</xref>), and <italic>GROUNDED</italic> or <italic>RKD4</italic>, a putative transcription factor of the RWP-RK motif family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Jeong et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Waki et al., 2011</xref>). <italic>RECEPTOR-LIKE PROTEIN KINASE1</italic> and <italic>TOADSTOOL2</italic> are also critical for embryonic pattern formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Nodine et al., 2007</xref>). These genes function in diverse pathways in plants, but how the signal events regulated by these genes converge during early embryogenesis to regulate pattern formation is not well understood. Recently, genomic approaches have been employed to understand how many genes are expressed in seeds and gametophyte as well as which genes are essential for making a seed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Meinke et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Le et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Autran et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Drews et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Hsieh et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Nodine and Bartel, 2012</xref>), but it seems that there is no definitive answer to what the minimal gene set is for making a seed in plants.</p><p>In eukaryotic cells, the nuclear envelope forms a physical barrier to separate the cytosol from the nucleus. The nuclear pore complexes (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref>) are channels embedded between the inner and outer nuclear membranes and consist of multiple copies of approximately 30 different proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hetzer and Wente, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Strambio-De-Castillia et al., 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> are the only channels that all nucleocytoplasmic traffic must go through, such as mRNA export from the nucleus to the cytoplasm and protein import from the cytoplasm to the nucleus. As a macromolecular complex, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> is not easy to study, but recent progress has shed light on its structure, assembly, and functions. Nucleoporins, the building blocks of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref>, can be generally divided into three classes: a small group of membrane-anchored proteins, a large group of barrier proteins containing Phe-Gly (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">FG</xref>) repeats, and a large group of scaffold proteins that form a stable architectural framework of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Brohawn et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Onischenko and Weis, 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> biogenesis occurs in both mitosis and interphase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Hetzer and Wente, 2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> disassemble into subcomplexes during mitosis. Subcomplexes and endoplasmic reticulum membranes are then recruited to chromatin at the end of mitosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Dultz et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Lupu et al., 2008</xref>). For example, it has been shown that recruitment of the Nup107/160 subcomplex initiates the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> assembly during nuclear envelope reformation in <italic>Xenopus</italic> spp. and is followed by the recruitment of endoplasmic reticulum membranes containing POM121 and Ndc1 and the subsequent integration of Nup155 and Nup53 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Rasala et al., 2008</xref>). During interphase, other newly synthesized nucleoporins are targeted and incorporated into the nuclear envelope to form <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Rasala et al., 2008</xref>). While the main function of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> is to mediate trafficking between the nucleus and the cytoplasm, functions of individual nucleoporins in growth and development have only begun to be understood. For example, the nucleoporin Nup98 stimulates the expression of cell cycle genes in <italic>Drosophila</italic> spp.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Kalverda et al., 2010</xref>).</p><p>CAN/NUP214 was originally discovered due to its involvement in myeloid leukemia in humans (<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">von Lindern et al., 1992a, 1992b</xref>). NUP214 is an <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">FG</xref> repeat-containing nucleoporin that is likely to serve as a docking site in the receptor-mediated import of substrates across the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bastos et al., 1997</xref>). It has been shown that <italic>nup214&#x2212;/&#x2212;</italic> mouse embryonic stem cells are not viable and that embryos die early in utero (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">van Deursen et al., 1996</xref>). Interestingly, these defective <italic>nup214&#x2212;/&#x2212;</italic> embryos do not display any obvious abnormal morphology in their nuclear envelopes or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">van Deursen et al., 1996</xref>). The <italic>Nup159/RAT7</italic> gene (for RNA trafficking) was identified in a screen for genes required for nucleocytoplasmic transport of mRNA in yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gorsch et al., 1995</xref>). Nup159p<italic>/</italic>Rat7p contains <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">FG</xref> repeats, is the yeast homolog of human NUP214, and is located on the cytoplasmic side at the nuclear rim (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Kraemer et al., 1995</xref>). mRNA export in the yeast temperature-sensitive <italic>rat7-1</italic> mutant was quickly stopped when the temperature was shifted from 23&#x00B0;C to 37&#x00B0;C, while the protein import from the cytoplasm to the nucleus did not seem to be affected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Gorsch et al., 1995</xref>). Recent studies in yeast have revealed the mechanism of the sequential interaction between DEAD-box protein5 (Dbp5) and Gle1 and Nup159 in regulating mRNA export (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Hodge et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Noble et al., 2011</xref>). The association of Dbp5 with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> is dynamic and correlated with translocation rates of mRNA protein (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">mRNP</xref>) through <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Hodge et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Noble et al., 2011</xref>). Inositol hexakisphosphate (IP<sub>6</sub>)-bound Gle1 promotes ATP binding to Dbp5 and activates its ATPase activity, and hydrolysis of Dbp5-ATP to Dbp5-ADP mediates the remodeling of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">mRNP</xref> complexes. Nup159 then functions to promote ADP release from Dbp5-ADP, and the resulting nucleotide-free Dbp5 is then ready for ATP loading upon stimulation from Gle1-IP<sub>6</sub>, starting a new round of nucleotide cycling, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">mRNP</xref> remodeling, and export (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Hodge et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Noble et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>Although the structure of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> is conserved in eukaryotes, not much is known about the structure of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> and functions of nucleoporins in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Meier and Brkljacic, 2009</xref>). Ten nucleoporins have been isolated and functionally characterized in plants: NUP160/SAR1, NUP133, NUP96/SAR3/MOS3, NUP88/MOS7, NUP75/NUP85, NUP1/NUP136, RAE1, TPR/NUA, NUP107, and NUP62 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Zhang and Li, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Dong et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Kanamori et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Parry et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Jacob et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Saito et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Xu et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Lee et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tamura et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Tamura and Hara-Nishimura, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Wiermer et al., 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Zhao and Meier, 2011</xref>). These nucleoporins have been shown to regulate cell division, hormone signaling, response to stress, rhizobial and fungal symbiosis, flowering, and other aspects of plant development. Recently, 22 nucleoporins have been identified through the mass spectrometry-based interactive proteomics in Arabidopsis, including Arabidopsis NUP214 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tamura et al., 2010</xref>), but the biological functions of most nucleoporins in plant growth and development remain unknown.</p><p>Here, we report the isolation and characterization of the <italic>lono1</italic> (<italic>lno1</italic>) mutant during early embryogenesis and seed development. <italic>LNO1</italic> encodes nucleoporin-containing <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">FG</xref> repeats in Arabidopsis, a homologous protein to the nucleoporin NUP214 in humans, and Nup159 in yeast. We show that <italic>LNO1</italic> can functionally complement the yeast nucleoporin temperature-sensitive mutant <italic>nup159</italic>. We also show that the nucleoporin LNO1 interacts with Arabidopsis DEAD-box helicase/ATPase, CRYOPHYTE/LOS4, in the yeast two-hybrid assay. Mutations in <italic>LNO1</italic> can abolish the first zygotic asymmetrical cell division, alter normal pattern formation in early embryogenesis, and lead to aborted seed. Remarkably, <italic>AtGLE1</italic>, an Arabidopsis homolog of the yeast <italic>Gle1</italic> functioning in the same pathway as <italic>Nup159</italic>, is also required for seed viability. Our studies suggest that LNO1 is a functionally conserved nucleoporin protein that is required for embryogenesis and seed development in Arabidopsis.</p><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Identification of the <italic>LNO1</italic> Gene and T-DNA Insertional Mutants</title><p>To understand embryogenesis and seed development, we took a genetic approach (see &#x201C;Materials and Methods&#x201D;) and identified genetic mutations that interrupt seed development. By screening a set of T-DNA insertional mutant lines, we identified a few mutants that had abnormal embryogenesis or seed abortion. We named these genes <italic>LONO</italic>, after a god who was associated with fertility, agriculture, rainfall, and music in Hawaiian mythology. We found that <italic>LNO1</italic> (<italic>At1G55540</italic>) was required for seed viability in Arabidopsis. When <italic>lno1-1</italic> became homozygous, the seed was not viable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), and we were not able to obtain viable <italic>lno1-1</italic>/<italic>lno1-1</italic> plants. In self-pollinated heterozygous <italic>LNO1</italic>/<italic>lno1-1</italic> plants, we counted seed abortion and found 357 aborted seeds among a total of 1,439 seeds (1,082:357, &#x03C7;<sup>2</sup> &#x003D; 0.009 for the 3:1 ratio, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.9; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tblI">Table I</xref>), suggesting that the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutation results in seed abortion and follows simple Mendelian inheritance. We backcrossed the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant to wild-type plants five times, and the result showed that the seed abortion phenotype was correlated with the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutation in each progeny and each generation. To further confirm that the seed abortion phenotype was caused by the T-DNA insertional mutation in <italic>LNO1</italic>, we transformed the <italic>LNO1</italic> transgene under the control of the <italic>35S</italic> promoter into <italic>LNO1/lno1-1</italic> heterozygous plants, and the result showed that the transgene was able to complement the mutant phenotype and restored the seed viability in the homozygous mutant <italic>lno1-1/lno1-1</italic> background.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Effect of the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutation on seed viability in Arabidopsis. Siliques of wild-type (<italic>LNO1/LNO1</italic>) and heterozygous (<italic>LNO1/lno1-1</italic>) plants were dissected and photographed at 6 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> (A), at 12 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> (B), and at 18 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> (C). Brown and green seeds in the silique on the right in C were aborted and viable seeds, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_202192_wc_f1" alt-version="no"/></fig><table-wrap id="tblI"><label>Table I.</label><caption><title>The lno1-1 mutation affects embryogenesis and seed viability in Arabidopsis</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col">Self-Pollinated</th><th colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup">Abnormal F1 Embryo<hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup">F1 Seed Abortion<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" scope="colgroup">Abnormal</th><th align="center" scope="col">Total</th><th align="center" scope="col">Percentage</th><th align="center" scope="col">Aborted</th><th align="center" scope="col">Total</th><th align="center" scope="col"> Percentage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td scope="row">Wild type</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">386</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="char" char=".">467</td><td align="char" char=".">0.4</td></tr><tr><td scope="row"><italic>LNO1/lno1-1</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">57</td><td align="char" char=".">483</td><td align="char" char=".">11.8</td><td align="char" char=".">357</td><td align="char" char=".">1439</td><td align="char" char=".">24.8</td></tr><tr><td scope="row"><italic>lno1-2/lno1-2</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">437</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">6</td><td align="char" char=".">875</td><td align="char" char=".">0.7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>We did not detect any morphological phenotype or defect in ovule or pollen development of the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant allele. We further examined whether the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant allele has any defects in transmission through female or male by reciprocally crossing the heterozygous <italic>LNO1</italic>/<italic>lno1-1</italic> with wild-type plants. In the F1 progeny, there were no empty positions in siliques, suggesting that there were no degenerated ovules or unfertilized ovules, and almost all the seeds were viable whether the <italic>LNO1</italic>/<italic>lno1-1</italic> plants were used as female or male in the cross (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblII">Table II</xref>). After the F1 progeny were planted, we genotyped each plant in the F1 and found that the <italic>lno1-1</italic> allele was transmitted to the next generation as efficiently as the wild-type allele either by female or male (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblII">Table II</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tblII"><label>Table II.</label><caption><title>The lno1-1 mutant has neither parent-of-origin effect nor defects in transmission</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="center" scope="col">Parental Genotype (Female &#x00D7; Male)</th><th align="center" scope="col">Viable Seed</th><th align="center" scope="col">Aborted Seed</th><th align="center" scope="col">Total Seed</th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>LNO1/LNO1</italic></th><th align="center" scope="col"><italic>LNO1/lno1-1</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td scope="row"><xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Col-0</xref> &#x00D7; <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Col-0</xref></td><td align="char" char=".">137</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="char" char=".">139</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td scope="row"><italic>LNO1</italic>/<italic>lno1-1</italic> &#x00D7; <italic>LNO1</italic>/<italic>LNO1</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">248</td><td align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="char" char=".">251</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td scope="row">F1 progeny</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">63</td><td align="center">54</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center" scope="row">&#x03C7;<sup>2</sup> &#x003D; 0.70</td><td align="center"><italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.40</td></tr><tr><td scope="row"><italic>LNO1</italic>/<italic>LNO1</italic> &#x00D7; <italic>LNO1</italic>/<italic>lno1-1</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">331</td><td align="char" char=".">1</td><td align="char" char=".">332</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td scope="row">F1 progeny</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">64</td><td align="center">51</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center" scope="row">&#x03C7;<sup>2</sup> &#x003D; 1.49</td><td align="center"><italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.22</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title><italic>LNO1</italic> Encodes a Nucleoporin Protein in Arabidopsis</title><p>In Arabidopsis, <italic>LNO1</italic> (<italic>At1G55540</italic>) has 18 exons and 17 introns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>) and encodes a protein with 1,819 amino acids that can be divided into an N-terminal &#x03B2;-propeller domain, a coiled-coil domain in the middle, and C-terminal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">FG</xref> repeats (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>). <italic>LNO1</italic> encodes a nucleoporin protein with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">FG</xref> repeats and is a homolog of NUP214/CAN in humans and Nup159 in yeast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>). In the N-terminal &#x03B2;-propeller domain, LNO1 shares 23% and 14% amino acid sequence identity with NUP214 and Nup159, respectively, and the C-terminal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">FG</xref> repeats of LNO1 show 33% and 30% sequence identity to those of NUP214 and Nup159, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>). We have identified two <italic>lno1</italic> mutant alleles: <italic>lno1-1</italic> and <italic>lno1-2</italic>. <italic>lno1-1</italic> and <italic>lno1-2</italic> had a T-DNA insertion in the second exon (&#x002B;609 bp relative to the transcription start) and in the promoter (&#x2212;187 bp relative to the transcription start), respectively. To examine whether the <italic>lno1</italic> mutant is a knockout allele, we used semiquantitative reverse transcription (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">RT</xref>)-PCR to examine <italic>LNO1</italic> expression in seeds. We found that <italic>lno1-1</italic> was a null allele (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2D</xref>) and homozygous lethal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, B and C</xref>), whereas <italic>lno1-2</italic> was a knockdown allele (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2D</xref>) that had no obvious defect in growth and development (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblI">Table I</xref>). This result indicates that a low expression of the nucleoporin <italic>LNO1</italic> is sufficient to sustain normal embryogenesis and seed development, although <italic>LNO1</italic> is essential.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><italic>LNO1</italic> encodes a nucleoporin protein containing <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">FG</xref> repeats in Arabidopsis. A, Gene structure of <italic>LNO1</italic> and locations of T-DNA insertions in two <italic>lno1</italic> mutant alleles. Boxes represent exons, and lines represent promoter or introns. B, The three domains of the LNO1 protein in Arabidopsis. Numbers represent positions of amino acids in LNO1. C, Protein sequence alignments at the N terminus and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">FG</xref> repeats of Arabidopsis LNO1, human NUP214, and yeast Nup159. The alignment was performed using ClustalW2 and followed by using BOXSHADE 3.21. Identical residues are highlighted in dark gray, and similar residues are highlighted in light gray. D, Expression of <italic>LNO1</italic> in the <italic>lno1-1</italic> and <italic>lno1-2</italic> mutant plants. Two sets of primers were used to examine <italic>LNO1</italic> expression in <italic>lno1-2</italic> and wild-type plants. <italic>ACT</italic>, <italic>ACTIN</italic>; WT, wild type.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_202192_gs_f2" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title><italic>LNO1</italic> Is Important for Embryogenesis</title><p>The seed with homozygous null allele <italic>lno1-1</italic> was aborted before seed maturation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, B and C</xref>), but it appeared the same as the wild-type seed before 6 d after pollination (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>) by regular light microscopy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>). To examine whether <italic>lno1-1</italic> had any defects in early embryogenesis, we cleared the seed and observed that 47% (<italic>n</italic> &#x003D; 121) of the putative homozygous <italic>lno1-1/lno1-1</italic> embryos developed abnormally. As described below, these homozygous <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant embryos displayed a variety of developmental abnormalities that were consistently observed.</p><p>Abnormalities in the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant embryos were first detected during the first zygotic division. At 1 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>, the wild-type zygote usually elongates and divides asymmetrically to give rise to a small apical cell and a large basal cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). However, we observed that <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant zygotes divided almost symmetrically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3G</xref>). Approximately 31% (<italic>n</italic> &#x003D; 86) of the <italic>lno1-1/lno1-1</italic> embryos had basal cells that failed to elongate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, G and H</xref>) as the wild-type embryos did (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, A and B</xref>). This result shows that the <italic>lno1</italic> mutation affects the earliest stage of embryogenesis in Arabidopsis. In wild-type embryos, the basal cell elongates and divides transversely to form a suspensor with seven to nine cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, C and D</xref>), and longitudinal divisions do not occur in suspensors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, C and D</xref>). By contrast, longitudinal cell divisions in the basal cell lineage were detected in approximately 36% (<italic>n</italic> &#x003D; 117) of the <italic>lno1-1/lno1-1</italic> embryos at 3 to 4 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, I and J</xref>). In wild-type embryos, there is a clear boundary between the spherical proembryo and the linear file of suspensor cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, C and D</xref>) at 3 to 4 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>. The hypophysis, the uppermost cell of the basal lineage, becomes prominent at 4 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3D</xref>). This clear demarcation between embryo and suspensor was often not detected in the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant embryos because of many longitudinal cell divisions in the suspensor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, I and J</xref>). These results indicate that mutations in <italic>LNO1</italic> can make the basal cell assume an embryonic cell fate that divides longitudinally.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>The <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutation affects suspensor and embryo proper development. A to L, Nomarski photographs of wild-type (WT) and homozygous <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant embryos at 1 to 6 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>. A to F show photographs of the wild type at 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>, respectively, and outline drawings of individual embryos immediately below the embryo; G to L show the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant embryos at 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>, respectively, and outline drawings of individual embryos immediately below the embryo. Small circles inside the cells represent nuclei in the drawings for A, B, G, and H. Photographs A to C and G to I are on the same scale, and photographs D to F and J to L are on the same scale. Arrowheads indicate the plane of the first zygotic cell division in A and G and the boundary between the apical and basal lineage-derived cells in B to F and H to L. Bars &#x003D; 20 &#x03BC;m in A and 50 &#x03BC;m in F.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_202192_gs_f3" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Abnormalities in number and planes of cell division persisted throughout embryogenesis in the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant. In wild-type Arabidopsis, the embryo passes through a series of stages that are defined morphologically as globular, transition, and heart stages at 4 to 6 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, D&#x2013;F</xref>), but in the abnormal <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant, the typical embryo morphology was not observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, J&#x2013;L</xref>). At the transition and early heart stages of wild-type embryos, two symmetrical cotyledons are initiated from lateral domains of the embryo and an embryonic shoot apical meristem is differentiated from the medial domain between the two cotyledons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3F</xref>; Berleth and Chatfield, 2002; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Prigge et al., 2005</xref>). Approximately 19% (<italic>n</italic> &#x003D; 58) of <italic>lno1-1/lno1-1</italic> embryos failed to differentiate two cotyledons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, K and L</xref>). Mutant embryos having one cotyledon also lacked a medial domain where the embryonic shoot meristem could be generated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, K and L</xref>). In summary, these results indicate that the knockout <italic>lno1</italic> mutation alters the number and planes of cell divisions required for generating the normal embryo proper and suspensor, apical-basal axis, cotyledons, and meristem.</p><p>To examine whether the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant allele has any parent-of-origin effects on embryogenesis, we crossed the heterozygous <italic>LNO1/lno1-1</italic> female plants with wild-type (<italic>LNO1/LNO1</italic>) male plants and examined 271, 254, 423, and 316 embryos at 2, 3, 5, and 10 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>, respectively, but we did not find any abnormal mutant embryos. In the reciprocal cross (<italic>LNO1/LNO1</italic> &#x00D7; <italic>LNO1/lno1-1</italic>), we examined 246, 168, 374, and 281 embryos at 2, 3, 5, and 10 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>, respectively, but we did not observe any abnormal mutant embryos either. This result showed that both the maternal and paternal mutant alleles are required for producing the abnormal embryo phenotype and that mutations in <italic>LNO1</italic> do not have any detectable parent-of-origin effects on embryogenesis.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>LNO1</italic> Is Highly Expressed in Reproductive Tissues</title><p>To obtain a preliminary overview of the microarray expression data, we searched a database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.genevestigator.com/gv/">https://www.genevestigator.com/gv/</ext-link>) and found that <italic>LNO1</italic> has very low expression in all the tissues examined except sperm cells. To examine the expression of <italic>LNO1</italic> in Arabidopsis, we fused the <italic>LNO1</italic> promoter with the reporter gene <italic>GUS</italic> (<italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic>) and examined the temporal and spatial expression patterns of the transgene in Arabidopsis. We did not detect expression of the transgene <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> in any vegetative tissues, such as leaves, shoots, stems, or roots, although we employed several GUS staining protocols as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Debrouwe and De Block, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Sessions et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Luo et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Yu et al., 2005</xref>). However, we were able to observe expression of the transgene <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> in reproductive tissues, such as flowers and early developing seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). We examined more than 70 flowers from seven independent transgenic lines and observed a consistent expression pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, A and B</xref>). When we dissected out the flowers, we found that <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> was expressed in anthers but not in other floral organs before flower stage 11 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, C&#x2013;F</xref>). The <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> transgene was not detected in early flower buds at stages 1 to 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, A and B</xref>), then started to express in flower buds at stages 6 and 7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, A and B</xref>), reached the highest expression in flower buds at stages 8 and 9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>), had reduced expression in flowers at stages 10 and 11 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4, D and E</xref>), and was almost undetected in its expression in flowers at stage 12 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4F</xref>). Interestingly, when flowers reached stage 13, <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> was specifically expressed in stigma papilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4G</xref>) and reached its highest expression in the stage 14 flower (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4H</xref>). We further checked the expression of <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> in the developing seed and observed that the transgene was expressed in both embryo and endosperm as early as 2 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4I</xref>), continually expressed at 3 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4J</xref>), and reached its highest expression at 4 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> in embryo and endosperm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4K</xref>). Then, its expression decreased, but it could still be detected at the outer layer cells of the embryo proper at the transition stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4L</xref>). In short, the temporal and spatial expression patterns of the <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> transgene are correlated with its functions in reproductive development in Arabidopsis.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Temporal and spatial expression of <italic>LNO1</italic> in Arabidopsis. A to L, Expression of the transgene <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> in Arabidopsis reproductive tissues. A and B, Vertical views of the apex of floral buds (stages 1&#x2013;12) of the transgenic plant. C and D, Side views of floral buds at stages 9 and 10, respectively, with sepals and petals dissected away. E to H, Side views of floral buds at stages 11, 12, 13, and 14, respectively, with sepals removed. I to L, Seed photographs of the <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> transgenic plant after GUS staining at 2, 3, 4, and 6 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>, respectively. EM, Embryo; EN, endosperm; EP, embryo proper; S, suspensor. Arrowheads indicate locations of GUS expression. M, Temporal and spatial expression of <italic>LNO1</italic> examined by quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">RT</xref>-PCR in Arabidopsis. The mean relative expression levels from three independent replicates for a sample are shown. Error bars indicate <sc>sd</sc>. Lane 1, 4-d-old seedlings; lane 2, 7-d-old seedlings; lane 3, 14-d-old seedlings; lane 4, 21-d-old plants; lane 5, rosette leaves; lane 6, cauline leaves; lane 7, flower buds at flower stages 1 to 4; lane 8, flower buds at flower stages 7 to 11; lane 9, stamens at flower stages 10 and 11; lane 10, carpels at flower stage 12; lane 11, embryo at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>; lane 12, endosperm at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_202192_wc_f4" alt-version="no"/></fig><p>Although we tried several GUS staining protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Debrouwe and De Block, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Sessions et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Luo et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Yu et al., 2005</xref>) and also modified some parameters, we were not able to detect any expression of the <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> transgene in vegetative tissues. To examine whether <italic>LNO1</italic> was expressed in vegetative tissues, we employed more sensitive quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">RT</xref>-PCR to examine <italic>LNO1</italic> temporal and spatial expression. We found that <italic>LNO1</italic> was expressed in all the tissues we examined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4M</xref>). We could detect the expression of <italic>LNO1</italic> in young seedlings (4-, 7-, and 14-d-old seedlings), mature plants (21-d-old plants), and rosette and cauline leaves. Expression of <italic>LNO1</italic> was relatively low in very early stage flowers (stage 1&#x2013;4 flowers) but was increased in later stages (stage 7&#x2013;11 flowers). <italic>LNO1</italic> was also expressed in stamens during flower stages 10 and 11, carpels at flower stage 12, and embryo and endosperm at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>. This quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">RT</xref>-PCR result is consistent with the expression pattern of the <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> transgene (high expression in flowers at flower stages 8 and 9) but also shows that <italic>LNO1</italic> expression was detected in the tissues where expression of the transgene <italic>LNO1 promoter</italic>:<italic>GUS</italic> was not detected.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>LNO1</italic> Can Complement the Temperature-Sensitive Yeast Mutant <italic>nup159</italic></title><p>Nup159, a homolog of Arabidopsis LNO1, has been well studied in yeast. The crystal structure shows that the N terminus of Nup159 forms an asymmetric seven-bladed &#x03B2;-propeller that is conserved in eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Weirich et al., 2004</xref>). The yeast mutant <italic>nup159<sup>&#x0394;1-456</sup></italic>, which has a deletion of the entire N-terminal domain and part of the central domain, has growth defects and is not able to grow at 37&#x00B0;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Del Priore et al., 1997</xref>). The mutant <italic>nup159<sup>VI&#x2192;EE</sup></italic> has also been shown to be temperature sensitive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Weirich et al., 2004</xref>). To test whether <italic>LNO1</italic> can functionally complement the growth defects in the yeast mutant, we cloned the Arabidopsis <italic>LNO1</italic> full-length complementary DNA (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">cDNA</xref>) into the yeast expression vector pAS1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Durfee et al., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Wang et al., 2005</xref>) and transformed the construct into the yeast mutants <italic>nup159<sup>&#x0394;1-456</sup></italic> and <italic>nup159<sup>VI&#x2192;EE</sup></italic>. Both mutants (<italic>nup159<sup>&#x0394;1-456</sup></italic> and <italic>nup159<sup>VI&#x2192;EE</sup></italic>) with the <italic>LNO1</italic> construct (<italic>pAS1-LNO1</italic>) grew well at the nonpermissive temperature (37&#x00B0;C; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). We further did the complementation experiment by using the N-terminal domain of LNO1 (<italic>pAS1-NTD</italic>) alone or LNO1 sequence with deletion of NTD (<italic>pAS1-LNO1<sup>&#x0394;NTD</sup></italic>). The result showed that neither of the constructs can complement the growth defect of <italic>nup159</italic> at the nonpermissive temperature (37&#x00B0;C; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). These results demonstrate that the full-length <italic>LNO1</italic> can functionally complement the growth defects of the yeast mutant <italic>nup159</italic> with the N-terminal deletion or mutations at residues Val-323 and Ile-326 but not the N-terminal or C-terminal domain of LNO1 by itself. These experiments suggest that LNO1 is a functionally conserved nucleoporin in eukaryotes.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>LNO1 functions as a nucleoporin protein in Arabidopsis. <italic>LNO1</italic> can functionally complement the defect in the yeast mutant <italic>nup159.</italic> The full-length <italic>LNO1</italic>, the N-terminal domain (<italic>NTD</italic>), and <italic>LNO1</italic> without the N-terminal domain (<italic>LNO1<sup>&#x0394;NTD</sup></italic>) were cloned into the vector pAS1 and transformed into the <italic>nup159<sup>&#x0394;1-456</sup></italic> and <italic>nup159<sup>VI&#x2192;EE</sup></italic> mutants. Yeast cultures were serially diluted (10&#x00D7;, 20&#x00D7;, 100&#x00D7;, 200&#x00D7;, 1,000&#x00D7;, and 2,000&#x00D7;) and spotted on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">YPD</xref> plates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_202192_gs_f5" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title>LNO1 Interacts with the DEAD-Box Helicase/ATPase LOS4</title><p>The yeast Nup159, localized to the cytoplasmic side of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref>, plays a critical role in exporting mRNA from the nucleus to the cytoplasm. The N terminus of Nup159 forms a &#x03B2;-propeller, which mediates protein-protein interaction, and recruits Dbp5, which functions in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">mRNP</xref> export (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Hodge et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Schmitt et al., 1999</xref>). The N-terminal domain of the human nucleoporin NUP214 has also been shown to interact with the DEAD-box RNA helicase Ddx19 in the crystal structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Napetschnig et al., 2009</xref>). We searched the database and found an Arabidopsis protein called LOS4 sharing high homology with the yeast Dbp5 and human Ddx19 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Gong et al., 2005</xref>). To examine whether LNO1 can interact with LOS4, we cloned the N-terminal domain, full-length, and C-terminal domain of <italic>LNO1</italic> with the <italic>Gal4</italic> DNA activation domain in pACT2 (<italic>pACT2-NTD</italic>, -<italic>LNO1</italic>, and -<italic>LNO1<sup>&#x0394;NTD</sup></italic>, respectively), fused <italic>LOS4</italic> with the <italic>Gal4</italic> DNA-binding domain in pAS1 (<italic>pAS1-LOS4</italic>), and examined the fusion protein interaction in a yeast two-hybrid assay. The result showed that the N-terminal domain and full-length LNO1 interacted with RNA helicase LOS4 in yeast, but the C-terminal domain of LNO1 alone (LNO1<sup>&#x0394;NTD</sup>) did not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). When we swapped the <italic>Gal4</italic> DNA-binding domain with the <italic>Gal4</italic> DNA activation domain in the yeast two-hybrid constructs, we obtained the same result as that shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202192/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>): the N-terminal domain and full-length LNO1 specifically interact with RNA helicase LOS4. This result implies that LNO1 is part of the mRNA export machinery in nucleocytoplasmic transport across the nuclear membrane in eukaryotes.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>LNO1 interacts with Arabidopsis DEAD-box helicase/ATPase and LOS4 in yeast two-hybrid assays. The N-terminal domain of LNO1 (NTD), full-length LNO1, and LNO1 with deletion of NTD (LNO1<sup>&#x0394;NTD</sup>) were fused with the GAL4 DNA activation domain (AD), and LOS4 was fused with the GAL4 DNA binding domain (BD). <italic>pACT2</italic> (<italic>AD</italic>) and <italic>pAS1</italic> (<italic>BD</italic>) empty vectors were included as negative controls. Yeast transformants were spotted on synthetic dropout plates without Leu (L) and Trp (W) or without Leu, Trp, and His (H) and with 20 m<sc>m</sc> 3-aminotriazole (3-AT). The 5-bromo-4-chloro-indolyl-&#x03B2;-<sc>d</sc>-galactopyranoside filter-lift assay was as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Rea et al., 2012</xref>). Yeast cultures were serially diluted (10&#x00D7;, 100&#x00D7;, and 1,000&#x00D7;). [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_202192_wc_f6" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec><sec><title><italic>AtGLE1</italic> Is Also Critical for Seed Viability</title><p>Nup159 functions together with other nucleoporins including Gle1 in exporting mRNAs from the nucleus to the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Alc&#x00E1;zar-Rom&#x00E1;n et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Noble et al., 2011</xref>). It has been reported that there is a homolog of the yeast <italic>Gle1</italic> in Arabidopsis, <italic>AtGLE1</italic> (<italic>At1G13120</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tamura et al., 2010</xref>). AtGLE1 is a relatively small protein with 611 amino acids and has a putative coiled-coil domain in the middle and a GLE1 domain in the C terminus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7A</xref>). The GLE1 domain of AtGLE1 shares 17% and 26% amino acid sequence identity with its homolog Gle1 in yeast and HsGle1 in humans, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7B</xref>). To examine if <italic>AtGLE1</italic> is required for seed viability, we searched the Arabidopsis database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.tair.org">www.tair.org</ext-link>) and found a T-DNA insertional line, <italic>CS16088</italic> or <italic>emb1745</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Tzafrir et al., 2004</xref>), and to be consistent with the nomenclature in Arabidopsis, we called the mutant <italic>Atgle1-1</italic>. Through genotyping, we found that there is a T-DNA insertion in the 5&#x2032; untranslated region (16 bp upstream of the translation start codon ATG) in the <italic>Atgle1-1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7C</xref>). We used <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">RT</xref>-PCR to examine <italic>AtGLE1</italic> expression in seeds and showed that the expression of <italic>AtGLE1</italic> was almost not detectable in the <italic>Atgle1</italic> mutant seed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7D</xref>). In self-pollinated heterozygous <italic>AtGLE1/Atgle1-1</italic> plants, we found aborted seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8</xref>). There were 127 aborted seeds among a total of 647 seeds (19.6% seed abortion). The <italic>Atgle1-1</italic> mutant was backcrossed and self-pollinated, and we found that the seed abortion phenotype was cosegregating with the mutant allele in each generation and plant. This result indicates that <italic>AtGLE1</italic>, the Arabidopsis homolog of yeast <italic>Gle1</italic> involved in the same poly(A) mRNA export pathway as <italic>Nup159</italic>, is also pivotal for seed viability in plants.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p><italic>AtGLE1</italic> encodes an Arabidopsis putative homolog of yeast Gle1 and human HsGLE1. A, The two domains of the AtGLE1 protein in Arabidopsis. Numbers represent positions of amino acids in AtGLE1. B, Protein sequence alignment of the Gle1 domain in the C terminus of Arabidopsis AtGLE1, human HsGLE1, and yeast ScGle1. The alignment was performed using ClustalW2 and followed by BOXSHADE 3.21. Identical residues are highlighted in dark gray, and similar residues are highlighted in light gray. C, Gene structure of <italic>AtGLE1</italic> and location of T-DNA insertion in the <italic>Atgle1-1</italic> mutant (16 bp upstream of the ATG start codon). D, Expression of <italic>AtGLE1</italic> in the <italic>Atgle1-1</italic> mutant and wild-type plants. <italic>ACT</italic>, <italic>ACTIN</italic>; WT, wild type. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_202192_wc_f7" alt-version="no"/></fig><fig id="fig8" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Effect of the <italic>Atgle1-1</italic> mutation on seed viability in Arabidopsis. Wild-type (<italic>AtGLE1/AtGLE1</italic>) and heterozygous (<italic>AtGLE1/Atgle1-1</italic>) siliques were dissected and photographed at 6 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> (A) and 18 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> (B). Brown and green seeds in the silique on the right in B were aborted and viable seeds, respectively. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PP_202192_wc_f8" alt-version="no"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> are important structures on the nuclear envelope that mediate trafficking between the nucleus and the cytoplasm. Nucleoporins participate in forming the nuclear pore structure and in nucleocytoplasmic transport. Genetic and biochemical evidence has shown that mutations in nucleoporins affect the structure of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> and the nuclear envelope (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Doye and Hurt, 1997</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPCs</xref> can also affect growth and development. In <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>, 17 out of 20 nucleoporins are required for embryonic development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Galy et al., 2003</xref>). The <italic>C. elegans</italic> homologs of vertebrate Nup93 and Nup205 were found to be essential for normal <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> distribution in the nuclear envelope in vivo and for cell viability, and depletion of Nup93 or Nup205 caused defects in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> exclusion, abnormal chromatin condensation, and early embryonic arrest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Galy et al., 2003</xref>). In mice, <italic>NUP214</italic> is required for embryonic stem cell and embryo viability, and the <italic>nup214</italic>&#x2212;/&#x2212; null embryos die in utero between 4.0 and 4.5 d post coitum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">van Deursen et al., 1996</xref>). However, its yeast homolog <italic>Nup159</italic> is not essential: null mutant <italic>nup159</italic> can grow at permissive temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Weirich et al., 2004</xref>). Here, we show that <italic>LNO1</italic>, a homolog of <italic>NUP214</italic>, is essential for embryogenesis and seed viability in plants. The <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutation can affect cell divisions and pattern formation in early embryogenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). Approximately 47% of the homozygous <italic>lno1-1</italic>/<italic>lno1-1</italic> embryos showed abnormal cell division and pattern formation in early embryogenesis, but more than half of the <italic>lno1-1/lno1-1</italic> embryos could continue to develop without obvious morphologic defects to certain levels. There are no other genes showing high homology with <italic>LNO1</italic> in Arabidopsis, so it is not clear why more than 50% of the null <italic>lno1-1/lno1-1</italic> embryos could continue to develop until the heart or torpedo stage during early embryogenesis and then abort at a late stage. One possibility is that <italic>LNO1</italic> plays a role in normal endosperm development in Arabidopsis. Since <italic>LNO1</italic> was expressed in early endosperm tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>), mutations in <italic>LNO1</italic> might affect normal endosperm development in Arabidopsis, thus leading to late-stage seed abortion of those normal-looking <italic>lno1-1/lno1-1</italic> embryos at an earlier stage. Alternatively, <italic>LNO1</italic> is required for mRNA export, and mutations in <italic>LNO1</italic> might abolish the export of mRNA of many essential genes in embryogenesis from the nucleus to the cytosol, thus causing seed abortion in all the <italic>lno1-1/lno1-1</italic> embryos at the late stage.</p><p>The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> consists of approximately 30 nucleoporins in eukaryotic cells. The nucleoporin CAN/NUP214 was originally found to be a putative oncogene product associated with myeloid leukemogenesis and is localized to the cytoplasmic side of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Kraemer et al., 1994</xref>). However, in cells overexpressing NUP214, NUP214 can bind to both the cytoplasmic and the nucleoplasmic sides of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Boer et al., 1997</xref>). NUP214 plays a role in nuclear protein import, mRNA export, and cell cycle progression and interacts with DDX19 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Napetschnig et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">von Moeller et al., 2009</xref>). In yeast, the nucleoporins Nup159 and Gle1 are both localized to the cytoplasmic side of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> and function in the same pathway in exporting mRNA. The N-terminal domain of Nup159 forms a &#x03B2;-propeller that functions in mRNA export by tethering the shuttling helicase Dbp5 at the nuclear periphery and locally concentrating this mRNA-remodeling factor at the cytoplasmic face of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Weirich et al., 2004</xref>). Nup159 and Nup82 form a cytoplasmically oriented subcomplex of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> that is essential for RNA export but not for classical nuclear localization sequence-mediated nuclear protein import (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Hurwitz et al., 1998</xref>). LNO1 (AtNUP214) is an Arabidopsis homolog of human NUP214 and yeast Nup159. AtNUP214 was localized to the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">NPC</xref> in the root tip cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Tamura et al., 2010</xref>). We showed that LNO1 complemented the yeast temperature-sensitive mutant <italic>nup159</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). LOS4, a homolog of ATPase DDX19 in human and Dbp5 in yeast, was shown to function in mRNA export in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Gong et al., 2005</xref>), and we showed that LOS4 interacts with LNO1 in yeast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). Furthermore, the Gle1 homolog, AtGLE1, is also required for seed viability in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figs. 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">8</xref>). These results suggest that LNO1 (AtNUP214), LOS4, AtGLE1, and perhaps other plant nucleoporins might form a functionally conserved pathway as those in human and yeast, which plays an essential role in nuclear and cytoplasmic trafficking in plants.</p><p>Patterning formation in early embryogenesis is regulated by auxin gradients and other signaling pathways. Interestingly, <italic>SUPPRESSOR OF AUXIN RESISTANCE1</italic> (<italic>SAR1</italic>) and <italic>SAR3</italic>, encoding nucleoporins NUP160 and NUP96, respectively, are involved in hormone auxin signaling and development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Parry et al., 2006</xref>). The defects in the mutant <italic>lno1</italic> are similar to those embryogenesis mutants in the auxin signaling pathway. One possibility is that <italic>LNO1</italic> as a nucleoporin might interact with other signaling pathways and regulate embryogenesis (e.g. the auxin signaling) or, at least in part, <italic>LNO1</italic> can affect the transport of mRNAs of components of those signaling pathways involved in early embryogenesis, thus affecting early pattern formation. Since the homozygous <italic>lno1-1/lno1-1</italic> seed is not viable, we are not able to examine the role of <italic>LNO1</italic> at the seedling stage or in mature plants. Thus, it is possible that <italic>LNO1</italic> can be an essential gene throughout the whole life cycle of plants. We expect that further biochemical characterization of LNO1 and genetic study will reveal its function in signal transduction or transporting other signaling components in early embryogenesis and perhaps in other developmental processes in plants.</p></sec><sec id="s10" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s11"><title>Plant Materials and Growth Conditions</title><p>We took a genetic approach to identify mutants that affect seed development or embryogenesis in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>). We performed a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">cDNA</xref> microarray using the F1 seed of the DNA methyltransferase <italic>met1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Xiao et al., 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">2006</xref>) crossed with wild-type ecotype Columbia (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Col-0</xref>) and a control wild-type cross and found over 1,300 genes that had altered expression in the <italic>met1</italic> mutant cross compared with the wild type (W. Xiao, C. Braud, and W. Zhang, unpublished data). We then chose 116 putative genes that affect embryogenesis, seed development, epigenetics, transcription, translation, or chromatin remodeling based on annotations in The Arabidopsis Information Resource, and there were putative T-DNA insertional mutants available for these genes at the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center. <italic>lno1-1</italic> is one of the mutants that we obtained and characterized in this screen. We have ordered all available putative T-DNA insertional lines (CS16007, CS423371, CS804562, CS810290, CS810299, CS813163, CS813171, CS842534, CS 842651, SALK_037979, SALK_108182, and SALK_108189) in the <italic>LNO1</italic> locus (<italic>At1G55540</italic>). However, we were only able to genotype and find T-DNA insertion in the <italic>At1G55540</italic> locus in two lines: CS810299 (<italic>lno1-1</italic>) and CS842651 (<italic>lno1-2</italic>). CS16007 was identified as emb1011-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Tzafrir et al., 2004</xref>), but it was later withdrawn from the database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.seedgenes.org">www.seedgenes.org</ext-link>). The T-DNA insertion in <italic>lno1-1</italic> (CS810299) was detected in the second exon by amplifying a PCR fragment with the following primers: forward primer, 5&#x2032;-CGGAAAGAAGGAGAACGACG-3&#x2032;, and LB3, 5&#x2032;-TAGCATCTGAATTTCATAACCAATCTC-3&#x2032;. The T-DNA insertion in <italic>lno1-2</italic> (CS842651) was detected in the promoter by amplifying a PCR fragment with two primers: 5&#x2032;-CAGTCTTCATCGGAATCACC-3&#x2032; and LB3 (see above). Once T-DNA insertions were found in a plant, PCR amplification was used to determine homozygosity by amplifying an endogenous gene fragment across the T-DNA insertion. An endogenous fragment was amplified in <italic>lno1-1</italic> with the following primers: forward, 5&#x2032;-TACGATCTCGAAAACCCTCC-3&#x2032;, and reverse, 5&#x2032;-CAGTCTTCATCGGAATCACC-3&#x2032;, and in <italic>lno1-2</italic> with the following primers: forward, 5&#x2032;-CGAAGCTTCCTTGTATCGTCCTTTGTAGG-3&#x2032;, and reverse, 5&#x2032;-CGTCTAGACTTTCAAACTCTTCTCAAGGT-3&#x2032;. By using the same approach, we found a T-DNA insertion in the 5&#x2032; untranslated region and 14 bp upstream of ATG in <italic>Atgle1-1</italic> (CS16088, emb1745) by amplifying a PCR fragment with two primers: 5&#x2032;-GTCTGGTTTGGTTCGTGATT-3&#x2032; and LB1, 5&#x2032;-GCCTTTTCAGAAATGGATAAATAGCC-3&#x2032;. Arabidopsis plants were grown in growth chambers or a greenhouse under 16 h of light and 8 h of dark at 23&#x00B0;C.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Complementation Assay for the <italic>lon1-1</italic> Mutant</title><p>The full-length coding region of <italic>LNO1</italic> was amplified by PCR using forward primer 5&#x2032;-CGC<underline>TCTAGA</underline>ATGAGCAGAGTTGAGATTGAAGAA-3&#x2032; (<italic>Xba</italic>I site underlined) and reverse primer 5&#x2032;-CGC<underline>GAGCTC</underline>TCATTTTCTCATCTGTGTGAAGAG-3&#x2032; (<italic>Sac</italic>I site underlined) and cloned into pBI121 vector (Clontech). The resulting construct was transformed into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain GV3101 and infiltrated into the <italic>LON1</italic>/<italic>lon1-1</italic> heterozygous plants by floral dipping. Positive transformants were selected based on their resistance to kanamycin on Murashige and Skoog medium, and the transgenic plants in the <italic>lon1-1</italic> mutant background were chosen for analysis of seed viability.</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Whole-Mount Seed Clearing and Microscopy</title><p>Whole-mount immature seeds were dissected from siliques 1 to 6 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref>, cleared in Hoyer&#x2019;s fluid (70% (w/v) chloral hydrate, 4% (v/v) glycerol, and 5% (v/v) gum arabic), and observed with a Zeiss Axioskop 50 microscope using differential interference contrast optics in the Department of Pathology of the Medical School at Saint Louis University.</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Gene Expression Analysis</title><p>For examining the expression of <italic>LNO1</italic> in the <italic>lno1-1</italic> mutant allele, viable (LNO1/LNO1) and aborted (<italic>lno1-1/lno1-1</italic>) seeds at 10 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> from the heterozygous <italic>LNO1/lno1-1</italic> plants were isolated, and total RNA was extracted. For examining the expression of <italic>LNO1</italic> in the <italic>lno1-2</italic> mutant allele, seeds of wild-type (<italic>LNO1/LNO1</italic>) and homozygous mutant (<italic>lno1-2/lno1-2</italic>) seeds at 10 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">DAP</xref> were isolated, and total RNA was extracted. Gene expression was examined by using semiquantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">RT</xref>-PCR using 28 to 30 PCR amplification cycles or quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">RT</xref>-PCR. First-strand <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">cDNA</xref> was synthesized using the ProtoScript First Strand <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">cDNA</xref> Synthesis Kit (New England Biolabs). PCR product was amplified using SABiosciences&#x2019; SYBR Green qPCR Mastermix, and <italic>ACTIN</italic> was used as an internal control. Quantitative <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">RT</xref>-PCR was performed using MJ Research PTC-200 Thermal Cycler and MJ Opticon Monitor Analysis Software (Bio-Rad). The primer pairs for amplifying <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">cDNA</xref> of <italic>LNO1</italic> were as follows: forward 9, 5&#x2032;-TACGATCTCGAAAACCCTCC-3&#x2032;, and reverse 8, 5&#x2032;-CAGTCTTCATCGGAATCACC-3&#x2032;. The second set of primer pairs for amplifying <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">cDNA</xref> of <italic>LNO1</italic> were as follows: forward 4, 5&#x2032;-GGATGCTTCTGCAGGAGCAA-3&#x2032;, and reverse 3, 5&#x2032;-GAGGCCTGATCAGATGACACTTGC-3&#x2032;. The primer pairs for amplifying <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">cDNA</xref> of <italic>AtGLE1</italic> were as follows: forward 3, 5&#x2032;-CCTATGAGTGAACCAAATTGT-3&#x2032;, and reverse 3, 5&#x2032;-AAGGAGGTTCCAAAACAATCC-3&#x2032;.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>The <italic>LNO1</italic> Promoter:GUS Construct and GUS Histochemical Staining</title><p>The 5&#x2032; promoter region of <italic>LNO1</italic> was PCR amplified with forward primer 5&#x2032;-CGCG<underline>TCGACC</underline>TAAACAATGGAGACAATAA-3&#x2032;, containing a <italic>Sal</italic>I restriction site, and reverse primer 5&#x2032;-CGC<underline>GGATCC</underline>GATGAGCCGACGACGGTTCA-3&#x2032;, containing a <italic>Bam</italic>HI restriction site, and cloned into the binary vector pBI101. The construct was confirmed by sequencing, transformed into <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strain GV3101, and infiltrated into <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">Col-0</xref>. Stable transgenic T2 plants were used for GUS staining analysis. GUS staining was performed as described with minor modifications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">Stangeland and Salehian, 2002</xref>). In short, plant tissues were harvested and immersed into the GUS staining buffer (10 m<sc>m</sc> sodium phosphate buffer, pH 7.2, 0.5% Triton X-100, 1 mg mL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl-&#x03B2;-glucuronic acid, and 2 m<sc>m</sc> potassium ferricyanide) on ice. Samples in the staining buffer were vacuum infiltrated on ice for 20 min and then incubated at 37&#x00B0;C with rotation for 24 h. Tissues were destained using 70% ethanol. Samples were imbibed in 50% glycerol on slides for imaging.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Yeast Two-Hybrid Assay</title><p>Yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) two-hybrid experiments were performed using the system described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Rea et al., 2012</xref>). To make Gal4 DNA activation domain (AD) constructs, the full-length <italic>LNO1</italic> was PCR amplified with primers LON1-ADF (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>GATATC</underline>GATGAGCAGAGTTGAGATTGAAGAA-3&#x2032;; <italic>Eco</italic>RV site underlined) and LON1-ADR (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>GTCGAC</underline>TCATTTTCTCATCTGTGTGAAGAG-3&#x2032;; <italic>Sal</italic>I site underlined) and inserted into pACT2 vector digested with <italic>Sma</italic>I and <italic>Xho</italic>I; the LNO1 N-terminal domain (1&#x2013;761 amino acids; NTD) coding region was PCR amplified with primers LNO1-NTD-ADF (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>GGATCC</underline>GAATGAGCAGAGTTGAGATTGAAGAA-3&#x2032;; <italic>Bam</italic>HI site underlined) and LNO1-NTD-ADR (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>GTCGAC</underline>TCATATAAACGCGCAAGAATCCTT-3&#x2032;; <italic>Sal</italic>I site underlined) and inserted into pACT2 digested with <italic>Bam</italic>HI and <italic>Xho</italic>I; the LNO1<sup>&#x0394;NTD</sup> fragment coding region was PCR amplified with primers LNO1-CCC-ADF (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>GATATC</underline>GCTGAAAAGCAATGTTGAAGAACTG-3&#x2032;; <italic>Eco</italic>RV site underlined) and LON1-ADR and inserted into pACT2 digested with <italic>Sma</italic>I and <italic>Xho</italic>I. For the Gal4 binding domain (BD) constructs, the Arabidopsis <italic>LOS4</italic> coding region was PCR amplified with primers LOS4-BDF (5&#x2032;-CCCGATATCGATGGCGGATACGGTAGAGAAAGTT-3&#x2032;; <italic>Eco</italic>RV site underlined) and LOS4-BDR (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>CTCGAG</underline>TCACTCGTCCAGCAGGCCAGCTTC-3&#x2032;; <italic>Xho</italic>I site underlined) and inserted into pAS1 vector digested with <italic>Sma</italic>I and <italic>Sal</italic>I. Positive transformants were selected on complete minimal (CM) dropout medium minus Trp and Leu. Positive interactions were selected on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">CM</xref> medium minus Trp, Leu, and His containing 20 m<sc>m</sc> 3-aminotriazole and were confirmed by filter lift assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Rea et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>To further confirm the interactions, a vector-swap experiment was performed. The full-length <italic>LNO1</italic> PCR amplified using primers LNO1-BDF (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>CATATG</underline>AGCAGAGTTGAGATTGAAGAA-3&#x2032;; <italic>Nde</italic>I site underlined) and LNO1-BDR (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>GTCGAC</underline>TCATTTTCTCATCTGTGTGAAGAG-3&#x2032;; <italic>Sal</italic>I site underlined), the LNO1-NTD coding region PCR amplified using primers LNO1-BDF and LNO1-NTD-BDR (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>GTCGAC</underline>TCATATAAACGCGCAAGAATCCTT-3&#x2032;; <italic>Sal</italic>I site underlined), and the LNO1<sup>&#x0394;NTD</sup> coding region PCR amplified using primers LNO1-CCC-BDF (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>CATATG</underline>CTGAAAAGCAATGTTGAAGAACTG-3&#x2032;; <italic>Nde</italic>I site underlined) and LNO1-BDR were cloned into pAS1 vector to make <italic>pAS1-LNO1</italic>, <italic>pAS1-NTD</italic>, and <italic>pAS1-LNO1<sup>&#x0394;NTD</sup></italic> constructs, respectively. The Arabidopsis <italic>LOS4</italic> coding region was PCR amplified with primers LOS4-ADF (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>GAATTC</underline>GAATGGCGGATACGGTAGAGAAAGTT-3&#x2032;; <italic>Eco</italic>RI site underlined) and LOS4-ADR (5&#x2032;-CCC<underline>CTCGAG</underline>TCACTCGTCCAGCAGGCCAGCTTC-3&#x2032;; <italic>Xho</italic>I site underlined) and inserted into pACT2 vector to make the <italic>pACT2-LOS4</italic> construct. Positive transformants and positive interactions were tested as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Yeast Complementation Test</title><p>The plasmid DNA of <italic>pAS1-LNO1</italic>, <italic>pAS1-NTD</italic>, or <italic>pAS1-LNO1<sup>&#x0394;NTD</sup></italic> was transformed into the yeast <italic>nup159</italic> mutant strains <italic>KWY1267</italic> (<italic>nup159<sup>&#x0394;1-456</sup></italic>) and <italic>KWY1269</italic> (<italic>nup159<sup>VI&#x2192;EE</sup></italic>). Positive transformants were selected on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">CM</xref> medium minus Trp and Leu. Five microliters of liquid culture in yeast extract peptone dextrose (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">YPD</xref>) medium for each positive transformant was spotted on <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">YPD</xref> plates after serial dilutions. Complementation tests were performed at 37&#x00B0;C (nonpermissive temperature). Control plates were incubated at 23&#x00B0;C for growth.</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.<list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.202192/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> LNO1 interacts with LOS4 in yeast.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank colleagues in the Xiao laboratory for discussion and Robert L. Fischer for critical reading of the manuscript and valuable comments. We thank Paul Smelcer for maintenance of Arabidopsis plants, the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center at Ohio State University for providing seeds, Karsten Weis for providing the yeast temperature-sensitive mutant <italic>nup159</italic>, Jan Ryerse and Barbara Nagel for providing assistance with differential interference contrast microscopy, and Matthew Rea, Brian Downes, and Yuqi Wang for technical assistance and helpful discussions.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Heidstra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Willemsen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Blilou</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Galinha</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nussaume</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The PLETHORA genes mediate patterning of the Arabidopsis root stem cell niche</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>119</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>120</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alc&#x00E1;zar-Rom&#x00E1;n</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wente</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Inositol hexakisphosphate and Gle1 activate the DEAD-box protein Dbp5 for nuclear mRNA export</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>711</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>716</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Autran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Baroux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Raissig</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenormand</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grob</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Steimer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Klostermeier</surname><given-names>UC</given-names></name><name><surname>Leblanc</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Maternal epigenetic pathways control parental contributions to Arabidopsis early embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>707</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>719</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bastos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribas de Pouplana</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Enarson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodoor</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Nup84, a novel nucleoporin that is associated with CAN/Nup214 on the cytoplasmic face of the nuclear pore complex</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>989</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1000</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Giglione</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Galli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinnel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukowitz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Paternal control of embryonic patterning in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>323</volume>: <fpage>1485</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1488</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berleth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The role of the monopteros gene in organising the basal body region of the Arabidopsis embryo</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>575</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>587</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>van Deursen</surname><given-names>JMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Croes</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fransen</surname><given-names>JAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosveld</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The nucleoporin CAN/Nup214 binds to both the cytoplasmic and the nucleoplasmic sides of the nuclear pore complex in overexpressing cells</article-title>. <source>Exp Cell Res</source> <volume>232</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>185</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breuninger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rikirsch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Differential expression of WOX genes mediates apical-basal axis formation in the Arabidopsis embryo</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>867</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>876</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brohawn</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittle</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>TU</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The nuclear pore complex has entered the atomic age</article-title>. <source>Structure</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1156</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1168</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Provart</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Berleth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <comment>Embryogenesis: pattern formation from a single cell. The Arabidopsis Book <bold>7:</bold> e0126, doi/10/1199/tab.0126</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Debrouwe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>De Block</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>In-situ enzyme histochemistry on plastic-embedded plant material: the development of an artefact-free beta-glucuronidase assay</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>266</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Del Priore</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Snay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>MacMillan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorsch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A structure/function analysis of Rat7p/Nup159p, an essential nucleoporin of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>2987</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2999</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A putative Arabidopsis nucleoporin, AtNUP160, is critical for RNA export and required for plant tolerance to cold stress</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>9533</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>9543</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doye</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>From nucleoporins to nuclear pore complexes</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>411</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drews</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumaker</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadegari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Identification of genes expressed in the angiosperm female gametophyte</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>1593</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1599</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dultz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wurzenberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabut</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sironi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Systematic kinetic analysis of mitotic dis- and reassembly of the nuclear pore in living cells</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>180</volume>: <fpage>857</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>865</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durfee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Becherer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilburn</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Elledge</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The retinoblastoma protein associates with the protein phosphatase type 1 catalytic subunit</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>569</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Auxin transport: shaping the plant</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>12</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weijers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Offringa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x00FC;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Efflux-dependent auxin gradients establish the apical-basal axis of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>426</volume>: <fpage>147</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>153</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattaj</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name><name><surname>Askjaer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Caenorhabditis elegans nucleoporins Nup93 and Nup205 determine the limit of nuclear pore complex size exclusion in vivo</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>5104</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5115</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>de Paiva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadegari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Plant embryogenesis: zygote to seed</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>266</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>614</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A DEAD box RNA helicase is essential for mRNA export and important for development and stress responses in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>256</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>267</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorsch</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dockendorff</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>A conditional allele of the novel repeat-containing yeast nucleoporin RAT7/NUP159 causes both rapid cessation of mRNA export and reversible clustering of nuclear pore complexes</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biol</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>939</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>955</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haecker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross-Hardt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiges</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Breuninger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Expression dynamics of WOX genes mark cell fate decisions during early embryonic patterning in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>657</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>668</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x00FC;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The auxin-insensitive bodenlos mutation affects primary root formation and apical-basal patterning in the Arabidopsis embryo</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>1387</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1395</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hetzer</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wente</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Border control at the nucleus: biogenesis and organization of the nuclear membrane and pore complexes</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>606</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>616</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Colot</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name><name><surname>Stafford</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Rat8p/Dbp5p is a shuttling transport factor that interacts with Rat7p/Nup159p and Gle1p and suppresses the mRNA export defect of xpo1-1 cells</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>5778</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5788</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcazar-Roman</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Yishay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarcelli</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Folkmann</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shav-Tal</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wente</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Dbp5 cycle at the nuclear pore complex during mRNA export. I. dbp5 mutants with defects in RNA binding and ATP hydrolysis define key steps for Nup159 and Gle1</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1052</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1064</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkbride</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilberman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Regulation of imprinted gene expression in Arabidopsis endosperm</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>1755</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1762</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Strambio-de-Castillia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Blobel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Two yeast nuclear pore complex proteins involved in mRNA export form a cytoplasmically oriented subcomplex</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>11241</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>11245</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mongkolsiriwatana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Veley</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The nuclear pore protein AtTPR is required for RNA homeostasis, flowering time, and auxin signaling</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>144</volume>: <fpage>1383</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1390</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukowitz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Taking the very first steps: from polarity to axial domains in the early Arabidopsis embryo</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>1687</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1697</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalverda</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickersgill</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shloma</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornerod</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Nucleoporins directly stimulate expression of developmental and cell-cycle genes inside the nucleoplasm</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>140</volume>: <fpage>360</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>371</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanamori</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Radutoiu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Frantescu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Quistgaard</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Downie</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Felle</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Haaning</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A nucleoporin is required for induction of Ca<sup>2&#x002B;</sup> spiking in legume nodule development and essential for rhizobial and fungal symbiosis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>364</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wozniak</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Blobel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Radu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) The human CAN protein, a putative oncogene product associated with myeloid leukemogenesis, is a nuclear pore complex protein that faces the cytoplasm. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <bold>91:</bold> 1519&#x2013;1523</citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Strambio-de-Castillia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Blobel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rout</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The essential yeast nucleoporin NUP159 is located on the cytoplasmic side of the nuclear pore complex and serves in karyopherin-mediated binding of transport substrate</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>19017</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>19021</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagmaister</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Belmonte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkbride</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Global analysis of gene activity during Arabidopsis seed development and identification of seed-specific transcription factors</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>8063</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>8070</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wi</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmit</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Dual functions of Nicotiana benthamiana Rae1 in interphase and mitosis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>278</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>291</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lotan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohto</surname><given-names>M-A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>MAL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamagishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis LEAFY COTYLEDON1 is sufficient to induce embryo development in vegetative cells</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1195</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1205</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukowitz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmenter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A MAPKK kinase gene regulates extra-embryonic cell fate in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>119</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilodeau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Expression and parent-of-origin effects for FIS2, MEA, and FIE in the endosperm and embryo of developing Arabidopsis seeds</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>10637</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>10642</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lupu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Doye</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Nuclear pore composition regulates neural stem/progenitor cell differentiation in the mouse embryo</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>831</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>842</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Brkljacic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Adding pieces to the puzzling plant nuclear envelope</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>752</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>759</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meinke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Muralla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickerman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Identifying essential genes in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>491</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Napetschnig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassube</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Debler</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Blobel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoelz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Structural and functional analysis of the interaction between the nucleoporin Nup214 and the DEAD-box helicase Ddx19</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>3089</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3094</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nawy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mravec</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukowitz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The GATA factor HANABA TARANU is required to position the proembryo boundary in the early Arabidopsis embryo</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>113</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Alc&#x00E1;zar-Rom&#x00E1;n</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wente</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Dbp5 cycle at the nuclear pore complex during mRNA export. II. Nucleotide cycling and mRNP remodeling by Dbp5 are controlled by Nup159 and Gle1</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1065</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1077</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nodine</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Maternal and paternal genomes contribute equally to the transcriptome of early plant embryos</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>482</volume>: <fpage>94</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>97</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nodine</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadegari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tax</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>RPK1 and TOAD2 are two receptor-like kinases redundantly required for Arabidopsis embryonic pattern formation</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>943</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>956</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Onischenko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Nuclear pore complex: a coat specifically tailored for the nuclear envelope</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>301</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cernac</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dharmasiri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Estelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SUPPRESSOR OF AUXIN RESISTANCE proteins are nucleoporins with an important role in hormone signaling and development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1590</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1603</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prigge</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Otsuga</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Drews</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Class III homeodomain-leucine zipper gene family members have overlapping, antagonistic, and distinct roles in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>76</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasala</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Harel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Capture of AT-rich chromatin by ELYS recruits POM121 and NDC1 to initiate nuclear pore assembly</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>3982</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3996</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Braud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhangu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rognan</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Histone H1 affects gene imprinting and DNA methylation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>776</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>786</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Asamizu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Imaizumi-Anraku</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Umehara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>NUCLEOPORIN85 is required for calcium spiking, fungal and bacterial symbioses, and seed production in <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>610</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>624</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Benfey</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Asymmetric cell division in plants</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>505</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>537</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlereth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00F6;ller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kientz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Flipse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rademacher</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x00FC;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Weijers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>MONOPTEROS controls embryonic root initiation by regulating a mobile transcription factor</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>464</volume>: <fpage>913</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>916</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>von Kobbe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pant&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Boscheron</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigaut</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x00E9;raphin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmo-Fonseca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Dbp5, a DEAD-box protein required for mRNA export, is recruited to the cytoplasmic fibrils of nuclear pore complex via a conserved interaction with CAN/Nup159p</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>4332</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>4347</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sessions</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana MERISTEM LAYER 1</italic> promoter specifies epidermal expression in meristems and young primordia</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>263</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stangeland</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salehian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>An improved clearing method for GUS assay in Arabidopsis endosperm and seed</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol Rep</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>114</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strambio-De-Castillia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Niepel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rout</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The nuclear pore complex: bridging nuclear transport and gene regulation</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>490</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>501</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haraguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara-Nishimura</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of nuclear pore complex components in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>4084</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>4097</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara-Nishimura</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Involvement of the nuclear pore complex in morphology of the plant nucleus</article-title>. <source>Nucleus</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>172</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzafrir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pena-Muralla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickerman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>McElver</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Identification of genes required for embryo development in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>1206</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1220</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Deursen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosveld</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>G2 arrest and impaired nucleocytoplasmic transport in mouse embryos lacking the proto-oncogene CAN/Nup214</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>5574</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>5583</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vernon</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinke</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Embryogenic transformation of the suspensor in twin, a polyembryonic mutant of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source> <volume>165</volume>: <fpage>566</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>573</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Lindern</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornerod</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Baal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaegle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Buijs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosveld</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992a</year>) <article-title>The translocation (6;9), associated with a specific subtype of acute myeloid leukemia, results in the fusion of two genes, dek and can, and the expression of a chimeric, leukemia-specific dek-can mRNA</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1687</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1697</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Lindern</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Baal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiegant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raap</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagemeijer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosveld</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992b</year>) <article-title>Can, a putative oncogene associated with myeloid leukemogenesis, may be activated by fusion of its 3&#x2032; half to different genes: characterization of the set gene</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>3346</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>3355</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Moeller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Basquin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The mRNA export protein DBP5 binds RNA and the cytoplasmic nucleoporin NUP214 in a mutually exclusive manner</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>254</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis RWP-RK protein RKD4 triggers gene expression and pattern formation in early embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1277</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1281</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Marotti</surname><given-names>LA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohlman</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Differential regulation of G protein alpha subunit trafficking by mono- and polyubiquitination</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>280</volume>: <fpage>284</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>291</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weijers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meurette</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooykaas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Offringa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Maintenance of embryonic auxin distribution for apical-basal patterning by PIN-FORMED-dependent auxin transport in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>2517</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>2526</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weirich</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Erzberger</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The N-terminal domain of Nup159 forms a beta-propeller that functions in mRNA export by tethering the helicase Dbp5 to the nuclear pore</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>749</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>760</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiermer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Imkampe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipka</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Putative members of the Arabidopsis Nup107-160 nuclear pore sub-complex contribute to pathogen defense</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>796</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>808</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiermer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Germain</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x00ED;a</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Nucleoporin MOS7/Nup88 contributes to plant immunity and nuclear accumulation of defense regulators</article-title>. <source>Nucleus</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>332</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>336</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Custard</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemmon</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>DNA methylation is critical for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> embryogenesis and seed viability</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>805</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>814</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Margossian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennell</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Imprinting of the MEA Polycomb gene is controlled by antagonism between MET1 methyltransferase and DME glycosylase</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>891</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>901</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Muthuswamy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatakrishnan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>NUCLEAR PORE ANCHOR, the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homolog of Tpr/Mlp1/Mlp2/megator, is involved in mRNA export and SUMO homeostasis and affects diverse aspects of plant development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1537</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1548</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundaresan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Analysis of the female gametophyte transcriptome of Arabidopsis by comparative expression profiling</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1853</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1869</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Suspensor-derived polyembryony caused by altered expression of valyl-tRNA synthetase in the twn2 mutant of Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>7349</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>7355</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A putative nucleoporin 96 is required for both basal defense and constitutive resistance responses mediated by <italic>suppressor of npr1-1,constitutive 1</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1306</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>1316</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of the Arabidopsis FG-repeat nucleoporin Nup62</article-title>. <source>Plant Signal Behav</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>330</fpage>&ndash;<lpage>334</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
