<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">242560</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.242560</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Articles</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>GENES, DEVELOPMENT, AND EVOLUTION</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>TRANSLOCASE OF THE INNER MEMBRANE9 and 10 Are Essential for Maintaining Mitochondrial Function during Early Embryo Cell and Endosperm Free Nucleus Divisions in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[C]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4"><sup>[OPEN]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Yingtian</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Wenxuan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Gang</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">State Key Laboratory of Hybrid Rice, College of Life Sciences, Wuhan University, Wuhan 430072, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.114.242560">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.114.242560</ext-link></p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Address correspondence to <email>jzhao@whu.edu.cn</email>.</corresp><fn id="afn1"><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Jie Zhao (<email>jzhao@whu.edu.cn</email>).</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>08</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>166</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>868</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>05</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>08</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#xa9; 2014 American Society of Plant Biologists. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p/></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="PP_242560_ic1.gif"/><self-uri content-type="alt-lang-pdf zh" xlink:href="853.chinese.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><italic>Two mitochondrial translocases are essential for the division during early embryo and endosperm development in Arabidopsis</italic>.</p></abstract><abstract><p>In the life cycle of flowering plants, the sporophytic generation takes up most of the time and plays a dominant role in influencing plant growth and development. The embryo cell and endosperm free nucleus divisions establish the critical initiation phase of early sporophyte development, which forms mature seeds through a series of cell growth and differentiation events. Here, we report on the biological functions of two Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) mitochondrial proteins, TRANSLOCASE OF THE INNER MEMBRANE9 (TIM9) and TIM10. We found that dysfunction of either <italic>AtTIM9</italic> or <italic>AtTIM10</italic> led to an early sporophyte-lethal phenotype; the embryo and endosperm both arrest division when the embryo proper developed to 16 to 32 cells. The abortion of <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> embryos at the 16/32-cell stage was caused by the loss of cell viability and the cessation of division in the embryo proper region, and this inactivation was due to the collapse of the mitochondrial structure and activity. Our characterization of <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> showed that mitochondrial membrane permeability increased and that cytochrome <italic>c</italic> was released from mitochondria into the cytoplasm in the 16/32-cell embryo proper, indicating that mitochondrial dysfunction occurred in the early sporophytic cells, and thus caused the initiation of a necrosis-like programmed cell death, which was further proved by the evidence of reactive oxygen species and DNA fragmentation tests. Consequently, we verified that AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 are nonredundantly essential for maintaining the mitochondrial function of early embryo proper cells and endosperm-free nuclei; these proteins play critically important roles during sporophyte initiation and development in Arabidopsis.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">IMS</term><def id="def1"><p>intermembrane space</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">PCD</term><def id="def2"><p>programmed cell death</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">T-DNA</term><def id="def3"><p>transfer DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">DAP</term><def id="def4"><p>days after pollination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">FDA</term><def id="def5"><p>fluorescein diacetate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">PI</term><def id="def6"><p>propidium iodide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">MMP</term><def id="def7"><p>mitochondrial membrane permeability</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8">ROS</term><def id="def8"><p>reactive oxygen species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9">BiFC</term><def id="def9"><p>bimolecular fluorescence complementation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></term><def id="def10"><p>cytochrome <italic>c</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term11">DIC</term><def id="def11"><p>differential interference contrast</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>Land plants have a remarkable life cycle that alternates between two distinct multicellular generations, the reduced gametophytes and the dominant sporophyte. The male and female gametophytes represent the gametophytic generation that alternates with the sporophytic generation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Kenrick and Crane, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Niklas and Kutschera, 2010</xref>). In Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), the sporophytic generation originates from the embryo and endosperm that are generated in the ovule after double fertilization. The embryo follows a predictable sequence of cell division and differentiation and develops from a zygote to a mature seed during embryogenesis. The endosperm grows rapidly as the syncytium and cellularizes, nourishing the developing embryo and determining the ovule size, and then disintegrates during the late stages of embryo development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Grossniklaus and Schneitz, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Berger et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Jenik et al., 2007</xref>).</p><p>Mitochondria play roles in a variety of fundamental and essential functions during the plant life cycle, including early sporophyte development. This has been confirmed through the identification of mitochondrial proteins with specific roles during Arabidopsis embryo and endosperm division (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Millar et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Hsu et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Law et al., 2012</xref>). These processes are regulated by a large number of different mitochondrial proteins, and about 99% of these are encoded by nuclear DNA, synthesized in the cytosol, and imported into the mitochondria across one or both membranes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Burger et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Elo et al., 2003</xref>). The mitochondrial protein import mechanism plays an important role in protein importation, including the TOM (for translocase of the outer membrane) complex and the TIM (for translocase of the inner membrane) complex on the mitochondrial outer and inner membranes, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Chacinska et al., 2009</xref>). Between the double membranes, the mitochondrial intermembrane space (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">IMS</xref>) contains several tiny TIM proteins (TIM8&#x2013;TIM10 and TIM13) that are known to be involved in the carrier transport pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Koehler et al., 1998a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Sirrenberg et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Adam et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Paschen et al., 2000</xref>). In yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) and human, TIM9 and TIM10 had been proposed to exist in the form of a hexamer composed of three TIM9 and three TIM10 subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Webb et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Baker et al., 2009</xref>). It was also revealed that in the carrier transport pathway, the TIM9:10 complex guided the precursor proteins through the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">IMS</xref> in yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Neupert and Herrmann, 2007</xref>). Once precursors translocate through the TOM channel into the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">IMS</xref>, they have to bind to the TIM9:10 complex and be transferred to the carrier translocase located on the inner membrane (TIM22 complex) to proceed to subsequent steps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Curran et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Rehling et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Wiedemann et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p>TIM9 and TIM10 are highly conserved proteins throughout the eukaryotic kingdom, including plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Braun and Schmitz, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Carrie et al., 2010</xref>). In potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>), TIM9 and TIM10 were found to be two components of import proteins in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">IMS</xref>, having functional roles in the efficient carrier proteins pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lister et al., 2002</xref>). By searching yeast homologs, the genes encoding potential TIM9 and TIM10 homologs in Arabidopsis were found and defined to be components of the mitochondrial protein import apparatus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Bauer et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Lister et al., 2003</xref>). Furthermore, the results of mitochondrial transport inhibitor treatment also suggested that AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 may participate in protein import (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lister et al., 2004</xref>). Recently, in addition to the basic import function, researchers have paid increasing attention to the function of TIM components during various phases of plant development, such as playing important roles in Arabidopsis seedling development (TIM21 and TIM23) and hypocotyl cell growth (TIM50; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Hamasaki et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Kumar et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Wang et al., 2012</xref>). Although the <italic>AtTIM9</italic> gene had been designated previously as <italic>EMB2474</italic> and its mutation showed an embryo-lethal phenotype in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Tzafrir et al., 2004</xref>), the mechanism of death during embryogenesis is unclear. Moreover, to date, little is known about the importance of TIM10 during Arabidopsis development, neither the relationship between AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 nor the potential functional roles of them in early sporophyte growth.</p><p>Here, we provide molecular and genetic evidence to demonstrate that loss of either <italic>AtTIM9</italic> or <italic>AtTIM10</italic> causes early sporophytic cells, including the embryo proper cells and endosperm-free nuclei, to stop dividing and arrest growth at the 16/32-cell stage of embryo development. The phenotypes we observed in the embryo proper and endosperm of the mutants were caused by initiation of necrosis-like programmed cell death (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref>) as defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">van Doorn and Woltering (2005)</xref>, and this <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> process probably resulted from a collapse of mitochondrial structure and a decrease in mitochondrial activity. Our results indicated that AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 play nonredundant, essential roles in continuously dividing embryo proper and endosperm-free nuclei during early sporophyte development by maintaining normal mitochondrial function.</p><sec id="s1" sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2"><title><italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> Genes Are Both Essential for Sporophytic Progeny</title><p>To investigate the function of the <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> genes during plant development, we obtained three Arabidopsis mutant lines from public mutant collections (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>): <italic>tim9-1</italic> (also known as <italic>emb2474</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Tzafrir et al., 2004</xref>), <italic>tim9-2</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic>. Segregation analysis of all three of the self-fertilized mutant progeny showed that the selective ratio was about 2:1 (resistant:sensitive), instead of the expected 3:1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblI">Table I</xref>). This result suggested that there was seed lethality in the resistant mutant progeny. PCR analysis also demonstrated that no viable homozygous mutant plants were found (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1A</ext-link>). Therefore, each of the <italic>tim9-1</italic>, <italic>tim9-2</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic> mutants contains a single-copy transfer DNA (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref>) insertion in the genome and presents in the form of heterozygous <italic>tim9-1/+</italic>, <italic>tim9-2/+</italic> and <italic>tim10/+</italic>, respectively, showing a homozygous seed-lethal phenotype.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Characterization of the <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> mutations. A, Schematic diagrams of the <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> gene structures with the positions of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref> insertions of three mutants. Exons are shown as black boxes, 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032; regions as white boxes, and introns and untranslated regions as lines. FP, Forward primer; RP, reverse primer. B, Silique phenotypes of the wild type and mutants. The white arrows show the aborted white ovules. C, Seed abortion rates in the mutants compared with the wild type. The total number (n) of counted seeds is listed on the top of the histogram, and the seed abortion rate values are shown on the bottom. D, Ovule phenotypes in wild-type and mutant siliques. Bars = 1 mm. E, White ovule length compared with green ovules from heterozygous <italic>tim</italic> mutant parents. The total number (n) of counted ovules and the average ovule length values are shown above the histogram. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_242560_f1"></graphic></fig><table-wrap id="tblI" position="float"><label>Table I.</label><caption><title>Segregation of the tim9-1<italic>/</italic>+, tim9-2<italic>/</italic>+, and tim10<italic>/</italic>+ mutants</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="center" scope="col">Cross (Female &#x00D7; Male)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblIfn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" scope="col">SM<sup>b</sup></th><th align="center" scope="col">Resistant</th><th align="center" scope="col">Sensitive</th><th align="center" scope="col">R:S Rate<sup>c</sup></th><th align="center" scope="col">Expected Rate</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim9-1/+ &#x00D7; tim9-1/+</italic></td><td align="center">Bas</td><td align="center">2,008</td><td align="char" char=".">1,052</td><td align="center">1.91:1<sup>d</sup></td><td align="center">3:1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim9-2/+ &#x00D7; tim9-2/+</italic></td><td align="center">Sul</td><td align="center">1,595</td><td align="char" char=".">796</td><td align="center">2.03:1<sup>d</sup></td><td align="center">3:1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim10/+ &#x00D7; tim10/+</italic></td><td align="center">Sul</td><td align="center">1,454</td><td align="char" char=".">718</td><td align="center">2.00:1<sup>d</sup></td><td align="center">3:1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblIfn1"><label>a</label><p>Seeds of the selfing lines were collected and grown on selective plates to determine the segregation.&#x2003;&#x2003;<sup>b</sup>Selection marker (SM): BASTA (Bas) and sulfadiazine (Sul).&#x2003;&#x2003;<sup>c</sup>Resistant (R):sensitive (S).&#x2003;&#x2003;<sup>d</sup>Significantly different from the segregation ratio of 3:1 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We dissected maturing siliques from <italic>tim9-1/+</italic>, <italic>tim9-2/+</italic>, and <italic>tim10/+</italic> plants to analyze the phenotypes of mutants and found that all of them contained a proportion of aborted white seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>, arrows). By contrast, the siliques from wild-type plants contained a well-ordered array of maturing green seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>). More than 2,000 selection marker-resistant progeny of each mutant displaying the aborted seed phenotype were observed, implying that the phenotypes are tightly linked to the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref> insertions in the respective mutants. We further calculated the percentage of aborted seeds in each mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>). The values were close to the expected value of 25%, reconfirming that mutations of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> led to homozygous progeny lethality. Additional reciprocal crosses showed that the genetic transmission capacity of both females and males in the three mutants was similar to that of the wild type, indicating that the gametophyte fertilities were not affected due to a loss of function specifically of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> or <italic>AtTIM10</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). Together, these results indicate that the defective fertility phenotype of the mutants was only caused by aborted homozygous sporophytes after fertilization.</p><p>To determine whether <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> are required for early sporophytic development, we performed complementation tests (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Materials and Methods S1</ext-link>). The self-progeny of three independent T3 generation homozygous transgenic plants for each construct were each analyzed by genotyping (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1A</ext-link>). Mutant <italic>tim9-1/+</italic>, <italic>tim9-2/+</italic>, and <italic>tim10/+</italic> all could be successfully complemented to become fertile (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1, B and C</ext-link>), indicating that the sporophyte-lethal phenotype was indeed caused by the loss of either <italic>AtTIM9</italic> or <italic>AtTIM10</italic> function. Thus, <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> both perform essential functions in early sporophyte development in Arabidopsis.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Mutations of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> Arrest Development in Both Embryo and Endosperm When the Embryo Proper Grows to the 16/32-Cell Stage</title><p>To precisely determine the developmental stage of the abortion of seeds of mutant plants, we examined embryos of immature ovules from <italic>tim9-1/+</italic>, <italic>tim9-2/+</italic>, and <italic>tim10/+</italic>. For controls, embryos in the normal ovules (mutant siliques) were developing into the early heart embryo stage at 4 d after pollination (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A, F, and K</xref>). Embryos in the aborted ovules were still delayed at the sequential stages containing one- to eight-cell embryo proper (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, B&#x2013;D, G&#x2013;I, and L&#x2013;N</xref>) and finally arrested at the 16/32-cell stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, E, J, and O</xref>). No abnormalities in the suspensor suggested that the delayed growth was only present in the mutant embryo proper. Meanwhile, we found that the white ovules were generally smaller than the green ones, as the aborted seeds could be distinguished from normal ones in siliques at 3 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref> in each heterozygous mutant, according to the ovule size, and inferential statistical analysis of ovule lengths at 5 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref> showed a significant difference between green and white ovules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, D and E</xref>), implying that the development of the endosperm was also arrested. Next, we carefully counted representative numbers of each of the embryonic morphologies at different development stages in wild-type and heterozygote (<italic>tim9-1/+</italic>, <italic>tim9-2/+</italic>, and <italic>tim10/+</italic>) plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblII">Table II</xref>). About 25% of embryos in the mutants showed delayed growth throughout the developmental process and stagnated at the 16/32-cell stage, which was consistent with the segregation and abortion rates of the mutants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblI">Table I</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>). According to the tallied numbers of endosperm-free nuclei, the development of the endosperm also showed delayed growth in the early stages following fertilization (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tblIII">Table III</xref>). These data demonstrated that the embryos and syncytial endosperm of aborted ovules in <italic>tim9-1/+</italic>, <italic>tim9-2/+</italic>, and <italic>tim10/+</italic> plants grew more slowly than did control ovules and finally arrested.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Status of embryo development in the mutants. Normal and aborted embryos at the age of 4 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref> are observed within heterozygous siliques of <italic>tim9-1/+</italic> (A&#x2013;E), <italic>tim9-2/+</italic> (F&#x2013;J), <italic>tim10/+</italic> (K&#x2013;O), and <italic>tim9-1/+tim10/+</italic> (P&#x2013;T). As controls, normal embryos in heterozygous siliques are at the early heart stage (A, F, K, and P). Aborted embryos at the one-cell (B, G, L, and Q), two/four-cell (C, H, M, and R), eight-cell (D, I, N, and S), and 16/32-cell (E, J, O, and T) stages are shown for each heterozygous silique. Bars = 30 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_242560_f2"></graphic></fig><table-wrap id="tblII" position="float"><label>Table II.</label><caption><title>Distribution of embryo phenotypes in the wild type and mutants at sequential development stages</title><p>Siliques were marked consecutively starting from 3 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref>, and the samples from days 3 to 6 were used for observation. For the siliques from the same line and at the same marking time, ovules in each silique were cleared and the embryos were counted at each stage, then the total and average of each stage embryo number were calculated and rounded to the whole number. Therefore, the number of each sample displays the embryo distribution of a whole silique. Nts/Nsi, Number of total ovules/number of siliques; Nas, number of average ovules in a single silique; EG, early globular; LG, later globular; EH, early heart; H, heart; ET, early torpedo; T, torpedo; C, cotyledon.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col">Parents</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col"><xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col">Nts/Nsi</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col">Nas</th><th colspan="11" align="center" scope="colgroup">Arrested Stages<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col">Percentage Aborted</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup">One Cell</th><th align="center" scope="col">Two/Four Cell</th><th align="center" scope="col">Eight Cell</th><th align="center" scope="col">16/32 Cell</th><th align="center" scope="col">EG</th><th align="center" scope="col">LG</th><th align="center" scope="col">EH</th><th align="center" scope="col">H</th><th align="center" scope="col">ET</th><th align="center" scope="col">T</th><th align="center" scope="col">C</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" scope="row">Wild type</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">226/6</td><td align="center">38</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">2</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">15</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">15</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">6</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">286/7</td><td align="center">41</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">5</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">16</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">20</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">350/8</td><td align="center">44</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">23</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">18</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">231/5</td><td align="center">46</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">28</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">10</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim9-1/</italic>+</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">233/5</td><td align="center">47</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">6</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">14</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">12</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">9</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">25.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">262/6</td><td align="center">44</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">8</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">4</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">6</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">17</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">6</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">25.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">266/6</td><td align="center">42</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">9</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">5</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">11</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">12</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">26.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">235/5</td><td align="center">47</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">12</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">25</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">25.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim9-2/</italic>+</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">280/6</td><td align="center">49</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">4</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">7</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">15</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">11</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">10</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">26.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">303/6</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">9</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">5</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">7</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">18</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">7</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">26.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">295/7</td><td align="center">42</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">8</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">2</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">8</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">12</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">10</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">23.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">257/6</td><td align="center">43</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">11</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">2</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">23</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">25.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim10/</italic>+</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">295/6</td><td align="center">49</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">5</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">14</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">13</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">10</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">26.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">289/7</td><td align="center">41</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">7</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">6</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">18</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">26.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">285/7</td><td align="center">41</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">9</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">8</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">14</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">8</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">26.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">224/5</td><td align="center">45</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">11</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">4</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">25</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">24.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim9-1/+tim10/</italic>+</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">305/6</td><td align="center">51</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">8</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">7</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">6</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">13</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">10</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">43.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">292/6</td><td align="center">49</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">7</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">8</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">4</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">5</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">16</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">42.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">298/6</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">6</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">10</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">2</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">5</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">14</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">7</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">44.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">252/5</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">5</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">12</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td align="center">&#x2013;</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">6</td><td valign="top" align="char" char=".">19</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">42.00</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tblIII" position="float"><label>Table III.</label><caption><title>Frequencies of embryo and endosperm in the wild type and mutants</title><p>Ovules of the wild type and mutations were isolated and cleared to count the number of embryos in different stages and surrounding endosperm free nuclei. <italic>N</italic>, Number of total ovules; nuc, endosperm free nuclei.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col"><xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col">Parents</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" scope="col"><italic>N</italic></th><th colspan="5" align="center" scope="colgroup">Embryo<hr/></th><th colspan="4" align="center" scope="colgroup">Endosperm<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup">Zygote</th><th align="center" scope="col">One Cell</th><th align="center" scope="col">Two/Four Cell</th><th align="center" scope="col">Eight Cell</th><th align="center" scope="col">16/32 Cell</th><th align="center" scope="col">Less Than 30 nuc</th><th align="center" scope="col">30 to 60 nuc</th><th align="center" scope="col">60 to 120 nuc</th><th align="center" scope="col">More Than 120 nuc</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" scope="row"></td><td align="left"></td><td align="left"></td><td colspan="9" align="center"><italic>%</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" scope="row">1</td><td align="left">Wild type</td><td align="center">156</td><td align="char" char=".">15</td><td align="char" char=".">27.9</td><td align="char" char=".">55.8</td><td align="char" char=".">1.3</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">16.4</td><td align="char" char=".">53.7</td><td align="char" char=".">22.4</td><td align="char" char=".">7.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim9-1/</italic>+</td><td align="center">139</td><td align="char" char=".">32.6</td><td align="char" char=".">41.9</td><td align="char" char=".">25.6</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">35.3</td><td align="char" char=".">58.9</td><td align="char" char=".">5.9</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim9-2/</italic>+</td><td align="center">148</td><td align="char" char=".">31.7</td><td align="char" char=".">39</td><td align="char" char=".">29.3</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">35.8</td><td align="char" char=".">56.6</td><td align="char" char=".">7.5</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim10/</italic>+</td><td align="center">134</td><td align="char" char=".">35.7</td><td align="char" char=".">35.7</td><td align="char" char=".">28.6</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">38.8</td><td align="char" char=".">55.1</td><td align="char" char=".">6.1</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" scope="row">2</td><td align="left">Wild type</td><td align="center">156</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">4.3</td><td align="char" char=".">23.9</td><td align="char" char=".">34.8</td><td align="char" char=".">37</td><td align="char" char=".">5.1</td><td align="char" char=".">20.5</td><td align="char" char=".">38.5</td><td align="char" char=".">35.9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim9-1/</italic>+</td><td align="center">139</td><td align="char" char=".">2.1</td><td align="char" char=".">11.8</td><td align="char" char=".">46.7</td><td align="char" char=".">35.2</td><td align="char" char=".">4.2</td><td align="char" char=".">20.9</td><td align="char" char=".">38.8</td><td align="char" char=".">28.8</td><td align="char" char=".">11.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim9-2/</italic>+</td><td align="center">148</td><td align="char" char=".">2.2</td><td align="char" char=".">11.1</td><td align="char" char=".">48.9</td><td align="char" char=".">33.3</td><td align="char" char=".">4.5</td><td align="char" char=".">21.6</td><td align="char" char=".">40</td><td align="char" char=".">27</td><td align="char" char=".">11.4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" align="left" scope="row"><italic>tim10/</italic>+</td><td align="center">134</td><td align="char" char=".">2.1</td><td align="char" char=".">10.9</td><td align="char" char=".">50</td><td align="char" char=".">32.7</td><td align="char" char=".">4.3</td><td align="char" char=".">20.1</td><td align="char" char=".">39.6</td><td align="char" char=".">27.6</td><td align="char" char=".">12.7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Considering that the lack of either <italic>AtTIM9</italic> or <italic>AtTIM10</italic> led to early sporophyte lethality, we crossed <italic>tim9-1/+</italic> with <italic>tim10/+</italic> to investigate if a more severe defective phenotype would occur in double mutant plants. In the F2 progeny, the <italic>tim9-1/+tim10/+</italic> lines were identified and observed by dissection of siliques (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>). The seed abortion rate of <italic>tim9-1/+tim10/+</italic> was 43.52% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>), which conforms to the expected 43.75% rate according to Mendel&#x2019;s second law; no more severe defective phenotype was observed in the double mutant, showing that the aborted embryos still arrested at the 16/32-cell stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, P&#x2013;T</xref>). These results indicated that <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> function nonredundantly during early sporophyte development to control embryo cell and endosperm-free nuclei division.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title><italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> Are Expressed Widely, Especially in the Embryo and Endosperm</title><p>Investigation of Arabidopsis Genevestigator expression data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Hruz et al., 2008</xref>) for <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> indicated that transcripts of both genes were present in all tissues (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). To further investigate the expression patterns of these two genes, we observed transgenic plants carrying <italic>ProAtTIM9</italic>::GUS and <italic>ProAtTIM10</italic>::GUS constructs and found that the two genes shared the same expression patterns (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Materials and Methods S1</ext-link>). In 10-d-old seedlings, GUS activity accumulated mainly in the tissues with actively dividing cells (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3, A&#x2013;C and G&#x2013;I</ext-link>). During reproductive growth, GUS signals were evident in inflorescences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3, D and J</ext-link>), mature flowers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3, E and K</ext-link>), as well as embryos and endosperm at different stages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3, F and L</ext-link>, arrows and arrowheads), while they were not observed in the anthers or ovaries, hinting that loss of either <italic>AtTIM9</italic> or <italic>AtTIM10</italic> function would not result in gametophyte defects.</p><p>By using quantitative reverse transcription-PCR assays, we also observed that <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> transcripts were widely expressed in Arabidopsis tissues, including in siliques at different developmental stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Since the mutant phenotypes were apparently associated with embryos and endosperm, we performed RNA in situ hybridization for wild-type ovules. <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> were detected both in the embryos and endosperm-free nuclei at different stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, B and C</xref>, arrows and arrowheads). Thus, the expression of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> is consistent with its functional relevance for early sporophyte, including embryo and endosperm development.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Expression analysis of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> genes at the transcriptional level. A, <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> temporal and spatial transcript levels as determined by quantitative real-time reverse transcription-PCR in wild-type plants. S, Seedlings; R, roots; I, inflorescences; F, flowers; 1Si to 9Si, siliques at 1 to 5 and 7, and 9 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref>. B and C, In situ hybridization of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> transcripts (brown-red staining) accumulated in wild-type embryos and endosperm. Arrows and arrowheads show the embryos and endosperm in the ovules, respectively. Bars = 20 &#x03BC;m. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_242560_f3"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s5"><title>AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 Proteins Are Highly Conserved and Localized in Mitochondria</title><p>In order to investigate the homology of AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 proteins, we performed alignments of the amino acid sequences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4</ext-link>) and modeled three-dimensional structures (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Materials and Methods S1</ext-link>) among TIM9 and TIM10 eukaryotic homologs. The results showed that both AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 have high homology at both the primary and secondary structure levels. Although the amino acid sequence identity between AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 is only 21.28% (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4C</ext-link>), their predicted secondary structures are similar (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5C</ext-link>), supporting the notion that TIM9 and TIM10 may have similar functions during embryonic development in Arabidopsis.</p><p>To further study the subcellular localization status of these proteins, transgenic lines were generated to express AtTIM9 or AtTIM10 in fusion with enhanced GFP (EGFP) at the N terminus under the control of their own promoters. The accumulation of AtTIM9-EGFP and AtTIM10-EGFP fusion proteins in stably transformed plantlets was verified (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>), suggesting that the fusion proteins were present. Mesophyll protoplasts isolated from the transformants were examined in order to observe subcellular localization signals in living cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). The results showed that protoplasts containing AtTIM9-EGFP and AtTIM10-EGFP both displayed dotted green fluorescence signals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>, left), which overlapped with the mitochondrial indicator MitoTracker (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>, middle and right). These results confirmed the localization of AtTIM9-EGFP and AtTIM10-EGFP in mitochondria.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Subcellular localization of AtTIM9 and AtTIM10. Either AtTIM9-GFP or AtTIM10-GFP is colocalized with mitochondria in Arabidopsis protoplasts. Bars = 10 &#x03BC;m. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_242560_f4"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s6"><title>AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 Can Directly Interact with Each Other in Arabidopsis</title><p>Initial confocal scanning of mesophyll protoplasts revealed that AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 are colocalized in the mitochondria of plants stably cotransformed with AtTIM9-EGFP and AtTIM10-enhanced cyan fluorescent protein (ECFP; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S7</ext-link>). This implied that AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 may possibly interact in some way. To investigate their interaction, we used yeast two-hybrid assays. Yeast cells that coexpressed the AtTIM10 bait and the AtTIM9 prey, or the AtTIM9 bait and the AtTIM10 prey, were allowed to grow on defective medium synthetic dextrose-adenine-His-Leu-Trp, showing that AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 strongly interact with each other on high-stringency selection plates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>). To confirm the interaction between AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 in vivo, we conducted a coimmunoprecipitation analysis. When the AtTIM9-EGFP and AtTIM10-4MYC fusion proteins were transiently coexpressed in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> leaf cells, the AtTIM9-EGFP fusion protein could be coimmunoprecipitated with AtTIM10-4MYC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>). We further performed a bimolecular fluorescence complementation (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">BiFC</xref>) assay to verify their interaction in living plant cells. The results showed that the yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) fluorescence signal could be observed only in transformed Arabidopsis protoplasts that coexpressed the constructs AtTIM9-YC (aa156-239) and AtTIM10-YN (aa1-155) or AtTIM10-YC and AtTIM9-YN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>). Moreover, the YFP fluorescence signal accumulated exclusively in the mitochondria, reconfirming the subcellular localization of AtTIM9 and AtTIM10. Together, these results suggested that AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 may form a TIM9:10 complex and nonredundantly execute their functions in Arabidopsis, while lack of either of the subunits may lead to early embryo and endosperm lethality.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Interaction between AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 proteins. A, Yeast two-hybrid assay showing interaction between AtTIM9 and AtTIM10. The 10-fold serial dilutions were plated onto lacking media. AD, pGADT7 vector; BK, pGBKT7 vector; Ade, adenine; SD, synthetic dextrose. B, Coimmunoprecipitation (IP) assay showing the interaction between AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves in vivo. C, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">BiFC</xref> assay showing the interaction between AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 directly in Arabidopsis living protoplasts. YC, YFP C-terminal fragment (aa156-239); YN, YFP N-terminal fragment (aa1-155). Bars = 10 &#x03BC;m. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_242560_f5"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Mutations of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> Deleteriously Affect Cell Viability, Mitochondrial Activity, and Mitochondrial Structure in the Embryo Proper Cells and Surrounding Endosperm of Embryos at the 16/32-Cell Stage</title><p>To study how the lack of AtTIM9 or AtTIM10 affected early sporophytic cell division, we carefully isolated homozygous embryos from within aborted white ovules and examined the lethal embryos of <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> mutants. Double staining with fluorescein diacetate (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">FDA</xref>) and propidium iodide (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">PI</xref>) showed that all cells in the embryos maintained cell viability until the eight-cell stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, A&#x2013;E, G, and H</xref>). In <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> embryos, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">PI</xref> signals were shown in the nucleus of embryo proper cells at the 16/32-cell stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, F and I</xref>), implying that cells in this region had died by this stage. Using MitoTracker as a marker, we detected active mitochondria throughout wild-type embryos, including in the embryo proper and in the suspensor cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, J&#x2013;L</xref>, arrows). Intriguingly, the active mitochondria of <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> homozygous embryos were distributed in the same manner as in wild-type embryos until the eight-cell stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, M, N, P, and Q</xref>, arrows). However, mitochondria were not evident in embryo proper cells at the 16/32-cell stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6, O and R</xref>, asterisks), indicating that mitochondria were not viable in the embryo proper cells of aborted embryos.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Cellular and mitochondrial viability in Arabidopsis embryos of the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic>. A to I, Cell viability in the embryos of the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic> at different stages. Bars = 20 &#x03BC;m. J to R, Mitochondrial activity in the embryos of the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic> at different stages. Each plate consists of two group images: MitoTracker Red fluorescence images (left) and corresponding <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">DIC</xref> images merged with the red fluorescence (right). Dotted lines in the left images divide the embryo into embryo proper (EP) and suspensor (Su) parts. Arrows show the active mitochondria in the embryos; asterisks indicate that no active mitochondria were found in the embryo proper cells. Bars = 20 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_242560_f6"></graphic></fig><p>Furthermore, we analyzed the ultrastructure of mitochondria using transmission electron microscopy. The results showed that healthy mitochondria with abundant cristae were distributed everywhere in wild-type embryo cells and endosperm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, B&#x2013;D</xref>, arrows), while embryo proper cells and syncytial endosperm in the <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> mutants contained swollen mitochondria with less intramitochondrial content and internal space lacking any obvious cristae structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, F, H, J, and L</xref>, arrowheads). Also, we noticed that the cells with abnormal mitochondria showed shrunken cytoplasm, with the density of cytoplasmic materials becoming thin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, F, H, J, and L</xref>, asterisks) compared with the thick cytoplasm in normal cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7, B&#x2013;D, G, and K</xref>). All of these features were consistent with other examples of necrotic cell death, which is a typical kind of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">van Doorn et al., 2011</xref>). Consequently, the absence of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> or <italic>AtTIM10</italic> could lose the mitochondrial activity and destroy the mitochondrial structure, to influence cell viability in early embryo proper and endosperm.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Mitochondrial structure in early embryo cells and endosperm of the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic>. A, E, and I, Ultrastructure of the early embryo cells at the 16/32-cell stage from the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic>. The embryo proper (EP), suspensor (Su), and endosperm (En) tissues are highlighted with red, green, and yellow, respectively. Bars = 20 &#x03BC;m. B to D, F to H, and J and L, Ultrastructural mitochondria of the embryo proper cells, suspensor cells, and endosperm-free nucleus in the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic>. Arrows and arrowheads show the integral and degraded mitochondria, respectively; asterisks indicate the shrunken cytoplasm. Bars = 1 &#x03BC;m. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_242560_f7"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Mitochondrial Membrane Permeability Increases in the Embryo Proper Cells of the <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> Mutants</title><p>The abnormal mitochondrial activity and structure found in early embryo proper and endosperm may be related to mitochondrial dysfunction in <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic>. To explore this possibility, we investigated mitochondrial membrane permeability (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MMP</xref>) level in <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> embryos by using the indicator 5,5&#x2032;,6,6&#x2032;-tetrachloro-1,1&#x2032;,3,3&#x2032;-tetraethylbenzimidazolylcarbocyanine iodide (JC-1). Normally, JC-1 monomers could aggregate in healthy mitochondria with low membrane permeability and exhibit red fluorescence. When the membrane permeability increases in abnormal mitochondria, JC-1 monomers remain unaggregated and show green fluorescence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Zamzami et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Martin et al., 2013</xref>). Our results showed that the fluorescence signals were more visibly red than green in embryo proper cells at the one- to eight-cell stages in the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8, A, B, D, E, G, and H</xref>). However, when the embryo proper grew to 16 to 32 cells, the green fluorescence signal was much stronger in <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> than in the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8, F and I</xref>). Quantitative analysis of red-to-green fluorescence ratios in embryo proper cells showed a wider range of dispersion in the wild type than in <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8, J and K</xref>), indicating that the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MMP</xref> level of the mutants was indeed increased in embryo proper samples at the 16/32-cell stage. In contrast, there were few differences in suspensor cells between the wild type and mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8L</xref>). These results showed that the <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> mutants contained abnormal mitochondria with increased <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MMP</xref> levels in the 16/32-cell embryo proper.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MMP</xref> in the embryos of the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic>. A to I, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MMP</xref> levels in the embryos of the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic> at different stages. Each plate consists of two group images: JC-1 aggregate red fluorescence merged with JC-1 monomer green fluorescence (left) and the red and green fluorescence merged with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">DIC</xref> microscopy channel (right). Bars = 20 &#x03BC;m. J to L, The red/green JC-1 fluorescence ratios measured in wild-type (<italic>n</italic> = 56), <italic>tim9-1</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 50), and <italic>tim10</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 47) embryos at the 16/32-cell stage. Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences compared with the wild type (&#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_242560_f8"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Cytochrome <italic>c</italic> Is Released from Mitochondria into the Cytoplasm in the Embryo Proper Cells of the <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> Mutants</title><p>The fact that 16/32-cell <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> embryo proper cells have increased <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MMP</xref> levels could conceivably lead to the release of cytochrome <italic>c</italic> (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref>) from mitochondria to the cytoplasm. The release of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> at the onset of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> is an evolutionarily conserved event appearing in organisms including plants and mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Mart&#x00ED;nez-F&#x00E1;bregas et al., 2013</xref>). To investigate whether this process occurred in the lethal cells of the <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> mutants, we used antibodies against <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> to detect its release in the embryo proper using immunofluorescence microscopy. At the eight-cell stage, most <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> was located in the mitochondria in both the wild type and mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9, A&#x2013;C</xref>). When <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> embryo proper reached the 16/32-cell stage, the green fluorescence signals of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> observed in the cytoplasm hardly overlapped with the mitochondria director (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9, E and F</xref>), implying that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> was released at this stage. Additional analysis of the fluorescence signal intensities produced along a randomly selected series of pixels revealed a correlation between <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> and mitochondria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9, G&#x2013;I</xref>). Further analysis of the ratio of overlapping green fluorescence also demonstrated that, at the 16/32-cell stage, most of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> was not colocalized with mitochondria but rather was released into the cytoplasm in the <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9J</xref>). These results suggest that the necrosis-like <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> was probably initiated in the embryo proper cells of the <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> mutants.</p><fig id="fig9" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Immunolocalization of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> in the embryo proper of the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic>. A to F, Localization of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> in the embryo proper of the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic> at the eight- to 32-cell stages. Each plate consists of four group images from left to right: anti-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> green fluorescence, MitoTracker Red fluorescence, green fluorescence merged with red fluorescence, and bright field. Bars = 10 &#x03BC;m. G to I, Intensity values of a plotted line by scanning through the merged regions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Figure 10, D to F</xref>. J, Overlapping ratio of green fluorescence measured in the embryo proper of the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic>. Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences compared with the wild type (&#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_242560_f9"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s10"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> Occurs in Early Embryo Proper Cells and Endosperm-Free Nuclei of <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> Mutants</title><p>To explore whether the changes of the mitochondria in the <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> mutants caused the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> event to happen, we used the fluorescent probes H<sub>2</sub>DCFDA (for 5-[and -6]-chloromethyl-2&#x2032;,7&#x2032;-dichlorodihydrofluorescein diacetate, acetyl ester) and MitoSOX Red to selectively indicate reactive oxygen species (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref>) in the cytosol and mitochondria, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Robinson et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Bi et al., 2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> are produced by mitochondria and can be involved in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref>, and the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> levels in cytosol and mitochondria are normally considered to be an important indicator for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Fleury et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Van Breusegem and Dat, 2006</xref>). In this assay, we found that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> levels in <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> embryos before the eight-cell stage were similar to those in the wild type. However, when the embryo proper grew to the 16/32-cell stage, compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10C</xref>), the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> level in cytosol (green fluorescence) became higher in <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic>, while the mitochondrial <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> (red fluorescence) almost disappeared (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10, F and I</xref>). These results indicated that in <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> 16/32-cell embryo proper cells, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> as toxic compounds were not detoxified by the cytoplasm and accumulated in the cytosol; mitochondria also stopped producing the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> source. These changes caused the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> level balance between cytosol and mitochondria to be broken, which displayed a classical <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> feature in the aborted embryo proper of the two mutants.</p><fig id="fig10" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p><xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> occurs in early embryos and endosperm of the wild type, <italic>tim9-1</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic>. A to I, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> levels in the embryos at different stages. Each plate consists of two group images: cellular <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> green fluorescence merged with mitochondrial <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> red fluorescence (left) and the red and green fluorescence merged with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">DIC</xref> microscopy channel (right). Bars = 20 &#x03BC;m. J to O, TUNEL-positive signal is indicated by the green fluorescence of fluorescein, and nuclei fluoresce deep red using the counterstain <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">PI</xref>. Each plate consists of two group images: TUNEL-positive green fluorescence merged with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">DIC</xref> microscopy (left) and TUNEL-positive green fluorescence merged with nuclei red fluorescence (right). Arrows and arrowheads show the TUNEL signals in the embryonic nucleus and endosperm-free nuclei, respectively. Bars = 20 &#x03BC;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_242560_f10"></graphic></fig><p>We further studied the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> event under the control of the indicator terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase-mediated dUTP nick-end labeling (TUNEL) assay to test the nuclear DNA fragmentation in early sporophytic cells. Our results showed that the TUNEL signal was negative at the eight-cell stage in <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> ovules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10, L and N</xref>). This was also the case in wild-type ovules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10J</xref>). However, TUNEL-positive signals appeared in the <italic>tim9-1</italic> (95%, <italic>n</italic> = 37) and <italic>tim10</italic> (91%, <italic>n</italic> = 44) embryo proper and endosperm at the 32-cell stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10, H and M</xref>, arrows and arrowheads). These results indicated that nucleic acids degenerated and led to the eventual complete abortion of embryo proper cells and endosperm-free nucleus, potentially explaining the halted division and dead embryos and endosperm observed in the mutants. As such, AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 are both required for normal early sporophyte development in both embryo cells and syncytial endosperm.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s11" sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><sec id="s12"><title>AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 Are Both Essential for Maintaining Mitochondrial Function in Arabidopsis</title><p>Previous studies on yeast have reported that TIM9 and TIM10 play essential roles in mitochondrial biogenesis; the disruption of either protein causes cell lethality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Jarosch et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Koehler et al., 1998b</xref>). In humans, among the Tim10/deafness/dystonia peptide protein family, only HmTIM8a has been investigated to be necessary during human neurological development to mediate the mitochondrial disease, deafness/dystonia syndrome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Tranebjaerg et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Roesch et al., 2002</xref>), while the functions of human TIM9 and TIM10 remain unknown. Here, we found that mutants of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> led to severe mitochondrial defects in early sporophytes, their encoding proteins AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 located in mitochondria, and play nonredundantly important roles in the division of early embryo cells and endosperm-free nuclei.,</p><p>Embryo cells contain a large number of mitochondria during development that enable a cell&#x2019;s vigorous division and growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Law et al., 2012</xref>). However, we found that mitochondria in the embryo proper and endosperm were not active and that mitochondrial cristae structure was lost when embryo arrest took place in the homozygous <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figs. 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>). This destruction of mitochondrial structure could lead to various mitochondrial dysfunctions. As an example, ATP synthesis (oxidative phosphorylation) is critically dependent on the structural integrity of the mitochondrion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Sherratt, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Frey and Mannella, 2000</xref>). Furthermore, we found the dysfunctional mitochondria increased <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MMP</xref> and released <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> into the cytoplasm in the mutant embryo proper cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figs. 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">9</xref>), suggesting that this is probably caused by the disruption of the mitochondrial import pathway in the absence of AtTIM9 or AtTIM10 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Lister et al., 2004</xref>). The TIM9:10 complex was reported to participate in the import of many important mitochondrial protein precursors, including ADP/ATP carrier in yeast and adenine nucleotide translocator in potato (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Lister et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Truscott et al., 2002</xref>). When TIM9 or TIM10 function is impaired, there may be an absence of ADP/ATP carrier proteins and a decrease of ATP level, which could abnormally increase <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MMP</xref> and release <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Pereira et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Hasson et al., 2010</xref>). Accordingly, AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 play very important roles in maintaining mitochondrial function to control cell viability and division during early embryo and endosperm development.</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>The Early Sporophytic Abortion of the <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> Mutants through the Necrosis-Like <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> Pathway</title><p>A number of genes encoding proteins located in the mitochondria have been found to be essential for early embryo development in Arabidopsis; mutants of these genes show the phenotype of embryo arrest at the early globular stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Okada et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Berg et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Vazzola et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Jiang et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Yu et al., 2012</xref>), indicating that their proteins involved in mitochondrial basal metabolic functions play many important roles during seed formation. However, the mechanism of death during early embryo lethality and how mitochondrial proteins are involved in the developmental process have been little studied. Therefore, in this study, we revealed that mutations of the <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> genes caused early embryo proper cell and syncytial endosperm lethality through the necrosis-like <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> pathway.</p><p>To date, there have only been a few reports about the relationship between mitochondrial import proteins and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref>. The small molecule MitoBloCK-6 was recently found to inhibit the import of TIM proteins and is further known to induce apoptosis via <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> release in human embryonic stem cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Dabir et al., 2013</xref>). The mitochondrial import machinery also has been proven to contribute to the naturally occurring <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> during human pathologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Sokol et al., 2014</xref>). In higher plants, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> is an integral part during development and defense of the whole life, mainly including two distinguished classes: vacuolar cell death and necrosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">van Doorn et al., 2011</xref>). Vacuolar cell death in plants is also known as autophagy in animals and commonly happens during normal tissue and organ formation and elimination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Edinger and Thompson, 2004</xref>), whereas necrosis, as a programmed event, is typically an acute cell death response and always occurs under abiotic stresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">van Doorn and Woltering, 2005</xref>). To date, there are no molecular markers for the necrosis-like <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref>, and it remains to be defined at the physiological level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">van Doorn et al., 2011</xref>). Our evidence from transmission electron microscopy, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> levels, and TUNEL signals indicated that when <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> embryos developed to the 16/32-cell stage, embryo proper cells and endosperm-free nuclei all display the features of necrosis-like <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figs. 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">9</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">10</xref>). During the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> in plants, it has been reported that mitochondria play a central role (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Jones, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Vianello et al., 2007</xref>). Hence, the changes of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MMP</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> localization that we found in the lethal embryo proper of <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figs. 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">8</xref>) confirmed that mitochondria significantly functioned in the necrosis-like <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> pathways in Arabidopsis.</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Mitochondrial Dysfunction in the Early Sporophyte of <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> Mutants Is Only Found in Embryo Proper and Syncytial Endosperm, But Not in Suspensor Cells</title><p>Arabidopsis embryogenesis starts from the asymmetrical division of the zygote to form two cells of different sizes. The larger basal cell develops into a stalk-like support structure of six to eight cells called the suspensor, and the smaller apical cell is the founder of the embryo proper that contributes to most of the later seedling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Yeung and Meinke, 1993</xref>). In this study, mutations of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> displayed the embryonic abortion phenotype, but with the well-developed suspensor, the lengths and cell numbers were similar to the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). Furthermore, we found that the features of abnormal mitochondria and necrosis-like <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref> only appeared in the mutant embryo proper cells and syncytial endosperm, while the suspensor cells remained normal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figs. 6</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">10</xref>). As a result, we conclude that the mitochondrial dysfunction induced by the absence of AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 function only occurs in the embryo proper and endosperm, but not in suspensor cells.</p><p>Most flowering plants studied to date including Arabidopsis exhibit maternal mitochondrial inheritance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Mogensen, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Nagata, 2010</xref>). The volume and density of mitochondria in zygote increase significantly as compared with the egg cell stage. This is followed by elongation of the zygote, which accumulates mitochondria in its apical region and subsequently starts asymmetrical division (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Mansfield and Briarty, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Russell, 1993</xref>). These findings indicate that mitochondria are required for the initial divisions of embryonic cells, and the ones that come from the female parent may play important roles during early sporophyte initiation and development. Our results showed that mitochondria in <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> mutants remained normal throughout the early sporophyte development stages until the eight-cell stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figs. 6</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">10</xref>), implying that the embryo proper and suspensor cells could divide into eight cells normally and that the endosperm-free nuclei also divide normally, with each region being sustained by their respective mitochondria. After the eight-cell stage in the <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic> mutants, the suspensor developed completely to eight cells and stopped dividing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Mansfield and Briarty, 1991</xref>); therefore, the presence of active mitochondria in the suspensor cells of mutant embryos at the stage of arrest reflects the fact that division of the suspensor is completed first. On the other hand, the embryo proper and endosperm need to keep dividing; however, the dysfunctional mitochondria may no longer support natural cell growth and division and subsequently lead these early sporophytic cells to undergo the necrosis-like <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PCD</xref>.</p><p>In conclusion, AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 form a complex and function nonredundantly in early embryo and endosperm development in Arabidopsis. Our research into the functions of these two mitochondrial proteins opens a new horizon that the import proteins perform important roles in the maintenance of mitochondrial function in plants, thereby providing novel insight into the functions of import proteins in controlling the fundamental and essential process of cell division in early embryo proper cells and in endosperm-free nuclei.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s15" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s16"><title>Plant Materials and Growth Conditions</title><p>Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) ecotype Columbia was used as the wild type in this study. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref> insertion mutant lines were obtained from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center and the Nottingham Arabidopsis Stock Centre: CS16114 (<italic>tim9-1/+</italic>; also known as <italic>emb2474</italic>), CS442853 (<italic>tim9-2/+</italic>), and CS415161 (<italic>tim10/+</italic>). The double mutant <italic>tim9-1/+tim10/+</italic> was generated by crossing <italic>tim9-1/+</italic> and <italic>tim10/+</italic>. For the genetics experiment, seeds were surface sterilized and germinated on Murashige and Skoog medium with correspondent antibiotics for 7 to 10 d, then transplanted and grown on soil. All plants were grown in a growth chamber at Wuhan University at 22&#x00B0;C &#x00B1; 2&#x00B0;C with a 16-h-light/8-h-dark photoperiod.</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Mutant Verification, Complementation Analysis, and Phenotype Observation</title><p>Heterozygous lines were isolated by using a PCR screening approach with <italic>AtTIM9</italic>- and <italic>AtTIM10</italic>-specific primers and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref> primer (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>), and the insertion positions were confirmed by sequencing with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref> primer.</p><p>For complementation, the <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> full-length genomic fragments were amplified with KOD-Plus DNA polymerase (Toyobo) from wild-type Arabidopsis and cloned into <italic>pCambia1300</italic> vector (Cambia), introduced into <italic>tim9-1/+</italic>, <italic>tim9-2/+</italic>, and <italic>tim10-1/+</italic> heterozygote mutants via <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> (GV3101), and then transformed using the floral dip method. Primers used in the experiments are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>.</p><p>Ovules were isolated using two needles and cleared with chloral hydrate following the protocol described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">Yadegari et al. (1994)</xref>. Specimens were observed using the Olympus IX71 microscope under differential interference contrast (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">DIC</xref>) optics and photographed by a SPOT Xplorer Camera (Diagnostic).</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Quantitative Real-Time PCR Assay</title><p>Quantitative real-time PCR was carried out using SYBR Green fluorescence and a Rotor-Gene Q real-time PCR machine (Qiagen). The expression of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> in various RNA samples was normalized to the expression of an internal gene, <italic>GLYCERALDEHYDE-3-PHOSPHATE DEHYDROGENASE</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Zhong and Simons, 1999</xref>). The relative expression levels were analyzed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Ma and Zhao, 2010</xref>). Three independent biological replicates and three technical replicates of each sample were made for quantitative PCR analysis. Primers used in the experiments are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>RNA in Situ Hybridization</title><p>The antisense and sense probes used in the experiments were all generated by PCR amplification with T7 promoters adding primers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>) and followed by in vitro transcription (DIG RNA Labeling Kit; Roche). Ovules at different developmental stages from wild-type Arabidopsis siliques were isolated. Fixating, embedding, and sectioning of ovules and procedures of RNA in situ hybridization were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Brewer et al., 2006</xref>). The section images were observed with the Olympus BX60 microscope and photographed by the Olympus DP72 CCD camera.</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Subcellular Localizations</title><p>Western blotting of AtTIM9-EGFP and AtTIM10-EGFP fusion proteins was performed as described before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Liu et al., 2013</xref>), and detection was with anti-GFP rabbit antibody (1:2,000; Abclonal). Fluorescence was observed in Arabidopsis protoplasts. Mesophyll protoplasts isolated from the 4-week-old transformants were incubated with 2 m<sc>m</sc> MitoTracker Red FM (Molecular Probes) for 10 min and examined with a confocal microscope (Fluoview1000; Olympus). The images were taken under EGFP fluorescence (excitation, 488 nm; emission, 505&#x2013;530 nm), the MitoTracker channel (excitation, 559 nm; emission, 530&#x2013;560 nm), and ECFP fluorescence (excitation, 440 nm; emission, 505&#x2013;530 nm). The merged images were generated using the Image Browser Fluoview version 2.7b software (Olympus).</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Yeast Two-Hybrid Assay</title><p>The yeast two-hybrid assay was performed according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions for the Matchmaker GAL4-based two-hybrid system 3 (Clontech). The full-length <italic>AtTIM9</italic> open reading frame was subcloned into the <italic>pGADT7</italic> or <italic>pGBKT7</italic> vector and then transformed into yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) strain AH109 by the lithium acetate method. The transformed colonies were plated onto the minimal synthetic dextrose base medium -Leu/-Trp or -Leu/-Trp/-His/-adenine (Clontech) at 30&#x00B0;C for 2 to 4 d to test for possible interactions. Positive yeast cells were grown to an optical density at 600 nm of 1, and then 5 &#x03BC;L of 10-fold serial dilutions of yeast cells was plated onto the two kinds of lacking media mentioned above. Primers used in this test are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s22"><title>Coimmunoprecipitation Analysis</title><p><italic>35S</italic>::<italic>AtTIM9-EGFP</italic> (<italic>pCambia1300</italic>) and <italic>35S</italic>::<italic>AtTIM10-4MYC</italic> (<italic>pCambia2301</italic>) constructs were introduced into <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> strain GV3101 and cotransformed into 6-week-old <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> leaves simultaneously using the agroinfiltration-mediated infiltration method. The proteins were extracted in the homogenization buffer adding 0.5 m<sc>m</sc> phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (Sigma-Aldrich) and incubated with 2 &#x03BC;g of anti-MYC mouse antibody (Abclonal) at 4&#x00B0;C for 4 h. After 10 &#x03BC;L of protein A sefinose (Bio Basic Inc.) was added and incubated at 4&#x00B0;C for 2 h, the beads were centrifuged and washed. The proteins were eluted with 40 &#x03BC;L of loading buffer and analyzed by immunoblotting using anti-GFP rabbit antibody (1:2,000; Abclonal). Primers used in this experiment are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s23"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">BiFC</xref> Assay</title><p>The full-length open reading frames of AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 were amplified and fused into the vectors <italic>pUC-SPYNE</italic> and <italic>pUC-SPYCE</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Walter et al., 2004</xref>) to produce the C-terminal fusions AtTIM9-YFP1-174 aa (for amino acid), AtTIM10-YFP1-174 aa, AtTIM9-YFP-175-end aa, and AtTIM10-YFP-175-end aa. Mesophyll protoplasts isolated from Arabidopsis leaves were transformed with column-purified plasmid DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Yoo et al., 2007</xref>). After 12 h of incubation at 22&#x00B0;C in the dark, protoplasts were incubated with MitoTracker staining and analyzed and checked for the presence of fluorescence with confocal microscopy under the YFP fluorescence channel (excitation, 515 nm; emission, 505&#x2013;530 nm) and the MitoTracker channel. Primers used in this experiment are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s24"><title>Cell Viability, Mitochondrial Activity, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> Level Analysis</title><p>Isolation of Arabidopsis early embryos was performed according to method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Hu et al. (2006)</xref>. Early embryos isolated from the aborted <italic>tim9-1/+</italic> and <italic>tim10/+</italic> ovules were judged as homozygote, and their genotypes were defined as <italic>tim9-1</italic> and <italic>tim10</italic>. All the isolated living early embryos were stained by 5 &#x03BC;g mL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">FDA</xref> (Sigma) and 10 &#x03BC;g mL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">PI</xref> (Sigma) mixed dyes to observe the activity of cells (for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">FDA</xref>: excitation, 488 nm; emission, 515&#x2013;545; for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">PI</xref>: excitation, 559 nm; emission, 505&#x2013;530 nm); by MitoTracker dye in 10% (w/v) mannitol to observe mitochondrial activity; and by 10 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> H<sub>2</sub>DCFDA (Molecular Probes) and 5 &#x03BC;<sc>m</sc> MitoSOX Red (Molecular Probes) mixed dyes to observe the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">ROS</xref> levels in cells and mitochondria, respectively (for H<sub>2</sub>DCFDA: excitation, 488 nm; emission, 515&#x2013;545; for MitoSOX Red: excitation, 559 nm; emission, 505&#x2013;530 nm). All images were obtained under confocal microscopy as described above.</p></sec><sec id="s25"><title>Transmission Electron Microscopy</title><p>The method for ultrathin sections was carried out as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Chen et al. (2012)</xref>. Ovules (2 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref>) in wild-type siliques and aborted (white) ovules in <italic>tim9-1/+</italic> and <italic>tim10/+</italic> siliques were isolated for fixation and embedding, respectively. The ultrathin sections (60 nm) were cut with an RMC-MTX (Elexience) ultramicrotome. After staining with uranyl acetate and lead citrate, the samples were examined and photographed with a transmission electron microscope (Hitachi HT7700).</p></sec><sec id="s26"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">MMP</xref> Analysis</title><p>Isolated early embryos from wild-type ovules (2 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref>) and mutant white ovules were incubated in 10% (w/v) mannitol with 10 mg mL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> JC-1 (Molecular Probes) for 30 min, then washed with 10% (w/v) mannitol, and their images were collected using the confocal microscope mentioned above. JC-1 aggregates were detected with red fluorescence (excitation, 559 nm; emission, 575&#x2013;590 nm), and JC-1 monomers were detected with green fluorescence (excitation, 488 nm; emission, 515&#x2013;545). The ratio of red to green fluorescence in JC-1 images was calculated by the Browser Fluoview version 2.7b software using R software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org/">http://www.r-project.org/</ext-link>) for the box plot and Origin software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.originlab.com/">http://www.originlab.com/</ext-link>) for the dispersion graphs.</p></sec><sec id="s27"><title>Fluorescence Immunolocalization Assay</title><p>For detecting <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> in the embryo proper, fluorescence immunolocalization was carried out as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Zhang et al., 2008</xref>), analyzed using anti-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">Cyt <italic>c</italic></xref> rabbit antibody (1:1,000; Agrisera), and observed using confocal microscopy as described above under the fluorescein isothiocyanate green fluorescence channel (excitation, 488 nm; emission, 505&#x2013;530 nm) and the MitoTracker channel.</p></sec><sec id="s28"><title>TUNEL Assay</title><p>Ovules in wild-type siliques (2 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">DAP</xref>) and aborted white ovules in <italic>tim9-1/+</italic> and <italic>tim10/+</italic> siliques were fixed in fixative (4% [w/v] paraformaldehyde) adding 0.1% (v/v) Triton X-100 on ice, embedded in the LR White (London Resin), and polymerized in 50&#x00B0;C for 24 h. Semithin sections of about 1 &#x00B5;m were cut using the MTX ultramicrotome (Elexience). The TUNEL assay was performed using the DeadEnd Fluorometric TUNEL system (Promega) according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. Slides were immediately stained with 10 &#x03BC;g mL<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">PI</xref> and mounted with SlowFade Gold antifade reagent (Invitrogen). Samples were analyzed under confocal microscopy as described above, observing fluorescein isothiocyanate green fluorescence to find fragmented DNA signals and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">PI</xref> fluorescence to view the nuclear location.</p><p>Sequence data in this article can be found in the Arabidopsis Genome Initiative or GenBank/EMBL databases under the following accession numbers: At3g46560 (<italic>AtTIM9</italic>, also known as <italic>EMB2474</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Tzafrir et al., 2004</xref>) and At2g29530 (<italic>AtTIM10</italic>).</p></sec><sec id="s29"><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> Complementation assays of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> Expression data of <italic>AtTIM9</italic> and <italic>AtTIM10</italic> from public databases.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S3.</bold></ext-link> GUS staining in the <italic>ProAtTIM9</italic>::GUS and <italic>ProAtTIM10</italic>::GUS transgenic plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S4.</bold></ext-link> AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 are conserved among eukaryotes.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S5.</bold></ext-link> Homology modeling of AtTIM9 and AtTIM10.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S6.</bold></ext-link> Immunoblot analysis of AtTIM9-EGFP and AtTIM10-EGFP fusion proteins.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S7.</bold></ext-link> Colocalization of AtTIM9 and AtTIM10 in mitochondria.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S1.</bold></ext-link> Transmission of the <italic>tim9-1</italic>/<italic>+</italic>, <italic>tim9-2</italic>/<italic>+</italic>, and <italic>tim10</italic>/<italic>+</italic> mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S2.</bold></ext-link> Primers used in the experiments.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.114.242560/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Materials and Methods S1.</bold></ext-link> Supplemental methods.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the Nottingham Arabidopsis Stock Centre (University of Nottingham), the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center (Ohio State University), and the SeedGene project (Meinke laboratory, Oklahoma State University) for kindly providing mutant seeds used in this study, Zhiyin Song (Wuhan University) for experimental instruction in mitochondria, Yingguo Zhu (Wuhan University) for providing <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">BiFC</xref> vectors, and Zhiyong Gao (Wuhan University) for sharing coimmunoprecipitation methods.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the National Basic Research Program of China (grant nos. 2012CB944801 and 2013CB126903) and the Key Grant Project of the Chinese Ministry of Education (grant no. 311026).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[C]</label><p>Some figures in this article are displayed in color online but in black and white in the print edition.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn4"><label>[OPEN]</label><p>Articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Endres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirrenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lottspeich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Neupert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Tim9, a new component of the TIM22.54 translocase in mitochondria</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>319</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Stroud</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Frazier</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chacinska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulbis</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Structural and functional requirements for activity of the Tim9-Tim10 complex in mitochondrial protein import</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>769</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>779</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothbauer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;hlenbein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerbitz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Neupert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The mitochondrial TIM22 preprotein translocase is highly conserved throughout the eukaryotic kingdom</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source> <volume>464</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>47</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Muralla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Requirement of aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases for gametogenesis and embryo development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>866</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>878</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Grini</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnittger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Endosperm: an integrator of seed growth and development</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>664</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>670</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Production of reactive oxygen species, impairment of photosynthetic function and dynamic changes in mitochondria are early events in cadmium-induced cell death in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Biol Cell</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>643</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The protein-import apparatus of plant mitochondria</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>209</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>274</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Heisler</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hej&#x00E1;tko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Benkov&#x00E1;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>In situ hybridization for mRNA detection in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> tissue sections</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1462</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1467</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial genomes: anything goes</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>709</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>716</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Murcha</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>An in silico analysis of the mitochondrial protein import apparatus of plants</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chacinska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Milenkovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lithgow</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfanner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Importing mitochondrial proteins: machineries and mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>628</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>644</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Distribution and change patterns of free IAA, ABP 1 and PM H&#x207A;-ATPase during ovary and ovule development of Nicotiana tabacum L</article-title>. <source>J Plant Physiol</source> <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>136</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Leuenberger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppliger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The Tim9p-Tim10p complex binds to the transmembrane domains of the ADP/ATP carrier</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>942</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>953</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dabir</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Setoguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Wongkongkathep</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Damoiseaux</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Teitell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A small molecule inhibitor of redox-regulated protein translocation into mitochondria</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>92</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edinger</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Death by design: apoptosis, necrosis and autophagy</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>663</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>669</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyznik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kachman</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Nuclear genes that encode mitochondrial proteins for DNA and RNA metabolism are clustered in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1619</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1631</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mignotte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vayssi&#x00E8;re</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial reactive oxygen species in cell death signaling</article-title>. <source>Biochimie</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>141</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mannella</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The internal structure of mitochondria</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>319</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>324</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneitz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The molecular and genetic basis of ovule and megagametophyte development</article-title>. <source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>238</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuromori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Imura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>SD3, an Arabidopsis thaliana homolog of TIM21, affects intracellular ATP levels and seedling development</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>471</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Damoiseaux</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Glavin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dabir</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Substrate specificity of the TIM22 mitochondrial import pathway revealed with small molecule inhibitor of protein translocation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>9578</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9583</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hruz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Laule</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wessendorp</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleuler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oertle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Widmayer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruissem</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Genevestigator v3: a reference expression database for the meta-analysis of transcriptomes</article-title>. <source>Adv Bioinformatics</source> <volume>2008</volume>: <fpage>420747</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Belmonte</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Indispensable roles of plastids in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Curr Genomics</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>338</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>349</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Localization of an arabinogalactan protein epitope and the effects of Yariv phenylglycoside during zygotic embryo development of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source> <volume>229</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>31</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarosch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x00F6;del</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweyen</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A soluble 12-kDa protein of the mitochondrial intermembrane space, Mrs11p, is essential for mitochondrial biogenesis and viability of yeast cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source> <volume>255</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>165</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenik</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillmor</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukowitz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Embryonic patterning in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>236</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>EMBRYONIC FACTOR 31 encodes a tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase that is essential for seed development</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Rep</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>8297</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8305</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Does the plant mitochondrion integrate cellular stress and regulate programmed cell death?</article-title> <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>230</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kenrick</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>The origin and early evolution of plants on land</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>389</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>39</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarosch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokatlidis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweyen</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year><comment>a</comment>) <article-title>Import of mitochondrial carriers mediated by essential proteins of the intermembrane space</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>373</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppliger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarosch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolfini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Junne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokatlidis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year><comment>b</comment>) <article-title>Tim9p, an essential partner subunit of Tim10p for the import of mitochondrial carrier proteins</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>6477</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6486</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hongo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoneda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis mitochondrial protein TIM50 affects hypocotyl cell elongation through intracellular ATP level</article-title>. <source>Plant Sci</source> <volume>183</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>217</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Narsai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Delannoy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraud</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Nucleotide and RNA metabolism prime translational initiation in the earliest events of mitochondrial biogenesis during Arabidopsis germination</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>158</volume>: <fpage>1610</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1627</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Heazlewood</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Clifton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A transcriptomic and proteomic characterization of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mitochondrial protein import apparatus and its response to mitochondrial dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>789</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mowday</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Zinc-dependent intermembrane space proteins stimulate import of carrier proteins into plant mitochondria</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>566</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Murcha</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The mitochondrial protein import machinery of plants (MPIMP) database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>325</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>327</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Replication factor C1 (RFC1) is required for double-strand break repair during meiotic homologous recombination in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>165</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Genome-wide identification, classification, and expression analysis of the arabinogalactan protein gene family in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>2647</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2668</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansfield</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Briarty</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Early embryogenesis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. II. The developing embryo</article-title>. <source>Can J Bot</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>476</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiol</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundaresan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabaleta</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagnussat</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>oiwa, a female gametophytic mutant impaired in a mitochondrial manganese-superoxide dismutase, reveals crucial roles for reactive oxygen species during embryo sac development and fertilization in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1573</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1591</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez-F&#x00E1;bregas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x00ED;az-Moreno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x00E1;lez-Arzola</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Janocha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Herv&#x00E1;s</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhardt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x00ED;az-Quintana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>De la Rosa</surname><given-names>M&#x00C1;</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>New Arabidopsis thaliana cytochrome c partners: a look into the elusive role of cytochrome c in programmed cell death in plants</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>3666</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3676</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial biogenesis and function in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>The Arabidopsis Book</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e0111</fpage>, doi/10.1199/tab.0111</citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mogensen</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The hows and whys of cytoplasmic inheritance in seed plants</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source> <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>383</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>404</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms for independent cytoplasmic inheritance of mitochondria and plastids in angiosperms</article-title>. <source>J Plant Res</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>199</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neupert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Translocation of proteins into mitochondria</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>723</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>749</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niklas</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutschera</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The evolution of the land plant life cycle</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>185</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>41</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamukai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nojiri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamane</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The AtPPT1 gene encoding 4-hydroxybenzoate polyprenyl diphosphate transferase in ubiquinone biosynthesis is required for embryo development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>577</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paschen</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothbauer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x00E1;ldi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Neupert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The role of the TIM8-13 complex in the import of Tim23 into mitochondria</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>6392</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6400</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Camougrand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Manon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x00F4;rte-Real</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>ADP/ATP carrier is required for mitochondrial outer membrane permeabilization and cytochrome c release in yeast apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>571</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>582</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rehling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Model</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovermann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sickmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x00FC;hlbrandt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Truscott</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfanner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Protein insertion into the mitochondrial inner membrane by a twin-pore translocase</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>299</volume>: <fpage>1747</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1751</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Janes</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pehar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Monette</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Selective fluorescent imaging of superoxide in vivo using ethidium-based probes</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>15038</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15043</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roesch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tranebjaerg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Human deafness dystonia syndrome is caused by a defect in assembly of the DDP1/TIMM8a-TIMM13 complex</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>477</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>486</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The egg cell: development and role in fertilization and early embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1349</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1359</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherratt</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Mitochondria: structure and function</article-title>. <source>Rev Neurol (Paris)</source> <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>430</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sirrenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Endres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x00F6;lsch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Neupert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Carrier protein import into mitochondria mediated by the intermembrane proteins Tim10/Mrs11 and Tim12/Mrs5</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>391</volume>: <fpage>912</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>915</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sokol</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sztolsztener</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasilewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chacinska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial protein translocases for survival and wellbeing</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source> <volume>588</volume>: <fpage>2484</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2495</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tranebjaerg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Ghelue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vnencak-Jones</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sund</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Elgjo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakobsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Warburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuglsang-Frederiksen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Neuronal cell death in the visual cortex is a prominent feature of the X-linked recessive mitochondrial deafness-dystonia syndrome caused by mutations in the TIMM8a gene</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmic Genet</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>223</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Truscott</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiedemann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Meisinger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfanner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Mitochondrial import of the ADP/ATP carrier: the essential TIM complex of the intermembrane space is required for precursor release from the TOM complex</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>7780</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7789</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzafrir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pena-Muralla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickerman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>McElver</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Identification of genes required for embryo development in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>1206</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1220</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Breusegem</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dat</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Reactive oxygen species in plant cell death</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>141</volume>: <fpage>384</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>390</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Doorn</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Beers</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dangl</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin-Tong</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallois</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara-Nishimura</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawai-Yamada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Morphological classification of plant cell deaths</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Differ</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1241</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1246</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Doorn</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Woltering</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Many ways to exit? Cell death categories in plants</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>122</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vazzola</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Losa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Soave</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Murgia</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Knockout of frataxin gene causes embryo lethality in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source> <volume>581</volume>: <fpage>667</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>672</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vianello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zancani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peresson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrussa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Casolo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraj&#x0148;&#x00E1;kov&#x00E1;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Patui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Braidot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Macr&#x00EC;</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Plant mitochondrial pathway leading to programmed cell death</article-title>. <source>Physiol Plant</source> <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>242</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>252</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaban</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x00FC;tze</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Batistic</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Weckermann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x00E4;ke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Blazevic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Grefen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Oecking</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Visualization of protein interactions in living plant cells using bimolecular fluorescence complementation</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>428</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>438</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraud</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Elhafez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Narsai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Murcha</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Dual location of the mitochondrial preprotein transporters B14.7 and Tim23-2 in complex I and the TIM17:23 complex in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> links mitochondrial activity and biogenesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>2675</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2695</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulbis</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Crystal structure of the mitochondrial chaperone TIM9.10 reveals a six-bladed &#x03B1;-propeller</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>133</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiedemann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfanner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chacinska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Chaperoning through the mitochondrial intermembrane space</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>148</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadegari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Paiva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Koltunow</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Apuya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Cell differentiation and morphogenesis are uncoupled in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> raspberry embryos</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1713</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1729</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinke</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Embryogenesis in angiosperms: development of the suspensor</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1371</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1381</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis mesophyll protoplasts: a versatile cell system for transient gene expression analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1565</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1572</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>EMBRYONIC FACTOR 19 encodes a pentatricopeptide repeat protein that is essential for the initiation of zygotic embryogenesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Integr Plant Biol</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>64</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zamzami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Castedo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Decaudin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Macho</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Susin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>PX</given-names></name><name><surname>Mignotte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroemer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Sequential reduction of mitochondrial transmembrane potential and generation of reactive oxygen species in early programmed cell death</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source> <volume>182</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>377</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Roles of extensins in cotyledon primordium formation and shoot apical meristem activity in Nicotiana tabacum</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>4045</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4058</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Direct comparison of GAPDH, &#x03B2;-actin, cyclophilin, and 28S rRNA as internal standards for quantifying RNA levels under hypoxia</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source> <volume>259</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>526</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
