<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">213009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.213009</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>GENES, DEVELOPMENT, AND EVOLUTION</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ubiquitin-Specific Proteases UBP12 and UBP13 Act in Circadian Clock and Photoperiodic Flowering Regulation in Arabidopsis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[OA]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Xia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Falong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn2"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yue</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Yongming</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Yanyuan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Shuaibin</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Qi</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Xiekui</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Shuzhi</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Bin</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Xiaodong</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Xiaofeng</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff1">State Key Laboratory of Plant Genomics and National Center for Plant Gene Research, Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100101, China (Xia C., F.L., Y.X., Y.K., S.Zha., Q.Q., Xie.C., S.Zhe., X.Cao)</aff><aff id="aff2">Hebei Key Laboratory of Molecular Cell Biology, College of Biological Sciences, Hebei Normal University, Shijiazhuang, Hebei 050016, China (Y.L., X.X.)</aff><aff id="aff3">University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Yuquan Road, Beijing 100039, China (Y.X., Y.K., S.Zha., Q.Q., Xie.C.); and</aff><aff id="aff4">Institute of Crop Sciences, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing 100081, China (B.L.)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Corresponding author; e-mail <email>xcui@genetics.ac.cn</email>.</corresp><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the National Basic Research Program of China (grant nos. 2011CB915401 to X.Cao and 2013CB967302 to Xia C.) and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant nos. 30971619 to Xia C., 30930048 to X.Cao, and 30971507 to X.X.).</p></fn><fn id="afn1" fn-type="equal"><label>2</label><p>These authors contributed equally to the article.</p></fn><fn id="afn2" fn-type="present-address"><label>3</label><p>Present address: Program in Cellular and Molecular Medicine, Boston Children&#x2019;s Hospital, Boston, MA, 02215.</p></fn><fn id="afn4"><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Xia Cui (<email>xcui@genetics.ac.cn</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[OA]</label><p>Open Access articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.213009">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.112.213009</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>06</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>05</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>162</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>897</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>04</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&copy; 2013 American Society of Plant Biologists. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p></p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="PP_213009_ic1.gif"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><italic>Deubiquitination plays a role in daylength measurement to regulate flowering time.</italic></p></abstract><abstract><p>Protein ubiquitination is involved in most cellular processes. In Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), ubiquitin-mediated protein degradation regulates the stability of key components of the circadian clock feedback loops and the photoperiodic flowering pathway. Here, we identified two ubiquitin-specific proteases, UBP12 and UBP13, involved in circadian clock and photoperiodic flowering regulation. Double mutants of <italic>ubp12</italic> and <italic>ubp13</italic> display pleiotropic phenotypes, including early flowering and short periodicity of circadian rhythms. In <italic>ubp12 ubp13</italic> double mutants, <italic>CONSTANS</italic> (<italic>CO</italic>) transcript rises earlier than that of wild-type plants during the day, which leads to increased expression of <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic>. This, and analysis of <italic>ubp12 co</italic> mutants, indicates that UBP12 and UBP13 regulate photoperiodic flowering through a CO-dependent pathway. In addition, UBP12 and UBP13 regulate the circadian rhythm of clock genes, including <italic>LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL</italic>, <italic>CIRCADIAN CLOCK ASSOCIATED1</italic>, and <italic>TIMING OF CAB EXPRESSION1</italic>. Furthermore, UBP12 and UBP13 are circadian controlled. Therefore, our work reveals a role for two deubiquitinases, UBP12 and UBP13, in the control of the circadian clock and photoperiodic flowering, which extends our understanding of ubiquitin in daylength measurement in higher plants.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">DUB</term><def id="def1"><p>deubiquitinating enzyme</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">CFP</term><def id="def2"><p>cyan fluorescent protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">T-DNA</term><def id="def3"><p>transfer DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">LD</term><def id="def4"><p>long-day</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">SD</term><def id="def5"><p>short-day</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">qRT-PCR</term><def id="def6"><p>quantitative reverse transcriptase PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">LL</term><def id="def7"><p>constant white light</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8">cDNA</term><def id="def8"><p>complementary DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9">ZT</term><def id="def9"><p>Zeitgeber time</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>Protein ubiquitination is a critical posttranslational mechanism regulating diverse cellular processes and signal transduction pathways in eukaryotes. Ubiquitin protein is a 76-amino-acid-long polypeptide conserved throughout all eukaryotic organisms. Attachment of ubiquitin to a Lys residue in the substrate protein requires multiple steps catalysis by E1 activating, E2 conjugating, and E3 ligating enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Finley, 2009</xref>). Among these enzymes, E3 ligases are responsible for specific substrate recognition. According to their mechanisms of action and subunit composition, four main types of E3s have been identified in plants, including E3-associated protein carboxyl terminus, Really Interesting New Gene (RING), U-box, and cullin-RING ligases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Vierstra, 2009</xref>). In Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), more than 1,400 genes encode components of the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway, and 90% of these genes encode subunits of E3 ligases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Moon et al., 2004</xref>). In higher plants, E3 ligases play important roles in hormone responses, photomorphogenesis, senescence, circadian rhythm, and floral development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Moon et al., 2004</xref>). For example, CONSTITUTIVE PHOTOMORPHOGENESIS1 (COP1), a RING domain E3 ligase, plays extensive roles in light response and photomorphogenesis by targeting multiple proteins, such as LONG HYPOCOTYL5, Phytochrome A, and LONG AFTER FAR-RED LIGHT1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Lau and Deng, 2012</xref>). Moreover, COP1 also regulates the circadian clock and flowering time by destabilizing GIGANTEA (GI) and CONSTANS (CO; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Jang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Liu et al., 2008a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Yu et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>Ubiquitination is dynamic and reversible; the enzymatic reaction that opposes ubiquitin conjugation is deubiquitination. In human genome, 79 deubiquitinating enzymes (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">DUBs</xref>) were predicted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Nijman et al., 2005</xref>). Most <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">DUBs</xref>, roughly 80%, belong to four subfamilies with Cys active sites containing a highly conserved catalytic triad; these families are ubiquitin C-terminal hydrolases, ubiquitin-specific proteases (UBPs/USPs), ovarian tumor proteases, and Machado-Josephin domain proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Katz et al., 2010</xref>). A minor subfamily is the JAB1/MPN/MOV34 metalloenzyme, members of which have a zinc active site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Wing, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Reyes-Turcu et al., 2009</xref>). The USP family includes more than 50 members in humans and is the largest family of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">DUBs</xref>. USPs are involved in tumor suppression, DNA repair, neural stem cell progenitor maintenance, immune response, viral replication, and epigenetic control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Katz et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Nicholson and Suresh Kumar, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Neutzner and Neutzner, 2012</xref>).</p><p>Compared with the large numbers of E3 ligases, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">DUBs</xref> in Arabidopsis comprise a relatively smaller group. USPs, the largest subfamily, include 27 proteins with Cys- and His-box signature motifs, which have been predicted to confer deubiquitination activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Yan et al., 2000</xref>). Among these proteins, UBP2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Yan et al., 2000</xref>), UBP3, UBP4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Chandler et al., 1997</xref>), UBP12 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Ewan et al., 2011</xref>), UBP14 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Doelling et al., 2001</xref>), UBP15 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Liu et al., 2008b</xref>), and UBP26 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sridhar et al., 2007</xref>) were shown to be active enzymes in vitro. These UBPs are involved in different signaling pathways and cellular processes. For example, UBP1 and UBP2 are required for the resistance to the amino acid analog Canavanine, but the single and double mutants have no obvious phenotype under normal growth conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Yan et al., 2000</xref>). UBP3 and UBP4 are homologs and share 93% amino acid sequence identity; they redundantly affect pollen development and transmission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Chandler et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Doelling et al., 2007</xref>). The <italic>ubp14</italic> mutant shows embryonic lethality at the globular stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Doelling et al., 2001</xref>). The <italic>ubp15</italic> mutant displays leaf developmental defects and other phenotypes, such as early flowering, weak apical dominance, and reduced fertility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Liu et al., 2008b</xref>). UBP26 can remove the monoubiquitin at Lys-143 on H2B and controls heterochromatic silencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Sridhar et al., 2007</xref>). The <italic>ubp26</italic> mutant also causes early flowering by repression of <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS C</italic> (<italic>FLC</italic>) transcription and seed developmental defects by activation of the imprinted gene <italic>PHERES1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Luo et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Schmitz et al., 2009</xref>). UBP12 in Arabidopsis or NtUBP12 in tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>) acts as a negative regulator in plant immunity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Ewan et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, unraveling the biological functions of UBPs and their substrates in Arabidopsis will add another layer to our understanding of the ubiquitination dynamics in plant development.</p><p>In this work, we report a novel role for two <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">DUBs</xref>, UBP12 and UBP13. These two enzymes are themselves circadian regulated, and the corresponding hypomorphic alleles display a short period of the circadian clock. Study of their roles in flowering time indicates that they repress premature flowering through the photoperiod pathway. Thus, we demonstrate that deubiquitination is also important for circadian clock and photoperiodic flowering regulation.</p><sec id="s1" sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2"><title>UBP12 and UBP13 Confer Deubiquitination Activities in Vitro</title><p>UBP12 (At5g06600) and UBP13 (At3g11910) are two Arabidopsis homologs of human ubiquitin-specific protease USP7/HAUSP (first identified as a herpes virus-associated cellular factor; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Everett et al., 1997</xref>). UBP12 and UBP13 share high amino acid sequence similarity, with 91% sequence identity, suggesting that their function may be redundant. They also share 34% amino acid sequence identity with USP7 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>) and have the conserved Cys- and His-box signature motifs, indicating that they have potential deubiquitination activity. At the N termini, these three proteins contain a meprin and tumor necrosis factor receptor-associated factor homology (MATH) domain, which is not found in other Arabidopsis UBP proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>UBP12 and UBP13 have deubiquitination activities. A, Schematic diagram of the UBP12 and UBP13 protein structures. The MATH domain, conserved Cys-box, and His-box are shown as squares or rectangles. The star indicates the Cys residue required for enzymatic activity. B, UBP12 and UBP13 are active <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">DUBs</xref>. In vivo cleavage of hexameric polyubiquitin (UBQ10, left) and ubiquitin extension protein (UBQ1, right). UBP12, UBP13, and their mutants UBP12C208S and UBP13C207S were coexpressed with the substrates UBQ1 and UBQ10 in <italic>E. coli</italic>; the cleavage products were detected by immunoblot analyses with anti-ubiquitin antibodies. The positions of the substrates and cleaved products are indicated by arrows.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213009_f1"></graphic></fig><p>To determine whether UBP12 and UBP13 have deubiquitination activity in vitro, we performed enzymatic activity assays using the hexameric polyubiquitin protein UBQ10 and ubiquitin extension protein UBQ1, which bears the 52 amino acid ribosomal protein appended to a single ubiquitin moiety as substrates. When wild-type UBP12 or UBP13 and their mutant forms UBP12C208S and UBP13C207S, in which conserved Cys of the enzymatic active sites were substituted by Ser, were coexpressed with UBQ10 and UBQ1 in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Yan et al., 2000</xref>), we can detect the cleaved products by immunoblotting analysis with ubiquitin antibody. The wild-type UBP12 and UBP13 were capable of cleaving ubiquitin from both UBQ10 and UBQ1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>). However, neither of the mutants, UBP12C208S or UBP13C207S, showed any enzymatic activity, indicating that activities of UBP12 and UBP13 were dependent on the conserved Cys residue. This result is consistent with previous findings that UBP12 can remove ubiquitin from Lys-48-linked ubiquitin chain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Ewan et al., 2011</xref>). All of these results demonstrate that UBP12 and UBP13 are bona fide <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">DUBs</xref> in Arabidopsis.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>UBP12 and UBP13 Are Ubiquitously Expressed and Localize to Both Cytoplasm and Nucleus</title><p>To figure out the biological functions of UBP12 and UBP13 in plant development, we first determined <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> expression patterns by examining the GUS signal in transgenic plants with <italic>GUS</italic> expressed under the control of the <italic>UBP12</italic> or <italic>UBP13</italic> promoter. <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> were both expressed in the hypocotyl, cotyledon, leaf, root, and inflorescence, especially in the vascular part of these tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A&#x2013;H</xref>). However, a few differences were observed. First, <italic>UBP12</italic> was expressed in hypocotyl and cotyledon of 4-d-old plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>), whereas <italic>UBP13</italic> was mainly expressed in hypocotyl, but not cotyledon, of 4-d-old seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2F</xref>). Second, in flowers, <italic>UBP12</italic> was expressed in carpel, sepal, and pollen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2D</xref>), whereas <italic>UBP13</italic> was mainly expressed only in the pollen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2H</xref>). The highly overlapping expression patterns of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> in Arabidopsis suggest that they may be functionally redundant in regulating plant development.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> have similar expression pattern and protein localization. A to D, GUS staining of dark-grown seedlings (A), 4-d-old seedlings under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> condition (B), 14-d-old seedlings under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> condition (C), and inflorescences (D) of the transformants containing <italic>UBP12pro</italic>:GUS. E to H, GUS staining of dark-grown seedlings (E), 4-d-old seedlings under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> condition (F), 14-d-old seedlings under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> condition (G), and inflorescences (H) of the transformants containing <italic>UBP13pro</italic>:GUS. I to L, UBP12 fused to GFP (K) and UBP13 fused to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">CFP</xref> (L) localize to the nuclei and cytoplasm; <italic>35Spro</italic>:GFP (I) and <italic>35Spro</italic>:<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">CFP</xref> (J) were used as control. Bar = 200 &#x00B5;m. UBP12/UBP13 protein was detected in both cytoplasmic and nuclear fractions. Histone H3 and phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase (PEPC) were used as control for nuclear or cytoplasmic fraction, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213009_f2"></graphic></fig><p>To examine the subcellular localizations of UBP12 and UBP13 proteins, we generated green fluorescent protein (GFP)- and cyan fluorescent protein (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">CFP</xref>)-tagged UBP12 and UBP13. In UBP12-GFP and UBP13-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">CFP</xref> transgenic plants, we observed that UBP12 and UBP13 were located in both cytoplasm and nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, K and L</xref>), which was similar to the GFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2I</xref>) and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">CFP</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2J</xref>) alone in 35S:GFP and 35S:<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">CFP</xref> transgenic plants. Moreover, we detected the UBP12/UBP13 protein in separated cytoplasmic or nuclear fractions using UBP antibodies. Consistent with our observation in these transgenic plants, the UBP12/UBP13 can be detected in both cytoplasm and nucleus, though more UBP12/UBP13 can be detected in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2M</xref>). These results suggest that UBP12 and UBP13 might affect substrates in both the cytoplasmic and nucleic compartments.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Mutations of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> Exhibit Pleiotropic Phenotypes</title><p>To investigate the biological functions of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic>, we isolated mutants from transfer DNA (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref>) insertion populations of Arabidopsis. Two insertional mutants of <italic>UBP12</italic> were identified, and the alleles were named as <italic>ubp12-1</italic> (GABI_244E11) and <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> (GABI_742C10; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>, top); the alleles contain <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref> insertions in exons 15 and 28, respectively. Three mutant alleles of <italic>UBP13</italic> were identified and designated as <italic>ubp13-1</italic> (SALK_128312), <italic>ubp13-2</italic> (SALK_024054), and <italic>ubp13-3</italic> (SALK_132368; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A</xref>, bottom). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNAs</xref> were inserted in the fifth, 10th, and 21st exons of these three mutants, respectively.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Mutations of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> affect plant development and flowering time. A, Schematic diagrams of the <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> gene structures, with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref> insertion sites indicated. Black boxes indicate exons, white boxes indicate untranslated regions, and lines indicate introns. B, Northern blots showing the expression levels of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref> insertion mutants (top). Ribosomal RNA stained with methylene blue was used as loading control (bottom). C to L, Phenotypes of 24-d-old seedlings of the wild type (C), <italic>ubp12-1</italic> (D), <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> (E), <italic>ubp13-1</italic> (F), <italic>ubp13-2</italic> (G), <italic>ubp13-3</italic> (H), <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-1</italic> (I), <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-2</italic> (J), <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> (K), and <italic>ubp12-1 ubp13-3</italic> (L). Bar = 1 cm. M to R, Phenotypes of the wild type (M), <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> (N), <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-1</italic> (O), <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-2</italic> (P), <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> (Q), and <italic>ubp12-1 ubp13-3</italic> (R) after bolting. Bar = 1 cm. S and T, Statistical analysis of leaf numbers of <italic>ubp12-2w</italic>, <italic>ubp13-3</italic>, <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> double mutants, and <italic>ubp12-1</italic> under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> (S) and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> (T) conditions compared with wild-type plants. Values are means &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of at least 20 plants. WT, Wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213009_f3"></graphic></fig><p>By northern-blot analysis, no accumulation of full-length UBP12 mRNA was detected in <italic>ubp12-1</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> mutant plants, and no full-length UBP13 mRNA was detected in <italic>ubp13-1</italic>, <italic>ubp13-2</italic>, and <italic>ubp13-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>). However, one smaller segment was found in <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> and <italic>ubp13-3</italic> mutant plants, suggesting that <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> and <italic>ubp13-3</italic> are not null alleles for <italic>UBP12</italic> or <italic>UBP13</italic>. In the <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> mutant, surprisingly, the mRNA level of <italic>UBP13</italic> was also decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3B</xref>), which might result from high transcription of the 3&#x2032; primer region of <italic>UBP12</italic> in <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> causing suppression of <italic>UBP13</italic> in trans (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>), indicating that <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> is a weak double mutant, although there is only one <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref> insertion in the genome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S3</ext-link>). Therefore, we named it as <italic>ubp12-2w</italic>. Different from other single mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, C, D, F, G, and H</xref>) with no obvious developmental phenotypes, the <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> exhibited distinct phenotypes, including small plants, round leaves, short petioles, dwarfism, and more branches after bolting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, E and N</xref>).</p><p>The similar expression patterns of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A&#x2013;H</xref>) indicate that they could have redundant biological functions in regulating plant development. To test this, we generated double mutants and obtained <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, I and O</xref>), <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, J and P</xref>), <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, K and Q</xref>), and <italic>ubp12-1 ubp13-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, L and R</xref>). All these double mutants displayed similar but much more severe phenotypes than <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, E and N</xref>), including smaller plants, rounder leaves, shorter petioles at seedling stage, more severe dwarf statures, and more bushy plants at mature stage. Among these viable double mutants, <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> showed weakest developmental phenotypes in every aspect we observed, which is consistent with the fact that partial transcripts can be detected in <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> or <italic>ubp13-3</italic>. Fertility of all these double mutants was dramatically decreased. Only <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> set enough seeds for further research, whereas <italic>ubp12-1 ubp13-3</italic> was completely infertile. The homozygous <italic>ubp12-1 ubp13-1</italic> and <italic>ubp12-1 ubp13-2</italic> double mutants could not be obtained, suggesting that these two genes are important for Arabidopsis embryo development and/or male/female gametophyte function. Taken together, we conclude that <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> are involved in diverse developmental processes.</p><p>In addition to the developmental patterning defects of <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic>, the single mutants of <italic>ubp12-1</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> and the double mutant <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> also showed early-flowering phenotype under both long-day (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref>; 16-h light/8-h dark; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3S</xref>) and short-day (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref>; 8-h-light/16-h-dark) conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3T</xref>) compared with wild-type plants. The phenotypes were profounder under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref>. The <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> mutant flowered after forming only about 10 leaves under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref>, which is similar to the mutants under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> condition, indicating that the double mutant is insensitive to photoperiod. The <italic>ubp12-1 ubp13-3</italic> double mutant also showed early flowering, if only according to leaf numbers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4, A and B</ext-link>). However, <italic>ubp12-1 ubp13-3</italic> displayed drastic developmental retardation under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref>, suggesting that it is not reasonable for us to analyze the flowering time (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S4C</ext-link>). Taken together, these results indicate that <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">DUBs</xref> UBP12 and UBP13 are involved in the photoperiodic floral transition pathway.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Role of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> in Photoperiodic Flowering Requires <italic>CO</italic></title><p>In Arabidopsis, transcriptional regulation of <italic>CO</italic> is crucial for daylength measurement. <italic>CO</italic> is activated under proper daylength and subsequently up-regulates the expression of <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (<italic>FT</italic>) to promote flowering. Changes in <italic>CO</italic> transcription are the key of many daylength-insensitive mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Yanovsky and Kay, 2002</xref>). To determine if the early-flowering phenotype caused by mutations of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> depends on <italic>CO</italic> and <italic>FT</italic>, we measured <italic>CO</italic> and <italic>FT</italic> transcripts by quantitative reverse transcription PCR (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">qRT-PCR</xref>) at 4-h intervals for 24 h under both <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions. In <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> double mutants, the expression level of <italic>CO</italic> started to increase at 4 or 8 h after dawn, which was earlier than that in wild-type plants under both <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>, left) and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>, left) conditions. This led to elevated <italic>CO</italic> expression during the day and then activated <italic>FT</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>, right), which was more evident in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). By contrast, the transcription of <italic>FLC</italic> was not affected in <italic>ubp12</italic> or <italic>ubp13</italic> single and double mutants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S5</ext-link>). These results indicate that UBP12 and UBP13 act in the photoperiodic flowering pathway by regulating <italic>CO</italic> and <italic>FT</italic> transcriptions.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>UBP12 and UBP13 regulate photoperiodic flowering. A, Expression patterns and transcript levels of <italic>CO</italic> (left) and <italic>FT</italic> (right) under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> condition in the wild type, <italic>ubp12-2w</italic>, <italic>ubp13-3</italic>, and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> double mutant. Values are means &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of three independent experiments. B, Expression patterns and transcript levels of <italic>CO</italic> (left) and <italic>FT</italic> (right) under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> condition in the wild type, <italic>ubp12-2w</italic>, <italic>ubp13-3</italic>, and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> double mutant. Values are means &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of three independent experiments. C, Statistical analysis of leaf numbers of <italic>ubp12-2w co</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w gi-4</italic> double mutants under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> condition. Values are means &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of at least 20 plants. D, Statistical analysis of leaf numbers of <italic>ubp12-2w svp32</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3 svp32</italic> plants under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> condition. Values are means &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of at least 20 plants. WT, Wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213009_f4"></graphic></fig><p>Genetic analysis of <italic>ubp12-2w co</italic> double mutants further supported our results. Both the <italic>ubp12-2w co</italic> double mutants and <italic>co</italic> single mutants flowered after forming around 30 leaves, but the <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> mutant flowered with only around 10 leaves under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>). This indicates that <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> act upstream of <italic>CO</italic>. <italic>GI</italic> is an upstream regulator of <italic>CO</italic> and positively regulates <italic>CO</italic> transcription. So we also analyzed <italic>ubp12-2w gi-4</italic> mutants and found that they flowered as late as <italic>gi-4</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S6</ext-link>), indicating that <italic>GI</italic> is also downstream of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> in regulating photoperiodic flowering. We also tested one MADS box protein involved in photoperiodic flowering regulation, SHORT VEGETATIVE PHASE (SVP), which negatively regulates <italic>FT</italic> expression in a <italic>CO</italic>-independent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Kim et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Fujiwara et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Li et al., 2008</xref>). <italic>ubp12-2w svp32</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3 svp32</italic> showed earlier flowering than <italic>svp32</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> or <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4D</xref>), indicating that UBP12/UBP13 and SVP regulate photoperiodic flowering in parallel. These genetic interactions suggest that <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> regulate flowering time through <italic>GI</italic> and <italic>CO</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Mutations of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> Result in Altered Circadian Rhythm</title><p>In the photoperiodic flowering pathway, the circadian oscillators take part in the daylength measurement by regulating <italic>CO</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Imaizumi and Kay, 2006</xref>). The plant circadian clock is composed of multiple feedback loops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Harmer, 2009</xref>). In Arabidopsis, two MYB transcription factors, CIRCADIAN CLOCK-ASSOCIATED1 (CCA1) and LATE ELONGATED HYPOCOTYL (LHY), are expressed in the morning. They can bind to the promoter of the evening gene <italic>TIMING OF CAB EXPRESSION1</italic> (<italic>TOC1</italic>) to repress its transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Alabad&#x00ED; et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Carr&#x00E9; and Kim, 2002</xref>). In turn, TOC1 regulates the expressions of <italic>CCA1</italic> and <italic>LHY</italic> as a repressor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Gendron et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Huang et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Pokhilko et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>We examined whether mutation of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> affects circadian rhythm and the expression patterns of these core clock genes. The rhythmic accumulations of <italic>LHY</italic> and <italic>TOC1</italic> were tested by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">qRT-PCR</xref> in <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> mutants. Under constant white light (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">LL</xref>) free-running condition, the periods of <italic>LHY</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>) and <italic>TOC1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>) expression were shortened by 4 h in <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> double mutants compared with that of wild-type plants. In addition, the transcription level of <italic>TOC1</italic> was obviously increased in <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5B</xref>). Moreover, the period of <italic>CCA1</italic> promoter:<italic>LUCIFERASE</italic> (<italic>pCCA1</italic>:<italic>LUC</italic>) circadian rhythm was also shortened by 4 h in <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 23) and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> mutants (<italic>n</italic> = 7) compared with the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5, C and D</xref>). Taken together, these results indicate that <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> function in the periodic control of the expression of core clock oscillators in Arabidopsis. Then we tested whether <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> are themselves circadianly regulated. mRNA levels of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> oscillated under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">LL</xref> condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5E</xref>). The transcripts of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> increased and reached their highest level at 4 h (Zeitgeber time [<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ZT</xref>] 28) and then decreased and reached their lowest level around 16 h (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ZT</xref> 40). Accumulation of UBP12 and UBP13 proteins was also highest at 8 h (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ZT</xref> 32) and lowest at 16 h (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ZT</xref> 40), which is similar to their mRNA levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5F</xref>). These results demonstrate that UBP12 and UBP13 are under circadian control. Taken together, we show that UBP12 and UBP13 are essential for proper circadian rhythm.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Mutation of UBP12 and UBP13 shortens the circadian period under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">LL</xref>. The expression patterns of <italic>LHY</italic> (A) and <italic>TOC1</italic> (B) under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">LL</xref> condition were analyzed by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">qRT-PCR</xref>. Wild-type, <italic>ubp12-2w</italic>, and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> plants were grown for 10 d in 12-h-light/12-h-dark cycles before released to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">LL</xref> and sampled every 4 h from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ZT</xref>0. Circadian rhythm of <italic>pCCA1</italic>:<italic>LUC</italic> was detected in transgenic seedlings in <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 23; C) or <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 7; D). The <italic>pCCA1:LUC</italic> transgenic plants in <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> were grown for 7 or 15 d, respectively, in 12-h-light/12-h-dark cycles and transferred to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">LL</xref> at <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ZT</xref> 0. Relative amplitude error is a measure of the strength of the oscillation. Statistical analysis of period length showed that in each case, the periods of <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> were shorter than that of the wild type (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> expression levels were tested from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ZT</xref> 24 to 48 by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">qRT-PCR</xref> in wild-type plants (E). Values are means &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of three independent experiments. The protein level of UBP12/UBP13 under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">LL</xref> was tested by immunoblot using UBP12/UBP13 antibodies from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">ZT</xref> 24 to 48 (F). The arrow indicates the UBP protein position. The asterisk indicates the nonspecific band. H3 was used as the loading control. WT, Wild type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_213009_f5"></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The circadian clock coordinates diverse aspects of plant development with daily cycles and promotes their adaption to the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">McClung, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Nagel and Kay, 2012</xref>). In Arabidopsis, proteasomal degradation pathway functions in the circadian clock and photoperiodic flowering by regulating the stability of key components in these pathways. Our research identified two circadian-regulated ubiquitin-specific proteases, UBP12 and UBP13, functioning in photoperiodic flowering and the circadian clock, which broadened our understanding of the proteasomal degradation mechanism in these processes.</p><sec id="s8"><title>UBP12 and UBP13 in Regulating Diverse Aspects of Plant Development</title><p>The ubiquitin-proteasome pathway contributes significantly to various aspects of development in Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Moon et al., 2004</xref>). As a counterbalance to ubiquitination, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">DUBs</xref> should also regulate diverse developmental processes. UBP12 and UBP13 affect plant development extensively. In addition to their role in the circadian clock and flowering, UBP12 and UBP13 are required for immunity against virulent <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> in tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Ewan et al., 2011</xref>). It is very likely that UBP12 and UBP13 target key factors in these processes and regulate protein levels by counteracting ubiquitin-mediated degradation.</p><p>Phylogenetic analysis shows that UBP12 and UBP13 are similar to human USP7, which plays crucial roles in diverse cellular processes by deubiquitinating different substrates to regulate protein stability and subcellular localization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Li et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">van der Knaap et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">van der Horst et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Song et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Daubeuf et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Maertens et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Huang et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Khoronenkova et al., 2012</xref>). Therefore, like USP7, UBP12 and UBP13 might have a wide range of targets in different developmental processes. Identifying the substrates of UBP12 and UBP13 in the future will help us to understand how they contribute to various aspects of plant development.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>UBP12/UBP13 in Circadian Clock and Photoperiodic Flowering Time Regulation</title><p>Daylength measurement plays an essential role in plant growth and development. Plants use endogenous clocks to adjust their physiological and developmental stages according to the change of environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Harmer, 2009</xref>). In Arabidopsis, transcriptional regulation of <italic>CO</italic> is crucial in the daylength measurement. Under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref>, the expression of <italic>CO</italic> is repressed before dusk, and <italic>FT</italic> can only express at a low level, which is insufficient to induce flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Imaizumi and Kay, 2006</xref>). On the contrary, the <italic>ubp12 ubp13</italic> double mutant shows reduced sensitivity to daylength and results in advance expression of <italic>CO</italic> before dusk. As a result, <italic>FT</italic> is highly expressed in <italic>ubp12 ubp13</italic> double mutants, which leads to the early-flowering phenotype. Moreover, our results indicate that both UBP12 and UBP13 are required to maintain the appropriate expression phases of the circadian genes.</p><p>UBP12 and UBP13 are <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">DUBs</xref> and might act in circadian and photoperiodic flowering by altering the proteasomal degradation pathway. By now, there are four E3 ligases, FLAVIN-BINDING, KELCH REPEAT AND F-BOX1 (FKF1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Nelson et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Imaizumi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Sawa et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Fornara et al., 2009</xref>), ZEITLUPE (ZTL; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">M&#x00E1;s et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kiba et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Kim et al., 2007</xref>), LOV KELCH PROTEIN2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Baudry et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Takase et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Ito et al., 2012</xref>), and COP1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Jang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Liu et al., 2008a</xref>), shown to function in the plant circadian rhythm and photoperiodic flowering pathway.</p><p>The mutation of <italic>FKF1</italic> displays late flowering under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref>, and the day peak of <italic>CO</italic> appears 3 h later in <italic>fkf1</italic> mutants than in wild-type plants. In contrast with <italic>fkf1</italic>, the <italic>ubp12 ubp13</italic> double mutant is early flowering, and <italic>CO</italic> expression rises earlier in <italic>ubp12 ubp13</italic> double mutants than in the wild type under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref>. The <italic>ztl</italic> mutant exhibits long periodicity in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">LL</xref> and decreased amplitude of the circadian genes. By contrast, <italic>ubp12 ubp13</italic> double mutants have short periodicity, and the expression level of the circadian gene <italic>TOC1</italic> is increased. These observations suggest that UBP12 and UBP13 might counteract the functions of these F-box proteins. It would be interesting to test if UPB12 and UBP13 can regulate the ubiquitination and stability of the substrates of these F-box proteins in the future.</p><p>The <italic>cop1</italic> mutant shows short periodicity and early flowering under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions by affecting CO protein stability and altering the <italic>CO</italic> and <italic>LHY</italic> expression through impacting on GI degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Jang et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Liu et al., 2008a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Yu et al., 2008</xref>). Mutation of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> resulted in similar phenotypes as <italic>cop1</italic> regarding flowering time, <italic>CO</italic> expression, and changes in circadian rhythm. These similarities suggest that UBP12 and UBP13 are not likely to function antagonistically to COP1. It would be interesting to see how these biochemically opposite enzymes contribute the same way to the response to daylength measurement. Thus, understanding the relationship between UBP12/UBP13 and COP1 in the future could help us to understand the circadian clock and photoperiodic flowering regulations better.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s10" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s11"><title>Plant Materials and Growth Conditions</title><p>Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) ecotype Columbia wild-type and mutant plants were grown on vermiculite saturated with water under either <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> (16-h-light/8-h-dark) or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> (8-h-light/16-h-dark) conditions with an intensity of 80 to 120 &#x03BC;E m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> of white light at 23&#x00B0;C as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lu et al., 2011</xref>). <italic>ubp12-1</italic> (GABI_244E11), <italic>ubp12-2w</italic> (GABI_742C10), <italic>ubp13-1</italic> (SALK_128312), <italic>ubp13-2</italic> (SALK_024054), <italic>ubp13-3</italic> (SALK_132368), <italic>co</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Liu et al., 2008a</xref>), <italic>gi-4</italic>, and <italic>svp32</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Fujiwara et al., 2008</xref>) were used for genetics analysis. The primers used for genotyping are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Alignment Analysis</title><p>Amino acid sequences of UBP12, UBP13, and mammalian USP7 were aligned using Jalview software through ClustalW. The domains were analyzed by the Pfam protein families database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://pfam.sanger.ac.uk/">http://pfam.sanger.ac.uk/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>GUS Staining and GFP Location</title><p><italic>UBP12pro</italic>::GUS and <italic>UBP13pro</italic>::GUS transgenic (T3) lines were used to determine the expression pattern of <italic>UBP12/UBP13</italic> via histochemical GUS staining as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Niu et al., 2008</xref>). The promoters of <italic>UBP12</italic> and <italic>UBP13</italic> were amplified by primers CX3019 and CX2973 and CX2971 and CX2972, respectively, and cloned into p1391Z (XF388) vector. The complementary DNAs (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">cDNAs</xref>) of UBP12 and UBP13 were amplified by primers CX2969 and CX2970 and CX2967 and CX2968, respectively, and cloned into vectors pCAMBIA1300-35S-GFP (XF215) or pCAMBIA1300-35S-<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">CFP</xref> (XF953). The subcellular localization of UBP12 and UBP13 was performed by observing the roots of transgenic (T3) plants carrying C-terminal fusion of GFP to UBP12 and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">CFP</xref> to UBP13 driven by the 35S promoter and analyzed by confocal microscopy (Leica TCS SP5).</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Deubiquitin Activity Assay</title><p>The full-length <italic>UBP12</italic> or <italic>UBP13</italic> coding sequences were amplified by primers CX3090 and CX3092 or CX3090 and CX3091, respectively. Their mutant forms, <italic>UBP12C208S</italic> and <italic>UBP13C207S</italic>, were generated by QuikChange II Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Stratagene) using primers CX3287 and CX3288 and CX3285 and CX3286, respectively. These products were cloned into MBP-LIC (XF510) vector and then coexpressed with the substrates UBQ1 and UBQ10 in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Yan et al., 2000</xref>). Lysates were subjected to SDS-PAGE, transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride membranes, and detected by immunoblot with anti-ubiquitin antibodies. The primers used for these constructions are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>RNA Gel-Blot Analysis, DNA Gel-Blot Analysis, and Quantitative PCR</title><p>Total RNA was extracted using Trizol reagent (Invitrogen), 10 d after germination from whole seedlings grown under the indicated conditions (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref>, and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">LL</xref> conditions) on Murashige and Skoog plates. RNA (20 &#x00B5;g per lane) was separated in an agarose gel containing 1% (v/v) formaldehyde, blotted onto Hybond N+ membrane (GE Healthcare), and probed with the PCR-amplified DNA fragments using specific primer pairs (CX3977 and CX3118 for <italic>UBP12</italic> and CX3976 and CX3120 for <italic>UBP13</italic>). Total DNA was extracted using cetyl-trimethyl-ammonium bromide reagent and digested by the restriction enzyme <italic>Eco</italic>RI or <italic>Xho</italic>I, and then digested DNA was separated in an agarose gel, blotted onto a Hybond N+ membrane, and probed with the PCR-amplified 35S promoter using specific primer pairs CX2532 and CX2533. For <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">qRT-PCR</xref>, 2.0 &#x03BC;g total RNA was treated with DNaseI (Ambion), and then the first-strand <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">cDNA</xref> was synthesized by using a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">cDNA</xref> synthesis kit (Transgen). <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">qRT-PCR</xref> was performed using a CFX96 Real-Time PCR Instrument (Bio-Rad) with the SYBR Green reaction mix (Kangwei S-7567). Primers for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">qRT-PCR</xref> can be found in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Bioluminescence Measurement</title><p>For luciferase measurement, the <italic>pCCA1</italic>:<italic>LUC</italic> transgenic seedlings were entrained for 7 d or 15 d in 12-h-light/12-h-dark cycles at 22&#x00B0;C before transfer to continuous light. Since the first day in continuous light condition, seedlings were transferred to 96-well microplates (Perkin-Elmer) containing 200 &#x03BC;L Murashige and Skoog medium plus 2% (w/v) Suc and 30 &#x03BC;L 2.5 m<sc>m</sc> luciferin. The bioluminescence production was record with a Packard TopCount luminometer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Xu et al., 2010</xref>). Data were assayed using the Biological Rhythms Analysis Software System 2.1.4, which integrates the fast Fourier transform nonlinear least squares analysis for circadian rhythms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Plautz et al., 1997</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s17"><title>UBP Antibody and UBP Abundance in Arabidopsis</title><p>UBP12/UBP13-specific antibody was produced using a fragment of the N-terminal 315 amino acids of UBP13 expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic>. Polyclonal antisera was raised in mouse and affinity purified by UBP13 antigen. The specificity of UBP antibody was confirmed by Western blot using the wild type and the double mutant of <italic>ubp12-2wubp13-2</italic>. As showed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Figure S7</ext-link>, the full-length band of UBP is present in the wild type but not in the double mutant, whereas the partial UBP12 is present in the mutant only. Total extracts were prepared from wild-type Columbia grown under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">LL</xref> condition every 4 h, and the nuclear and cytoplasmic fractions were separated as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Weigel and Glazebrook, 2002</xref>). Immunoblot assay was performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Lu et al., 2011</xref>). Histone H3 was used as control for loading and nuclear fraction. Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase was used as control for cytoplasmic fraction; antibodies included anti-H3:ab1791 (Abcam) and anti-PEPC:1004163 (Rockland).</p></sec><sec id="s18"><title>Generation of Double Mutants</title><p>The double mutants were generated from the cross of homozygous mutants and identified from the F2 progeny grown on soil by comparing with their parental phenotypes and PCR-based characterization. The primers used for genotyping are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.<list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> Amino acid sequence alignment of UBP12, UBP13, and HsUSP7.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> Schematic diagram of raw unique reads mapped onto the region around the 3&#x2032; primer end of <italic>UBP12</italic> in the WT and the <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic> double mutant.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S3.</bold></ext-link> The number of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">T-DNA</xref> insertions in <italic>ubp12-2w</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S4.</bold></ext-link> Statistical analysis of leaf numbers of <italic>ubp12-2w</italic>, <italic>ubp13-3</italic>, <italic>ubp12-2w ubp13-3</italic>, <italic>ubp12-1</italic>, and <italic>ubp12-1 ubp13-3</italic> mutants under <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">LD</xref> and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">SD</xref> conditions compared with wild-type plants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S5.</bold></ext-link> <italic>FLC</italic> expression level in <italic>ubp12</italic> and <italic>ubp13</italic> single and double mutants of 12 DAG seedlings.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S6.</bold></ext-link> The phenotypes of <italic>ubp12-2w co</italic> and <italic>ubp12-2w gi-4</italic> double mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S7.</bold></ext-link> UBP antibody specificity assay by western blot.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.112.213009/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S1.</bold></ext-link> Primers used for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">qRT-PCR</xref>, constructions, and genotyping.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Qingbao Zhu for technical help, Richard D. Vierstra (University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI) for providing UBQ1 and UBQ10 plasmids, Hongquan Yang (Shanghai Jiaotong University) for providing <italic>co</italic> (SAIL_H_024) seed, and Chentao Lin (University of California, Los Angeles) for providing <italic>gi-4</italic> mutant seed.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alabad&#x00ED;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00E1;s</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Reciprocal regulation between TOC1 and LHY/CCA1 within the Arabidopsis circadian clock</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>293</volume>: <fpage>880</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>883</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baudry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Strait</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruneda-Paz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>F-box proteins FKF1 and LKP2 act in concert with ZEITLUPE to control <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> clock progression</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>606</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>622</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carr&#x00E9;</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>MYB transcription factors in the Arabidopsis circadian clock</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>1551</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1557</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>McArdle</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Callis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>AtUBP3 and AtUBP4 are two closely related <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> ubiquitin-specific proteases present in the nucleus</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source> <volume>255</volume>: <fpage>302</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>310</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daubeuf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Federoff</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>HSV ICP0 recruits USP7 to modulate TLR-mediated innate response</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>3264</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3275</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doelling</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Soyler-Ogretim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Callis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Otegui</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The ubiquitin-specific protease subfamily UBP3/UBP4 is essential for pollen development and transmission in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>801</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>813</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doelling</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurepa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The ubiquitin-specific protease UBP14 is essential for early embryo development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>405</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Everett</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kathoria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A novel ubiquitin-specific protease is dynamically associated with the PML nuclear domain and binds to a herpesvirus regulatory protein</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>566</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>577</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ewan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pangestuti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadanandom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Deubiquitinating enzymes AtUBP12 and AtUBP13 and their tobacco homologue NtUBP12 are negative regulators of plant immunity</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source> <volume>191</volume>: <fpage>92</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>106</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Recognition and processing of ubiquitin-protein conjugates by the proteasome</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>477</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>513</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fornara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Panigrahi</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gissot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauerbrunn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x00FC;hl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarillo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis DOF transcription factors act redundantly to reduce CONSTANS expression and are essential for a photoperiodic flowering response</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>86</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Niinuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomozoe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Circadian clock proteins LHY and CCA1 regulate SVP protein accumulation to control flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2960</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2971</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gendron</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruneda-Paz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis circadian clock protein, TOC1, is a DNA-binding transcription factor</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>3167</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3172</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harmer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The circadian system in higher plants</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Plant Biol</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>377</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x00E9;rez-Garc&#x00ED;a</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pokhilko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Antoshechkin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Riechmann</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Mapping the core of the Arabidopsis circadian clock defines the network structure of the oscillator</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>336</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>79</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Guryanova</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Deubiquitylase HAUSP stabilizes REST and promotes maintenance of neural progenitor cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>142</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>152</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imaizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Photoperiodic control of flowering: not only by coincidence</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>550</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>558</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imaizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>FKF1 F-box protein mediates cyclic degradation of a repressor of CONSTANS in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>297</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Imaizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>LOV domain-containing F-box proteins: light-dependent protein degradation modules in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>582</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Panigrahi</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenkel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soppe</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><name><surname>Valverde</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Coupland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis COP1 shapes the temporal pattern of CO accumulation conferring a photoperiodic flowering response</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1277</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1288</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Isasa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Crosas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A new map to understand deubiquitination</article-title>. <source>Biochem Soc Trans</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>28</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khoronenkova</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Dianova</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name><surname>Ternette</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dianov</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>ATM-dependent downregulation of USP7/HAUSP by PPM1G activates p53 response to DNA damage</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>801</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>813</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Targeted degradation of PSEUDO-RESPONSE REGULATOR5 by an SCFZTL complex regulates clock function and photomorphogenesis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>2516</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2530</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Putterill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>ZEITLUPE is a circadian photoreceptor stabilized by GIGANTEA in blue light</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>449</volume>: <fpage>356</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>360</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Independent roles for <italic>EARLY FLOWERING 3</italic> and <italic>ZEITLUPE</italic> in the control of circadian timing, hypocotyl length, and flowering time</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1557</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1569</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The photomorphogenic repressors COP1 and DET1: 20 years later</article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>584</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>593</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Helliwell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerowitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A repressor complex governs the integration of flowering signals in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>110</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>120</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiloh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaev</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Deubiquitination of p53 by HAUSP is an important pathway for p53 stabilization</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>416</volume>: <fpage>648</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>653</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year><comment>a</comment>) <article-title>COP1-mediated ubiquitination of CONSTANS is implicated in cryptochrome regulation of flowering in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>292</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>306</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year><comment>b</comment>) <article-title>Functional characterization of the Arabidopsis ubiquitin-specific protease gene family reveals specific role and redundancy of individual members in development</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>844</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>856</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenuwein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis REF6 is a histone H3 lysine 27 demethylase</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>715</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>719</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Buzas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Finnegan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Helliwell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>UBIQUITIN-SPECIFIC PROTEASE 26 is required for seed development and the repression of PHERES1 in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>180</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>236</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maertens</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>El Messaoudi-Aubert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Elderkin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiom</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Ubiquitin-specific proteases 7 and 11 modulate Polycomb regulation of the INK4a tumour suppressor</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>2553</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2565</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x00E1;s</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Targeted degradation of TOC1 by ZTL modulates circadian function in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>426</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>570</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The genetics of plant clocks</article-title>. <source>Adv Genet</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>139</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Estelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The ubiquitin-proteasome pathway and plant development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>3181</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3195</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Complexity in the wiring and regulation of plant circadian networks</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>R648</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>R657</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasswell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogg</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>FKF1, a clock-controlled gene that regulates the transition to flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>340</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neutzner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Neutzner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Enzymes of ubiquitination and deubiquitination</article-title>. <source>Essays Biochem</source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>50</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Suresh Kumar</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The multifaceted roles of USP7: new therapeutic opportunities</article-title>. <source>Cell Biochem Biophys</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>68</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nijman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Luna-Vargas</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Velds</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brummelkamp</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dirac</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sixma</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernards</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A genomic and functional inventory of deubiquitinating enzymes</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>773</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>786</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Redundant requirement for a pair of PROTEIN ARGININE METHYLTRANSFERASE4 homologs for the proper regulation of Arabidopsis flowering time</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>490</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>503</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plautz</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Straume</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanewsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowse</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Quantitative analysis of Drosophila period gene transcription in living animals</article-title>. <source>J Biol Rhythms</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>217</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pokhilko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x00E1;ndez</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Southern</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The clock gene circuit in Arabidopsis includes a repressilator with additional feedback loops</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>574</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reyes-Turcu</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ventii</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Regulation and cellular roles of ubiquitin-specific deubiquitinating enzymes</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>397</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusinow</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Imaizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>FKF1 and GIGANTEA complex formation is required for day-length measurement in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>318</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>265</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Amasino</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Histone H2B deubiquitination is required for transcriptional activation of <italic>FLOWERING LOCUS C</italic> and for proper control of flowering in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>149</volume>: <fpage>1196</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1204</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmena</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Carracedo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Egia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo-Coco</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Teruya-Feldstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The deubiquitinylation and localization of PTEN are regulated by a HAUSP-PML network</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>455</volume>: <fpage>813</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>817</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bressan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Control of DNA methylation and heterochromatic silencing by histone H2B deubiquitination</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>447</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>738</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takase</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanihigashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyosue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>LOV KELCH PROTEIN2 and ZEITLUPE repress Arabidopsis photoperiodic flowering under non-inductive conditions, dependent on FLAVIN-BINDING KELCH REPEAT F-BOX1</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>608</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>621</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Horst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries-Smits</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenkman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>van Triest</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Broek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Colland</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurice</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgering</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>FOXO4 transcriptional activity is regulated by monoubiquitination and USP7/HAUSP</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1064</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1073</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Knaap</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moshkin</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Langenberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Krijgsveld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Verrijzer</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>GMP synthetase stimulates histone H2B deubiquitylation by the epigenetic silencer USP7</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>695</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>707</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The ubiquitin-26S proteasome system at the nexus of plant biology</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>397</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Glazebrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Arabidopsis: A Laboratory Manual.</source> <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc></citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Deubiquitinating enzymes&#x2014;the importance of driving in reverse along the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>590</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>605</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>McClung</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Robust circadian rhythms of gene expression in <italic>Brassica rapa</italic> tissue culture</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>153</volume>: <fpage>841</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>850</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Doelling</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Falbel</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Durski</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vierstra</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The ubiquitin-specific protease family from Arabidopsis. AtUBP1 and 2 are required for the resistance to the amino acid analog canavanine</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>1828</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1843</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yanovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular basis of seasonal time measurement in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>419</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>312</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Irigoyen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>COP1 and ELF3 control circadian function and photoperiodic flowering by regulating GI stability</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>617</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>630</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
