<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">plantphysiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aspb</journal-id><journal-title>Plant Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Plant Physiology</abbrev-journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2548</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">0032-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Plant Biologists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">226761</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.226761</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>BIOCHEMISTRY AND METABOLISM</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Alterations in Seed Development Gene Expression Affect Size and Oil Content of Arabidopsis Seeds<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"><sup>[C]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3"><sup>[W]</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4"><sup>[OPEN]</sup></xref></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fatihi</surname><given-names>Abdelhak</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zbierzak</surname><given-names>Anna Maria</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>D&#x00F6;rmann</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x002A;</xref></contrib><aff>Institute of Molecular Physiology and Biotechnology of Plants, University of Bonn, 53115 Bonn, Germany</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="fn1" fn-type="supported-by"><label>1</label><p>This work was supported by the program Plant-Omics-based Strategies to Increase the Oil Content in Rapeseed of the German Initiative Genome Analysis in the Biological System Plant (GABI-OIL) funded by the German Federal Department of Education and Research.</p></fn><fn id="afn2" fn-type="present-address"><label>2</label><p>Present address: Department of Plant Sciences and Plant Pathology, Montana State University, P.O. Box 173150, Bozeman, MT 59717.</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x002A;</label>Address correspondence to <email>doermann@uni-bonn.de</email>.</corresp><fn><p>The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org">www.plantphysiol.org</ext-link>) is: Peter D&#x00F6;rmann (<email>doermann@uni-bonn.de</email>).</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>[C]</label><p>Some figures in this article are displayed in color online but in black and white in the print edition.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>[W]</label><p>The online version of this article contains Web-only data.</p></fn><fn id="fn4"><label>[OPEN]</label><p>Articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></fn><fn><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.113.226761">www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/doi/10.1104/pp.113.226761</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>09</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>163</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>973</fpage><lpage>985</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>08</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>09</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x00A9; 2013 American Society of Plant Biologists. All Rights Reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p>Articles can be viewed online without a subscription.</p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="PP_226761_ic1.gif"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><italic>Analysis of mutant and overexpressing lines of Arabidopsis seed development genes uncovers the impact of a leucine-rich repeat kinase on seed size and oil content</italic>.</p></abstract><abstract><p>Seed endosperm development in Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) is under control of the polycomb group complex, which includes <italic>Fertilization Independent Endosperm</italic> (<italic>FIE</italic>). The polycomb group complex regulates downstream factors, e.g. <italic>Pheres1</italic> (<italic>PHE1</italic>), by genomic imprinting. In heterozygous <italic>fie</italic> mutants, an endosperm develops in ovules carrying a maternal <italic>fie</italic> allele without fertilization, finally leading to abortion. Another endosperm development pathway depends on <italic>MINISEED3</italic> (a WRKY10 transcription factor) and <italic>HAIKU2</italic> (a leucine-rich repeat kinase). While the role of seed development genes in the embryo and endosperm establishment has been studied in detail, their impact on metabolism and oil accumulation remained unclear. Analysis of oil, protein, and sucrose accumulation in mutants and overexpression plants of the four seed development genes revealed that (1) seeds carrying a maternal <italic>fie</italic> allele accumulate low oil with an altered composition of triacylglycerol molecular species; (2) homozygous mutant seeds of <italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic>, which are smaller, accumulate less oil and slightly less protein, and starch, which accumulates early during seed development, remains elevated in mutant seeds; (3) embryo-specific overexpression of <italic>FIE</italic>, <italic>PHE1</italic>, and <italic>MINI3</italic> has no influence on seed size and weight, nor on oil, protein, or sucrose content; and (4) overexpression of <italic>IKU2</italic> results in seeds with increased size and weight, and oil content of overexpressed <italic>IKU2</italic> seeds is increased by 35%. Thus, <italic>IKU2</italic> overexpression represents a novel strategy for the genetic manipulation of the oil content in seeds.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta><notes><glossary><title>Glossary</title><def-list><def-item><term id="term1">PgC</term><def id="def1"><p>polycomb group complex</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2">PcG</term><def id="def2"><p>polycomb group</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3">LRR</term><def id="def3"><p>Leucine-rich repeat</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4">T-DNA</term><def id="def4"><p>transfer DNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5">RT</term><def id="def5"><p>reverse transcription</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6">Col-0</term><def id="def6"><p>ecotype Columbia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7">GC</term><def id="def7"><p>gas chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term8">DAF</term><def id="def8"><p>d after flowering</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term9">Q-TOF</term><def id="def9"><p>quadrupole time-of-flight</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term10">TAG</term><def id="def10"><p>triacylglycerol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term11">NASC</term><def id="def11"><p>Nottingham Arabidopsis Stock Centre</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term12">cDNA</term><def id="def12"><p>complementary DNA</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></notes></front><body><p>In Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>), the seed endosperm is derived from the fusion of the two maternal polar nuclei with the other sperm nucleus and thus is triploid with two maternal and one paternal genomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Reiser and Fischer, 1993</xref>). Cell division of the fertilized egg cell results in embryo development with different morphological stages (globular, heart, torpedo, and cotyledon; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Sun et al., 2010</xref>). Seed development in Arabidopsis from anthesis to maturity takes about 20 d and can be organized into two phases. The early phase encompasses the proliferation of the endosperm while the embryo develops into the heart stage and remains small. In the second phase, the embryo grows in size until it fills the cavity provided by the endosperm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Sun et al., 2010</xref>). In mature Arabidopsis seeds, the embryo fills almost the entire seed space, while the endosperm represents a thin layer around the embryo. The outermost layer of the seed is the seed coat, which is of maternal origin and is derived from the inner and outer integument cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Haughn and Chaudhury, 2005</xref>). Embryo proliferation in the second phase is accompanied with accumulation of the seed storage compounds, in particular of proteins and triacylglycerol (TAG), which are crucial to nourish the seedling before the onset of photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Focks and Benning, 1998</xref>). The seed accumulates large amounts of starch in the early phase but this starch is later degraded. The endosperm in the mature seed contains only low amounts of TAG that however contribute to the feeding of the seedling after germination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Penfield et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>Embryo and endosperm development are under epigenetic control of the polycomb group complex (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PgC</xref>). In Arabidopsis, the four proteins MEDEA (MEA), FERILIZATION INDEPENDENT ENDOSPERM (FIE), FERTILIZATION INDEPENDENT SEED2, and MULTI-COPY OF IRA1 are components of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PgC</xref>, which structurally and functionally resembles the Polycomb Repressor Complex2 complex of animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Baroux et al., 2007</xref>). Control of endosperm development by the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PgC</xref> is mediated via imprinting. One of the downstream factors regulated by the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PgC</xref> is PHERES1 (PHE1), a type 1 MADS box transcription factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">K&#x00F6;hler et al., 2003</xref>). <italic>PHE1</italic> is transiently expressed during the early phase of embryo and endosperm development. Mutations in the <italic>MEA</italic> or <italic>FIE</italic> genes result in elevated <italic>PHE1</italic> expression during seed development, e.g. by increased methylation of 3&#x2032; region of the <italic>PHE1</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">K&#x00F6;hler et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Makarevich et al., 2008</xref>). Ovules of heterozygous <italic>fie</italic> mutants carrying a mutant allele undergo endosperm development without fertilization. The unfertilized embryo reaches early heart stage before it aborts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Ohad et al., 1996</xref>). It is believed that the derepression of the maternal <italic>PHE1</italic> allele in polycomb group (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PcG</xref>) mutants causes endosperm overproliferation and seed abortion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">K&#x00F6;hler et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Makarevich et al., 2008</xref>). Homozygous <italic>phe1-1</italic> mutants plant carrying a transposon insertion showed no difference in vegetative and reproductive development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">K&#x00F6;hler et al., 2005</xref>).</p><p>In addition to the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PcG</xref> pathway, further genes, e.g. <italic>MINISEED3</italic> (<italic>MINI3</italic>) and <italic>HAIKU2</italic> (<italic>IKU2</italic>), are involved in the regulation of seed development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Garcia et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Luo et al., 2005</xref>). <italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>IKU2</italic> encode a WRKY10 transcription factor and a Leucine-rich repeat (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LRR</xref>) kinase, respectively. <italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>IKU2</italic> are expressed in developing endosperm during the early stage, and <italic>MINI3</italic> is additionally expressed in the embryo at the globular stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Luo et al., 2005</xref>). Homozygous mutant plants of <italic>mini3</italic> and <italic>iku2</italic> produce smaller seeds. The exact mechanism or downstream factors of the <italic>MINI3/IKU2</italic> pathway remain unknown. <italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>IKU2</italic> are under control of the <italic>SHORT HYPOCOTYL UNDER BLUE1</italic> (<italic>SHB1</italic>) gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Zhou et al., 2009</xref>). SHB1 harbors SPX (for SYG1, PHOSPHATE TRANSPORTER81 and XENOTROPIC AND POLYTROPIC MURINE LEUKEMIA VIRUSES RECEPTOR1 proteins) and EXS (for Endoplasmic Reticulum RETENSION-DEFECTIVE1, XENOTROPIC AND POLYTROPIC MURINE LEUKEMIA VIRUSES RECEPTOR1 proteins) domains, which are found in proteins such as yeast (<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) SYG1 (for suppressor of yeast <italic>gpa1</italic> [Guanine nucleotide-binding protein &#x03B1;-1 subunit]) or mouse XPR1 (for XENOTROPIC AND POLYTROPIC MURINE LEUKEMIA VIRUSES RECEPTOR1), but the functions of these domains remain unclear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Kang and Ni, 2006</xref>). The SHB1 protein associates with the promoters of <italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>IKU2</italic>, thereby inducing their expression and triggering endosperm proliferation and seed growth. In line with this scenario, the <italic>shb1-<sc>d</sc></italic> mutant, which confers <italic>SHB1</italic> overexpression, produces larger seeds, while homozygous mutant seeds of a loss of function allele, <italic>shb1</italic>, are smaller (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Zhou et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>While the role of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def1">PgC</xref> genes and of <italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>IKU2</italic> during endosperm and embryo development has been studied, only little is known about the role of these genes in seed storage compound allocation. We selected four genes, <italic>FIE</italic> and <italic>PHE1</italic> of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def2">PcG</xref> regulative pathway, <italic>MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic> to study the changes in carbohydrate, protein, and TAG accumulation in the respective loss-of-function mutants. From these studies, it became clear that a reduced seed size in the knockout mutants is primarily associated with reduced TAG content in the embryo. Furthermore, transgenic lines with strong seed-specific overexpression of the four genes were generated. The results demonstrate that overexpression of specific seed development genes can be employed to increase embryo size and TAG content in transgenic Arabidopsis seeds.</p><sec id="s1" sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2"><title>Isolation of Mutants of Arabidopsis Seed Development Genes</title><p>Embryo and endosperm development in seeds are strictly controlled and depend on the concerted action of different genetic factors. To study the influence of alterations in the seed developmental program on metabolism and on the accumulation of the storage components, Arabidopsis genes known to be involved in seed development were selected for analysis: <italic>FIE</italic> (At3g20740), <italic>PHE1</italic> (At1g65330), <italic>MINI3</italic> (At1g55600), and <italic>IKU</italic>2 (At3g19700). Mutant lines were derived from the original alleles (<italic>fie-11</italic>, <italic>phe1-1</italic>, <italic>mini3-1</italic>, <italic>mini3-2</italic>, and <italic>iku2-3</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Guitton et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">K&#x00F6;hler et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Luo et al., 2005</xref>). Furthermore, new alleles carrying transfer DNA (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">T-DNA</xref>) or transposon insertions were obtained from stock centers (<italic>fie-13</italic>, <italic>fie-14</italic>, <italic>phe1-6</italic>, <italic>phe1-7</italic>, <italic>mini3-3</italic>, and <italic>iku2-4</italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). Two alleles with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">T-DNA</xref> insertions between start and stop codon (<italic>fie-13</italic> and <italic>fie13</italic>) were obtained. Two insertion lines were collected for <italic>phe1</italic>, carrying insertions between the start and stop codon, with the insertion site of <italic>phe1-7</italic> very close to the 3&#x2032; end of the open reading frame. For <italic>MINI3</italic>, two insertion lines were isolated harboring a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">T-DNA</xref> between start and stop codon. Furthermore, a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">T-DNA</xref> line, <italic>iku2-4</italic>, was obtained. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">T-DNA</xref> insertion in line <italic>iku2-4</italic> is located at the 3&#x2032; site of the start codon.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Insertional mutants of the seed development genes <italic>FIE</italic>, <italic>PHE1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic>. A, Exon intron structure and location of mutations. Exons and introns are depicted by boxes and lines, respectively. The locations of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">T-DNA</xref> or transposon insertions are indicated by triangles. The mutants are derived from different ecotype backgrounds (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>). B, Expression analysis of seed development genes in the <italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> mutants. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR products obtained with RNA isolated from developing siliques (5 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>) of homozygous mutant plants (<italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic>) were separated in agarose gels and stained with ethidium bromide. Ubiquitin-specific primers were used as control. C, The seed size (length, black bars; width, gray bars) was determined after scanning the seeds using the Evaluator software. Data represent mean and <sc>sd</sc> of a minimum of 100 seeds. D, Seed weight obtained by measuring 100 seeds (<italic>n</italic> = 3, mean and <sc>sd</sc>). Mutants are organized according to their respective ecotype. Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_226761_f1"></graphic></fig><p>Homozygous mutant lines for <italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> were obtained after PCR screening of genomic DNA from plants obtained after selfing of heterozygous lines. For the <italic>fie</italic> mutant lines, homozygous plants cannot be isolated, because ovules carrying the <italic>fie</italic> allele cannot develop into fertile seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Ohad et al., 1996</xref>). Expression of the genes was studied by reverse transcription (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>)-PCR of RNA extracted from young siliques (5 d post pollination; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR signal of the <italic>PHE1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic> genes was strongly suppressed in the corresponding homozygous mutants compared with the wild-type lines. A faint <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR signal was detected in the <italic>phe1-7</italic> line, indicating that there is residual expression. For the other mutant lines, no <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR signal could be detected, suggesting that they represent null alleles.</p><p>In agreement with previous results that showed that loss-of-function mutations in the genes <italic>MINI3</italic> and <italic>IKU2</italic> result in reduced seed size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Luo et al., 2005</xref>), the seed length and width and the seed weight of the lines <italic>mini3-2</italic>, <italic>mini3-3</italic>, <italic>iku2-4</italic>, <italic>mini3-1</italic>, and <italic>iku2-</italic>3 were reduced as compared to their wild-type controls, ecotypes Columbia (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>) and Landsberg <italic>erecta</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, C and D</xref>). Seeds sizes (length and width) of <italic>phe-1</italic>, <italic>phe1-7</italic>, and <italic>phe1-6</italic> were only slightly reduced compared with the respective controls, ecotypes Landsberg <italic>erecta</italic> and Nossen, while their weight was strongly reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1, C and D</xref>). Close inspection of the seeds under the microscope revealed that the surfaces of the mutant alleles of <italic>mini3</italic>, <italic>iku2</italic>, and <italic>phe1</italic> were shriveled, indicating a reduced accumulation of storage compounds during seed maturation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). The fact that the surface of <italic>phe1</italic> seeds was shriveled can explain why the weight of the seeds was reduced to a much stronger extent than seed size.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Oil, Protein, and Sugars in Mutants of Arabidopsis Seed Development Genes</title><p>The changes observed in seed size and weight of the <italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> mutants prompted us to analyze the contents of seed storage compounds. TAG and proteins are the most abundant forms for carbon deposition in Arabidopsis seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Focks and Benning, 1998</xref>). Total fatty acids were quantified in the mutant seeds by gas chromatography (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GC</xref>) of methyl esters as a measure for the content of storage oil. Total fatty acids amount to approximately 7 to 8 &#x00B5;g per seed in the Arabidopsis wild type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Baud et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Li et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). This amount was reduced in all mutant lines by approximately 15% to 40%. The fatty acid composition revealed no major changes between the mutants and the controls (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). There was a tendency that the amount of linoleic acid (18:2) was reduced while the &#x03B1;-linolenic acid (18:3) content was increased in the lines <italic>mini3-2</italic>, <italic>mini3-3</italic>, <italic>phe1-1</italic>, <italic>phe1-6</italic>, and <italic>phe1-7</italic>.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Oil, protein, and Suc content in mutants of Arabidopsis seed development genes. A, Total fatty acids were measured in seeds of the <italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> mutants after transmethylation by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GC</xref>. B, Total protein content of seeds was determined photometrically. C, Suc in seeds was measured enzymatically. Data show mean and <sc>sd</sc> of at least three measurements of five seeds (fatty acids), 20 seeds (protein), and 50 seeds (Suc) each. Mutants of <italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> are organized according to their respective ecotype. Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_226761_f2"></graphic></fig><p>Furthermore, seed storage protein was measured. The total protein content was slightly reduced in the mutant lines, in particular in <italic>min3-1, mini3-2, phe1-1</italic>, <italic>and iku2-3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Furthermore, Suc was determined photometrically using an enzyme-based assay. Suc is known to be imported into the embryo and to represent the main source for acetyl-CoA production and oil biosynthesis in the seed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Baud et al., 2005</xref>). The amount of Suc in mature Arabidopsis wild-type seeds is around 0.5 &#x00B5;g per seed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Focks and Benning, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Baud et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>). The Suc content in mature <italic>mini3</italic> and <italic>iku2</italic> seeds was similar to corresponding controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>). The seeds of <italic>phe1</italic> lines contained an increased amount of Suc. These results demonstrate that the reduction in weight observed in the seed development mutants is mainly based on a reduction in oil, while the impact on storage protein is smaller.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Accumulation of Storage Compounds during Seed Development</title><p>Storage compound accumulation was recorded in developing seeds of the <italic>mini3</italic>, <italic>phe1</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> mutants to study the metabolic changes associated with the reduced oil and protein contents. Seeds were harvested at 7, 11, 15, and 19 d after flowering (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>). The seeds of two lines of each mutant were subjected to the determination of fatty acids, protein, starch, Suc, and Glc contents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). Seed fatty acid content increased from approximately 0 to approximately 5 &#x00B5;g per seed in the wild type, and it was reduced in all mutant lines from day 11 on. At 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>, fatty acid content in the wild type was still lower than 7 to 8 &#x00B5;g per seed as measured in mature seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>), indicating that oil accumulation and seed development were not finished. Protein content in the wild type was 2 to 3 &#x00B5;g per seed at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>, and it increased to approximately 5 &#x00B5;g per seed at 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>. The mutant seed protein content was lower in some mutant lines. Starch is known to accumulate in the early phase of seed development. At 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>, the starch content was highest, and it declined during the later phase of seed development to reach values of 0 to 1 &#x00B5;g per seed at 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> in the wild type. The starch degradation in all mutant seeds was retarded. Therefore, the starch content in the seeds of <italic>mini3</italic>, <italic>phe1</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> was elevated at 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>. Suc accumulated in the wild type from approximately 0.2 &#x00B5;g per seed at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> to approximately 0.4 &#x00B5;g per seed at 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> in a linear way. The Suc contents of the <italic>iku2</italic> and <italic>mini3</italic> mutant seeds were similar to the wild type. In the <italic>phe1</italic> seeds, the amount of Suc was comparable to approximately at 7, 11, and 15 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>, but it was elevated at 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>. The Glc content declined during development of wild-type seeds. Glc content in the mutant seeds was, in general, slightly lower, and it was similar to the wild type at 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>, except in <italic>mini3-1</italic> seeds, which contained less Glc. Taken together, major changes in storage compound synthesis were associated with a reduction of oil and protein accumulation, while starch degradation in the mutant seeds was retarded.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Accumulation of fatty acids, protein, starch, Suc, and Glc in <italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> mutants during seed development. Flowers were tagged at anthesis, and seeds were collected after 7, 11, 15, and 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>. The isolated seeds were employed for the determination of total fatty acids (A), protein (B), starch (C), Suc (D), and Glc (E). Data represent mean &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of five measurements. Similar results were obtained in an independent biological experiment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_226761_f3"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Changes in Oil Content and Composition in <italic>fie</italic> Mutant Seeds</title><p>After selfing, endosperm and embryo development in mutant ovules of heterozygous <italic>fie</italic> plants is initiated, but the embryo is aborted at the early heart stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Ohad et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Vinkenoog et al., 2000</xref>). The endosperm finally dries out and forms extremely small, infertile seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Ohad et al., 1996</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). To study the oil accumulation in the <italic>fie</italic> mutant, a large number of aborted seeds was collected from a heterozygous <italic>fie</italic> plant, and total fatty acids were measured by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GC</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A</xref> shows that the oil content of the aborted <italic>fie</italic> seeds is extremely low, at around 0.05 &#x00B5;g per seed, compared with 8 &#x00B5;g in <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> or C24 seeds. Analysis of the fatty acid composition of the aborted seeds of three <italic>fie</italic> mutant alleles revealed characteristic differences to the wild-type controls. The mutant lines contained an increase in the saturated fatty acids palmitic acid (16:0) and stearic acid (18:0), a decrease in linoleic acid (18:2), &#x03B1;-linolenic acid (18:3), and eicosenoic acid (20:1), and an increase in erucic acid (22:1; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4B</xref>). TAG molecular species were measured in whole wild-type C24 and aborted <italic>fie-11</italic> seeds by quadrupole time-of-flight (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Q-TOF</xref>) mass spectrometry. On a per seed basis, the amounts of all molecular <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">TAG</xref> species were drastically reduced in the <italic>fie-11</italic> mutant. Compared on a percentage basis, the molecular species containing saturated fatty acids (16:0 and 18:0) were increased, while those rich in unsaturated fatty acids, in particular 18:3 and 20:1, were decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4C</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Lipid composition of the <italic>fie</italic> mutant. Lipids were measured in aborted seeds derived from mutant ovules of heterozygous <italic>fie</italic> mutant plants after selfing. A, Total fatty acids were determined by transmethylation and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GC</xref>. B, Fatty acid composition measured by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GC</xref> of fatty acid methyl esters. C, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">TAG</xref> molecular species were quantified by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Q-TOF</xref> mass spectrometry. Data represent mean and <sc>sd</sc> of three (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GC</xref>) or five (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Q-TOF</xref>) measurements of five seeds (the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> and C24 wild type) or 25 seeds (<italic>fie-11</italic> seeds). Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_226761_f4"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Overexpression of <italic>IKU2</italic> Leads to an Increased Seed Size and Weight</title><p>To study the effect of an increased expression level on seed development, the four genes <italic>FIE</italic>, <italic>PHE1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic> were overexpressed in transgenic Arabidopsis plants under control of the seed-specific glycinin promoter from soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic>). For each construct, at least 15 independent transformants were isolated. The expression level of the transgenes was measured by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR of RNA isolated from siliques harvested approximately 13 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>. Three independent lines were selected for each construct that showed strong expression of <italic>FIE</italic>, <italic>PHE1, MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU</italic>2 as compared with an empty vector control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5A</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Overexpression of seed development genes in Arabidopsis. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">cDNA</xref>s of the genes <italic>FIE</italic>, <italic>PHE1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic> were cloned behind the seed-specific glycinin promoter and transferred into transgenic Arabidopsis plants. A, Expression of <italic>FIE, PHE1, MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic> in overexpression lines of Arabidopsis. Developing siliques were harvested (approximately 13 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>) from three independent plants each and used to isolate RNA for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> plants transformed with an empty vector (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV) were used as control. The four lanes (1&#x2013;4) of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV represent <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR reactions using primers for <italic>FIE</italic>, <italic>PHE1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, and <italic>IKU2</italic>, respectively. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR products were separated in agarose gels and stained with ethidium bromide. Ubiquitin-specific primers were used as a reference. Note that expression of the four genes in the control lanes (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV) is much lower compared with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> because the RNA was isolated from older siliques. B, Size of T2 seeds harvested from transgenic plants overexpressing <italic>FIE</italic>, <italic>PHE1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, or <italic>IKU2</italic>. Transgenic T2 seeds were selected based on their red fluorescence (DsRed marker). The photo shows transgenic seeds (top) and wild-type segregants (bottom) of the same plant. Bar = 0.5 mm. C, The size (length and width) of transgenic T2 seeds. Data show mean and <sc>sd</sc> of approximately 100 seeds. D, The weight of transgenic T2 seeds was determined by weighing three times 100 seeds each. Data show mean and <sc>sd</sc>. Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_226761_f5"></graphic></fig><p>The seeds were first visually inspected under a fluorescence microscope. Because the overexpression constructs harbor a DsRed marker gene, transgenic seeds can easily be identified by their red fluorescence under green light. For the T2 seeds of the different T1 lines, a three-to-one segregation of fluorescent to nonfluorescent seeds was observed, indicating a heterozygous integration of the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">T-DNA</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5B</xref> shows transgenic (top) and nontransgenic seeds (bottom) for one representative line for each construct. The seed sizes for the overexpressing lines <italic>FIE</italic>-OE, <italic>PHE1</italic>-OE, and <italic>MINI3</italic>-OE were very similar as the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-empty vector (EV) control and the nontransgenic segregant seeds. Overexpression of <italic>IKU2</italic>, however, resulted in seeds that were larger than <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV. Seed length and width of the fluorescent (transgenic) seeds was determined after scanning the seeds. In agreement with the microscopic analysis, seed length and width of <italic>FIE</italic>-OE, <italic>PHE1</italic>-OE, and <italic>MINI3</italic>-OE lines were unchanged. For the <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds, the length was increased by approximately 20%, while the width was similar to the control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5C</xref>). In agreement with the seed size measurement, the weight of the transgenic seeds of the lines <italic>FIE</italic>-OE, <italic>PHE1</italic>-OE, and <italic>MINI3</italic>-OE was not altered as compared with <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV. However, the weight of the transgenic seeds of the three <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE lines was increased by approximately 30% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Overexpression of <italic>IKU2</italic> Results in an Increase in Oil</title><p>To study the impact of overexpression of seed development genes on the allocation of storage compounds, total fatty acids, total protein, and Suc were measured in the seeds of the lines <italic>FIE</italic>-OE, <italic>PHE1</italic>-OE, <italic>MINI3</italic>-OE, and <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE. Total fatty acid content was very similar to the control in the lines <italic>FIE</italic>-OE, <italic>PHE1</italic>-OE, and <italic>MINI3</italic>-OE, but it was increased by approximately 35% in the seeds of <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6A</xref>). The fatty acid composition of the seeds of all lines as determined by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GC</xref> was not altered (not shown). Total protein was similar to the wild type in mature seeds of the transgenic lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6B</xref>). The content of Suc was similar to the control in the seeds of the overexpressing lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6C</xref>). Therefore, only the overexpression of <italic>IKU2</italic> resulted in an increase of storage oil, in agreement with the increase in seed size and weight of <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Content of oil, protein, and sugars in seeds of transgenic overexpression plants. T2 seeds from heterozygous plants overexpressing <italic>FIE</italic>, <italic>PHE1</italic>, <italic>MINI3</italic>, or <italic>IKU2</italic> were selected based on their red fluorescence. A, Total fatty acid content was measured by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GC</xref> after transmethylation. B, Protein content was measured photometrically. C, The content of Suc was determined enzymatically. Data show mean and <sc>sd</sc> of at least three measurements of five seeds (fatty acids), 20 seeds (protein), and 50 seeds (Suc) each. Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_226761_f6"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Accumulation of Storage Compounds in <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE Seeds during Development</title><p>Two <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE lines were selected for the analysis of seed storage compound accumulation during seed development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). Total fatty acid content was indistinguishable from the wild type at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>, but already at 11 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>, it was higher in <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 and <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE2 seeds, and it stayed elevated at 15 and 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>. The protein content of the <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds was also slightly higher at all time points. Interestingly, the amount of starch at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> was strongly increased in <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds to 8 to 10 &#x00B5;g per seed, about two times higher as compared with the wild type. Then, the starch was degraded such that it was similar to the wild type at 11, 15, and 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>, when it amounted to approximately 1 &#x00B5;g per seed. The pattern of Suc accumulation showed an opposite effect, as it was lower than the wild type at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> in the two <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE lines, but it reached values similar to the wild type at 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>. The Glc content was similar to the wild type at all time points.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Accumulation of fatty acids, protein, starch, Suc, and Glc in <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE lines during seed development. Developing seeds of heterozygous transgenic <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 and <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE2 plants were harvested at 7, 11, 15, and 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> and employed for the measurements of total fatty acids (A), protein (B), starch (C), Suc (D), and Glc (E). Data are mean &#x00B1; <sc>sd</sc> of five measurements. Similar results were obtained in a second independent experiment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_226761_f7"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Seed Yield in Transgenic <italic>IKU2</italic> Overexpressing Plants</title><p>The overexpression of <italic>IKU2</italic> in the seeds of transgenic plants resulted in the production of larger seeds with increased seed weight and oil content. To study the impact of <italic>IKU2</italic> overexpression on seed yield, the silique length, number of seeds per silique, and the total amount of seeds per plant were determined for three independent heterozygous transgenic <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plants. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8, A and B</xref>, the silique length and number of seeds per silique were not altered in the <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plants. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figure 8C</xref> shows that the seed yield for all three <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE lines was reduced by approximately 25% to 50% compared with the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV control. Therefore, <italic>IKU2</italic> overexpression has no impact on the number of seeds per silique, but the total weight of seeds per plant is decreased.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Seed yield of plants overexpression <italic>IKU2</italic> (<italic>IKU2</italic>-OE). Siliques and seeds of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV and of three independent heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plants were analyzed. A, Silique length (<italic>n</italic> = 10, mean and <sc>sd</sc>). B, Numbers of seeds per silique (<italic>n</italic> = 10, mean and <sc>sd</sc>). C, Total weight of seeds per plant (mean and <sc>sd</sc>, <italic>n</italic> = 7&#x2013;10). Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_226761_f8"></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s10"><title>The Increase in Seed Size of <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE Plants Is Suppressed in Homozygous Transgenic Plants</title><p>Overexpression of <italic>IKU2</italic> resulted in an increase in seed size, weight, and oil content when transgenic seeds of a heterozygous line were analyzed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). We obtained T2 lines homozygous for the <italic>IKU2</italic> overexpression construct from each of the three independent T1 plants, as judged by the segregation of the DsRed marker. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9</xref> shows the results for homozygous and heterozygous seeds obtained from the <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 line. The siliques from heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 plants where thicker compared with siliques from a homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 line or the controls (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV1 or <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9A</xref>). Developing seeds of the late cotyledon stage from the different siliques were microscopically analyzed after thin sectioning and toluidine blue staining. The embryos of developing seeds of homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 plants had a size similar to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV1, while seeds of a heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plant contained embryos of different sizes, i.e. small embryos with a size comparable to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9B</xref>, left) and large embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9B</xref>, right). This result was confirmed by the analysis of mature seeds under the fluorescent microscope. Seeds of a homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 plant were of similar size as <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV seeds. Seeds from the heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 line contained different types of seeds, i.e. large fluorescent (transgenic, heterozygous) seeds, small fluorescent (transgenic, homozygous) seeds, and large nonfluorescent seeds (wild-type segregants), in a ratio of about 1:2:1. The measurement of length and width of the seeds confirmed these results. The length of the seeds of a homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 line was similar to that of a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9D</xref>). Seeds of a heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 line were separated into two classes, i.e. fluorescent (transgenic, homozygous/heterozygous) and nonfluorescent (nontransgenic segregant) seeds. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9D</xref> shows that the mean of the length of the transgenic seeds was larger compared with seeds of a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV or homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9D</xref>).</p><fig id="fig9" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Variation in sizes of seeds from homozygous and heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plants. A, Siliques from a heterozygous IKU2-OE1 plant are thicker than those from a homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 plant or from the controls (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>, <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV1). Bar = 5 mm. B, Light microscopy of immature seeds of the late cotyledon stage (14 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>) after thin sectioning and toluidine blue staining. Representative seeds from siliques from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV and a heterozygous (two adjacent seeds) and homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 plant are shown. Note that siliques of a heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plant contain large (heterozygous, nontransgenic segregants) or small seeds (homozygous). Bar = 200 &#x00B5;m. C, Mature seeds from a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV and heterozygous and homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plant. The photo shows red fluorescence of the DsRed marker. Seeds of a homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-O1 plant are small, similar to <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV1. Seeds of the heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 plant segregate into three classes, large fluorescent seeds (heterozygous, left), small fluorescent seeds (homozygous, right), and large nonfluorescent seeds (nontransgenic segregants, center). Bar = 500 &#x00B5;m. D, Size measurement of transgenic seeds from a heterozygous <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV1 plant, fluorescent/transgenic (homozygous/heterozygous) seeds of a heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 plant, wild-type segregant seeds of a heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plant, and seeds of a homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 plant. The length of the transgenic and wild-type segregant seeds of a heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plant is larger than that of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV or homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds. E, F1 seeds from reciprocal crosses of wild-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> with a homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 plant. The photo shows fluorescent seeds of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV and F1 seeds obtained after reciprocal crosses (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> &#x00D7; <italic>IKU2-</italic>OE1, <italic>IKU2-</italic>OE1 &#x00D7; <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>). Nontransgenic, nonfluorescent <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> seeds were mixed to the F1 seeds as an internal size control. F, Expression analysis of <italic>IKU2</italic> in seeds of heterozygous and homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE lines. Total RNA was isolated from immature siliques (approximately 13 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>). The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR products were separated in agarose gels and stained with ethium bromide. Expression in seeds of a homozygous plant is severely repressed compared with seeds from the heterozygous plant and is even lower than in seeds of a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV1 plant. Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic> test, &#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#x002A;&#x002A;<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01. [See online article for color version of this figure.]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pp_226761_f9"></graphic></fig><p>Interestingly, the length of the nontransgenic segregants of the <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE1 line was also larger than that of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV1, and it was similar to the large fluorescent (heterozygous) seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9D</xref>). This increase in the size of nontransgenic segregant seeds from a heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE line can already be observed after visual inspection of the seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9C</xref>) and is indicative for a maternal effect on seed size of the heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plant.</p><p>A reciprocal cross of a homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE line with wild-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> was performed to unravel whether the increased seed phenotype, which is suppressed in the homozygous stage, can be derepressed in the F1 generation. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9E</xref> shows F1 seeds from the reciprocal crosses of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> with a homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plant. Furthermore, wild-type <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> seeds were mixed to the F1 seeds of the reciprocal crosses. The fluorescent (heterozygous) <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds are clearly larger compared with the small nonfluorescent <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> seeds. This result was independent of the direction of the cross. The finding was confirmed by measuring the size of the seeds, because the length of the heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE F1 seeds derived from the reciprocal crosses (0.572 &#x00B1; 0.039 and 0.550 &#x00B1; 0.032 &#x00B5;m for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> &#x00D7; <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE and <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE &#x00D7; <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>, respectively) was larger than that of the control <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> (0.495 &#x00B1; 0.035 &#x00B5;m). Therefore, the increase in seed size was only observed in heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds, but not in homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds.</p><p>To study the molecular origin for the suppression of the increased seed size in homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE lines, <italic>IKU2</italic> expression was measured by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR in siliques harvested at 13 d after pollination of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV plants, heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plants, and homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plants. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Figure 9F</xref> shows that <italic>IKU2</italic> expression is low in the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV siliques and is strongly increased in the siliques of the heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE line. However, expression of <italic>IKU2</italic> was also low in seeds of the homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic> plant, similar to the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV control. Therefore, expression of <italic>IKU2</italic> is silenced in homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds, presumably by cosuppression, due to the combination of two transgenic <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE alleles in a single seed. This result demonstrates that the expression level of IKU2 is critical for the regulation of seed development.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s11" sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><sec id="s12"><title>Isolation and Characterization of Mutant Alleles for <italic>fie</italic>, <italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic></title><p>Arabidopsis mutants deficient in seed development genes (<italic>fie-11</italic>, <italic>phe1-1</italic>, <italic>mini3-1</italic>, <italic>mini3-2</italic>, and <italic>iku2-3</italic>) were previously isolated. Here, we present the isolation of additional mutant alleles for fie (<italic>fie-13</italic>, <italic>fie-14</italic>), <italic>phe1</italic> (<italic>phe1-6</italic>, <italic>phe1-7</italic>), <italic>mini3</italic> (<italic>mini3-3</italic>), and <italic>iku2</italic> (<italic>iku2-4</italic>). The <italic>mini3-3</italic> and <italic>iku2-4</italic> mutants produce smaller seeds with reduced weight, as previously described for <italic>mini3-1</italic>, <italic>mini3-2</italic>, and <italic>iku2-3</italic>. The <italic>phe1-1</italic> mutant was previously isolated, and no defect in growth or reproductive development was found (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">K&#x00F6;hler et al., 2005</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref> shows that homozygous seeds of <italic>phe1-1</italic>, <italic>phe1-6</italic>, and <italic>phe1-7</italic> have a slightly reduced weight, but the length and width are similar to the wild type. This discrepancy can be explained by the finding that the <italic>phe1</italic> seeds have a shriveled surface (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>), indicating that seed filling during development and therefore seed weight is reduced.</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Storage Compounds in <italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> Mutant Seeds</title><p>In the <italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> lines, the amount of total fatty acids per seed was reduced by approximately 25% to 40% in mature seeds, while protein content was also slightly reduced. The reduction in oil content became already visible at 11 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>, i.e. when oil synthesis strongly increased. Therefore, the disturbance in seed development primarily becomes visible at 7 to 11 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>, when storage compound production begins. In the <italic>phe1</italic>, <italic>mini3</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> lines, a slight increase in 18:3 and a decrease in 18:2 content were observed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). This increase in the degree of desaturation by an enhanced conversion of 18:2 to 18:3 has previously been observed in Arabidopsis mutants affected in seed oil deposition. It can be explained by the reduction in the pool size of fatty acids available for desaturases in the mutants resulting in an enhanced conversion to the unsaturated fatty acids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Focks and Benning, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Moreno-P&#x00E9;rez et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p>Starch degradation was retarded during mutant seed development, and therefore, the starch content remained elevated at 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> compared with the wild type. These results point toward a block in starch degradation in the mutants during the later phase of seed development. Seed starch synthesis and degradation are crucial to sustain high oil accumulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Vigeolas et al., 2004</xref>). A reduction in oil accumulation accompanied with a retardation in starch degradation was already observed in seeds of the <italic>wrinkled1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Focks and Benning, 1998</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Baud et al. (2002)</xref> showed that only about 10% of the transient starch accumulating during Arabidopsis seed development localizes to the embryo, but that larger amounts of starch are associated with the integuments. It is possible that the altered endosperm functions in the <italic>mini3, phe1</italic>, and <italic>iku2</italic> mutants affect transient starch degradation during seed development. The reduced oil accumulation in the embryo might in turn be a consequence of the decrease in starch mobilization. Suc in the mature seeds of <italic>mini3</italic> and <italic>iku2</italic> remains similar to the wild type, but in the mature <italic>phe1</italic> seeds, Suc content was increased. In line with this result, the Suc content in developing <italic>mini3</italic> and <italic>iku2</italic> seeds was similar to the wild type, but it was elevated at 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> in <italic>phe1</italic> seeds. The increased Suc content in <italic>phe1</italic> seeds can be explained by a decreased sink strength associated with a reduced conversion of Suc into fatty acids as also observed for other seed mutants, e.g. <italic>wrinkled1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Focks and Benning, 1998</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Oil Composition in <italic>fie</italic> Seeds</title><p>All three <italic>fie</italic> lines produce aborted seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). Concomitantly, the oil content of <italic>fie</italic> seeds is strongly reduced below 1% of the wild type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Ohad et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Luo et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Vinkenoog et al., 2000</xref>). The fatty acid pattern of aborted <italic>fie</italic> seeds showed characteristic differences to the wild type, because the amounts of saturated fatty acids (16:0, 18:0) were increased, while the contents of unsaturated fatty acids, particularly 18:3 and 20:1, were decreased. This result was confirmed by the analysis of molecular species of <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">TAG</xref> by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Q-TOF</xref> mass spectrometry. The <xref ref-type="list" rid="def10">TAG</xref> fatty acid composition of <italic>fie-11</italic> resembles that of heart stage wild-type seeds, which contain high amounts of 16:0 and 18:0 and low amounts of 18:3 and 20:1 compared with mature seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Baud et al., 2002</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Seed-Specific Overexpression of <italic>FIE</italic> and <italic>PHE</italic> Has No Effect on Seed Development</title><p>To study the impact of the increased expression level on seed size and storage compound accumulation, the <italic>FIE</italic> and <italic>PHE1</italic> genes were overexpressed. We used the promoter of the soybean seed storage protein glycinin1, which is embryo specific (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Nielsen et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Thomas, 1993</xref>). Expression in nonseed organs (leaves, stems, or roots) is very low (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Nielsen et al., 1989</xref>). The glycinin promoter is active during the mid to late phase of seed development. By contrast, <italic>FIE</italic> and <italic>PHE1</italic> are expressed early (approximately 1&#x2013;4 d post pollination) during seed development, and their expression pattern is restricted to different tissues of the seed. <italic>FIE</italic> expression was detected in the prepollination embryo sac and in embryo and endosperm around 4 d after pollination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Luo et al., 2000</xref>). The fact that, in <italic>FIE</italic> cosuppression plants, plant development and organ establishment was severely affected indicates that <italic>FIE</italic> also exerts its function throughout sporophyte development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Katz et al., 2004</xref>). Therefore, <italic>FIE</italic> must also be expressed in other plant organs, at least to a low extent. The <italic>PHE1</italic> gene is expressed in the preglobular embryo and in the endosperm during early development. Later, expression is restricted to the chalazal endosperm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">K&#x00F6;hler et al., 2003</xref>). This difference in expression has to be taken into account for the interpretation of the results obtained after overexpression of the respective genes. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Vinkenoog et al. (2000)</xref> showed that lethality of seeds carrying a maternal <italic>fie</italic> allele could be rescued by pollination with pollen from hypomethylated plants. These results are in line with the finding that overexpression of <italic>FIE</italic> or <italic>PHE1</italic> per se has no strong effect on seed development.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Seed-Specific Overexpression of <italic>IKU2</italic> and <italic>MINI3</italic></title><p>The <italic>MINI3</italic> gene is expressed in pollen and in the ovules during the first 4 d after pollination. <italic>MINI3</italic> expression was detected in the endosperm and embryo until the globular stage, but was absent from heart stage embryos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Luo et al., 2005</xref>). <italic>IKU2</italic> expression was found in young ovules after fertilization and in the endosperm of developing seeds, but it was not expressed in the embryo or pollen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Luo et al., 2005</xref>). Therefore, the temporal and spatial gene expression pattern in the overexpression lines under control of the glycinin promoter differs from the expression pattern of the authentic genes. <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plants produced seeds with an increase in size, weight, and oil content. The increase in oil became visible as early as 7 to 11 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). At this time, oil accumulation begins in the embryo. It is tempting to speculate that the elevated starch content at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>, accompanied with an increased starch degradation rate at later time points, is associated with the increase in oil accumulation. In line with this scenario, the Suc content in <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds is reduced at 7 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> but steadily increases to reach values similar to the wild type at 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref>. The protein content was also slightly higher in developing <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds until 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> but was similar to the wild type in mature seeds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figs. 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>). This result indicates that seed developing has not finished at 19 <xref ref-type="list" rid="def8">DAF</xref> and that protein accumulation in <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE and wild-type seeds reaches similar values in mature seeds.</p><p>The overexpression of <italic>IKU2</italic> resulted in a decrease in the total amount of seeds per plant. Therefore, the increase in carbon deposition per seed is associated with a seed yield penalty. As the number of seeds per silique remained unchanged, the number of siliques per plant must be reduced. Furthermore, the fact that the total weight of seeds per plant is reduced indicates that in <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plants, less carbon is deposited in the seeds compared with the control (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV). Therefore, the reduction in total seed weight cannot be caused by a general limitation in photosynthetic capacity. However, it is possible that the expression of <italic>IKU2</italic> under the control of the strong glycinin promoter has negative effects on overall plant development, e.g. flower initiation, which would explain the reduced number of siliques per plant. In this regard, it is interesting to note that overexpression of <italic>LEAFY COTYLEDON1</italic> (<italic>LEC1</italic>) and <italic>LEC1-LIKE</italic> in Arabidopsis and rapeseed (<italic>Brassica napus</italic>) under control of the strong seed-specific napin promoter also led to an increase in seed size, but this was accompanied with an abnormal development of the seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Tan et al., 2011</xref>). Using truncated versions of the napin promoter, it was possible to separate these two effects, i.e. to obtain transgenic <italic>LEC1</italic>-overexpressing rapeseed plants that produce larger seeds without any detrimental effects on plant development. Thus, it is possible that the use of truncated versions of the glycinin promoter can result in the generation of transgenic <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plants, which produce larger seeds, but without reduction of the total seed yield per plant.</p><p>Overexpression of <italic>IKU2</italic> resulted in an increase in seed size of heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds, and the nontransgenic segregant seeds in siliques of a heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plant were also larger than those of an empty vector control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9, C and D</xref>). This finding points to a maternal effect of <italic>IKU2</italic> overexpression in heterozygous siliques on the nontransgenic progeny. At present, the basis for this effect remains unknown, but it is possible that a small increase in the expression of <italic>IKU2</italic> in maternal tissue, e.g. seed coat or siliques, caused by side activity of the glycinin promoter has a positive effect on the development of the seeds.</p><p>Furthermore, a strong cosuppression effect was observed in homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE plants, because the <italic>IKU2</italic> transcript abundance was reduced to control (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>-EV) levels, whereas it was strongly increased in heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds. In line with this result, the increase in seed size, weight, and oil content was only observed in transgenic seeds of a heterozygous plant, but not in homozygous seeds. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figures 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">9</xref>, the size, weight, and oil content of fluorescent (transgenic seeds) of a heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE line were measured. These plants produce heterozygous and homozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds in a predicted ratio of 2:1. The increase in seed size, weight, and oil for a collection of heterozygous <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE seeds free of homozygous seeds would be expected to be even higher. Therefore, the seed size is correlated with the abundance of <italic>IKU2</italic> transcript during seed development. Interestingly, expression of the authentic <italic>IKU2</italic> mRNA is restricted to the endosperm, while in the transgenic <italic>IKU2</italic>-OE lines, expression was redirected to the embryo. This result indicates that IKU2 activity for seed development can also be exerted in the embryo.</p><p>Overexpression of the <italic>SHB1</italic> gene was found to result in an increase in seed size, weight, and oil content presumably by an increased expression of <italic>MINI3</italic> or <italic>IKU2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Zhou et al., 2009</xref>). In line with these data, our results show that overexpression of <italic>IKU2</italic> resulted in an increase in seed size. IKU2 encodes a <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LRR</xref> kinase involved in endosperm proliferation. <xref ref-type="list" rid="def3">LRR</xref> kinase-like proteins are involved in a large number of regulative processes, in particular in hormone functions (brassinosteroids, abscisic acid) and in the regulation of organ shape, reproductive cell shapes, and plant pathogen interactions. Our results demonstrate that increased expression of <italic>IKU2</italic> in embryos exerts a positive effect on seed development.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s17" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s18"><title>Plant Material</title><p>Plants were grown in the phytochamber at 55% relative humidity and 22&#x00B0;C with 16 h of fluorescent light per day (150 &#x00B5;mol s<sup>&#x2013;1</sup> m<sup>&#x2013;2</sup>). The origin of the different Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>) mutants and control lines is indicated in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>. The lines <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref>, Landsberg <italic>erecta</italic>, and C24 and a Feodoroff transposon line (Nottingham Arabidopsis Stock Centre [<xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">NASC</xref>] stock N8511, ecotype Nossen) were used as controls. Homozygous mutant plants were selected by PCR using oligonucleotides specific to the flanking genomic sequence or to the insertion (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental Table S2</ext-link>).</p><p>The mutant <italic>fie-11</italic> was obtained from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">NASC</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Guitton et al., 2004</xref>). Two new alleles, <italic>fie-13</italic> (GK-362D08) and <italic>fie-14</italic> (GK-532F01), were obtained from <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">NASC</xref> (GABI-Kat). The genomic locus of <italic>FIE</italic> was amplified with the primer pairs Bn165/Bn166 (1,178 bp) or Bn205/Bn206 (1,033 bp). The flanking DNA of the insertions was amplified with the primer combinations Bn142/Bn166 (549 bp) and Bn142/Bn206 (441 bp) for <italic>fie-13</italic> and <italic>fie-14</italic>, respectively.</p><p>The mutant <italic>phe1-1</italic> (ET189) was obtained from the <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">NASC</xref> stock center (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">K&#x00F6;hler et al., 2005</xref>). Two new alleles, <italic>phe1-6</italic> (RATM11-2982-1_H) and <italic>phe1-7</italic> (GT_5_6830), were obtained from RIKEN and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">NASC</xref>, respectively. PCR with the genomic primers Bn66/Bn67 or with Bn273/Bn274 yielded products of 1,045 or 1,059 bp, respectively, for the <italic>PHE1</italic> wild-type locus. The flanking regions of the insertions were amplified with the primer combinations Bn66/Bn277 (750 bp), Bn130/Bn67 (790 bp), or Bn130/Bn274 (506 bp) for <italic>phe1-1</italic>, <italic>phe1-6</italic>, or <italic>phe1-7</italic>, respectively.</p><p>The mutants <italic>mini3-1</italic> (ethylmethanesulfonate mutant) and <italic>mini3-2</italic> (Salk_050364) mutant alleles were obtained from William James Peacock (Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation) and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">NASC</xref>, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Luo et al., 2005</xref>). One new allele, <italic>mini3-3</italic>, was provided by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">NASC</xref> (Salk_056336). Genomic DNA of the <italic>MINI3</italic> locus was amplified with the primer pairs Bn68/Bn69 (1,167 bp) or Bn171/Bn172 (1,099 bp). PCR of the flanking DNA resulted in the production of fragments of 803 bp (primers Bn78/Bn69; <italic>mini3-2</italic>) or 534 bp (Bn78/Bn172; <italic>mini3-3</italic>).</p><p>The mutant alleles <italic>iku2-3</italic> and <italic>iku2-4</italic> (Salk_073260) were provided by W.J. Peacock and <xref ref-type="list" rid="def11">NASC</xref>, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Luo et al., 2005</xref>). The genomic locus of <italic>IKU2</italic> was amplified using the primers Bn60/Bn61 (900 bp) or Bn167/Bn187 (1,084 bp). PCR of the flanking regions yielded PCR products of 900 bp (Bn78/Bn61; <italic>iku2-4</italic>).</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Overexpression of Seed Development Genes in Arabidopsis Seeds</title><p>The expressed sequence tags PYAT1G65330, U60089, and DQ446362 carrying the full-length complementary DNAs (<xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">cDNA</xref>s) for <italic>PHE1</italic>, <italic>FIE</italic>, and <italic>MINI3</italic>, respectively, were obtained from the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center. The coding sequence of <italic>PHE1</italic> was amplified from PYAT1G65330 by PCR using the oligonucleotides Bn155/Bn156, adding Eco<italic>RI</italic>/Mlu<italic>I</italic> and Xho<italic>I</italic> sites at the 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032; end of the PCR product, respectively. The <italic>PHE1</italic> PCR fragment was cloned into pGEM-T Easy and then ligated into the Eco<italic>RI</italic>, Xho<italic>I</italic> sites of the binary vector pBinGlyRed1 (Edgar Cahoon) for expression under control of the strong embryo-specific glycinin promoter. This vector harbors a DsRed marker for selection of transgenic seeds under the fluorescence microscope. This pBinGlyRed1-<italic>PHE1</italic> construct contains an extra Mlu<italic>I</italic> site derived from the 5&#x2032; primer Bn155 that was used for the cloning of the other constructs (see below).</p><p>The coding region of <italic>FIE</italic> was amplified from the EST U60089 using the primers Bn157/Bn158 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental Table S3</ext-link>), subcloned into pGEM-T Easy, and then ligated into the Mlu<italic>I</italic>, Xho<italic>I</italic> sites of pBinGlyRed1-<italic>PHE1</italic>. Similarly, the <italic>MINI3</italic> coding region was amplified from DQ446362 with the primers Bn159/Bn160, cloned into pGEM-T Easy, and ligated into the Mlu<italic>I</italic>, Xho<italic>I</italic> sites of pBinGlyRed1-<italic>PHE1</italic>.</p><p>No full-length <xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">cDNA</xref> for <italic>IKU2</italic> was available in the stock centers. Therefore, the 3&#x2032; part (726 bp) of the coding sequence was amplified by PCR from the EST clone X3G19700EFK (Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center) using the primers Bn553/Bn551, thereby introducing an Xho<italic>I</italic> site at the 3&#x2032; end, and the PCR product cloned into pGEM-T Easy. The 5&#x2032; part of the coding sequence (2,248 bp) was amplified from genomic DNA using the primers Bn550/Bn669, introducing an Mlu<italic>I</italic> site at the 5&#x2032; end, and the fragment cloned into pGEM-T Easy. This PCR product encompasses part of exon 1 of the <italic>IKU2</italic> gene and therefore contains no introns. The two PCR fragments contain a partially overlapping sequence with an authentic Pst<italic>I</italic> site. Finally, the 5&#x2032; PCR fragment (released with Mlu<italic>I</italic>, Pst<italic>I</italic> from pGEM-T Easy) and the 3&#x2032; PCR fragment (released with Pst<italic>I</italic>, Xho<italic>I</italic>) were ligated into the Mlu<italic>I</italic>, Xho<italic>I</italic> sites of pBinGlyRed1-<italic>PHE1</italic> in one step.</p><p>Binary constructs were transferred into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> and used for Arabidopsis <xref ref-type="list" rid="def6">Col-0</xref> infiltration using floral dip (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Clough and Bent, 1998</xref>). Transformed seeds were selected by their red fluorescence under green light using a fluorescent microscope (Olympus SZX 16).</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Determination of Seed Weight and Seed Size</title><p>Seeds were dried in the vacuum for 48 h prior to the determination of the 100 seed weight. For size determination, approximately 100 Arabidopsis seeds were spread on a microscope slide and fixed with transparent tape. The slide and a scale bar were scanned with high resolution and saved as a TIFF file, which was subsequently exported into bitmap format. The measurement of seed length and width was performed using the Evaluator software (developed by Dmitry Peschansky, IPK Gatersleben) according to the software instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s21"><title>Fatty Acid and TAG Measurements</title><p>Total fatty acid content and fatty acid composition in seeds were measured by converting the lipids into fatty acid methyl esters in 1 <sc>n</sc> methanolic HCl for 2 h at 80&#x00B0;C. Measurements are based on three replicas of five seeds each. Fatty acid methyl esters were quantified by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def7">GC</xref> in the presence of internal standard (pentadecanoic acid, 15:0) as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Browse et al., 1986</xref>). TAG molecular species were determined by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Q-TOF</xref> mass spectrometry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Lippold et al., 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s22"><title>Sugar, Starch, and Protein Measurements</title><p>Soluble sugars were extracted from the seeds with ethanol as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Focks and Benning, 1998</xref>). For sugar quantification, the extract was added to reaction buffer containing Glc-6-P dehydrogenase. Glc and Suc were measured after addition of hexokinase, phosphoglucoisomerase, and fructosidase (invertase), respectively. The production of NADPH was followed in the photometer at a wavelength of 340 nm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Stitt et al., 1989</xref>). Starch was measured in the ethanol-insoluble pellet after hydrolysis with KOH using a starch quantification kit (Roche/R-Biopharm). Total seed proteins were extracted as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Focks and Benning (1998)</xref>. Protein was quantified photometrically with the bicinchoninic acid method (Bio-Rad).</p></sec><sec id="s23"><title><xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR</title><p>RNA was isolated from green siliques as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Kay et al. (1987)</xref>. First-strand <xref ref-type="list" rid="def12">cDNA</xref> was synthesized from total RNA using the SuperScript III kit (Invitrogen). Transcripts were amplified by <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR and separated in agarose gels, and the bands were visualized with ethidium bromide. A <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR reaction with oligonucleotides to ubiquitin were used as control. Primers and expected <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR product sizes are given in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1">Supplemental</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1"> Table S4</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s24"><title>Light Microscopy</title><p>Green seeds were removed from siliques and placed into fixative solution (4% [w/v] paraformaldehyde, 0.2% [w/v] glutaraldehyde in 0.1 <sc>m</sc> sodium phosphate buffer, pH 8.0). The samples were incubated in the vacuum for 1 h and then subjected to dehydration using a series of buffers with increasing content of ethanol (from 30%&#x2013;100% [v/v]). Specimens were preinfiltrated with 100% (v/v) ethanol/Technovit 700 solution (1:1) and then incubated in solution A (1 g of Hardener added to 100 mL Technovit 7100) for 24 h prior to transfer to embedding solution (solution A/Hardener II, 15:1) for polymerization (Heraeus Kulzer). Thin sections (3&#x2013;4 &#x00B5;m) were prepared with a microtome and stained with 0.05% toluidine blue followed by four to five washes with water and then dried for 10 min at 42&#x00B0;C. The embryo structure was observed using a light microscope (Olympus BH-2).</p></sec><sec id="s25"><title>Supplemental Data</title><p>The following materials are available in the online version of this article.</p><list id="L1" list-type="simple"><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S1.</bold></ext-link> Morphological phenotype of Arabidopsis seeds affected in seed development.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Figure S2.</bold></ext-link> Fatty acid composition in Arabidopsis seeds of mutants affected in seed development.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S1.</bold></ext-link> Mutant lines used in this study.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S2.</bold></ext-link> Oligonucleotides for PCR selection of Arabidopsis <xref ref-type="list" rid="def4">T-DNA</xref> and transposon mutants.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S3.</bold></ext-link> Oligonucleotides used for generating overexpression constructs.</p></list-item><list-item><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantphysiol.org/cgi/content/full/pp.113.226761/DC1"><bold>Supplemental Table S4.</bold></ext-link> Oligonucleotides used for <xref ref-type="list" rid="def5">RT</xref>-PCR.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank William James Peacock (Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation) for the <italic>iku2-3</italic> and <italic>mini3-1</italic> mutant seeds, Edgar Cahoon (University of Nebraska) for providing the vector pBinGlyRed1, Meike Siebers (University of Bonn) for help during light microscopical analysis of seed morphology, Katharina vom Dorp for her assistance during <xref ref-type="list" rid="def9">Q-TOF</xref> measurements, and Tanja Fuchs and Andreas Ahrens (University of Bonn) for their help with oil and protein analyses.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baroux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pien</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Chromatin modification and remodeling during early seed development</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>473</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>479</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutin</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Miquel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepiniec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rochat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>An integrated overview of seed development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> ecotype WS</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>160</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wuill&#x00E8;me</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemoine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronenberger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Caboche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepiniec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rochat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The AtSUC5 sucrose transporter specifically expressed in the endosperm is involved in early seed development in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>824</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>836</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McCourt</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Fatty acid composition of leaf lipids determined after combined digestion and fatty acid methyl ester formation from fresh tissue</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source> <volume>152</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>145</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Floral dip: a simplified method for <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transformation of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>743</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Focks</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Benning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title><italic>wrinkled1</italic>: a novel, low-seed-oil mutant of Arabidopsis with a deficiency in the seed-specific regulation of carbohydrate metabolism</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>101</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Saingery</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambrier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x00FC;rgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis <italic>haiku</italic> mutants reveal new controls of seed size by endosperm</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>1661</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1670</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guitton</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambrier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lionnet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Identification of new members of Fertilisation Independent Seed Polycomb Group pathway involved in the control of seed development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>2971</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2981</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haughn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genetic analysis of seed coat development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Trends Plant Sci</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>472</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>477</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SHORT HYPOCOTYL UNDER BLUE1 contains SPX and EXS domains and acts in cryptochrome signaling</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>921</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>934</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosquna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakim</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>FIE and CURLY LEAF polycomb proteins interact in the regulation of homeobox gene expression during sporophyte development</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>707</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>719</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Duplication of CaMV 35S promoter sequences creates a strong enhancer for plant genes</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>236</volume>: <fpage>1299</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1302</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x00F6;hler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Spillane</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pien</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruissem</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The Polycomb-group protein MEDEA regulates seed development by controlling expression of the MADS-box gene PHERES1</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1540</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1553</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x00F6;hler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagliardini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossniklaus</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> MEDEA Polycomb group protein controls expression of PHERES1 by parental imprinting</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>30</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Beisson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Oil content of Arabidopsis seeds: the influence of seed anatomy, light and plant-to-plant variation</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>904</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>915</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lippold</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>vom Dorp</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x00F6;lzl</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wewer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lager</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Montandon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Besagni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Fatty acid phytyl ester synthesis in chloroplasts of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>2001</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2014</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilodeau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Expression and parent-of-origin effects for <italic>FIS2</italic>, <italic>MEA</italic>, and <italic>FIE</italic> in the endosperm and embryo of developing <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>10637</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10642</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhury</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>MINISEED3</italic> (<italic>MINI3</italic>), a <italic>WRKY</italic> family gene, and <italic>HAIKU2</italic> (<italic>IKU2</italic>), a leucine-rich repeat (<italic>LRR</italic>) <italic>KINASE</italic> gene, are regulators of seed size in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>17531</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17536</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makarevich</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>CBR</given-names></name><name><surname>Erilova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x00F6;hler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mechanism of <italic>PHERES1</italic> imprinting in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source> <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>906</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>912</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno-P&#x00E9;rez</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Venegas-Caler&#x00F3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaistij</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Salas</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x00E9;s</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x00ED;nez-Force</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Reduced expression of FatA thioesterases in Arabidopsis affects the oil content and fatty acid composition of the seeds</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>235</volume>: <fpage>629</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>639</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thanh</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name><surname>Scallon</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Drews</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Characterization of the glycinin gene family in soybean</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>328</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Margossian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>Y-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Repetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>A mutation that allows endosperm development without fertilization</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>5319</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5324</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rylott</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilday</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Reserve mobilization in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> endosperm fuels hypocotyl elongation in the dark, is independent of abscisic acid, and requires <italic>PHOSPHOENOLPYRUVATE CARBOXYKINASE1</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>2705</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2718</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The ovule and the embryo sac</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1291</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1301</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>RMC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerhardt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heldt</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Determination of metabolite levels in specific cells and subcellular compartments of plant cells</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source> <volume>174</volume>: <fpage>518</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>552</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shantharaj</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional and hormonal signaling control of Arabidopsis seed development</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>611</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>620</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Enhanced seed oil production in canola by conditional expression of <italic>Brassica napus LEAFY COTYLEDON1</italic> and <italic>LEC1-LIKE</italic> in developing seeds</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>156</volume>: <fpage>1577</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1588</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Gene expression during plant embryogenesis and germination: an overview</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1401</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1410</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vigeolas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00F6;hlmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Martini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Geigenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Embryo-specific reduction of ADP-Glc pyrophosphorylase leads to an inhibition of starch synthesis and a delay in oil accumulation in developing seeds of oilseed rape</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source> <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>2676</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2686</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vinkenoog</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Spielman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Hypomethylation promotes autonomous endosperm development and rescues postfertilization lethality in <italic>fie</italic> mutants</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>2271</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2282</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>SHORT HYPOCOTYL UNDER BLUE1 associates with <italic>MINISEED3</italic> and <italic>HAIKU2</italic> promoters in vivo to regulate <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seed development</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>106</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>117</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
